<regulation xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>BANKS AND BANKING</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>82</volume>
    <date>2017-07-19</date>
    <originalDate>2017-07-19</originalDate>
    <title>Arbitration Agreements</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</agency>
    <regLetter></regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1040</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2017-14225</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2017-09-18</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2017/07/19/2017-14225/arbitration-agreements</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>

  <part label="1040">
    <tableOfContents>
      <tocSecEntry target="1040-1">
        <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1040.1 Authority and purpose.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1040-2">
        <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1040.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1040-3">
        <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1040.3 Coverage and exclusions from coverage.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1040-4">
        <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1040.4 Limitations on the use of pre-dispute arbitration agreements.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1040-5">
        <sectionNum>5</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1040.5 Compliance date and temporary exception.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocInterpEntry target="1040-Interp">
	<interpTitle>Supplement I to Part 1040-Official Interpretations</interpTitle>
      </tocInterpEntry>
    </tableOfContents>

    <content>
      <subpart label="1040-Subpart">
        <content>
          <section label="1040-1" sectionNum="1">
            <subject>Authority and purpose.</subject>
            <paragraph marker="(a)" label="1040-1-a">
              <title>Authority</title>
              <content>The regulation in this part is issued by the Bureau of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Financial Protection (Bureau) pursuant to sections 1022(b)(1) and (c) and 1028(b) of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Protection Act (Dodd-Frank Act) (12 U.S.C. 5512(b)(1) and (c) and 5518(b)).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph marker="(b)" label="1040-1-b">
              <title>Purpose</title>
              <content>The purposes of this part are the furtherance of the public interest and the protection of consumers regarding the use of agreements for <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products and services providing for arbitration of any future dispute, and also to monitor for risks to consumers in the offering or provision of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services, including developments in markets for such products or services.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1040-2" sectionNum="2">
            <subject>Definitions.</subject>
            <paragraph marker="(a)" label="1040-2-a">
              <content><def term="class action">Class action</def> means a lawsuit in which one or more parties seek or obtain class treatment pursuant to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 23 or any State process analogous to Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 23.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph marker="(b)" label="1040-2-b">
              <content><def term="consumer">Consumer</def> means an individual or an agent, trustee, or representative acting on behalf of an individual.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph marker="(c)" label="1040-2-c">
              <content><def term="pre-dispute arbitration agreement">Pre-dispute arbitration agreement</def> means an agreement between a covered person as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(6) and a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> providing for arbitration of any future dispute concerning a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph marker="(d)" label="1040-2-d">
              <content><def term="provider">Provider</def> means:</content>
              <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-2-d-1">
                <content>A person as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(19) that engages in an activity covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> to the extent that the person is not excluded under § <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)</ref>; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-2-d-2">
                <content>An affiliate of a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> as defined in paragraph <ref target="1040-2-d-1" reftype="internal">(d)(1)</ref> of this section when that affiliate is acting as a service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> to the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> with which the service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is affiliated consistent with 12 U.S.C. 5481(6)(B).</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1040-3" sectionNum="3">
            <subject>Coverage and exclusions from coverage.</subject>
            <paragraph marker="(a)" label="1040-3-a">
              <title>Covered products and services</title>
              <content>Except for persons when excluded from coverage pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> of this section, this part applies to the offering or provision of the following products or services when such offering or provision is a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(5):</content>
              <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-3-a-1">
		<content></content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-a-1-i">
                  <content>Providing an “extension of credit” that is “<ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit” when performed by a “creditor” as those terms are defined in Regulation B, 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2" reftype="internal">1002.2</ref>;</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-a-1-ii">
		  <content>“Participat[ing] in [ ] credit decision[s]” within the meaning of 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2-l" reftype="internal">1002.2(l)</ref> when performed by a “creditor” with regard to “<ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit” as those terms are defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2" reftype="internal">1002.2</ref>;</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-3-a-1-iii">
		  <content></content>
		  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-3-a-1-iii-A">
		    <content>Referring applicants or prospective applicants for “<ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit” to creditors when performed by a “creditor” as those terms are defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2" reftype="internal">1002.2</ref>; or</content>
		  </paragraph>
		  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-3-a-1-iii-B">
		    <content>Selecting or offering to select creditors to whom requests for “<ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit” may be made when done by a “creditor” as those terms are defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2" reftype="internal">1002.2</ref>;</content>
		  </paragraph>
		  <paragraph marker="(C)" label="1040-3-a-1-iii-C">
		    <content>Except that this paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(iii)</ref> does not apply when the referral or selection activity by the creditor described in paragraphs <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii-A" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(iii)(A)</ref> or <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii-B" reftype="internal">(B)</ref> of this section is incidental to a business activity of that creditor that is not covered by this section;</content>
		  </paragraph>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iv)" label="1040-3-a-1-iv">
		  <content>Acquiring, purchasing, or selling an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section; or</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(v)" label="1040-3-a-1-v">
		  <content>Servicing an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section;</content>
		</paragraph>
	      </paragraph>
	      <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-3-a-2">
		<content>Extending automobile leases as defined by 12 CFR <ref target="1090-108" reftype="internal">1090.108</ref> or brokering such leases;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(3)" label="1040-3-a-3">
		<content></content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-a-3-i">
		  <content>Providing services to assist with debt management or debt settlement, modify the terms of any extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, or avoid foreclosure;</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-a-3-ii">
		  <content>Providing products or services represented to remove derogatory information from, or improve, a person's credit history, credit record, or credit rating;</content>
		</paragraph>
	      </paragraph>
	      <paragraph marker="(4)" label="1040-3-a-4">
		<content>Providing directly to a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> report, as defined by the Fair Credit Reporting Act, 15 U.S.C. 1681a(d), a credit score, as defined by 15 U.S.C. 1681g(f)(2)(A), or other information specific to a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> derived from a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> file, as defined by 15 U.S.C. 1681a(g), in each case except for a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> report provided solely in connection with an adverse action as defined in 15 U.S.C. 1681a(k) with respect to a product or service that is not covered by this section;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(5)" label="1040-3-a-5">
		<content>Providing accounts subject to the Truth in Savings Act, 12 U.S.C. 4301et seq.,as implemented by 12 CFR part 707 and Regulation DD, 12 CFR part 1030;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(6)" label="1040-3-a-6">
		<content>Providing accounts or remittance transfers subject to the Electronic Fund Transfer Act, 15 U.S.C. 1693et seq.,as implemented by Regulation E, 12 CFR part 1005;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(7)" label="1040-3-a-7">
		<content>Transmitting or exchanging funds as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(29) except when necessary to another product or service if that product or service:</content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-a-7-i">
                  <content>Is offered or provided by the person transmitting or exchanging funds; and</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-a-7-ii">
                  <content>Is not covered by this section;</content>
		</paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(8)" label="1040-3-a-8">
		<content>Accepting financial or banking data or providing a product or service to accept such data directly from a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for the purpose of initiating a payment by a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> via any payment instrument as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(18) or initiating a credit card or charge card transaction for the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, except by a person selling or marketing a good or service that is not covered by this section, for which the payment or credit card or charge card transaction is being made;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(9)" label="1040-3-a-9">
		<content>Providing check cashing, check collection, or check guaranty services; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(10)" label="1040-3-a-10">
		<content>Collecting debt arising from any of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services described in paragraphs <ref target="1040-3-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> through <ref target="1040-3-a-9" reftype="internal">(9)</ref> of this section when performed by:</content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-a-10-i">
                  <content>A person offering or providing the product or service giving rise to the debt being collected, an affiliate of such person, or a person acting on behalf of such person or affiliate;</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-a-10-ii">
                  <content>A person purchasing or acquiring an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, an affiliate of such person, or a person acting on behalf of such person or affiliate; or</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-3-a-10-iii">
                  <content>A debt collector as defined by 15 U.S.C. 1692a(6).</content>
		</paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
           
            <paragraph marker="(b)" label="1040-3-b">
              <title>Excluded persons</title>
              <content>This part does not apply to the following persons in the following circumstances:</content>
              <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-3-b-1">
		<content></content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-b-1-i">
                  <content>A person regulated by the Securities and Exchange Commission as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(21); or</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-b-1-ii">
		  <content>A person to the extent regulated by a State securities commission as described in 12 U.S.C. 5517(h) as either:</content>
		  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-3-b-1-ii-A">
                    <content>A broker dealer; or</content>
		  </paragraph>
		  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-3-b-1-ii-B">
                    <content>An investment adviser; or</content>
		  </paragraph>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-3-b-1-iii">
		  <content>A person regulated by the Commodity Futures Trading Commission as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(20) or a person with respect to any account, contract, agreement, or transaction to the extent subject to the jurisdiction of the Commodity Futures Trading Commission under the Commodity Exchange Act, 7 U.S.C. 1et seq.</content>
		</paragraph>
	      </paragraph>
	      
              <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-3-b-2">
		<content></content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-b-2-i">
		  <content>A Federal agency as defined in 28 U.S.C. 2671;</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-b-2-ii">
		  <content>Any State, Tribe, or other person to the extent such person qualifies as an “arm” of a State or Tribe under Federal sovereign immunity law and the person's immunities have not been abrogated by the U.S. Congress;</content>
		</paragraph>
	      </paragraph>
	      
              <paragraph marker="(3)" label="1040-3-b-3">
		<content>Any person with respect to a product or service described in paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">(a)</ref> of this section that the person and any of its affiliates collectively provide to no more than 25 consumers in the current calendar year and to no more than 25 consumers in the preceding calendar year;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(4)" label="1040-3-b-4">
		<content>A merchant, retailer, or other seller of nonfinancial goods or services to the extent such person:</content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-3-b-4-i">
                  <content>Offers or provides an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section that is of the type described in 12 U.S.C. 5517(a)(2)(A)(i); and</content>
                  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-3-b-4-i-A">
                    <content>Is not subject to the Bureau's rulemaking authority under 12 U.S.C. 5517(a)(2)(B); or</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-3-b-4-i-B">
                    <content>Is subject to the Bureau's rulemaking authority only under 12 U.S.C. 5517(a)(2)(B)(i) but not 12 U.S.C. 5517(a)(2)(B)(ii) or (iii); or</content>
                  </paragraph>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-3-b-4-ii">
                  <content>Purchases or acquires an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit excluded by paragraph <ref target="1040-3-b-4-i" reftype="internal">(b)(4)(i)</ref> of this section.</content>
		</paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(5)" label="1040-3-b-5">
		<content>Any “employer” as defined in the Fair Labor Standards Act, 29 U.S.C. 203(d), to the extent it is offering or providing a product or service described in paragraph <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">(a)</ref> of this section to its employee as an employee benefit; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(6)" label="1040-3-b-6">
		<content>A person to the extent providing a product or service in circumstances where they are excluded from the Bureau's rulemaking authority including pursuant to 12 U.S.C. 5517 or 5519.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
	  
          <section label="1040-4" sectionNum="4">
            <subject>Limitations on the use of pre-dispute arbitration agreements.</subject>
            <paragraph marker="(a)" label="1040-4-a">
	      <title>Use of pre-dispute arbitration agreements in class actions</title>
	      <content></content>
	      <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-4-a-1">
		<title>General rule.</title>
		<content>A provider shall not rely in any way on a pre-dispute arbitration agreement entered into after the date set forth in § 1040.5(a) with respect to any aspect of a class action that concerns any of the consumer financial products or services covered by § 1040.3, including to seek a stay or dismissal of particular claims or the entire action, unless and until the presiding court has ruled that the case may not proceed as a class action and, if that ruling may be subject to appellate review on an interlocutory basis, the time to seek such review has elapsed or such review has been resolved such that the case cannot proceed as a class action.</content>
	      </paragraph>
              
              <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-4-a-2">
		<title>Provision required in covered pre-dispute arbitration agreements</title>
		<content>Upon entering into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref> after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>:</content>
		<paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-4-a-2-i">
                  <content>Except as provided elsewhere in this paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> or in § <ref target="1040-5-b" reftype="internal">1040.5(b)</ref>, a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall ensure that any such <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> contains the following provision: “We agree that neither we nor anyone else will rely on this agreement to stop you from being part of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> case in court. You may file a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> in court or you may be a member of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> filed by someone else.”</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-4-a-2-ii">
                  <content>When the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> applies to multiple products or services, only some of which are covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> may include the following alternative provision in place of the one required by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> of this section: “We are providing you with more than one product or service, only some of which are covered by the Arbitration Agreements Rule issued by the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Financial Protection Bureau. The following provision applies only to <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> claims concerning the products or services covered by that Rule: We agree that neither we nor anyone else will rely on this agreement to stop you from being part of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> case in court. You may file a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> in court or you may be a member of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> filed by someone else.”</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-4-a-2-iii">
                  <content>When the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> existed previously between other parties and does not contain either the provision required by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> of this section or the alternative permitted by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(ii)</ref> of this section:</content>
                  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-4-a-2-iii-A">
                    <content>The <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall either ensure the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> is amended to contain the provision specified in paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> or <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(ii)</ref> of this section or provide any <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to whom the agreement applies with the following written notice: “We agree not to rely on any <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> to stop you from being part of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> case in court. You may file a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> in court or you may be a member of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> filed by someone else.” When the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> applies to multiple products or services, only some of which are covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> may, in this written notice, include the following optional additional language: “This notice applies only to <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> claims concerning the products or services covered by the Arbitration Agreements Rule issued by the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Financial Protection Bureau.”</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-4-a-2-iii-B">
                    <content>The <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall ensure the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> is amended or provide the notice to consumers within 60 days of entering into the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>.</content>
                  </paragraph>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(iv)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv">
                  <content>A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> may add any one or more of the following sentences at the end of the disclosures required by paragraphs <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> and <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> of this section:</content>
                  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv-A">
		    <content></content>
		    <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv-A-1">
                      <content>“This provision does not apply to parties that entered into this agreement before March 19, 2018.”</content>
		    </paragraph>
		    <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv-A-2">
		      <content>“This provision does not apply to products or services first provided to you before March 19, 2018 that are subject to an arbitration agreement entered into before that date.”</content>
		    </paragraph>
                  </paragraph>
		  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv-B">
		    <content>“This provision does not apply to persons that are excluded from the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Financial Protection Bureau's Arbitration Agreements Rule.”</content>
		  </paragraph>
		  <paragraph marker="(C)" label="1040-4-a-2-iv-C">
		    <content>“This provision also applies to the delegation provision.” A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> using this sentence as part of the disclosure required by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> or <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> of this section in a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> is not required to separately insert the disclosure required by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> or <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> of this section into a delegation provision that relates to such a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>.</content>
		  </paragraph>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(v)" label="1040-4-a-2-v">
		  <content>In any provision or notice required by this paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref>, if the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> uses a standard term in the rest of the agreement to describe the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> or the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> may use that term instead of the term “we” or “you.”</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(vi)" label="1040-4-a-2-vi">
		  <content>In any provision or notice required by this paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref>, if a person has a genuine belief that sovereign immunity from suit under applicable law may apply to any person that may seek to assert the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, then the provision or notice may include, after the sentence reading “You may file a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> in court or you may be a member of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> filed by someone else,” the following language: “However, the defendants in the <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> may claim they cannot be sued due to their sovereign immunity. This provision does not create or waive any such immunity.” In the preceding sentence, the word “notice” may be substituted for the word “provision” when the included language is in a notice.</content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph marker="(vii)" label="1040-4-a-2-vii">
		  <content>A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> may provide any provision or notice required by this paragraph <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> in a language other than English if the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> also is written in that other language.</content>
		</paragraph>	
              </paragraph>
	    </paragraph>

            <paragraph marker="(b)" label="1040-4-b">
              <title>Submission of arbitral and court records</title>
              <content>For any <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref> entered into after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>, a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall comply with the requirements set forth below.</content>
              <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-4-b-1">
                <title>Records to be submitted</title>
                <content>A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall submit a copy of the following records to the Bureau, in the form and manner specified by the Bureau:</content>
                <paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-4-b-1-i">
                  <content>In connection with any claim filed in arbitration by or against the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> concerning any of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>:</content>
                  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-4-b-1-i-A">
                    <content>The initial claim and any counterclaim;</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-4-b-1-i-B">
                    <content>The answer to any initial claim and/or counterclaim, if any;</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(C)" label="1040-4-b-1-i-C">
                    <content>The <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> filed with the arbitrator or arbitration administrator;</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(D)" label="1040-4-b-1-i-D">
                    <content>The judgment or award, if any, issued by the arbitrator or arbitration administrator; and</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(E)" label="1040-4-b-1-i-E">
                    <content>If an arbitrator or arbitration administrator refuses to administer or dismisses a claim due to the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>'s failure to pay required filing or administrative fees, any communication the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> receives from the arbitrator or an arbitration administrator related to such a refusal;</content>
                  </paragraph>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-4-b-1-ii">
                  <content>Any communication the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> receives from an arbitrator or an arbitration administrator related to a determination that a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref> does not comply with the administrator's fairness principles, rules, or similar requirements, if such a determination occurs; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-4-b-1-iii">
                  <content>In connection with any case in court by or against the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> concerning any of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>:</content>
                  <paragraph marker="(A)" label="1040-4-b-1-iii-A">
                    <content>Any submission to a court that relies on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> in support of the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>'s attempt to seek dismissal, deferral, or stay of any aspect of a case; and</content>
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph marker="(B)" label="1040-4-b-1-iii-B">
                    <content>The <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> relied upon in the motion or filing.</content>
                  </paragraph>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-4-b-2">
                <title>Deadline for submission</title>
                <content>A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall submit any record required pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section within 60 days of filing by the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> of any such record with the arbitrator, arbitration administrator, or court, and within 60 days of receipt by the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> of any such record filed or sent by someone other than the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, such as the arbitration administrator, the court, or the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(3)" label="1040-4-b-3">
                <title>Redaction</title>
                <content>Prior to submission of any records pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall redact the following information:</content>
                <paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-4-b-3-i">
                  <content>Names of individuals, except for the name of the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> or the arbitrator where either is an individual;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-4-b-3-ii">
                  <content>Addresses of individuals, excluding city, State, and zip code;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-4-b-3-iii">
                  <content>Email addresses of individuals;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(iv)" label="1040-4-b-3-iv">
                  <content>Telephone numbers of individuals;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(v)" label="1040-4-b-3-v">
                  <content>Photographs of individuals;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(vi)" label="1040-4-b-3-vi">
                  <content>Account numbers;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(vii)" label="1040-4-b-3-vii">
                  <content>Social Security and tax identification numbers;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(viii)" label="1040-4-b-3-viii">
                  <content>Driver's license and other government identification numbers; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(ix)" label="1040-4-b-3-ix">
                  <content>Passport numbers.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(4)" label="1040-4-b-4">
                <title>Internet posting of arbitral and court records</title>
                <content>The Bureau shall establish and maintain on its publicly available internet site a central repository of the records that providers submit to it pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section, and such records shall be easily accessible and retrievable by the public on its internet site.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(5)" label="1040-4-b-5">
                <title>Further redaction prior to Internet posting</title>
                <content>Prior to making records identified in paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section easily accessible and retrievable by the public as required by paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-4" reftype="internal">(b)(4)</ref> of this section, the Bureau shall make such further redactions as are needed to comply with applicable privacy laws.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(6)" label="1040-4-b-6">
                <title>Deadline for internet posting of arbitral and court records</title>
                <content>The Bureau shall initially make records submitted to the Bureau by providers under paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section easily accessible and retrievable by the public on its internet site no later than July 1, 2019. The Bureau will annually make records submitted under paragraph <ref target="1040-4-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> available each year thereafter for documents received by the end of the prior calendar year.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1040-5" sectionNum="5">
            <subject>Compliance date and temporary exception.</subject>
            <paragraph marker="(a)" label="1040-5-a">
              <title>Compliance date</title>
              <content>Compliance with this part is required for any <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> entered into on or after March 19, 2018.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph marker="(b)" label="1040-5-b">
              <title>Exception for pre-packaged general-purpose reloadable prepaid card agreements</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> shall not apply to a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for a general-purpose reloadable prepaid card if the requirements set forth in either paragraphs <ref target="1040-5-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> or <ref target="1040-5-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref> of this section are satisfied.</content>
              <paragraph marker="(1)" label="1040-5-b-1">
                <content>For a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that does not have the ability to contact the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in writing:</content>
                <paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-5-b-1-i">
                  <content>The <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> acquires a general-purpose reloadable prepaid card in person at a retail store;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-5-b-1-ii">
                  <content>The <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> was inside of packaging material when the general-purpose reloadable prepaid card was acquired; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(iii)" label="1040-5-b-1-iii">
                  <content>The <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> was packaged prior to the compliance date of the rule.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph marker="(2)" label="1040-5-b-2">
                <content>For a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that has the ability to contact the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in writing:</content>
                <paragraph marker="(i)" label="1040-5-b-2-i">
                  <content>The requirements set forth in paragraphs <ref target="1040-5-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> through <ref target="1040-5-b-1-iii" reftype="internal">(iii)</ref> of this section are satisfied; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph marker="(ii)" label="1040-5-b-2-ii">
                  <content>Within 30 days of obtaining the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s contact information, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> notifies the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in writing that the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> complies with the requirements of § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> by providing an amended <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> to the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. </content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
        </content>
      </subpart>
      <interpretations label="1040-Interp">
	<title>Supplement I to Part 1040&#8212;Staff Commentary</title>
        <interpSection label="1040-2-Interp">
          <title>Section 1040.2—Definitions</title>
	  
          <interpParagraph label="1040-2-c-Interp" target="1040-2-c">
	    <title>2(c) Pre-dispute arbitration agreement.</title>
	    <content></content>
	    <interpParagraph label="1040-2-c-Interp-1" marker="1.">
	      <title>Scope of the term includes agreements with covered persons that are not providers.</title>
              <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-2-c-Interp-i">
		<content>While § <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="internal">1040.2(c)</ref> defines “<ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>” as an agreement between a covered person and a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, the rule's substantive requirements, which are contained in § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref>, apply only to “providers.” “Covered persons” as that term is defined in 12 U.S.C. 5481(6) include persons excluded from the Bureau's rulemaking authority under 12 U.S.C. 5517 and 5519. Therefore, the requirements contained in § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> would not apply to any such excluded persons entering into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> because they are not “providers,” by virtue of the definition in § <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)</ref> which excludes persons described in § <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)</ref> including its paragraph <ref target="1040-3-b-6" reftype="internal">(b)(6)</ref> (under which any person is excluded under § <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)</ref> to the extent it is not subject to the Bureau's rulemaking authority including under sections 1027 or 1029). The requirements in § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> could apply, however, to the use of any such <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> by a different person that meets the definition of <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> in § <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)</ref>, when the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> was entered into after the compliance date.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-2-c-Interp-ii">
		<content>For example, an automobile dealer that extends <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit is a covered person under 12 U.S.C. 5481(6). Its <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> would therefore fall within the scope of the definition in § <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="internal">1040.2(c)</ref>. However, an automobile dealer excluded from the Bureau's rulemaking authority in circumstances described by Dodd-Frank section 1029 would not be required to comply with the requirements in § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref>, because those requirements apply only to providers, and such dealers are excluded by § <ref target="1040-3-b-6" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(6)</ref> and therefore are not providers under § <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)</ref>. The requirements in § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> would apply, however, to the use of the automobile dealer's <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> by a different person that meets the definition of <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, such as a servicer or purchaser or acquirer of the automobile loan, when the agreement was entered into after the compliance date.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-2-c-Interp-2">
		<title>Delegation provisions</title>
		<content>The term <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> as defined in § <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="internal">1040.2(c)</ref> includes delegation provisions. Delegation provisions are agreements to arbitrate threshold issues concerning a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, and may sometimes appear elsewhere in a contract containing or relating to the arbitration agreement.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="3." label="1040-2-c-Interp-3">
		<title>Form of pre-dispute arbitration agreements</title>
		<content>A <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service includes any agreement between a covered person and a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> providing for arbitration of any future disputes between the parties concerning a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service described in § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref>, regardless of the form or structure of the agreement. Examples include a standalone <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that applies to a product or service, as well as a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that is included within, annexed to, incorporated into, or otherwise made a part of a larger agreement that governs the terms of the provision of a product or service.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

          <interpParagraph label="1040-2-d-Interp" target="1040-2-d">
	    <title>2(d) Provider.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-2-d-Interp-1">
              <title>Providers of multiple products or services.</title>
              <content>A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> as defined in § <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)</ref> that also engages in offering or providing products or services not covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref> must comply with this part only for the products or services that it offers or provides that are covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>. For example, a merchant that transmits funds for its customers as a general service, when that funds transmittal activity is not necessary to its offering or provision of products or services that are not covered by this part, would be covered pursuant to § <ref target="1040-3-a-7" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(7)</ref> with respect to the transmittal of funds. That same merchant generally would not be covered with respect to the sale of durable goods to consumers, however, except when extending <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit in certain circumstances as provided in 12 U.S.C. 5517(a)(2)(B)(ii) or (iii).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-2-d-Interp-2">
              <title>Affiliated service providers</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-2-d-2" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)(2)</ref> defines the term “<ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>” to include an affiliate of another <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> as defined in § <ref target="1040-2-d-1" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)(1)</ref> when the affiliate is acting as a service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> to the other <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> consistent with 12 U.S.C. 5481(6)(B). The rule applies to such an affiliated service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> in connection with the offering or provision of a covered <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service by the other <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, even when the affiliated service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is not itself directly engaged in offering or providing a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref>. However, even if an affiliated service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> does not meet the definition of <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> in § <ref target="1040-2-d-2" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)(2)</ref> because it provides services to a person who is excluded from the rule under § <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)</ref> and thus is not a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, the affiliated service <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> still could be a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> as defined in § <ref target="1040-2-d-1" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)(1)</ref>. For example, if an affiliate of a merchant excluded by § <ref target="1040-3-b-6" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(6)</ref> services <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit extended by the merchant, the affiliate may, in its own right, be “servicing an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by paragraph <ref target="1040-2-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section” as discussed in § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-v" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(v)</ref>. As a result, the affiliate servicer may meet the definition of <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> in § <ref target="1040-2-d-1" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)(1)</ref> even though the merchant is not a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpSection>
	
        <interpSection label="1040-3-Interp">
          <title>Section 1040.3—Coverage and Exclusions From Coverage</title>
	  
          <interpParagraph marker="(a)" label="1040-3-a-Interp" target="1040-3-a">
	    <title>3(a) Covered products and services.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-Interp-1">
              <content>Consumer financial products or services pursuant to 12 U.S.C. 5481(5).Section <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> provides that the products or services listed therein are covered by part 1040 when they are <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services as defined by 12 U.S.C. 5481(5). Products or services generally meet this definition in either of two ways: They are offered or provided for use by consumers primarily for personal, family, or household purposes, or they are delivered, offered, or provided in connection with the first type of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services. An example of the second type of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service is debt collection, when the underlying loan that is the subject of collection is a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-3-a-Interp-2">
              <title>Mobile phone applications and online access tools</title>
              <content>If a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> of a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by this part offers or provides a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> a technological means for accessing information about that product or service, such as a mobile phone application or an internet Web site, this part shall apply to the application or internet Web site as it concerns that product or service.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-1-iii-Interp" target="1040-3-a-1-iii">
	    <title>Paragraph (a)(1)(iii)</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-1-iii-Interp-1">
              <title>Offering or providing creditor referral or selection services.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(iii)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 providing referrals or selecting or offering to select creditors for <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit consistent with the meaning in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2-l" reftype="internal">1002.2(l)</ref> by a creditor as defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2-l" reftype="internal">1002.2(l)</ref>. Section <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(iii)</ref> does not apply when such a creditor's referral or selection activity is incidental to its business activity not covered by this section.See§ <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii-C" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(iii)(C)</ref>. For example, a merchant may regularly and in the ordinary course of its business provide creditor referrals or selection services to help a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> pay for nonfinancial goods or services sold by that merchant. By virtue of such activities, such a merchant may be a creditor as defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1002-2-l" reftype="internal">1002.2(l)</ref>. Nonetheless, such a merchant would not be covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-iii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(iii)</ref> because its creditor referral or selection services are incidental to its sale of goods or services not covered by this section.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>
	  
	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-1-v-Interp" target="1040-3-a-1-v">
	    <title>Paragraph (a)(1)(v)</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-1-v-Interp-1">
              <title>Servicing of credit</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-1-v" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(v)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 servicing of extensions of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(i)</ref>. Servicing of extensions of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit includes, but is not limited to, student loan servicing as defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1090-106" reftype="internal">1090.106</ref> and mortgage loan servicing as defined in 12 CFR <ref target="1024-2-b" reftype="internal">1024.2(b)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-3-i-Interp" target="1040-3-a-3-i">
	    <title>Paragraph (a)(3)(i)</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-3-i-Interp-1">
              <title>Debt relief products and services</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-3-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(3)(i)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 services that offer to renegotiate, settle, or modify the terms of a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s debt. Providers of these services would be covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a-3-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(3)(i)</ref> regardless of the source of the debt, including but not limited to when seeking to relieve consumers of a debt that does not arise from a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit transaction as described by § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(i)</ref> or from a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service more generally.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-3-ii-Interp" target="1040-3-a-3-ii">
	    <title>Paragraph (a)(3)(ii)</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-3-ii-Interp-1">
              <title>Credit repair products or services</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-3-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(3)(ii)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 products or services represented to remove derogatory information from, or improve, a person's credit history, credit record, or credit rating. The description of these products and services in § <ref target="1040-3-a-3-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(3)(ii)</ref> is generally based upon the coverage of credit repair goods or services in regulations implementing 15 U.S.C. 6101et seq.,codified at 16 CFR <ref target="310-4-a-2" reftype="internal">310.4(a)(2)</ref>. However, part 1040 also would apply even if such credit repair goods or services would not be covered under the regulations implementing 15 U.S.C. 6101et seq.,codified at 16 CFR <ref target="310-4-a-2" reftype="internal">310.4(a)(2)</ref>, solely because they were not the subject of telemarketing as defined in 16 CFR <ref target="310-2-gg" reftype="internal">310.2(gg)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-8-Interp" target="1040-3-a-8">
	    <title>Paragraph 3(a)(8).</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-8-Interp-1">
              <title>Credit card and charge card transactions</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-8" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(8)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 certain payment processing activities involving the initiation of credit card or charge card transactions. The terms “credit card” and “charge card” are defined in Regulation Z, 12 CFR <ref target="1026-2-a-15" reftype="internal">1026.2(a)(15)</ref>. For purposes of § <ref target="1040-3-a-8" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(8)</ref>, those definitions in Regulation Z apply.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

	  <interpParagraph label="1040-3-a-10-Interp" target="1040-3-a-10">
	    <title>Paragraph (a)(10)</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-a-10-Interp-1">
              <title>Collection of debt by the same person arising from covered and noncovered products and services</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-3-a-10-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(10)(i)</ref> includes in the coverage of part 1040 the collection of debt by a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that arises from its providing any of the products and services described in paragraphs <ref target="1040-3-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> through <ref target="1040-3-a-9" reftype="internal">(9)</ref> of § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>, including, for example, an extension of <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit described in § <ref target="1040-3-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)</ref>. If the person collecting such debt also collects other debt that does not arise from any of the products and services described in paragraphs <ref target="1040-3-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> through <ref target="1040-3-a-9" reftype="internal">(9)</ref> of § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>, the collection of that other debt is not included in the coverage of § <ref target="1040-3-a-10-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(10)(i)</ref>. For example, if a creditor extended <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit to consumers and business credit to other persons, § <ref target="1040-3-a-10-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(10)(i)</ref> would include in the coverage of part 1040 the collection of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit but not the collection of the business credit. Similarly, if a debt buyer purchases a portfolio of credit card debt that includes both <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and business debt, § <ref target="1040-3-a-10-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(10)(ii)</ref> would include in the coverage of part 1040 only the collection of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit card debt.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-3-a-10-Interp-2">
              <title>Collection of debt by affiliates.</title>
              <content>Paragraphs <ref target="1040-3-a-10-i" reftype="internal">(a)(10)(i)</ref> and <ref target="1040-3-a-10-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> of § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref> cover certain collection activities not only by providers themselves, but also by their affiliates. The term “affiliate” is defined in 12 U.S.C. 5481(1) as any person that controls, or is controlled by, or is under common control with another person.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>

          <interpParagraph label="1040-3-b-Interp">
	    <title>3(b) Excluded Persons.</title>
            <content></content>
	    <interpParagraph label="1040-3-b-2-ii-Interp" target="1040-3-b-2-ii">
	      <title>Paragraph (b)(2)(ii).</title>
	      <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-b-2-ii-Interp-1">
		<title>Exclusion for States under Federal sovereign immunity law</title>
		<content>Section <ref target="1043-3-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1043.3(b)(2)(ii)</ref> excludes States and other persons to the extent they would be an arm of the State under Federal sovereign immunity law and their immunity has not been abrogated by the U.S. Congress. For purposes of this rule, the term State includes any State, territory, or possession of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the U.S. Virgin Islands.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-3-b-2-ii-Interp-2">
		<title>Exclusion for Tribes under Federal sovereign immunity law</title>
		<content>Section <ref target="1040-3-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(2)(ii)</ref> excludes Tribes and other persons to the extent that they would be an arm of a Tribe under Federal sovereign immunity law and their immunity has not been abrogated by the U.S. Congress. For purposes of this exclusion, the term “Tribe” refers to any federally recognized Indian Tribe, as defined by the Secretary of the Interior under section 104(a) of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994, 25 U.S.C. 479a-1(a).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	    </interpParagraph>

	    <interpParagraph label="1040-3-b-3-Interp" target="1040-3-b-3">
	      <title>Paragraph (b)(3).</title>
	      <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-b-3-Interp-1">
		<title>Including consumers to whom affiliates provide a product or service toward the numerical threshold for exemption of a person under § 1040.3(b)(3).</title>
		<content>Section <ref target="1040-3-b-3" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(3)</ref> provides an exclusion to persons providing a product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> if no more than 25 consumers are provided the product or service in the current and prior calendar years by the person and its affiliates. The exclusion applies based on the frequency with which the product is provided, regardless of the number of times a product is offered. Note, however, that participating in a credit decision with regard to <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit in circumstances described in § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(ii)</ref>, for example, constitutes providing a product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref>, even if an application for <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit is denied. In addition, for purposes of this test, the number of consumers to whom affiliates of a person provide a product or service is combined with the number of consumers to whom the person itself provides that product or service. The term “affiliate” is defined in 12 U.S.C. 5481(1) as any person that controls, or is controlled by, or is under common control with another person.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-3-b-3-Interp-2">
		<title>Effect of exceeding the numerical threshold for the exemption</title>
		<content>If, during a calendar year, a person to that point excluded by § <ref target="1040-3-b-3" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(3)</ref> for a given product or service described in § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> provides that product or service to a 26th <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, then that person ceases to be eligible for this exclusion at that time with respect to that product or service. The <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> must begin complying with this part with respect to the covered product or service provided to that 26th <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. In addition, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> will not be eligible for the exclusion in § <ref target="1040-3-b-3" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(3)</ref> whenever it offers or provides that product or service for the remainder of that calendar year and the following calendar year.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	    </interpParagraph>

	    <interpParagraph label="1040-3-b-4-Interp" target="1040-3-b-4">
	      <title>Paragraph 3(b)(4)</title>
	      <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-b-4-Interp-1">
		<title>Exemption for merchants who purchase or acquire consumer credit from other merchants who are exempt</title>
		<content>Section <ref target="1040-3-b-4-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(4)(ii)</ref> provides an exemption for a merchant who purchases or acquires <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit from another merchant when the merchant from whom the credit is being purchased or acquired is exempt under § <ref target="1040-3-b-4-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(4)(i)</ref>. This exemption in § <ref target="1040-3-b-4-ii" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(4)(ii)</ref> applies not only to the purchase or acquisition itself, but also to any servicing or collection activities by the merchant purchaser or acquirer.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	    </interpParagraph>

	    <interpParagraph label="1040-3-b-5-Interp" target="1040-3-b-5">
	      <title>Paragraph 3(b)(5)</title>
	      <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-3-b-Interp-1">
		<title>Exemption for employers providing employee benefits</title>
		<content>Section <ref target="1040-3-b-5" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(5)</ref> provides an exemption for an employer to the extent it is offering or providing a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service to an employee as an employee benefit. If an employer offers or provides a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> to an employee on terms and conditions that the employer makes available to the general public, such product or service is not an employee benefit for purposes of § <ref target="1040-3-b-5" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(5)</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	    </interpParagraph>
	    
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpSection>
        <interpSection label="1040-4-Interp">
          <title>Section 1040.4—Limitations on the Use of Pre-Dispute Arbitration Agreements</title>

	  <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-Interp-1">
	    <title>Enters into a pre-dispute arbitration agreement.</title>
	    <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-4-Interp-1-i">
              <content>Examples of when a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for purposes of § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> include but are not limited to when the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>:</content>
	      <interpParagraph marker="A." label="1040-4-Interp-1-i-A">
		<content>Provides to a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>, a new product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> that is subject to a pre-existing agreement to arbitrate future disputes between the parties, and the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is a party to that agreement, regardless of whether that agreement predates the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>. When that agreement predates the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>, § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> applies only with respect to any such new product or service;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	      <interpParagraph marker="B." label="1040-4-Interp-1-i-B">
		<content>Acquires or purchases after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> a product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)</ref> that is subject to a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> and becomes a party to that <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, even if the seller is excluded from coverage under § <ref target="1040-3-b" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)</ref> or the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> was entered into before the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>; or</content>
              </interpParagraph>
	      <interpParagraph marker="C." label="1040-4-Interp-1-i-C">
		<content>Adds a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> to an existing product or service.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>

            <interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-4-Interp-1-ii">
              <content>Examples of when a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> does not enter into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for purposes of § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> include but are not limited to when the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>:</content>
	      <interpParagraph marker="A." label="1040-4-Interp-1-ii-A">
		<content>Modifies, amends, or implements the terms of a product or service that is subject to a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> without engaging in the conduct described in comment 4-1.i after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>. However, a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> does enter into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for purposes of § <ref target="1040-4" reftype="internal">1040.4</ref> when the modification, amendment, or implementation constitutes the provision of a new product or service. See comment 4-1.i<ref target="1040-4-Interp-1-i-A" reftype="internal">(A)</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="B." label="1040-4-Interp-1-ii-B">
		<content>Acquires or purchases a product or service that is subject to a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> but does not become a party to the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that applies to the product or service.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

          <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-Interp-2">
	    <title>Application of section 1040.4 to providers that do not enter into pre-dispute arbitration agreements.</title>
	    <content></content>
	    <interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-4-Interp-2-i">
              <content>Pursuant to § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref>, a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that has not entered into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> cannot rely on any <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> entered into by another person after the compliance date specified in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> with respect to any aspect of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> concerning a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial product or service covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>. In addition, pursuant to § <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is required to submit certain specified records concerning claims filed in arbitration pursuant to such pre-dispute arbitration agreements. However, as discussed in comment 4<ref target="1040-4-a-2-Interp-1" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref>-1, § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> does not apply to providers that do not enter into pre-dispute arbitration agreements.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-4-Interp-2-ii">
              <content>For example, when a debt collector collecting on <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> credit covered by § <ref target="1040-3-a-1-i" reftype="internal">1040.3(a)(1)(i)</ref> has not entered into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> nevertheless prohibits the debt collector from relying on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> entered into by the creditor after the compliance date specified in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> with respect to any aspect of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> filed against the debt collector concerning its debt collection products or services covered by section § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>. The debt collector in this example is subject to § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> even if the creditor was a merchant, government, or other person who was excluded from coverage by § <ref target="1040-3-b-5" reftype="internal">1040.3(b)(5)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>

          <interpParagraph label="1040-4-a-Interp">
	    <title>4(a) Use of pre-dispute arbitration agreements in class actions.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph label="1040-4-a-1-Interp" target="1040-4-a-1">
	      <title>Paragraph 4(a)(1) General rule.</title>
              <content></content>
	      <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1">
		<title>Reliance on pre-dispute arbitration agreement.</title>
		<content></content>
		<interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i">
                  <title>Examples of conduct that constitutes reliance</title>
                  <content>Sections <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1040-4-Interp-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref> both use the term “rely on.” For purposes of these provisions, reliance on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> includes, but is not limited to, doing any of the following on the basis of a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>:</content>
		  <interpParagraph marker="A." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-A">
                    <content>Seeking dismissal, deferral, or stay of any aspect of a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref>;</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		  <interpParagraph marker="B." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-B">
                    <content>Seeking to exclude a person or persons from a class in a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref>;</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		  <interpParagraph marker="C." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-C">
                    <content>Objecting to or seeking a protective order intended to avoid responding to discovery in a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref>;</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		  <interpParagraph marker="D." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-D">
                    <content>Filing a claim in arbitration against a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who has filed a claim on the same issue in a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref>;</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		  <interpParagraph marker="E." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-E">
                    <content>Filing a claim in arbitration against a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who has filed a claim on the same issue in a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> after the trial court has denied a motion to certify the class but before an appellate court has ruled on an interlocutory appeal of that motion, if the time to seek such an appeal has not elapsed or the appeal has not been resolved; and</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		  <interpParagraph marker="F." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-1-i-F">
                    <content>Filing a claim in arbitration against a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who has filed a claim on the same issue in a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> after the trial court in that <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> has granted a motion to dismiss the claim and, in doing so, the court noted that the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has leave to refile the claim on a class basis, if the time to refile the claim has not elapsed.</content>
		  </interpParagraph>
		</interpParagraph>
		
		<interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-ii">
                  <title>Example of conduct that does not constitute reliance</title>
                  <content>Reliance on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for purposes of § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1040-4-Interp-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref> does not include, among other things, a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> defendant seeking or taking steps to preserve the defendant's ability to seek arbitration after the trial court has denied a motion to certify the class and either an appellate court has affirmed that decision on an interlocutory appeal of that motion, or the time to seek such an appeal has elapsed.</content>
		</interpParagraph>
	      </interpParagraph>
	    </interpParagraph>
		
	    <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-2">
              <title>Protected petitioning conduct</title>
              <content>A <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> defendant does not violate § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> by relying on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> where it has a genuine belief that it is not subject to this part. For example, a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> defendant does not violate § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> by relying on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> where it has a genuine belief either that it is not covered by the rule because it is not a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> pursuant to § <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="internal">1040.2(d)</ref>, or that none of the claims asserted in the <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> concern any of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services covered pursuant to § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>.</content>
	    </interpParagraph>

	    <interpParagraph marker="3." label="1040-4-a-1-Interp-3">
              <title>Class actions concerning multiple products or services</title>
              <content>In a <ref target="1040-2-a" reftype="term">class action</ref> concerning multiple products or services only some of which are covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>, the prohibition in § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref> applies only to claims that concern the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>.</content>
	    </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>
			      
          <interpParagraph label="1040-4-a-2-Interp" target="1040-4-a-2">
	    <title>Paragraph 4(a)(2) Required provision.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-a-2-Interp-1">
              <content>Application of section <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> to providers that do not enter into pre-dispute arbitration agreements.Section <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> sets forth requirements only for providers that enter into pre-dispute arbitration agreements for a covered product or service after the compliance date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>. Accordingly, the requirements of § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> do not apply to a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that does not enter into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> with a <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-a-2-Interp-2">
              <title>Entering into a pre-dispute arbitration agreement that had existed previously between other parties</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-a-2-iii" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(iii)</ref> requires a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that had existed previously as between other parties and does not contain the provision required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(i)</ref> or <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> to ensure the agreement is amended to contain either of those provisions, as applicable, or to provide a written notice to any <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to whom the agreement applies. This could occur, when, for example, Bank A is acquiring Bank B after the compliance date specified in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>, and Bank B had entered into pre-dispute arbitration agreements before the compliance date specified in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref>. If, as part of the acquisition, Bank A enters into the pre-dispute arbitration agreements of Bank B, Bank A would be required either to ensure the account agreements were amended to contain the provision required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(i)</ref> or the alternative permitted by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(ii)</ref>, or to provide the notice specified in § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(iii)(B)</ref>. See comment 4-1 for examples of when a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="3." label="1040-4-a-2-Interp-3">
              <title>Notice to consumers</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-a-2-iii" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(iii)</ref> requires a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that does not contain the provision required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(i)</ref> or <ref target="1040-4-a-2-ii" reftype="internal">(ii)</ref> to either ensure the agreement is amended to contain a specified provision or to provide any consumers to whom the agreement applies with written notice. The notice may be provided in any way that the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> communicates with the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, including electronically. The notice may be provided either as a standalone document or included in another notice that the customer receives, such as a periodic statement, to the extent permitted by other laws and regulations.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="4." label="1040-4-a-2-Interp-4">
              <title>Contract provision for a delegation provision</title>
              <content>If a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> has included in its <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> the language required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref>, and the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>'s <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> contains a delegation provision, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> must also separately insert the language required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> into the delegation provision, except under § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-iv-C" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(iv)(C)</ref>. Under § <ref target="1040-4-a-2-iv-C" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)(iv)(C)</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> need not also include the language required by § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> within a separate delegation provision</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
	    
          <interpParagraph label="1040-4-b-Interp" target="1040-4-b">
	    <title>4(b) Submission of arbitral records</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-b-Interp-1">
              <title>Submission by entities other than providers</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref> requires providers to submit specified arbitral and court records to the Bureau. Providers are not required to submit the records themselves if they arrange for another person, such as an arbitration administrator or an agent of the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, to submit the records on the providers' behalf. The obligation to comply with § <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref> nevertheless remains on the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, and thus the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> must ensure that the person submits the records in accordance with § <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-b-Interp-2">
              <title>Redaction by entities other than providers</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-b-3" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)(3)</ref> requires providers to redact records before submitting them to the Bureau. Providers are not required to perform the redactions themselves and may arrange for another person, such as an arbitration administrator, or an agent of the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>, to redact the records. The obligation to comply with § <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref> nevertheless remains on the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> and thus the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> must ensure that the person redacts the records in accordance with § <ref target="1040-4-b" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>

          <interpParagraph label="1040-4-b-1-Interp">
	    <title>Paragraph 4(b)(1) Records to be submitted.</title>
            <content></content>
	    <interpParagraph label="1040-b-1-ii-Interp" target="1040-b-1-ii">
	      <title>Paragraph 4(b)(1)(ii)</title>
	      <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-b-1-ii-Interp-1">
                <title>Determinations that a pre-dispute arbitration agreement does not comply with an arbitration administrator's fairness principles</title>
                <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)(1)(ii)</ref> requires submission to the Bureau of any communication the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> receives related to any arbitration administrator's determination that the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>'s <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> entered into after the date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> does not comply with the administrator's fairness principles or rules. The submission of such records is required both when the determination occurs in connection with the filing of a claim in arbitration as well as when it occurs if no claim has been filed. However, when the determination occurs with respect to a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> that the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> has not entered into with any consumers, submission of any communication related to that determination is not required. For example, if the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> submits a prototype <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> for review by the arbitration administrator and never includes it in any <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> agreements, the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> would not be entered into and thus submission to the Bureau of communication related to a determination made by the administrator concerning the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> would not be required.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-b-1-ii-Interp-2">
                <title>Examples of fairness principles, rules, or similar requirements</title>
                <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)(1)(ii)</ref> requires submission to the Bureau of records related to any administrator's determination that a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref>'s <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> violates the administrator's fairness principles, rules, or similar requirements. What constitutes an administrator's fairness principles, rules, or similar requirements should be interpreted broadly. Examples of such principles or rules include, but are not limited to:</content>
		<interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-4-b-1-ii-Interp-2-i">
                  <content>The American Arbitration Association's <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Due Process Protocol; or</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-4-b-1-ii-Interp-2-ii">
                  <content>JAMS Policy on <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Arbitrations Pursuant to Pre-Dispute Clauses Minimum Standards of Procedural Fairness.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            
            <interpParagraph label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp" target="1040-4-b-1-iii">
	      <title>Paragraph 4(b)(1)(iii).</title>
              <content></content>
              <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp-1">
                <title>Reliance on a pre-dispute arbitration agreement</title>
                <content>Section <ref target="1040-4-b-1-iii" reftype="internal">1040.4(b)(1)(iii)</ref> requires that a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> shall submit to the Bureau certain submissions in court that rely on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> entered into after the compliance date set forth in § <ref target="1040-5-a" reftype="internal">1040.5(a)</ref> with respect to certain aspects of a case concerning any of the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial products or services covered by § <ref target="1040-3" reftype="internal">1040.3</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph marker="2." label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp-2">
                <content>A submission does not rely on a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, for purposes of § 1040<ref target="1040-4-b-1-iii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(iii)</ref>, if it:</content>
		<interpParagraph marker="i." label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp-2-i">
                  <content>Objects to or seeks a protective order intended to avoid responding to discovery;</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph marker="ii." label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp-2-ii">
                  <content>Is only referred to in an answer to a complaint or a counterclaim; or</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph marker="iii." label="1040-4-b-1-iii-Interp-2-iii">
                  <content>Is only incidentally part of an attachment to a submission. For instance, if a motion attaches the entire <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> financial contract, including the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, but the motion does not cite or rely on the <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is not required to submit the motion to the Bureau.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>

            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>

        </interpSection>
        <interpSection label="1040-5-Interp">
          <title>Section 1040.5—Compliance Date and Temporary Exception</title>
          <interpParagraph label="1040-5-b-Interp" target="1040-5-b">
	    <title>5(b) Exception for pre-packaged general-purpose reloadable prepaid card agreements.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-5-b-Interp-1">
	      <title>Application of § 1040.4(a)(1) to providers of general-purpose reloadable prepaid card agreements.</title>
              <content>Where § <ref target="1040-4-a-2" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(2)</ref> does not apply to a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that enters into a <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> on or after the compliance date by virtue of the temporary exception in § <ref target="1040-5-b-2" reftype="internal">1040.5(b)(2)</ref>, the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> must still comply with § <ref target="1040-4-a-1" reftype="internal">1040.4(a)(1)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
	  </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1040-5-b-2-Interp" target="1040-5-b-2">
	    <title>Paragraph 5(b)(2).</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1040-5-b-2-Interp-1">
              <title>Examples</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1040-5-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1040.5(b)(2)(ii)</ref> requires a <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> that has the ability to contact the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in writing to provide an amended <ref target="1040-2-c" reftype="term">pre-dispute arbitration agreement</ref> to the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in writing within 30 days after the issuer has the ability to contact the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. A <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> is able to contact the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> when, for example, the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref> registers the card and gives the <ref target="1040-2-d" reftype="term">provider</ref> the <ref target="1040-2-b" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s mailing address or email address.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpSection>
      </interpretations>
    </content>
  </part>
</regulation>
