<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<regulation xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2011-07-28</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>RULES RELATING TO INVESTIGATIONS</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1080</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2011-19035</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2011-07-28</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2011/07/28/2011-19035/rules-relating-to-investigations</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <part label="1080">
    <tableOfContents>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-1">
        <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.1 Scope.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-2">
        <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-3">
        <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.3 Policy as to private controversies.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-4">
        <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.4 Initiating and conducting investigations.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-5">
        <sectionNum>5</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.5 Notification of purpose.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-6">
        <sectionNum>6</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.6 Civil investigative demands.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-7">
        <sectionNum>7</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.7 Investigational hearings.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-8">
        <sectionNum>8</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.8 Withholding requested material.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-9">
        <sectionNum>9</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.9 Rights of witnesses in investigations.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-10">
        <sectionNum>10</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.10 Noncompliance with civil investigative demands.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-11">
        <sectionNum>11</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.11 Disposition.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-12">
        <sectionNum>12</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.12 Orders requiring witnesses to testify or provide other information and granting immunity.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-13">
        <sectionNum>13</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.13 Custodians.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1080-14">
        <sectionNum>14</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1080.14 Confidential treatment of demand material and non-public nature of investigations.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
    </tableOfContents>
    <content>
      <subpart label="1080-Subpart">
        <tableOfContents label="1080-Subpart-TOC">
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-1">
            <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.1 Scope.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-2">
            <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-3">
            <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.3 Policy as to private controversies.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-4">
            <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.4 Initiating and conducting investigations.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-5">
            <sectionNum>5</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.5 Notification of purpose.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-6">
            <sectionNum>6</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.6 Civil investigative demands.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-7">
            <sectionNum>7</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.7 Investigational hearings.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-8">
            <sectionNum>8</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.8 Withholding requested material.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-9">
            <sectionNum>9</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.9 Rights of witnesses in investigations.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-10">
            <sectionNum>10</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.10 Noncompliance with civil investigative demands.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-11">
            <sectionNum>11</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.11 Disposition.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-12">
            <sectionNum>12</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.12 Orders requiring witnesses to testify or provide other information and granting immunity.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-13">
            <sectionNum>13</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.13 Custodians.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1080-14">
            <sectionNum>14</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1080.14 Confidential treatment of demand material and non-public nature of investigations.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
        </tableOfContents>
        <content>
          <section label="1080-1" sectionNum="1">
            <subject>§ 1080.1 Scope.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-1-p1" marker="">
              <content>The rules of this part apply to Bureau investigations conducted pursuant to section 1052 of the Dodd-Frank Act, 12 U.S.C. 5562.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-2" sectionNum="2">
            <subject>§ 1080.2 Definitions.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-a" marker="">
              <content>For the purposes of this part, unless explicitly stated to the contrary:</content> 
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-b" marker="">
              <content><def term="bureau">Bureau</def> means the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-c" marker="">
              <content><def term="bureau investigation">Bureau investigation</def> means any inquiry conducted by a Bureau investigator for the purpose of ascertaining whether any person is or has been engaged in any conduct that is a violation.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-d" marker="">
              <content><def term="bureau investigator">Bureau investigator</def> means any attorney or investigator employed by the Bureau who is charged with the duty of enforcing or carrying into effect any Federal consumer financial law.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-e" marker="">
              <content><def term="custodian">Custodian</def> means the custodian or any deputy custodian designated by the Bureau for the purpose of maintaining custody of information produced pursuant to this part.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-f" marker="">
              <content><def term="director">Director</def> means the Director of the Bureau or a person authorized to perform the functions of the Director in accordance with the law.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-g" marker="">
              <content><def term="documentary material">Documentary material</def> means the original or any copy of any book, document, record, report, memorandum, paper, communication, tabulation, chart, log, electronic file, or other data or data compilation stored in any medium, including electronically stored information.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-h" marker="">
              <content><def term="dodd-frank act">Dodd-Frank Act</def> means the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010, as amended, Public Law 111-203 (July 21, 2010), title X, codified at 12 U.S.C. 5481 et seq.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-i" marker="">
              <content><def term="electronically stored information">Electronically stored information</def> (ESI) means any information stored in any electronic medium from which information can be obtained either directly or, if necessary, after translation by the responding party into a reasonably usable form.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-j" marker="">
              <content><def term="office of enforcement">Office of Enforcement</def> means the office of the Bureau responsible for enforcement of Federal consumer financial law.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-k" marker="">
              <content><def term="person">Person</def> means an individual, partnership, company, corporation, association (incorporated or unincorporated), trust, estate, cooperative organization, or other entity.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-2-l" marker="">
              <content><def term="violation">Violation</def> means any act or omission that, if proved, would constitute a violation of any provision of Federal consumer financial law.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-3" sectionNum="3">
            <subject>§ 1080.3 Policy as to private controversies.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-3-p1" marker="">
              <content>The Bureau shall act only in the public interest and will not initiate an investigation or take other enforcement action when the alleged violation is merely a matter of private controversy and does not tend to affect adversely the public interest.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-4" sectionNum="4">
            <subject>§ 1080.4 Initiating and conducting investigations.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-4-p1" marker="">
              <content>The Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement have the nondelegable authority to initiate investigations. Bureau investigations are conducted by Bureau investigators designated and duly authorized under section 1052 of the Dodd-Frank Act, 12 U.S.C. 5562, to conduct such investigations. Bureau investigators are authorized to exercise and perform their duties in accordance with the laws of the United States and the regulations of the Bureau.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-5" sectionNum="5">
            <subject>§ 1080.5 Notification of purpose.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-5-p1" marker="">
              <content>Any person compelled to furnish documentary material, tangible things, written reports or answers to questions, oral testimony, or any combination of such material, answers, or testimony to the Bureau shall be advised of the nature of the conduct constituting the alleged violation that is under investigation and the provisions of law applicable to such violation.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-6" sectionNum="6">
            <subject>§ 1080.6 Civil investigative demands.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-a" marker="(a)">
              <title>In general.</title>
              <content>In accordance with section 1052(c) of <ref target="USC:12-1080" reftype="external">the Act</ref>, the Director of the Bureau, the Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement, and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement, have the nondelegable authority to issue a civil investigative demand in any Bureau investigation directing the person named therein to produce documentary material for inspection and copying or reproduction in the form or medium requested by the Bureau; to submit tangible things; to provide a written report or answers to questions; to appear before a designated representative at a designated time and place to testify about documentary material, tangible things, or other information; and to furnish any combination of such material, things, answers, or testimony.</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-a-1" marker="(1)">
                <title type="keyterm">Documentary material.</title>
                <content/>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>Civil investigative demands for the production of documentary material shall describe each class of material to be produced with such definiteness and certainty as to permit such material to be fairly identified, prescribe a return date or dates that will provide a reasonable period of time within which the material so demanded may be assembled and made available for inspection and copying or reproduction, and identify the custodian to whom such material shall be made available. Documentary material for which a civil investigative demand has been issued shall be made available as prescribed in the civil investigative demand.</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>Production of documentary material in response to a civil investigative demand shall be made under a sworn certificate, in such form as the demand designates, by the person to whom the demand is directed or, if not a natural person, by any person having knowledge of the facts and circumstances relating to such production, to the effect that all of the documentary material required by the demand and in the possession, custody, or control of the person to whom the demand is directed has been produced and made available to the custodian.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-a-2" marker="(2)">
                <title type="keyterm">Tangible things.</title>
                <content/>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>Civil investigative demands for tangible things shall describe each class of tangible things to be produced with such definiteness and certainty as to permit such things to be fairly identified, prescribe a return date or dates which will provide a reasonable period of time within which the things so demanded may be assembled and submitted, and identify the custodian to whom such things shall be submitted.</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>Submissions of tangible things in response to a civil investigative demand shall be made under a sworn certificate, in such form as the demand designates, by the person to whom the demand is directed or, if not a natural person, by any person having knowledge of the facts and circumstances relating to such production, to the effect that all of the tangible things required by the demand and in the possession, custody, or control of the person to whom the demand is directed have been submitted to the custodian.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-a-3" marker="(3)">
                <title type="keyterm">Written reports or answers to questions.</title>
                <content/>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-3-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>Civil investigative demands for written reports or answers to questions shall propound with definiteness and certainty the reports to be produced or the questions to be answered, prescribe a date or dates at which time written reports or answers to questions shall be submitted, and identify the custodian to whom such reports or answers shall be submitted.</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>Each reporting requirement or question in a civil investigative demand shall be answered separately and fully in writing under oath. Responses to a civil investigative demand for a written report or answers to questions shall be made under a sworn certificate, in such form as the demand designates, by the person to whom the demand is directed or, if not a natural person, by any person responsible for answering each reporting requirement or question, to the effect that all of the information required by the demand and in the possession, custody, control, or knowledge of the person to whom the demand is directed has been submitted to the custodian.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-a-4" marker="(4)">
                <title type="keyterm">Oral testimony.</title>
                <content/>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-4-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>Civil investigative demands for the giving of oral testimony shall prescribe a date, time, and place at which oral testimony shall be commenced, and identify a Bureau investigator who shall conduct the investigation and the custodian to whom the transcript of such investigation shall be submitted. Oral testimony in response to a civil investigative demand shall be taken in accordance with the procedures for investigational hearings prescribed by §§ 1080.7 and 1080.9 of this part.</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-6-a-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>Where a civil investigative demand requires oral testimony from an entity, the civil investigative demand shall describe with reasonable particularity the matters for examination and the entity must designate one or more officers, directors, or managing agents, or designate other persons who consent to testify on its behalf. Unless a single individual is designated by the entity, the entity must designate the matters on which each designee will testify. The individuals designated must testify about information known or reasonably available to the entity and their testimony shall be binding on the entity.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-b" marker="(b)">
              <title type="keyterm">Manner and form of production of ESI.</title>
              <content>When a civil investigative demand requires the production of ESI, it shall be produced in accordance with the instructions provided by the Bureau regarding the manner and form of production. Absent any instructions as to the form for producing ESI, ESI must be produced in the form in which it is ordinarily maintained or in a reasonably usable form.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-c" marker="(c)">
              <title type="keyterm">Meet and confer.</title>
              <content>The recipient of a civil investigative demand shall meet and confer with a Bureau investigator within 10 calendar days after receipt of the demand or before the deadline for filing a petition to modify or set aside the demand, whichever is earlier, to discuss and attempt to resolve all issues regarding compliance with the civil investigative demand. The Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement may authorize the waiver of this requirement for routine third-party civil investigative demands or in other circumstances where he or she determines that a meeting is unnecessary. The meeting may be in person or by telephone.</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <title type="keyterm">Personnel.</title>
                <content>The recipient must make available at the meeting personnel with the knowledge necessary to resolve any issues relevant to compliance with the demand. Such personnel could include individuals knowledgeable about the recipient's information or records management systems and/or the recipient's organizational structure.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <title type="keyterm">ESI.</title>
                <content>If the civil investigative demand seeks ESI, the recipient shall ensure that a person familiar with its ESI systems and methods of retrieval participates in the meeting.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-c-3" marker="(3)">
                <title type="keyterm">Petitions.</title>
                <content>The Bureau will not consider petitions to set aside or modify a civil investigative demand unless the recipient has meaningfully engaged in the meet and confer process described in this subsection and will consider only issues raised during the meet and confer process.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-d" marker="(d)">
              <title type="keyterm">Compliance.</title>
              <content>The Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement are authorized to negotiate and approve the terms of satisfactory compliance with civil investigative demands and, for good cause shown, may extend the time prescribed for compliance.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-e" marker="(e)">
              <title type="keyterm">Petition for order modifying or setting aside demand—in general.</title>
              <content>Any petition for an order modifying or setting aside a civil investigative demand shall be filed with the Executive Secretary of the Bureau with a copy to the Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement within 20 calendar days after service of the civil investigative demand, or, if the return date is less than 20 calendar days after service, prior to the return date. Such petition shall set forth all factual and legal objections to the civil investigative demand, including all appropriate arguments, affidavits, and other supporting documentation. The attorney who objects to a demand must sign any objections.</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-e-1" marker="(1)">
                <title type="keyterm">Statement.</title>
                <content>Each petition shall be accompanied by a signed statement representing that counsel for the petitioner has conferred with counsel for the Bureau pursuant to section <ref target="1080-6-c" reftype="internal">1080.6(c)</ref> in a good-faith effort to resolve by agreement the issues raised by the petition and has been unable to reach such an agreement. If some of the matters in controversy have been resolved by agreement, the statement shall specify the matters so resolved and the matters remaining unresolved. The statement shall recite the date, time, and place of each such meeting between counsel, and the names of all parties participating in each such meeting.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-e-2" marker="(2)">
                <title type="keyterm">Extensions of time.</title>
                <content>The Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement are authorized to rule upon requests for extensions of time within which to file such petitions. Requests for extensions of time are disfavored.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-e-3" marker="(3)">
                <title>Bureau investigator response.</title>
                <content>Bureau investigators may, without serving the petitioner, provide the Director with a statement setting forth any factual and legal response to a petition for an order modifying or setting aside the demand.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-6-e-4" marker="(4)">
                <title type="keyterm">Disposition.</title>
                <content>The Director has the authority to rule upon a petition for an order modifying or setting aside a civil investigative demand. The order may be served on the petitioner via email, facsimile, or any other method reasonably calculated to provide notice of the order to the petitioner.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-f" marker="(f)">
              <title type="keyterm">Stay of compliance period.</title>
              <content>The timely filing of a petition for an order modifying or setting aside a civil investigative demand shall stay the time permitted for compliance with the portion challenged. If the petition is denied in whole or in part, the ruling will specify a new return date.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-6-g" marker="(g)">
              <title type="keyterm">Public disclosure.</title>
              <content>All such petitions and the Director's orders in response to those petitions are part of the public records of the Bureau unless the Bureau determines otherwise for good cause shown. Any showing of good cause must be made no later than the time the petition is filed.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-7" sectionNum="7">
            <subject>§ 1080.7 Investigational hearings.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-7-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>Investigational hearings, as distinguished from hearings in adjudicative proceedings, may be conducted pursuant to a civil investigative demand for the giving of oral testimony in the course of any Bureau investigation, including inquiries initiated for the purpose of determining whether or not a respondent is complying with an order of the Bureau.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-7-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>Investigational hearings shall be conducted by any Bureau investigator for the purpose of hearing the testimony of witnesses and receiving documentary material, tangible things, or other information relating to any subject under investigation. Such hearings shall be under oath or affirmation and stenographically reported, and a transcript thereof shall be made a part of the record of the investigation. The Bureau investigator conducting the investigational hearing also may direct that the testimony be recorded by audio, audiovisual, or other means, in which case the recording shall be made a part of the record of the investigation as well.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-7-c" marker="(c)">
              <content>In investigational hearings, the Bureau investigators shall exclude from the hearing room all persons except the person being examined, his or her counsel, the officer before whom the testimony is to be taken, any investigator or representative of an agency with which the Bureau is engaged in a joint investigation, and any individual transcribing or recording such testimony. At the discretion of the Bureau investigator, and with the consent of the person being examined, persons other than those listed in this paragraph may be present in the hearing room. The Bureau investigator shall certify or direct the individual transcribing the testimony to certify on the transcript that the witness was duly sworn and that the transcript is a true record of the testimony given by the witness. A copy of the transcript shall be forwarded promptly by the Bureau investigator to the custodian designated in section <ref target="1080-13" reftype="internal">1080.13</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-8" sectionNum="8">
            <subject>§ 1080.8 Withholding requested material.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-8-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>Any person withholding material responsive to a civil investigative demand or any other request for production of material shall assert a claim of privilege not later than the date set for the production of material. Such person shall, if so directed in the civil investigative demand or other request for production, submit, together with such claim, a schedule of the items withheld which states, as to each such item, the type, specific subject matter, and date of the item; the names, addresses, positions, and organizations of all authors and recipients of the item; and the specific grounds for claiming that the item is privileged. The person who submits the schedule and the attorney stating the grounds for a claim that any item is privileged must sign it.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-8-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>A person withholding material solely for reasons described in this subsection shall comply with the requirements of this subsection in lieu of filing a petition for an order modifying or setting aside a civil investigative demand pursuant to section <ref target="1080-6-e" reftype="internal">1080.6(e)</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-8-c" marker="(c)">
              <content>Disclosure of privileged or protected information or communications produced pursuant to a civil investigative demand shall be handled as follows:</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-8-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>The disclosure of privileged or protected information or communications shall not operate as a waiver with respect to the Bureau if:</content>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-1-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>The disclosure was inadvertent;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>The holder of the privilege or protection took reasonable steps to prevent disclosure; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
                  <content>The holder promptly took reasonable steps to rectify the error, including notifying a Bureau investigator of the claim of privilege or protection and the basis for it.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-8-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>After being notified, the Bureau investigator must promptly return, sequester, or destroy the specified information and any copies; must not use or disclose the information until the claim is resolved; must take reasonable steps to retrieve the information if he or she disclosed it before being notified; and, if appropriate, may sequester such material until such time as a hearing officer or court rules on the merits of the claim of privilege or protection. The producing party must preserve the information until the claim is resolved.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-8-c-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>The disclosure of privileged or protected information or communications shall waive the privilege or protection with respect to the Bureau as to undisclosed information or communications only if:</content>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-3-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>The waiver is intentional;</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>The disclosed and undisclosed information or communications concern the same subject matter; and</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1080-8-c-3-iii" marker="(iii)">
                  <content>They ought in fairness to be considered together.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-9" sectionNum="9">
            <subject>§ 1080.9 Rights of witnesses in investigations.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-9-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>Any person compelled to submit documentary material, tangible things, or written reports or answers to questions to the Bureau, or to testify in an investigational hearing, shall be entitled to retain a copy or, on payment of lawfully prescribed costs, request a copy of the materials, things, reports, or written answers submitted, or a transcript of his or her testimony. The Bureau, however, may for good cause deny such a request and limit the witness to inspection of the official transcript of the testimony. Upon completion of transcription of the testimony of the witness, the witness shall be offered an opportunity to read the transcript of his or her testimony. Any changes by the witness shall be entered and identified upon the transcript by the Bureau investigator with a statement of the reasons given by the witness for making such changes. The transcript shall then be signed by the witness and submitted to the Bureau unless the witness cannot be found, is ill, waives in writing his or her right to signature, or refuses to sign. If the signed transcript is not submitted to the Bureau within 30 calendar days of the witness being afforded a reasonable opportunity to review it, the Bureau investigator, or the individual transcribing the testimony acting at the Bureau investigator's direction, shall sign the transcript and state on the record the fact of the waiver, illness, absence of the witness, or the refusal to sign, together with any reasons given for the failure to sign.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-9-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>Any witness compelled to appear in person at an investigational hearing may be accompanied, represented, and advised by counsel as follows:</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-9-b-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>Counsel for a witness may advise the witness, in confidence and upon the initiative of either counsel or the witness, with respect to any question asked of the witness where it is claimed that a witness is privileged to refuse to answer the question. Counsel may not otherwise consult with the witness while a question directed to the witness is pending.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-9-b-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>Any objections made under the rules in this part shall be made only for the purpose of protecting a constitutional or other legal right or privilege, including the privilege against self-incrimination. Neither the witness nor counsel shall otherwise object or refuse to answer any question. Any objection during an investigational hearing shall be stated concisely on the record in a nonargumentative and nonsuggestive manner. Following an objection, the examination shall proceed and the testimony shall be taken, except for testimony requiring the witness to divulge information protected by the claim of privilege or work product.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-9-b-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>Counsel for a witness may not, for any purpose or to any extent not allowed by paragraphs <ref target="1080-9-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1080-9-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref> of this section, interrupt the examination of the witness by making any objections or statements on the record. Petitions challenging the Bureau's authority to conduct the investigation or the sufficiency or legality of the civil investigative demand shall be addressed to the Bureau in advance of the hearing in accordance with § 1080.6(e). Copies of such petitions may be filed as part of the record of the investigation with the Bureau investigator conducting the investigational hearing, but no arguments in support thereof will be allowed at the hearing.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-9-b-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Following completion of the examination of a witness, counsel for the witness may, on the record, request that the Bureau investigator conducting the investigational hearing permit the witness to clarify any of his or her answers. The grant or denial of such request shall be within the sole discretion of the Bureau investigator conducting the hearing.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-9-b-5" marker="(5)">
                <content>The Bureau investigator conducting the hearing shall take all necessary action to regulate the course of the hearing to avoid delay and to prevent or restrain disorderly, dilatory, obstructionist, or contumacious conduct, or contemptuous language. Such Bureau investigator shall, for reasons stated on the record, immediately report to the Bureau any instances where an attorney has allegedly refused to comply with his or her obligations under the rules in this part, or has allegedly engaged in disorderly, dilatory, obstructionist, or contumacious conduct, or contemptuous language in the course of the hearing. The Bureau will thereupon take such further action, if any, as the circumstances warrant, including actions consistent with those described in <ref target="CFR:12-1081-107" reftype="external">12 CFR 1081.107</ref>(c) to suspend or disbar the attorney from further practice before the Bureau or exclude the attorney from further participation in the particular investigation.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-10" sectionNum="10">
            <subject>§ 1080.10 Noncompliance with civil investigative demands.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-10-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>In cases of failure to comply in whole or in part with Bureau civil investigative demands, appropriate action may be initiated by the Bureau, including actions for enforcement.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-10-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>The Director, the Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement, and the General Counsel of the Bureau are authorized to:</content>
              <paragraph label="1080-10-b-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>Institute, on behalf of the Bureau, an enforcement proceeding in the district court of the United States for any judicial district in which a person resides, is found, or transacts business, in connection with the failure or refusal of such person to comply with, or to obey, a civil investigative demand in whole or in part if the return date or any extension thereof has passed; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1080-10-b-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>Seek civil contempt or other appropriate relief in cases where a court order enforcing a civil investigative demand has been violated.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-11" sectionNum="11">
            <subject>§ 1080.11 Disposition.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-11-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>When the facts disclosed by an investigation indicate that an enforcement action is warranted, further proceedings may be instituted in Federal or State court or pursuant to the Bureau's administrative adjudicatory process. Where appropriate, the Bureau also may refer investigations to appropriate Federal, State, or foreign governmental agencies.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-11-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>When the facts disclosed by an investigation indicate that an enforcement action is not necessary or would not be in the public interest, the investigational file will be closed. The matter may be further investigated, at any time, if circumstances so warrant.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-11-c" marker="(c)">
              <content>The Assistant Director of the Office of Enforcement and the Deputy Assistant Directors of the Office of Enforcement are authorized to close Bureau investigations.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-12" sectionNum="12">
            <subject>§ 1080.12 Orders requiring witnesses to testify or provide other information and granting immunity.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-12-p1" marker="">
              <content>The Director has the nondelegable authority to request approval from the Attorney General of the United States for the issuance of an order requiring a witness to testify or provide other information and granting immunity under 18 U.S.C. 6004.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-13" sectionNum="13">
            <subject>§ 1080.13 Custodians.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-13-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>The Bureau shall designate a custodian and one or more deputy custodians for material to be delivered pursuant to a civil investigative demand in an investigation. The custodian shall have the powers and duties prescribed by <ref target="CFR:12-1070-3" reftype="external">12 CFR 1070.3</ref> and section 1052 of <ref target="USC:12-1080" reftype="external">the Act</ref>, <ref target="USC:12-5562" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 5562</ref>. Deputy custodians may perform all of the duties assigned to custodians.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-13-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>Material produced pursuant to a civil investigative demand, while in the custody of the custodian, shall be for the official use of the Bureau in accordance with <ref target="USC:12-1080" reftype="external">the Act</ref>; but such material shall upon reasonable notice to the custodian be made available for examination by the person who produced such material, or his or her duly authorized representative, during regular office hours established for the Bureau.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1080-14" sectionNum="14">
            <subject>§ 1080.14 Confidential treatment of demand material and non-public nature of investigations.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1080-14-a" marker="(a)">
              <content>Documentary materials, written reports, answers to questions, tangible things or transcripts of oral testimony the Bureau receives in any form or format pursuant to a civil investigative demand are subject to the requirements and procedures relating to the disclosure of records and information set forth in part 1070 of this title.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1080-14-b" marker="(b)">
              <content>Bureau investigations generally are non-public. Bureau investigators may disclose the existence of an investigation to potential witnesses or third parties to the extent necessary to advance the investigation.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
        </content>
      </subpart>
    </content>
  </part>
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1080-10" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.10 Noncompliance With Civil Investigative Demands</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section authorizes the Assistant Director of the Division of Enforcement, the General Counsel, or their delegees, to initiate an action to enforce a civil investigative demand in connection with the failure or refusal of a person to comply with, or to obey, a civil investigative demand. In addition, they are authorized to seek civil contempt or other appropriate relief in cases where a court order enforcing a civil investigative demand has been violated.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-11" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.11 Disposition</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section explains that an enforcement action may be instituted in federal or state court or through administrative proceedings when warranted by the facts disclosed by an investigation. This section further provides that the Bureau may refer investigations to appropriate federal, state, or foreign government agencies as appropriate. It also authorizes the Assistant Director of the Division of Enforcement to close the investigation when the facts of an investigation indicate an enforcement action is not necessary or warranted in the public interest.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-12" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.12 Orders Requiring Witnesses To Testify or Provide Other Information and Granting Immunity</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section authorizes the Assistant Director of the Division of Enforcement to request approval from the Attorney General for the issuance of an order requiring a witness to testify or provide other information and granting immunity under 18 U.S.C. 6004. It also sets forth the Bureau's right to review the exercise of these functions, and states that the Bureau will entertain an appeal from an order requiring a witness to testify or provide other information only upon a showing that a substantial question is involved, the determination of which is essential to serve the interests of justice. Finally, this section describes the applicable rules and time limits for such appeals.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-13" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.13 Custodians</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section describes the procedures for designating a custodian and deputy custodian for material produced pursuant to a civil investigative demand in an investigation. It also states that these materials are for the official use of the Bureau, but, upon notice to the custodian, must be made available for examination during regular office hours by the person who produced them.
        </analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-14" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.14 Confidential Treatment of Demand Material and Non-Public Nature of Investigations</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Section 1080.14 explains that documentary materials and tangible things obtained by the Bureau pursuant to a civil investigative demand are subject to the requirements and procedures relating to disclosure of records and information in part 1070 of this title. This section also states that investigations generally are non-public. A Bureau investigator may disclose the existence of an investigation to the extent necessary to advance the investigation.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-8" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.8 Withholding Requested Material</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section describes the procedures that apply when persons withhold material responsive to a civil investigative demand. It requires that they assert a privilege by the production date and, if so directed in the civil investigative demand, also submit a detailed schedule of the items withheld. Section 1080.8 also sets forth the procedures for handling the disclosure of privileged or protected information or communications.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-9" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.9 Rights of Witnesses in Investigations</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section describes the rights of persons compelled to submit information or provide testimony in an investigation. It details the procedures for obtaining a copy of submitted documents or a copy of or access to a transcript of the person's testimony. This section also describes a witness's right to make changes to his or her transcript and the rules for signing the transcript.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Section 1080.9 lays out a person's right to counsel at an investigational hearing and describes his or her counsel's right to advise the witness as to any question posed for which an objection may properly be made. It also describes the witness's or counsel's rights to object to questions or requests that the witness is privileged to refuse to answer. This section states that counsel for the witness may not otherwise object to questions or interrupt the examination to make statements on the record but may request that the witness have an opportunity to clarify any of his or her answers. Finally, this section authorizes the Bureau investigator to take all necessary action during the course of the hearing to avoid delay and to prevent or restrain disorderly, dilatory, obstructionist, or contumacious conduct, or contemptuous language.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-2" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.2 Definitions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section defines several terms used throughout the Rules. Many of these definitions also may be found in section 1051 of the Act.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-3" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.3 Policy as to Private Controversies</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section states the Bureau's policy of pursuing investigations that are in the public interest. Section 1080.3 is consistent with the Bureau's mission to protect consumers by investigating potential violations of Federal consumer financial law.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-1" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.1 Scope</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section describes the scope of the Rules. It makes clear that these Rules only apply to investigations under section 1052 of the Act.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-6" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.6 Civil Investigative Demands</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section lays out the Bureau's procedures for issuing civil investigative demands. It authorizes the Assistant Director of the Division of Enforcement to issue civil investigative demands for documentary material, tangible things, written reports or answers to questions, and oral testimony. This section details the information that must be included in civil investigative demands and the requirement that responses be made under a sworn certificate. Section 1080.6 also authorizes the Assistant Director of the Division of Enforcement to negotiate and approve the terms of compliance with civil investigative demands and grant extensions for good cause. Finally, this section describes the procedures for seeking an order to modify or set aside a civil investigative demand, which will be ruled upon by the Bureau Director.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-7" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.7 Investigational Hearings</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section describes the procedures for investigational hearings initiated pursuant to a civil investigative demand for oral testimony. It also lays out the roles and responsibilities of the Bureau investigator conducting the investigational hearing, which include excluding unauthorized persons from the hearing room and ensuring that the investigational hearing is transcribed, the witness is duly sworn, the transcript is a true record of the testimony, and the transcript is provided to the designated custodian.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-4" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.4 By Whom Conducted</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section explains that Bureau investigators are authorized to conduct investigations pursuant to section 1052 of the Act.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1080-5" notice="2011-19035" date="2011-07-28">
      <title>Section 1080.5 Notification of Purpose</title>
      <analysisParagraph>This section provides that a person compelled to provide information to the Bureau or testify in an investigational hearing must be advised of the nature of the conduct constituting the alleged violation under investigation and the applicable provisions of law. This section implements the requirements for civil investigative demands described in section 1052(c)(2) of the Act.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</regulation>
