<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs ../../eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-06-01</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-12125</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2013-06-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/articles/2013/05/23/2013-12125/amendments-to-the-2013-escrows-final-rule-under-the-truth-in-lending-act-regulation-z</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-a-2">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-a-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>“Average prime offer rate” means an annual percentage rate that is derived from average interest rates, points, and other loan pricing terms currently offered to &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; by a representative sample of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditors&lt;/ref&gt; for mortgage transactions that have low-risk pricing characteristics. The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; publishes average prime offer rates for a broad range of types of transactions in a table updated at least weekly as well as the methodology the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; uses to derive these rates.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c" marker="(c)">
        <content>[Reserved]</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
        <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-1-ii">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, a county is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure <ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term">Act</ref> (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. Specifically, a county is “underserved” if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien covered transactions with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only covered transactions are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e" marker="(e)">
        <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability, prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>Repayment ability, prepayment penalties. &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Higher-priced mortgage loans&lt;/ref&gt; are subject to the following restrictions:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
          <content>Repayment ability. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall not extend &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; based on the value of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s collateral without regard to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s repayment ability as of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; as provided in § &lt;ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.34(a)(4)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
          <content>Prepayment penalties. A loan may not include a penalty described by § &lt;ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(d)(6)&lt;/ref&gt; unless:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>The penalty is otherwise permitted by law, including § &lt;ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(d)(7)&lt;/ref&gt; if the loan is a mortgage transaction described in § &lt;ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(a)&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>Under the terms of the loan:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>The penalty will not apply after the two-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or an &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>The amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-3" marker="(3)">
          <title type="keyterm">Sunset of requirements on repayment ability and prepayment penalties.</title>
          <content>Sunset of requirements on repayment ability and prepayment penalties. The requirements described in this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-e" reftype="internal"&gt;(e)&lt;/ref&gt; shall expire at 11:59 p.m. on January 9, 2014.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-Interp" target="1026-35-e">
        <title>35(e) Rules for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2">
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii">
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
              <title>Paragraph 35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-1">
                <content>Payment change. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-1</ref>. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-2" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-2</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2">
                <content>Negative amortization. Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)(iv)</ref> does not include examples of payment changes in connection with negative amortization. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan agreement permits negative amortization:</content>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
                  <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
                  <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-20">
      <section label="1026-20" sectionNum="20">
        <subject>§ 1026.20 Subsequent disclosure requirements.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Refinancings.</title>
          <content>Refinancings. A refinancing occurs when an existing obligation that was subject to this subpart is satisfied and replaced by a new obligation undertaken by the same &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;. A refinancing is a new transaction requiring new disclosures to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;. The new finance charge shall include any unearned portion of the old finance charge that is not credited to the existing obligation. The following shall not be treated as a refinancing:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>A renewal of a single payment obligation with no change in the original terms.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>A reduction in the annual percentage rate with a corresponding change in the payment schedule.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>An agreement involving a court proceeding.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>A change in the payment schedule or a change in collateral requirements as a result of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s default or delinquency, unless the rate is increased, or the new amount financed exceeds the unpaid balance plus earned finance charge and premiums for continuation of insurance of the types described in § &lt;ref target="1026-4-d" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.4(d)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The renewal of optional insurance purchased by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; and added to an existing transaction, if disclosures relating to the initial purchase were provided as required by this subpart.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Assumptions.</title>
          <content>Assumptions. An assumption occurs when a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; expressly agrees in writing with a subsequent &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; to accept that &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; as a primary obligor on an existing &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-24" reftype="term"&gt;residential mortgage transaction&lt;/ref&gt;. Before the assumption occurs, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall make new disclosures to the subsequent &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;, based on the remaining obligation. If the finance charge originally imposed on the existing obligation was an add-on or discount finance charge, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; need only disclose:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The unpaid balance of the obligation assumed.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The total charges imposed by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; in connection with the assumption.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>The information required to be disclosed under § &lt;ref target="1026-18-k" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18(k)&lt;/ref&gt;, &lt;ref target="1026-18-l" reftype="internal"&gt;(l)&lt;/ref&gt;, &lt;ref target="1026-18-m" reftype="internal"&gt;(m)&lt;/ref&gt;, and &lt;ref target="1026-18-n" reftype="internal"&gt;(n)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The annual percentage rate originally imposed on the obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The payment schedule under § &lt;ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18(g)&lt;/ref&gt; and the total of payments under § &lt;ref target="1026-18-h" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18(h)&lt;/ref&gt; based on the remaining obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-c" marker="(c)">
          <title type="keyterm">Variable-rate adjustments.</title>
          <content>Variable-rate adjustments. Except as provided in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-20-d" reftype="internal"&gt;(d)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, an adjustment to the interest rate with or without a corresponding adjustment to the payment in a variable-rate transaction subject to § &lt;ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.19(b)&lt;/ref&gt; is an event requiring new disclosures to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;. At least once each year during which an interest rate adjustment is implemented without an accompanying payment change, and at least 25, but no more than 120, calendar days before a payment at a new level is due, the following disclosures, as applicable, must be delivered or placed in the mail:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The current and prior interest rates.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The index values upon which the current and prior interest rates are based.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>The extent to which the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; has foregone any increase in the interest rate.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The contractual effects of the adjustment, including the payment due after the adjustment is made, and a statement of the loan balance.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The payment, if different from that referred to in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-20-c-4" reftype="internal"&gt;(c)(4)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, that would be required to fully amortize the loan at the new interest rate over the remainder of the loan term.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-d" marker="(d)">
          <content>Information provided in accordance with variable-rate subsequent disclosure regulations of other Federal agencies may be substituted for the disclosure required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-20-c" reftype="internal"&gt;(c)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
        <content>Neither the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; nor its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section for any extension of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by real property or a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; that the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; currently services, other than:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
          <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loans&lt;/ref&gt; on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
          <content>Escrow accounts established after &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; as an accommodation to distressed &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; to assist such &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>Under the terms of the loan:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>The penalty will not apply after the two-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>The penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or an &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>The amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-2-i">
        <content>A county is considered “rural” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available UIC designations, which are updated by the USDA-ERS once every ten years. As an example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien covered transactions in County X during calendar year 2014, and the most recent UIC designations have been published in the second quarter of 2013. To determine “rural” status for County X during calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2013 UIC designations. However, to determine “rural” status for County X during 2012 or 2013, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> would use the UIC designations last published in 2003.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph (b)(2)(iv) of th&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal"&gt;is section&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-2">
        <content>Examples.</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-2-i">
          <content>A county is considered “rural” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available UIC designations, which are updated by the USDA-ERS once every ten years. As an example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien covered transactions in County X during calendar year 2014, and the most recent UIC designations have been published in the second quarter of 2013. To determine “rural” status for County X during calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2013 UIC designations. However, to determine “rural” status for County X during 2012 or 2013, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> would use the UIC designations last published in 2003.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-2-ii">
          <content>A county is considered “underserved” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available HMDA data. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien covered transactions in County Y during calendar year 2013, and the most recent HMDA data is for calendar year 2012, published in the third quarter of 2013. To determine “underserved” status for County Y in calendar year 2013 for the purposes of qualifying for the “rural or underserved” exemption in calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2012 HMDA data.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
        <title>Paragraph 35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-1">
          <content>Payment change. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-1</ref>. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-2" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-2</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2">
          <content>Negative amortization. Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)(iv)</ref> does not include examples of payment changes in connection with negative amortization. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan agreement permits negative amortization:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
            <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
            <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-1-i">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, a county is rural during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. These areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">States</ref> Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). Accordingly, for purposes of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A), “adjacent” has the meaning applied by the USDA-ERS in determining a county's UIC; as so applied, “adjacent” entails a county not only being physically contiguous with a metropolitan statistical area but also meeting certain minimum population commuting patterns. Specifically, a county is “rural” if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx. A county for which there is no currently applicable UIC (because the county has been created since the USDA-ERS last categorized counties) is rural only if all counties from which the new county's land was taken are themselves rural under currently applicable UICs.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
        <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; and its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliates&lt;/ref&gt; together originated 500 or fewer covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien; and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>Insurance premiums described in paragraph (b)(1) of this section need not be included in escrow accounts for loans secured by &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwellings&lt;/ref&gt; in condominiums, planned unit developments, or other common interest communities in which &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; ownership requires participation in a governing association, where the governing association has an obligation to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; owners to maintain a master policy insuring all &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwellings&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
        <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;Consumer&lt;/ref&gt; Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii&lt;/ref&gt; for the current threshold); and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Act&lt;/ref&gt; (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditors&lt;/ref&gt; extended covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term"&gt;States&lt;/ref&gt; Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19">
      <section label="1026-19" sectionNum="19">
        <subject>§ 1026.19 Certain mortgage and variable-rate transactions.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage transactions subject to RESPA</title>
          <content>Mortgage transactions subject to RESPA —</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1" marker="(1)">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
              <title type="keyterm">Time of disclosures.</title>
              <content>Time of disclosures. In a mortgage transaction subject to the Real Estate Settlement Procedures &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Act&lt;/ref&gt; (&lt;ref target="USC:12-2601" reftype="external"&gt;12 U.S.C. 2601&lt;/ref&gt; et seq.) that is secured by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt;, other than a home equity line of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; subject to § &lt;ref target="1026-40" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.40&lt;/ref&gt; or mortgage transaction subject to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-5" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(5)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall make good faith estimates of the disclosures required by § &lt;ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18&lt;/ref&gt; and shall deliver or place them in the mail not later than the third business day after the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; receives the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s written application.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <title type="keyterm">Imposition of fees.</title>
              <content>Imposition of fees. Except as provided in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(iii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, neither a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; nor any other &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term"&gt;person&lt;/ref&gt; may impose a fee on a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; in connection with the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s application for a mortgage transaction subject to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has received the disclosures required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section. If the disclosures are mailed to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; is considered to have received them three &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term"&gt;business days&lt;/ref&gt; after they are mailed.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <title type="keyterm">Exception to fee restriction.</title>
              <content>Exception to fee restriction. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or other &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term"&gt;person&lt;/ref&gt; may impose a fee for obtaining the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; history before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has received the disclosures required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, provided the fee is bona fide and reasonable in amount.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2" marker="(2)">
            <title type="keyterm">Waiting periods for early disclosures and corrected disclosures.</title>
            <content>Waiting periods for early disclosures and corrected disclosures.</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall deliver or place in the mail the good faith estimates required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section not later than the seventh &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term"&gt;business day&lt;/ref&gt; before &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; of the transaction.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>If the annual percentage rate disclosed under paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section becomes inaccurate, as defined in § &lt;ref target="1026-22" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.22&lt;/ref&gt;, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall provide corrected disclosures with all changed terms. The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; must receive the corrected disclosures no later than three &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term"&gt;business days&lt;/ref&gt; before &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;. If the corrected disclosures are mailed to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; or delivered to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; by means other than delivery in &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term"&gt;person&lt;/ref&gt;, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; is deemed to have received the corrected disclosures three &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term"&gt;business days&lt;/ref&gt; after they are mailed or delivered.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-3" marker="(3)">
            <title type="keyterm">Consumer's waiver of waiting period before consummation.</title>
            <content>&lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;Consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s waiver of waiting period before &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;. If the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; determines that the extension of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; is needed to meet a bona fide personal financial emergency, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; may modify or waive the seven-business-day waiting period or the three-business-day waiting period required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(2)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, after receiving the disclosures required by § &lt;ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18&lt;/ref&gt;. To modify or waive a waiting period, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; shall give the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; a dated written statement that describes the emergency, specifically modifies or waives the waiting period, and bears the signature of all the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; who are primarily liable on the legal obligation. Printed forms for this purpose are prohibited.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-4" marker="(4)">
            <title type="keyterm">Notice.</title>
            <content>Notice. Disclosures made pursuant to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; or paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(2)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section shall contain the following statement: “You are not required to complete this agreement merely because you have received these disclosures or signed a loan application.” The disclosure required by this paragraph shall be grouped together with the disclosures required by paragraphs &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; or &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(2)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5" marker="(5)">
            <title type="keyterm">Timeshare plans.</title>
            <content>Timeshare plans. In a mortgage transaction subject to the Real Estate Settlement Procedures &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Act&lt;/ref&gt; (&lt;ref target="USC:12-2601" reftype="external"&gt;12 U.S.C. 2601&lt;/ref&gt; et seq.) that is secured by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s interest in a timeshare plan described in &lt;ref target="USC:11-101" reftype="external"&gt;11 U.S.C. 101&lt;/ref&gt;(53(D)):</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The requirements of paragraphs &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; through &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-4" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(4)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section do not apply;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall make good faith estimates of the disclosures required by § &lt;ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.18&lt;/ref&gt; before &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;, or shall deliver or place them in the mail not later than three business days after the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; receives the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s written application, whichever is earlier; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>If the annual percentage rate at the time of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; varies from the annual percentage rate disclosed under paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-a-5-ii" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(5)(ii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section by more than 1/8 of 1 percentage point in a regular transaction or more than 1/4 of 1 percentage point in an irregular transaction, as defined in § &lt;ref target="1026-22" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.22&lt;/ref&gt;, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall disclose all the changed terms no later than &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; or settlement.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Certain variable-rate transactions.</title>
          <content>Certain variable-rate transactions. Except as provided in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-d" reftype="internal"&gt;(d)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, if the annual percentage rate may increase after &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; in a transaction secured by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; with a term greater than one year, the following disclosures must be provided at the time an application form is provided or before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; pays a non-refundable fee, whichever is earlier (except that the disclosures may be delivered or placed in the mail not later than three business days following receipt of a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s application when the application reaches the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; by telephone, or through an intermediary agent or broker):</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The booklet titled &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;Consumer&lt;/ref&gt; Handbook on Adjustable Rate Mortgages, or a suitable substitute.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>A loan program disclosure for each variable-rate program in which the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; expresses an interest. The following disclosures, as applicable, shall be provided:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The fact that the interest rate, payment, or term of the loan can change.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>The index or formula used in making adjustments, and a source of information about the index or formula.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>An explanation of how the interest rate and payment will be determined, including an explanation of how the index is adjusted, such as by the addition of a margin.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
              <content>A statement that the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; should ask about the current margin value and current interest rate.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
              <content>The fact that the interest rate will be discounted, and a statement that the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; should ask about the amount of the interest rate discount.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-vi" marker="(vi)">
              <content>The frequency of interest rate and payment changes.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-vii" marker="(vii)">
              <content>Any rules relating to changes in the index, interest rate, payment amount, and outstanding loan balance including, for example, an explanation of interest rate or payment limitations, negative amortization, and interest rate carryover.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii" marker="(viii)">
              <content>At the option of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;, either of the following:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>A historical example, based on a $10,000 loan amount, illustrating how payments and the loan balance would have been affected by interest rate changes implemented according to the terms of the loan program disclosure. The example shall reflect the most recent 15 years of index values. The example shall reflect all significant loan program terms, such as negative amortization, interest rate carryover, interest rate discounts, and interest rate and payment limitations, that would have been affected by the index movement during the period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>The maximum interest rate and payment for a $10,000 loan originated at the initial interest rate (index value plus margin, adjusted by the amount of any discount or premium) in effect as of an identified month and year for the loan program disclosure assuming the maximum periodic increases in rates and payments under the program; and the initial interest rate and payment for that loan and a statement that the periodic payment may increase or decrease substantially depending on changes in the rate.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix" marker="(ix)">
              <content>An explanation of how the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; may calculate the payments for the loan amount to be borrowed based on either:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>The most recent payment shown in the historical example in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-b-2-viii-A" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(viii)(A)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>The initial interest rate used to calculate the maximum interest rate and payment in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-b-2-viii-B" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(viii)(B)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-x" marker="(x)">
              <content>The fact that the loan program contains a demand feature.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-xi" marker="(xi)">
              <content>The type of information that will be provided in notices of adjustments and the timing of such notices.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-xii" marker="(xii)">
              <content>A statement that disclosure forms are available for the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;'s other variable-rate loan programs.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-c" marker="(c)">
          <title type="keyterm">Electronic disclosures.</title>
          <content>Electronic disclosures. For an application that is accessed by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; in electronic form, the disclosures required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section may be provided to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; in electronic form on or with the application.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-d" marker="(d)">
          <content>Information provided in accordance with variable-rate regulations of other Federal agencies may be substituted for the disclosures required by paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <content>Except as provided in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(v)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, an escrow account need not be established for a transaction if, at the time of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph (b)(2)(iv) of th&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal"&gt;is section&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; and its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliates&lt;/ref&gt; together originated 500 or fewer covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;Consumer&lt;/ref&gt; Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii&lt;/ref&gt; for the current threshold); and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>Neither the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; nor its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section for any extension of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by real property or a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; that the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; currently services, other than:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loans&lt;/ref&gt; on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>Escrow accounts established after &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; as an accommodation to distressed &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; to assist such &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-23-a-3-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-23-a-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>For purposes of this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-23-a-3" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(3)&lt;/ref&gt;, the term “material disclosures” means the required disclosures of the annual percentage rate, the finance charge, the amount financed, the total of payments, the payment schedule, and the disclosures and limitations referred to in §§ &lt;ref target="1026-32-c" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(c)&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal"&gt;(d)&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.35(e)(2)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>The penalty will not apply after the two-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" marker="(C)">
        <content>The amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>The penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or an &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2" marker="(2)">
        <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>Prepayment penalties. A loan may not include a penalty described by § &lt;ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(d)(6)&lt;/ref&gt; unless:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The penalty is otherwise permitted by law, including § &lt;ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(d)(7)&lt;/ref&gt; if the loan is a mortgage transaction described in § &lt;ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(a)&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Under the terms of the loan:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The penalty will not apply after the two-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or an &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-3">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Sunset of requirements on repayment ability and prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>Sunset of requirements on repayment ability and prepayment penalties. The requirements described in this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-e" reftype="internal"&gt;(e)&lt;/ref&gt; shall expire at 11:59 p.m. on January 9, 2014.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a">
      <paragraph label="1026-51-a" marker="(a)">
        <title type="keyterm">General rule</title>
        <content>General rule —</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1" marker="(1)">
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <title type="keyterm">Consideration of ability to pay.</title>
            <content>Consideration of ability to pay. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; must not open a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term"&gt;credit card&lt;/ref&gt; account for a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; under an open-end (not home-secured) &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; plan, or increase any &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; limit applicable to such account, unless the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; considers the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments under the terms of the account based on the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s income or assets and the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s current obligations.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Reasonable policies and procedures.</title>
            <content>Reasonable policies and procedures. &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;Card issuers&lt;/ref&gt; must establish and maintain reasonable written policies and procedures to consider the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s ability to make the required minimum payments under the terms of the account based on a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s income or assets and a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s current obligations. Reasonable policies and procedures include treating any income and assets to which the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has a reasonable expectation of access as the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s income or assets, or limiting consideration of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s income or assets to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s independent income and assets. Reasonable policies and procedures also include consideration of at least one of the following: The ratio of debt obligations to income; the ratio of debt obligations to assets; or the income the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; will have after paying debt obligations. It would be unreasonable for a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; not to review any information about a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s income or assets and current obligations, or to issue a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term"&gt;credit card&lt;/ref&gt; to a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; who does not have any income or assets.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Minimum periodic payments</title>
          <content>Minimum periodic payments —</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <title type="keyterm">Reasonable method.</title>
            <content>Reasonable method. For purposes of paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-a-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; must use a reasonable method for estimating the minimum periodic payments the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; would be required to pay under the terms of the account.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Safe harbor.</title>
            <content>Safe harbor. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; complies with paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-a-2-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(2)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section if it estimates required minimum periodic payments using the following method:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; assumes utilization, from the first day of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term"&gt;billing cycle&lt;/ref&gt;, of the full &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; line that the issuer is considering offering to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; uses a minimum payment formula employed by the issuer for the product the issuer is considering offering to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; or, in the case of an existing account, the minimum payment formula that currently applies to that account, provided that:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes interest charges, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; estimates those charges using an interest rate that the issuer is considering offering to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; for purchases or, in the case of an existing account, the interest rate that currently applies to purchases; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes mandatory fees, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; must assume that such fees have been charged to the account.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
        <content>Repayment ability. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall not extend &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; based on the value of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s collateral without regard to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s repayment ability as of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; as provided in § &lt;ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.34(a)(4)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-1">
        <content>Application of repayment ability rule. The § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition against making loans without regard to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>' repayment ability applies to mortgage loans described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref>. In addition, the § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition applies to higher-priced mortgage loans described in § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. See § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(1)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <content>For purposes of paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)(A)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term"&gt;States&lt;/ref&gt; Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Act&lt;/ref&gt; (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditors&lt;/ref&gt; extended covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-1">
        <content>Requirements for “rural” or “underserved” status. A county is considered to be “rural” or “underserved” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> if it satisfies either of the two tests in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> applies both tests to each county in the United <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">States</ref>. If a county satisfies either test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will include the county on a published list of “rural” or “underserved” counties for a particular calendar year. To facilitate compliance with apprai<ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">sal requir</ref>ements in § 1026.35(c), the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will also create a list of only those counties that are “rural” but excluding those that are only “underserved.” The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will post on its public Web site the applicable lists for each calendar year by the end of that year, thus permitting <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to ascertain the availability to them of the exemption during the following year. For 2012, however, the list will be published before June 1, 2013. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor, pursuant to section 130(f) of the Truth in Lending <ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term">Act</ref>, on the lists of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” or “underserved” for a <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">particular calendar y</ref>ear. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s originations of covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, in such counties during that year are considered in determining whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the condition in § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) and therefore will be eligible for the exemption during the following calendar year.</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-1-i">
          <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, a county is rural during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. These areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">States</ref> Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). Accordingly, for purposes of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A), “adjacent” has the meaning applied by the USDA-ERS in determining a county's UIC; as so applied, “adjacent” entails a county not only being physically contiguous with a metropolitan statistical area but also meeting certain minimum population commuting patterns. Specifically, a county is “rural” if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx. A county for which there is no currently applicable UIC (because the county has been created since the USDA-ERS last categorized counties) is rural only if all counties from which the new county's land was taken are themselves rural under currently applicable UICs.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-1-ii">
          <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, a county is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure <ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term">Act</ref> (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. Specifically, a county is “underserved” if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien covered transactions with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only covered transactions are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4">
        <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4) Repayment Ability for High-Cost Mortgages</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-1">
          <content>Application of repayment ability rule. The § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition against making loans without regard to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>' repayment ability applies to mortgage loans described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref>. In addition, the § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition applies to higher-priced mortgage loans described in § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. See § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(1)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-2" target="1026-34-a-4-2">
          <content>General prohibition. Section <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibits a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> from extending <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref> to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> based on the value of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s collateral without regard to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s repayment ability as of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, including the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current and reasonably expected income, employment, assets other than the collateral, current obligations, and property tax and insurance obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may base its determination of repayment ability on current or reasonably expected income from employment or other sources, on assets other than the collateral, or both.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-3" target="1026-34-a-4-3">
          <content>Other <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>-secured obligations. For purposes of § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref>, current obligations include another <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> obligation of which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has knowledge undertaken prior to or at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of the transaction and secured by the same <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that secures the transaction subject to § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref> or § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref>. For example, where a transaction subject to § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> is a first-lien transaction for the purchase of a home, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must consider a “piggyback” second-lien transaction of which it has knowledge that is used to finance part of the down payment on the house.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-4" target="1026-34-a-4-4">
          <content>Discounted <ref target="1026-16-g-2-ii" reftype="term">introductory rates</ref> and non-amortizing or negatively-amortizing payments. A <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> agreement may determine a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s initial payments using a temporarily discounted interest rate or permit the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to make initial payments that are non-amortizing or negatively amortizing. (Negative amortization is permissible for loans covered by § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>, but not § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref>). In such cases the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may determine repayment ability using the assumptions provided in § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-iv" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(iv)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-5" target="1026-34-a-4-5">
          <content>Repayment ability as of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibits a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> from disregarding repayment ability based on the facts and circumstances known to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. In general, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not violate this provision if a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> defaults because of a significant reduction in income (for example, a job loss) or a significant obligation (for example, an obligation arising from a major medical expense) that occurs after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. However, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has knowledge as of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of reductions in income, for example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s written application <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">states</ref> that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> plans to retire within twelve months without obtaining new employment, or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">states</ref> that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will transition from full-time to part-time employment, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must consider that information.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-6" target="1026-34-a-4-6">
          <content>Income, assets, and employment. Any current or reasonably expected assets or income may be considered by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, except the collateral itself. For example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may use information about current or expected salary, wages, bonus pay, tips, and commissions. Employment may be full-time, part-time, seasonal, irregular, military, or self-employment. Other sources of income could include interest or dividends; retirement benefits; public assistance; and alimony, child support, or separate maintenance payments. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may also take into account assets such as savings accounts or investments that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> can or will be able to use.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-7" target="1026-34-a-4-7">
          <content>Interaction with Regulation B. Section <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> does not require or permit the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to make inquiries or verifications that would be prohibited by Regulation B, <ref target="CFR:12-1002" reftype="external">12 CFR part 1002</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-i">
          <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(i) Mortgage-Related Obligations</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-i-1">
            <content>Mortgage-related obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must include in its repayment ability analysis the expected property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b), as w</ref>ell as similar mortgage-related expenses. Similar mortgage-related expenses include homeowners' association dues and condominium or cooperative fees.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-ii">
          <title>34(a)(4)(ii) Verification of Repayment Ability</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-1">
            <content>Income and assets relied on. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must verify the income and assets the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> relies on to evaluate the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s repayment ability. For example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> earns a salary and also <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">states</ref> that he or she is paid an annual bonus, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> only relies on the applicant's salary to evaluate repayment ability, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> need only verify the salary.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-Interp-2" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-2">
            <content>Income and assets—co-applicant. If two <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> jointly apply for <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> and both list income or assets on the application, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must verify repayment ability with respect to both applicants unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> relies only on the income or assets of one of the applicants in determining repayment ability.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-Interp-3" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-3">
            <content>Expected income. If a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> relies on expected income, the expectation must be reasonable and it must be verified with third-party documents that provide reasonably reliable evidence of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s expected income. For example, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> relies on an expectation that a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will receive an annual bonus, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may verify the basis for that expectation with documents that show the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s past annual bonuses and the expected bonus must bear a reasonable relationship to past bonuses. Similarly, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> relies on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s expected salary following the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s receipt of an educational degree, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may verify that expectation with a written statement from an employer indicating that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will be employed upon graduation at a specified salary.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A">
            <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(ii)(A)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-1">
              <content>Internal Revenue Service (IRS) Form W-2. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may verify a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income using a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s IRS Form W-2 (or any subsequent revisions or similar IRS Forms used for reporting wages and tax withholding). The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may also use an electronic retrieval service for obtaining the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s W-2 information.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp-2" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-2">
              <content>Tax returns. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may verify a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets using the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s tax return. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may also use IRS Form 4506 “Request for Copy of Tax Return,” Form 4506-T “Request for Transcript of Tax Return,” or Form 8821 “Tax Information Authorization” (or any subsequent revisions or similar IRS Forms appropriate for obtaining tax return information directly from the IRS) to verify the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may also use an electronic retrieval service for obtaining tax return information.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp-3" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-3">
              <content>Other third-party documents that provide reasonably reliable evidence of <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may verify income and assets using documents produced by third parties. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may not rely on information provided orally by third parties, but may rely on correspondence from the third party, such as by letter or email. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely on any third-party document that provides reasonably reliable evidence of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets. For example, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> may verify the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income using receipts from a check-cashing or remittance service, or by obtaining a written statement from the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s employer that <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">states</ref> the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp-4" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-4">
              <content>Information specific to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> must verify a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets using information that is specific to the individual <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may use third-party databases that contain individual-specific data about a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, such as a third-party database service used by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s employer for the purpose of centralizing income verification requests, so long as the information is reasonably current and accurate. Information about average incomes for the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s occupation in the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s geographic location or information about average incomes paid by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s employer, however, would not be specific to the individual <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-Interp-5" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A-5">
              <content>Duplicative collection of documentation. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that has made a loan to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and is refinancing or extending new <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> to the same <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> need not collect from the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> a document the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> previously obtained if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has no information that would reasonably lead the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to believe that document has changed since it was initially collected. For example, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has obtained the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s 2006 tax return to make a home purchase loan in May 2007, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely on the 2006 tax return if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes a home equity loan to the same <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in August 2007. Similarly, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has obtained the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s bank statement for May 2007 in making the first loan, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely on that bank statement for that month in making the subsequent loan in August 2007.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-B-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-B">
            <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(ii)(B)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-B-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-B-1">
              <content>No violation if income or assets relied on not materially greater than verifiable amounts. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that does not verify income or assets used to determine repayment ability with reasonably reliable third-party documents does not violate § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-ii" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(ii)</ref> if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> demonstrates that the income or assets it relied upon were not materially greater than the amounts that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> would have been able to verify pursuant to § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-ii" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(ii)</ref>. For example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> determines a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s repayment ability by relying on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s annual income of $40,000 but fails to obtain documentation of that amount before extending the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will not have violated this section if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> later obtains evidence that would satisfy § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(ii)(A)</ref>, such as tax return information, showing that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> could have documented, at the time the loan was consummated, that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> had an annual income not materially less than $40,000.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-B-Interp-2" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-B-2">
              <content>Materially greater than. Amounts of income or assets relied on are not materially greater than amounts that could have been verified at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> if relying on the verifiable amounts would not have altered a reasonable <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s decision to extend <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> or the terms of the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-C">
            <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(ii)(C)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-ii-C-1">
              <content>In general. A <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> report may be used to verify current obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> report, however, might not reflect an obligation that a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has listed on an application. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is responsible for considering such an obligation, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is not required to independently verify the obligation. Similarly, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is responsible for considering certain obligations undertaken just before or at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of the transaction and secured by the same <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that secures the transaction (for example, a “piggy back” loan), of which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> knows, even if not reflected on a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> report. See comment <ref target="1026-34-a-4-Interp-3" reftype="internal">34(a)(4)-3</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-iii">
          <title>34(a)(4)(iii) Presumption of Compliance</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-1">
            <content>In general. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is presumed to have complied with § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> follows the three underwriting procedures specified in paragraph <ref target="1026-34-a-4-iii" reftype="internal">34(a)(4)(iii)</ref> for verifying repayment ability, determining the payment obligation, and measuring the relationship of obligations to income. The procedures for verifying repayment ability are required under paragraph <ref target="1026-34-a-4-ii" reftype="internal">34(a)(4)(ii)</ref>; the other procedures are not required but, if followed along with the required procedures, create a presumption that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has complied with § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may rebut the presumption with evidence that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> nonetheless disregarded repayment ability despite following these procedures. For example, evidence of a very high debt-to-income ratio and a very limited residual income could be sufficient to rebut the presumption, depending on all of the facts and circumstances. If a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> fails to follow one of the non-required procedures set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-34-a-4-iii" reftype="internal">34(a)(4)(iii)</ref>, then the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s compliance is determined based on all of the facts and circumstances without there being a presumption of either compliance or violation.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B">
            <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(iii)(B)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1">
              <content>Determination of payment schedule. To retain a presumption of compliance under § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(iii)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must determine the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to pay the principal and interest obligation based on the maximum scheduled payment in the first seven years following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. In general, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> should determine a payment schedule for purposes of § <ref target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)(iii)(B)</ref> based on the guidance in the commentary to § <ref target="1026-17-c-1-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(1)</ref>. Examples of how to determine the maximum scheduled payment in the first seven years are provided as follows (all payment amounts are rounded):</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-i" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-i">
                <content>Balloon-payment loan; fixed interest rate. A loan in an amount of $100,000 with a fixed interest rate of 8.0 percent (no points) has a 7-year term but is amortized over 30 years. The monthly payment scheduled for 7 years is $733 with a balloon payment of remaining principal due at the end of 7 years. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will retain the presumption of compliance if it assesses repayment ability based on the payment of $733.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-ii" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-ii">
                <content>Fixed-rate loan with interest-only payment for five years. A loan in an amount of $100,000 with a fixed interest rate of 8.0 percent (no points) has a 30-year term. The monthly payment of $667 scheduled for the first 5 years would cover only the interest due. After the fifth year, the scheduled payment would increase to $772, an amount that fully amortizes the principal balance over the remaining 25 years. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will retain the presumption of compliance if it assesses repayment ability based on the payment of $772.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-iii" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-iii">
                <content>Fixed-rate loan with interest-only payment for seven years. A loan in an amount of $100,000 with a fixed interest rate of 8.0 percent (no points) has a 30-year term. The monthly payment of $667 scheduled for the first 7 years would cover only the interest due. After the seventh year, the scheduled payment would increase to $793, an amount that fully amortizes the principal balance over the remaining 23 years. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will retain the presumption of compliance if it assesses repayment ability based on the interest-only payment of $667.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-iv" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-iv">
                <content>Variable-rate loan with discount for five years. A loan in an amount of $100,000 has a 30-year term. The loan agreement provides for a fixed interest rate of 7.0 percent for an initial period of 5 years. Accordingly, the payment scheduled for the first 5 years is $665. The agreement provides that, after 5 years, the interest rate will adjust each year based on a specified index and margin. As of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the sum of the index value and margin (the fully-indexed rate) is 8.0 percent. Accordingly, the payment scheduled for the remaining 25 years is $727. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will retain the presumption of compliance if it assesses repayment ability based on the payment of $727.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-v" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-v">
                <content>Variable-rate loan with discount for seven years. A loan in an amount of $100,000 has a 30-year term. The loan agreement provides for a fixed interest rate of 7.125 percent for an initial period of 7 years. Accordingly, the payment scheduled for the first 7 years is $674. After 7 years, the agreement provides that the interest rate will adjust each year based on a specified index and margin. As of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the sum of the index value and margin (the fully-indexed rate) is 8.0 percent. Accordingly, the payment scheduled for the remaining years is $725. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will retain the presumption of compliance if it assesses repayment ability based on the payment of $674.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-Interp-1-vi" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-B-1-vi">
                <content>Step-rate loan. A loan in an amount of $100,000 has a 30-year term. The agreement provides that the interest rate will be 5 percent for two years, 6 percent for three years, and 7 percent thereafter. Accordingly, the payment amounts are $537 for two years, $597 for three years, and $654 thereafter. To retain the presumption of compliance, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must assess repayment ability based on the payment of $654.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-C-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-C">
            <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(iii)(C)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-iii-C-1">
              <content>“Income” and “debt”. To determine whether to classify particular inflows or obligations as “income” or “debt,” <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> may look to widely accepted governmental and non-governmental underwriting standards, including, for example, those set forth in the Federal Housing Administration's handbook on Mortgage <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">Credit</ref> Analysis for Mortgage Insurance.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iv-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-iv">
          <title>34(a)(4)(iv) Exclusions From Presumption of Compliance</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iv-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-iv-1">
            <content>In general. The exclusions from the presumption of compliance should be interpreted consistent with comments <ref target="1026-32-d-1-i-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(1)(i)-1</ref> and <ref target="1026-32-d-2-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(2)-1</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-iv-Interp-2" target="1026-34-a-4-iv-2">
            <content>Renewable balloon loan. If a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is unconditionally obligated to renew a balloon-payment loan at the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s option (or is obligated to renew subject to conditions within the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control), the full term resulting from such renewal is the relevant term for purposes of the exclusion of certain balloon-payment loans. See comment <ref target="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11" reftype="internal">17(c)(1)-11</ref> for a discussion of conditions within a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control in connection with renewable balloon-payment loans.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-h">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-h" marker="(h)">
        <title type="keyterm">Prohibition on mandatory arbitration clauses and waivers of certain consumer rights.</title>
        <content>Prohibition on mandatory arbitration clauses and waivers of certain &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; rights.</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-36-h-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Arbitration.</title>
          <content>Arbitration. A contract or other agreement for a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; transaction secured by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; (including a home equity line of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt;) may not include terms that require arbitration or any other non-judicial procedure to resolve any controversy or settle any claims arising out of the transaction. This prohibition does not limit a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or any assignee from agreeing, after a dispute or claim under the transaction arises, to settle or use arbitration or other non-judicial procedure to resolve that dispute or claim.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-36-h-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">No waivers of Federal statutory causes of action.</title>
          <content>No waivers of Federal statutory causes of action. A contract or other agreement relating to a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; transaction secured by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; (including a home equity line of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt;) may not be applied or interpreted to bar a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; from bringing a claim in court pursuant to any provision of law for damages or other relief in connection with any alleged violation of any Federal law. This prohibition does not limit a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or any assignee from agreeing, after a dispute or claim under the transaction arises, to settle or use arbitration or other non-judicial procedure to resolve that dispute or claim.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-d">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-d" marker="(d)">
        <title type="keyterm">Evasion; open-end credit.</title>
        <content>Evasion; &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="term"&gt;open-end credit&lt;/ref&gt;. In connection with &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; that does not meet the definition of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="term"&gt;open-end credit&lt;/ref&gt; in § &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.2(a)(20)&lt;/ref&gt;, a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; shall not structure a home-secured loan as an open-end plan to evade the requirements of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b">
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b" marker="(b)">
        <title type="keyterm">Rules affecting young consumers</title>
        <content>Rules affecting young &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt;—</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Applications from young consumers.</title>
          <content>Applications from young &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt;. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; may not open a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term"&gt;credit card&lt;/ref&gt; account under an open-end (not home-secured) &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; plan for a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; less than 21 years old, unless the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has submitted a written application and the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term"&gt;card issuer&lt;/ref&gt; has:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Financial information indicating the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the proposed extension of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; in connection with the account; or&lt;ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>A signed agreement of a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old to be either secondarily liable for any debt on the account incurred by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has attained the age of 21 or jointly liable with the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; for any debt on the account; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Financial information indicating such cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on such debts, consistent with paragraph (a) of this &lt;ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal"&gt;sec&lt;/ref&gt;tion.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Credit line increases for young consumers.</title>
          <content>&lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;Credit&lt;/ref&gt; line increases for young &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt;. &lt;ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>If a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term"&gt;credit card&lt;/ref&gt; account has been opened pursuant to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, no increase in the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; limit may be made on such account before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; attains the age of 21 unless:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>At the time of the contemplated increase, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit consistent with paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)(i)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>A cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old agrees in writing to assume liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)(ii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>If a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term"&gt;credit card&lt;/ref&gt; account has been opened pursuant to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)(ii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, no increase in the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; limit may be made on such account before the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; attains the age of 21 unless the cosigner, guarantor, or joint accountholder who assumed liability at account opening agrees in writing to assume liability on the increase.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-34-a-4-i" marker="(i)">
        <title type="keyterm">Mortgage-related obligations.</title>
        <content>Mortgage-related obligations. For purposes of this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal"&gt;(a)(4)&lt;/ref&gt;, mortgage-related obligations are expected property taxes, premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; as set forth in § &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.35(b), and &lt;/ref&gt;similar expenses.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii">
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
          <title>Paragraph 35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-1">
            <content>Payment change. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-1</ref>. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-2" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-2</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2">
            <content>Negative amortization. Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)(iv)</ref> does not include examples of payment changes in connection with negative amortization. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan agreement permits negative amortization:</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
              <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
              <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-i-1">
        <content>Mortgage-related obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must include in its repayment ability analysis the expected property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b), as w</ref>ell as similar mortgage-related expenses. Similar mortgage-related expenses include homeowners' association dues and condominium or cooperative fees.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-a-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>“Higher-priced mortgage loan” means a closed-end &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-3-v" reftype="internal"&gt;it transa&lt;/ref&gt;ction secured by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; with an annual percentage rate that exceeds the &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term"&gt;average prime offer rate&lt;/ref&gt; for a comparable transaction as of the date the interest rate is set:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>By 1.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a first lien with a principal obligation at &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; that does not exceed the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>By 2.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a first lien with a principal obligation at &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; that exceeds the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>By 3.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a subordinate lien.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>The penalty is otherwise permitted by law, including § &lt;ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(d)(7)&lt;/ref&gt; if the loan is a mortgage transaction described in § &lt;ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.32(a)&lt;/ref&gt;; and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>An escrow account need not be established for:&lt;ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A transaction secured by shares in a cooperative;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A transaction to finance the initial construction of a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>A temporary or “bridge” loan with a loan term of twelve months or less, such as a loan to purchase a new &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; where the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; plans to sell a current &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; within twelve months; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>A &lt;ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term"&gt;reverse mortgage transaction&lt;/ref&gt; subject to § &lt;ref target="1026-33-c" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.33(c)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
        <content>Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(2) of this section, a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may not extend a &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loan&lt;/ref&gt; secured by a first li&lt;ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal"&gt;en on a consu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s principal &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; unless an escrow account is established before &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt;, such as insurance against loss of or damage to property, or against liability arising out of the ownership or use of the property, or insurance protecting the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; against the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s default or other &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term"&gt;credit&lt;/ref&gt; loss. For purposes of this paragraph (b), the term “escrow account” has the same meaning as under Regulation X (12 CFR 1024.17(b)), as amended.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp" target="1026-34-a-4-i">
        <title>Paragraph 34(a)(4)(i) Mortgage-Related Obligations</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1" target="1026-34-a-4-i-1">
          <content>Mortgage-related obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must include in its repayment ability analysis the expected property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b), as w</ref>ell as similar mortgage-related expenses. Similar mortgage-related expenses include homeowners' association dues and condominium or cooperative fees.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-3">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Escrows</title>
        <content>Cancellation—</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i" marker="(i)">
          <title type="keyterm">Failure to escrow for property taxes and insurance.</title>
          <content>General. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(3)(ii) of this section, a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or s&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-3-ii" reftype="internal"&gt;ervicer ma&lt;/ref&gt;y cancel an escrow account required in paragraph (b)(1) of this section only upon the earlier of:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Termination of the underlying debt obligation; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Receipt no earlier than five years after &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; of a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s request to cancel the escrow account.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title type="keyterm">Exemptions for loans secured by shares in a cooperative and for certain condominium units.</title>
          <content>Delayed cancellation. Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section, a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or servicer shall not cancel an escrow account pursuant to a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt;'s request described in paragraph (b)(3)(i)(B) of this section unless the following conditions are satisfied:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The unpaid principal balance is less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; currently is not delinquent o&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal"&gt;r in defa&lt;/ref&gt;ult on the underlying debt obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2" marker="(2)">
        <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>Exemptions. Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(1) of this section:&lt;ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>An escrow account need not be established for:&lt;ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal"&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>A transaction secured by shares in a cooperative;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>A transaction to finance the initial construction of a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>A temporary or “bridge” loan with a loan term of twelve months or less, such as a loan to purchase a new &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; where the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumer&lt;/ref&gt; plans to sell a current &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; within twelve months; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>A &lt;ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term"&gt;reverse mortgage transaction&lt;/ref&gt; subject to § &lt;ref target="1026-33-c" reftype="internal"&gt;1026.33(c)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Insurance premiums described in paragraph (b)(1) of this section need not be included in escrow accounts for loans secured by &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwellings&lt;/ref&gt; in condominiums, planned unit developments, or other common interest communities in which &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; ownership requires participation in a governing association, where the governing association has an obligation to the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; owners to maintain a master policy insuring all &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwellings&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>Except as provided in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(v)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, an escrow account need not be established for a transaction if, at the time of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph (b)(2)(iv) of th&lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal"&gt;is section&lt;/ref&gt;;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>During the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; and its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliates&lt;/ref&gt; together originated 500 or fewer covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;Consumer&lt;/ref&gt; Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii&lt;/ref&gt; for the current threshold); and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>Neither the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; nor its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section for any extension of &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term"&gt;consumer credit&lt;/ref&gt; secured by real property or a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term"&gt;dwelling&lt;/ref&gt; that the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; or its &lt;ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term"&gt;affiliate&lt;/ref&gt; currently services, other than:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loans&lt;/ref&gt; on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>Escrow accounts established after &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt; as an accommodation to distressed &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; to assist such &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term"&gt;consumers&lt;/ref&gt; in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
          <content>For purposes of paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)(A)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term"&gt;States&lt;/ref&gt; Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;Act&lt;/ref&gt; (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditors&lt;/ref&gt; extended covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. A &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term"&gt;creditor&lt;/ref&gt; may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term"&gt;Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
          <content>Notwithstanding paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, an escrow account must be established pursuant to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section for any first-lien &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loan&lt;/ref&gt; that, at &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;, is subject to a commitment to be acquired by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term"&gt;person&lt;/ref&gt; that does not satisfy the conditions in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, unless otherwise exempted by this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-v">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>Notwithstanding paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, an escrow account must be established pursuant to paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(1)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section for any first-lien &lt;ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term"&gt;higher-priced mortgage loan&lt;/ref&gt; that, at &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term"&gt;consummation&lt;/ref&gt;, is subject to a commitment to be acquired by a &lt;ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term"&gt;person&lt;/ref&gt; that does not satisfy the conditions in paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)(iii)&lt;/ref&gt; of this section, unless otherwise exempted by this paragraph &lt;ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal"&gt;(b)(2)&lt;/ref&gt;.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2">
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii">
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
            <title>Paragraph 35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-1">
              <content>Payment change. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-1</ref>. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-2" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-2</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2">
              <content>Negative amortization. Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)(iv)</ref> does not include examples of payment changes in connection with negative amortization. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan agreement permits negative amortization:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
                <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
                <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-32-d-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-32-d-Interp-1" target="1026-32-d-1">
        <content>Additional prohibitions applicable under other sections. Section <ref target="1026-34" reftype="internal">1026.34</ref> sets forth certain prohibitions in connection with mortgage <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref>, in addition to the limitations in § <ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)</ref>. Further, § <ref target="1026-35-b" reftype="internal">1026.35 pr</ref>ohibits certain practices in connection with transactions that meet the coverage test in § 102<ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">6.35(a). B</ref>ecause the coverage test in § 102<ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">6.35(a) is</ref> generally broader than the coverage test in § 102<ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">6.32(a), m</ref>ost § 102<ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">6.32 mo</ref>rtgage loans are also subject to the prohibitions set forth in § 102<ref target="1026-35-b" reftype="internal">6.35 (such</ref> as escrows), in addition to the limitations in § 1026.3<ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal">2(d).</ref></content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2">
        <content>Negative amortization. Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)(iv)</ref> does not include examples of payment changes in connection with negative amortization. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan agreement permits negative amortization:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-i">
          <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-2-ii">
          <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan agreement permits negative amortization to occur. Under the loan agreement, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if negative amortization occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-1">
        <content>Payment change. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-1" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-1</ref>. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment <ref target="1026-32-d-7-iv-Interp-2" reftype="internal">32(d)(7)(iv)-2</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii" target="1026-35-b-2-iv-2-ii">
        <content>A county is considered “underserved” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available HMDA data. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien covered transactions in County Y during calendar year 2013, and the most recent HMDA data is for calendar year 2012, published in the third quarter of 2013. To determine “underserved” status for County Y in calendar year 2013 for the purposes of qualifying for the “rural or underserved” exemption in calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2012 HMDA data.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
