<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-05-23</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-12125</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2013-06-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2013/05/23/2013-12125/amendments-to-the-2013-escrows-final-rule-under-the-truth-in-lending-act-regulation-z</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-01503_20130601" rightDocumentNumber="2013-12125">
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-23-a-3-ii">
    <paragraph label="1026-23-a-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
      <content>For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-23-a-3" reftype="internal">(a)(3)</ref>, the term “<def term="material disclosure">material disclosures</def>” means the required disclosures of the annual percentage rate, the finance charge, the amount financed, the total of payments, the payment schedule, and the disclosures and limitations referred to in §§ <ref target="1026-32-c" reftype="internal">1026.32(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-34-a-4-i" marker="(i)">
      <title type="keyterm">Mortgage-related obligations.</title>
      <content>For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">(a)(4)</ref>, mortgage-related obligations are expected property taxes, premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)</ref>, and similar expenses.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-1">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-1" marker="(1)">
      <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
      <content>Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance. Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may not extend a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> unless an escrow account is established before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, such as insurance against loss of or damage to property, or against liability arising out of the ownership or use of the property, or insurance protecting the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> against the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s default or other credit loss. For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref>, the term “escrow account” has the same meaning as under Regulation X (<ref target="CFR:12-1024" reftype="external">12 CFR 1024</ref>.17(b)), as amended.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended more than 50 percent of its total <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iv)</ref> of this section;</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="added" label="1026-35-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-e" marker="(e)">
      <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability, prepayment penalties.</title>
      <content><ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">Higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> are subject to the following restrictions:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall not extend <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> based on the value of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s collateral without regard to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s repayment ability as of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as provided in § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2" marker="(2)">
        <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>A loan may not include a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The penalty is otherwise permitted by law, including § <ref target="1026-32-d-7" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(7)</ref> if the loan is a mortgage transaction described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref>; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Under the terms of the loan:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The penalty will not apply after the two-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or an <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-e-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Sunset of requirements on repayment ability and prepayment penalties.</title>
        <content>The requirements described in this paragraph <ref target="1026-35-e" reftype="internal">(e)</ref> shall expire at 11:59 p.m. on January 9, 2014.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-32-d-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-32-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Additional prohibitions applicable under other sections.</title>
      <content>Section <ref target="1026-34" reftype="internal">1026.34</ref> sets forth certain prohibitions in connection with mortgage <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref>, in addition to the limitations in § <ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)</ref>. Further, § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> prohibits certain practices in connection with transactions that meet the coverage test in § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. Because the coverage test in § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref> is generally broader than the coverage test in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref>, most § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref> mortgage loans are also subject to the prohibitions set forth in § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> (such as escrows), in addition to the limitations in § <ref target="1026-32-d" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Application of repayment ability rule.</title>
      <content>The § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition against making loans without regard to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>' repayment ability applies to <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref>. In addition, the § <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">1026.34(a)(4)</ref> prohibition applies to <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> described in § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. See § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(1)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-34-a-4-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Mortgage-related obligations.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must include in its repayment ability analysis the expected property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)</ref>, as well as similar mortgage-related expenses. Similar mortgage-related expenses include homeowners' association dues and condominium or cooperative fees.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1" subpath="content">
    <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(v)</ref>, a creditor need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the higher-priced mortgage loan is consummated:</content>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" subpath="content">
  <content>During the preceding calendar year, more than 50 percent of the creditor's total first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), are secured by properties located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. Pursuant to that section, a creditor may rely as a safe harbor on a list of counties published by the Bureau to determine whether counties in the United States are rural or underserved for a particular calendar year. Thus, for example, if a creditor originated 90 covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, during 2013, the creditor meets this condition for an exemption in 2014 if at least 46 of those transactions are secured by first liens on properties that are located in such counties.</content>
  </change><change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Requirements for “rural” or “underserved” status.</title>
      <content>A county is considered to be “rural” or “underserved” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> if it satisfies either of the two tests in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> applies both tests to each county in the United States. If a county satisfies either test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will include the county on a published list of “rural” or “underserved” counties for a particular calendar year. To facilitate compliance with apprai<ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">sal requir</ref>ements in § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will also create a list of only those counties that are “rural” but excluding those that are only “underserved.” The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will post on its public Web site the applicable lists for each calendar year by the end of that year, thus permitting <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to ascertain the availability to them of the exemption during the following year. For 2012, however, the list will be published before June 1, 2013. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor, pursuant to section 130(f) of the Truth in Lending Act, on the lists of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” or “underserved” for a <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">particular calendar y</ref>ear. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s originations of <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, in such counties during that year are considered in determining whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the condition in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> and therefore will be eligible for the exemption during the following calendar year.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, a county is rural during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. These areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). Accordingly, for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, “adjacent” has the meaning applied by the USDA-ERS in determining a county's UIC; as so applied, “adjacent” entails a county not only being physically contiguous with a metropolitan statistical area but also meeting certain minimum population commuting patterns. Specifically, a county is “rural” if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx. A county for which there is no currently applicable UIC (because the county has been created since the USDA-ERS last categorized counties) is rural only if all counties from which the new county's land was taken are themselves rural under currently applicable UICs.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, a county is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, five or more times in the county. Specifically, a county is “underserved” if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title type="keyterm">Examples.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
        <content>A county is considered “rural” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available UIC designations, which are updated by the USDA-ERS once every ten years. As an example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in County X during calendar year 2014, and the most recent UIC designations have been published in the second quarter of 2013. To determine “rural” status for County X during calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2013 UIC designations. However, to determine “rural” status for County X during 2012 or 2013, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> would use the UIC designations last published in 2003.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>A county is considered “underserved” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available HMDA data. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in County Y during calendar year 2013, and the most recent HMDA data is for calendar year 2012, published in the third quarter of 2013. To determine “underserved” status for County Y in calendar year 2013 for the purposes of qualifying for the “rural or underserved” exemption in calendar year 2014, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2012 HMDA data.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><change operation="added" label="1026-35-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-Interp">
      <title>35(e) Rules for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-Interp">
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-Interp">
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp" target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C">
            <title>Paragraph 35(e)(2)(ii)(C).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Payment change.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> provides that a loan subject to this section may not have a penalty described by § <ref target="1026-32-d-6" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(6)</ref> unless certain conditions are met. Section <ref target="1026-35-e-2-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)(ii)(C)</ref> lists as a condition that the amount of the periodic payment of principal or interest or both may not change during the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. For examples showing whether a prepayment penalty is permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, see comment 32(d)(7)(iv)-1. Those examples, however, include a condition that § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> does not include: The condition that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s total monthly debt payments may not exceed 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s monthly gross income. For guidance about circumstances in which payment changes are not considered payment changes for purposes of this section, see comment 32(d)(7)(iv)-2.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Negative amortization.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-32-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(d)(2)</ref> provides that a loan described in § <ref target="1026-32-a" reftype="internal">1026.32(a)</ref> may not have a payment schedule with regular periodic payments that cause the principal balance to increase. Therefore, the commentary to § 1026.32(d)(7)(iv) does not include examples of payment changes in connection with <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref>. The following examples show whether, under § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref>, prepayment penalties are permitted or prohibited in connection with particular payment changes, when a loan <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> permits <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref>:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010, are $1,000 per month and the loan <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> permits <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> to occur. Under the loan <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not have the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date even if <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> occurs. A prepayment penalty is permitted with this mortgage transaction provided that the other § <ref target="1026-35-e-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(e)(2)</ref> conditions are met, that is: Provided that the prepayment penalty is permitted by other applicable law, the penalty expires on or before December 31, 2011, and the penalty will not apply if the source of the prepayment funds is a refinancing by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-e-2-ii-C-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>Initial payments for a variable-rate transaction consummated on January 1, 2010 are $1,000 per month and the loan <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> permits <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> to occur. Under the loan <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, the first date that a scheduled payment in a different amount may be due is January 1, 2014, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has the right to change scheduled payments prior to that date if <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> occurs. A prepayment penalty is prohibited with this mortgage transaction because the payment may change within the four-year period following <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
