<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2014-01-18</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-30108_20140118</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2014-01-18</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/articles/2013/12/26/2013-30108/appraisals-for-higher-priced-mortgage-loans</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-01809" rightDocumentNumber="2013-30108_20140118">
    <!-- Changes include 1026.35 and Appendix N -->
    <!-- Revise the paragraph (c) subject heading and paragraphs (c)(1)(ii) through (iv); -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c" subpath="content">
      <content>Appraisals—</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-1-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>Credit risk means the financial risk that a consumer will default on a loan.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-1-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <content><def term="manufactured home">Manufactured home</def> has the same meaning as in <ref target="CFR:24-3280-2" reftype="external">24 CFR 3280.2</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-1-iv">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <content>Manufacturer’s invoice means a document issued by a manufacturer and provided with a <ref target="1026-35-c-1-iii" reftype="term">manufactured home</ref> to a retail dealer that separately details the wholesale (base) prices at the factory for specific models or series of manufactured homes and itemized options (large appliances, built-in items and equipment), plus actual itemized charges for freight from the factory to the dealer’s lot or the homesite (including any rental of wheels and axles) and for any sales taxes to be paid by the dealer. The invoice may recite such prices and charges on an itemized basis or by stating an aggregate price or charge, as appropriate, for each category.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <!-- Add paragraphs (c)(1)(v) through (vii); -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-1-v">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>National Registry means the database of information about <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> certified and licensed appraisers maintained by the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-1-vi">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-vi" marker="(vi)">
        <content><def term="new manufactured home">New manufactured home</def> means a <ref target="1026-35-c-1-iii" reftype="term">manufactured home</ref> that has not been previously occupied.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-1-vii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-1-vii" marker="(vii)">
        <content><ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> agency means a “State appraiser certifying and licensing agency” recognized in accordance with section 1118(b) of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989 (<ref target="USC:12-3347" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3347</ref>(b)) and any implementing regulations.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <!-- Revise paragraphs (c)(2) introductory text, (c)(2)(i) and (ii), and (v) -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2" subpath="content">
      <content>Unless otherwise specified, the requirements in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-c-3" reftype="internal">(c)(3)</ref> through <ref target="1026-35-c-6" reftype="internal">(6)</ref> of this section do not apply to the following types of transactions:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>A loan that satisfies the criteria of a qualified mortgage as defined pursuant to <ref target="USC:15-1639" reftype="external">15 U.S.C. 1639c</ref>;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>An extension of credit for which the amount of credit extended is equal to or less than the applicable threshold amount, which is adjusted every year to reflect increases in the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, as applicable, and published in the official staff commentary to this paragraph <ref target="1026-35-c-2-ii" reftype="internal">(c)(2)(ii)</ref>;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2-v">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>A loan with maturity of 12 months or less, if the purpose of the loan is a “bridge” loan connected with the acquisition of a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> intended to become the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <!-- Add paragraphs (c)(2)(vii) and (viii).  -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-vii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii" marker="(vii)">
        <content>An extension of credit that is a refinancing secured by a first lien, with refinancing defined as in § 1026.20(a) (except that the creditor need not be the original creditor or a holder or servicer of the original obligation), provided that the refinancing meets the following criteria:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Either—</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The credit risk of the refinancing is retained by the person that held the credit risk of the existing obligation and there is no commitment, at consummation, to transfer the credit risk to another person; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The refinancing is insured or guaranteed by the same Federal government agency that insured or guaranteed the existing obligation;</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>The regular periodic payments under the refinance loan do not—</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>Cause the principal balance to increase;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>Allow the consumer to defer repayment of principal; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>Result in a balloon payment, as defined in § 1026.18(s)(5)(i); and</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>The proceeds from the refinancing are used solely to satisfy the existing obligation and amounts attributed solely to the costs of the refinancing; and</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-viii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-c-2-viii" marker="(viii)">
        <content>A transaction secured in whole or in part by a <ref target="1026-35-c-1-iii" reftype="term">manufactured home</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <!-- Appendix N intro para and paragraph 7 -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-N-p1" subpath="content">
      <content>To qualify for the safe harbor provided in § <ref target="1026-35-c-3-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)(3)(ii)</ref>, a creditor must confirm that the written appraisal:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-N-p1-7" subpath="content">
      <content>Indicates that a physical property visit of the interior of the property was performed, as applicable.</content>
    </change>

    <!-- Supplement I (Interp) updates -->
    <!-- The 35(c)(2) entry is amended by adding paragraph 1. -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2-Interp" subpath="content">
      <content>Compliance with title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989 (FIRREA). Section 1026.35(c)(2) provides exemptions solely from the requirements of section 1026.35(c)(3) through (6). Institutions subject to the requirements of FIRREA and its implementing regulations that make a loan qualifying for an exemption under section 1026.35(c)(2) must still comply with appraisal and evaluation requirements under FIRREA and its implementing regulations.</content>
    </change>
    <!-- A 35(c)(2)(i) entry is added. -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-i-Interp" target="1026-35-c-2-i">
        <title>Paragraph 35(c)(2)(i)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Qualified mortgage criteria.</title>
          <content>Under § 1026.35(c)(2)(i), a loan is exempt from the appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c) if either:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-i-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>The loan is—(1) subject to the Bureau’s ability-to-repay requirements in § 1026.43 as a “covered transaction” (defined in § 1026.43(b)(1)) and (2) a qualified mortgage pursuant to the Bureau’s rules or, for loans insured, guaranteed, or administered by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), U.S. Department of Veterans Affairs (VA), U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA), or Rural Housing Service (RHS), a qualified mortgage pursuant to applicable rules prescribed by those agencies (but only once such rules are in effect; otherwise, the Bureau’s definition of a qualified mortgage applies to those loans); or</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-i-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>The loan is—(1) not subject to the Bureau’s ability-to-repay requirements in § 1026.43 as a “covered transaction” (defined in § 1026.43(b)(1)), but (2) meets the criteria for a qualified mortgage in the Bureau’s rules or, for loans insured, guaranteed, or administered by HUD, VA, USDA, or RHS, meets the criteria for a qualified mortgage in the applicable rules prescribed by those agencies (but only once such rules are in effect; otherwise, the Bureau’s criteria for a qualified mortgage applies to those loans). To explain further, loans enumerated in § 1026.43(a) are not “covered transaction” under the Bureau’s ability-to-repay requirements in § 1026.43, and thus cannot be qualified mortgages (entitled to a rebuttable presumption or safe harbor of compliance with the ability-to-repay requirements of § 1026.43, see, e.g., § 1026.43(e)(1)). These include an extension of credit made pursuant to a program administered by a Housing Finance Agency, as defined under 24 CFR 266.5, or pursuant to a program authorized by sections 101 and 109 of the Emergency Economic Stabilization Act of 2008. See § 1026.43(a)(3)(iv) and (vi). They also include extensions of credit made by a creditor identified in § 1026.43(a)(3)(v). However, these loans are eligible for the exemption in § 1026.35(c)(2)(i) if they meet the Bureau’s qualified mortgage criteria in § 1026.43(e)(2), (4), (5), or (6) or § 1026.43(f) (including limits on when loans must be consummated) or, for loans that are insured, guaranteed, or administered by HUD, VA, USDA, or RHS, in applicable rules prescribed by those agencies (but only once such rules are in effect; otherwise, the Bureau’s criteria for a qualified mortgage applies to those loans). For example, assume that HUD has prescribed rules to define loans insured under its programs that are qualified mortgages and those rules are in effect. Assume further that a creditor designated as a Community Development Financial Institution, as defined under 12 CFR 1805.104(h), originates a loan insured by the Federal Housing Administration, which is a part of HUD. The loan is not a “covered transaction” and thus is not a qualified mortgage. See § 1026.43(a)(3)(v)(A) and (b)(1). Nonetheless, the transaction is eligible for an exemption from the appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c) if it meets the qualified mortgage criteria in HUD’s rules. Nothing in § 1026.35(c)(2)(i) alters the definition of a qualified mortgage under regulations of the Bureau, HUD, VA, USDA, or RHS.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <!-- The 35(c)(2)(ii) entry is revised. -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-2-ii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-ii-Interp" target="1026-35-c-2-ii">
        <title>Paragraph 35(c)(2)(ii)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Threshold amount.</title>
          <content>For purposes of § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii), the threshold amount in effect during a particular one-year period is the amount stated below for that period. The threshold amount is adjusted effective January 1 of every year by the percentage increase in the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers (CPI–W) that was in effect on the preceding June 1. Every year, this comment will be amended to provide the threshold amount for the upcoming one-year period after the annual percentage change in the CPI–W that was in effect on June 1 becomes available. Any increase in the threshold amount will be rounded to the nearest $100 increment. For example, if the percentage increase in the CPI–W would result in a $950 increase in the threshold amount, the threshold amount will be increased by $1,000. However, if the percentage increase in the CPI–W would result in a $949 increase in the threshold amount, the threshold amount will be increased by $900.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-ii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>From January 18, 2014, through December 31, 2014, the threshold amount is $25,000.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Qualifying for exemption—in general.</title>
          <content>A transaction is exempt under § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii) if the creditor makes an extension of credit at consummation that is equal to or below the threshold amount in effect at the time of consummation. 3. Qualifying for exemption—subsequent changes. A transaction does not meet the condition for an exemption under § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii) merely because it is used to satisfy and replace an existing exempt loan, unless the amount of the new extension of credit is equal to or less than the applicable threshold amount. For example, assume a closed-end loan that qualified for a § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii) exemption at consummation in year one is refinanced in year ten and that the new loan amount is greater than the threshold amount in effect in year ten. In these circumstances, the creditor must comply with all of the applicable requirements of § 1026.35(c) with respect to the year ten transaction if the original loan is satisfied and replaced by the new loan, unless another exemption from the requirements of § 1026.35(c) applies. See § 1026.35(c)(2) and § 1026.35(c)(4)(vii).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <!-- The 35(c)(2)(iv) entry is amended by adding paragraph 2. -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-iv-Interp-2" after="1026-35-c-2-iv-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-iv-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Financing initial construction.</title>
        <content>The exemption for construction loans in § 1026.35(c)(2)(iv) applies to temporary financing of the construction of a dwelling that will be replaced by permanent financing once construction is complete. The exemption does not apply, for example, to loans to finance the purchase of manufactured homes that have not been or are in the process of being built when the financing obtained by the consumer at that time is permanent. See § 1026.35(c)(2)(viii).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <!-- A 35(c)(2)(vii)(A)(1) entry is added. -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp" parent="1026-35-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-35-c-2-vii-A">
        <title type="keyterm">Paragraph 35(c)(2)(vii)(A)(1)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Same credit risk holder.</title>
        <content>The requirement that the holder of the credit risk on the existing obligation and the refinancing be the same applies to situations in which an entity bears the financial responsibility for the default of a loan by either holding the loan in its portfolio or guaranteeing payments of principal and any interest to investors in a mortgage-backed security in which the loan is pooled. See § 1026.35(c)(1)(ii) (defining “credit risk”). For example, a credit risk holder could be a bank that bears the credit risk on the existing obligation by holding the loan in the bank’s portfolio. Another example of a credit risk holder would be a government-sponsored enterprise that bears the risk of default on a loan by guaranteeing the payment of principal and any interest on a loan to investors in a mortgage-backed security. The holder of credit risk under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii)(A)(1) does not mean individual investors in a mortgage-backed security or providers of private mortgage insurance.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Same credit risk holder-illustrations.</title>
          <content>Illustrations of the credit risk holder of the existing obligation continuing to be the credit risk holder of the refinancing include, but are not limited to, the following:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
            <content>The existing obligation is held in the portfolio of a bank, thus the bank holds the credit risk. The bank arranges to refinance the loan and also will hold the refinancing in its portfolio. If the refinancing otherwise meets the requirements for an exemption under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii), the transaction will qualify for the exemption because the credit risk holder is the same for the existing obligation and the refinance transaction. In this case, the exemption would apply regardless of whether the bank arranged to refinance the loan directly or indirectly, such as through the servicer or subservicer on the existing obligation.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>The existing obligation is held in the portfolio of a government-sponsored enterprise (GSE), thus the GSE holds the credit risk. The existing obligation is then refinanced by the servicer of the loan and immediately transferred to the GSE. The GSE pools the refinancing in a mortgage-backed security guaranteed by the GSE, thus the GSE holds the credit risk on the refinance loan. If the refinance transaction otherwise meets the requirements for an exemption under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii), the transaction will qualify for the exemption because the credit risk holder is the same for the existing obligation and the refinance transaction. In this case, the exemption would apply regardless of whether the existing obligation was refinanced by the servicer or subservicer on the existing obligation (acting as a “creditor” under § 1026.2(a)(17)) or by a different creditor.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Forward commitments.</title>
          <content>A creditor may make a mortgage loan that will be sold or otherwise transferred pursuant to an agreement that has been entered into at or before the time the transaction is consummated. Such an agreement is sometimes known as a “forward commitment.” A refinance loan does not satisfy the requirement of § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii)(A)(1) if the loan will be acquired pursuant to a forward commitment, such that the credit risk on the refinance loan will transfer to a person who did not hold the credit risk on the existing obligation.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <!-- Entries for 35(c)(2)(vii)(B) and (C) are added. -->
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-Interp" after="1026-35-c-2-vii-A-1-Interp" parent="1026-35-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-35-c-2-vii-B">
        <title type="keyterm">Paragraph 35(c)(2)(vii)(B)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Regular periodic payments.</title>
          <content>Under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii)(B), the regular periodic payments on the refinance loan must not: result in an increase of the principal balance (negative amortization); allow the consumer to defer repayment of principal (see comment 43(e)(2)(i)–2); or result in a balloon payment. Thus, the terms of the legal obligation must require the consumer to make payments of principal and interest on a monthly or other periodic basis that will repay the loan amount over the loan term. Except for payments resulting from any interest rate changes after consummation in an adjustablerate or step-rate mortgage, the periodic payments must be substantially equal. For an explanation of the term “substantially equal,” see comment 43(c)(5)(i)–4. In addition, a single-payment transaction is not a refinancing meeting the requirements of § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii) because it does not require “regular periodic payments.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-c-2-vii-C-Interp" after="1026-35-c-2-vii-B-Interp" parent="1026-35-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-C-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-35-c-2-vii-C">
        <title type="keyterm">Paragraph 35(c)(2)(vii)(C)</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-2-vii-C-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Permissible use of proceeds.</title>
          <content>The exemption for a refinancing under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii) is available only if the proceeds from the refinancing are used exclusively for the existing obligation and amounts attributed solely to the costs of the refinancing. The existing obligation includes the unpaid principal balance of the existing first lien loan, any earned unpaid finance charges, and any other lawful charges related to the existing loan. For guidance on the meaning of refinancing costs, see comment 23(f)–4. If the proceeds of a refinancing are used for other purposes, such as to pay off other liens or to provide additional cash to the consumer for discretionary spending, the transaction does not qualify for the exemption for a refinancing under § 1026.35(c)(2)(vii) from the appraisal requirements in § 1026.35(c).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <!-- Under the 35(c)(6)(ii) entry, paragraph 2 is removed and paragraph 3 is redesignated as paragraph 2. -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-c-6-ii-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-c-6-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">No waiver.</title>
        <content>Regulation B, <ref target="CFR:12-1002-14" reftype="external">12 CFR 1002.14</ref>(a)(1), allowing the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to waive the requirement that the appraisal copy be provided three business days before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, does not apply to <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> of a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref> may not waive the timing requirement to receive a copy of the appraisal under § <ref target="1026-35-c-6-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)(6)(i)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-c-6-ii-Interp-3" />
    <!-- End of notice changes -->
  </changeset>
    <!-- SxS analysis updates -->
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-1-i" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(1)(i) Certified or Licensed Appraiser</title>
      <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129H(b)(3) defines “certified or licensed appraiser” as a person who “(A) is, at a minimum, certified or licensed by the State in which the property to be appraised is located; and (B) performs each appraisal in conformity with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice and title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, and the regulations prescribed under such title, as in effect on the date of the appraisal.” 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(3). Consistent with the statute, the Agencies proposed to define “certified or licensed appraiser” as a person who is certified or licensed by the State agency in the State in which the property that secures the transaction is located, and who performs the appraisal in conformity with the Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice (USPAP) and the requirements applicable to appraisers in title XI of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989, as amended (FIRREA title XI) (12 U.S.C. 3331 et seq.), and any implementing regulations in effect at the time the appraiser signs the appraiser's certification.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The proposed definition of “certified or licensed appraiser” generally mirrors the statutory language in TILA section 129H(b)(3) regarding State licensing and certification. However, the Agencies proposed to use the defined term “State agency” to clarify that the appraiser must be certified or licensed by a State agency that meets the standards of FIRREA title XI. The proposal defined the term “State agency” to mean a “State appraiser certifying and licensing agency” recognized in accordance with section 1118(b) of FIRREA title XI (12 U.S.C. 3347(b)) and any implementing regulations.<footnote ref="22">If the Appraisal Subcommittee of the Federal Financial Institutions Examination Council issues certain written findings concerning, among other   things, a State agency's failure to recognize and enforce FIRREA title XI standards, appraiser certifications and licenses issued by that State are not recognized for purposes of title XI and appraisals performed by appraisers certified or licensed by that State are not acceptable for federally-related transactions. 12 U.S.C. 3347(b).</footnote> See section-by-section analysis of § 1026.35(c)(1)(iv), below.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed below, the Agencies are adopting the proposed definition of “certified or licensed appraiser” without change.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice (USPAP). Consistent with the statutory definition of “certified or licensed appraiser,” the proposal incorporated into the proposed definition the requirement that, to be a “certified or licensed appraiser” under the appraisal rules, the appraiser has to perform the appraisal in conformity with the “Uniform Standards of Professional Appraisal Practice.” A comment was proposed to clarify that USPAP refers to the professional appraisal standards established by the Appraisal Standards Board of the “Appraisal Foundation,” as defined in FIRREA section 1121(9). 12 U.S.C. 3350(9). The Agencies believe that this terminology is appropriate for consistency with the existing definition in FIRREA title XI and adopt the definition and comment as proposed. See § 1026.35(c)(1)(i) and comment 35(c)(1)(i)-1.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In addition, TILA section 129H(b)(3) requires that the appraisal be performed in conformity with USPAP “as in effect on the date of the appraisal.” 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(3). The Agencies proposed to incorporate this concept in the definition of “certified or licensed appraiser” and to include a comment clarifying that the “date of the appraisal” is the date on which the appraiser signs the appraiser's certification. Again, the Agencies adopt the definition and comment as proposed. See § 1026.35(c)(1)(i) and comment 35(c)(1)(i)-1. Thus, the relevant edition of USPAP is the one in effect at the time the appraiser signs the appraiser's certification.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Appraiser's certification. The proposal also included a comment to clarify that the term “appraiser's certification” refers to the certification that must be signed by the appraiser for each appraisal assignment as specified in USPAP Standards Rule 2-3.<footnote ref="23">See Appraisal Standards Bd., Appraisal Fdn., Standards Rule 2-3, USPAP (2012-2013 ed.) at U-29, available at http://www.uspap.org.</footnote> The final rule adopts this clarification without change. See comment 35(c)(1)(i)-2.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>FIRREA title XI and implementing regulations. As noted, TILA section 129H(b)(3) defines “certified or licensed appraiser” as a person who is certified or licensed as an appraiser and “performs each appraisal in accordance with [USPAP] and title XI of [FIRREA], and the regulations prescribed under such title, as in effect on the date of the appraisal.” 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(3). Section 1110 of FIRREA directs each Federal financial institutions regulatory agency<footnote ref="24">The Federal financial institutions regulatory agencies are the Board, the FDIC, the OCC, and the NCUA.</footnote> to prescribe “appropriate standards for the performance of real estate appraisals in connection with federally related transactions under the jurisdiction of each such agency or instrumentality.” 12 U.S.C. 3339. These rules must require, at a minimum—(1) that real estate appraisals be performed in accordance with generally accepted appraisal standards as evidenced by the appraisal standards promulgated by the Appraisal Standards Board of the Appraisal Foundation; and (2) that such appraisals shall be written appraisals. 12 U.S.C. 3339(1) and (2).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Dodd-Frank Act added a third requirement—that real estate appraisals be subject to appropriate review for compliance with USPAP—for which the Federal financial institutions regulatory agencies must prescribe implementing regulations. FIRREA section 1110(3), 12 U.S.C. 3339(3). FIRREA section 1110 also provides that each Federal banking agency may require compliance with additional standards if the agency determines in writing that additional standards are required to properly carry out its statutory responsibilities. 12 U.S.C. 3339. Accordingly, the Federal financial institutions regulatory agencies have prescribed appraisal regulations implementing FIRREA title XI that set forth, among other requirements, minimum standards for the performance of real estate appraisals in connection with “federally related transactions,” which are defined as real estate-related financial transactions that a Federal banking agency engages in, contracts for, or regulates, and that require the services of an appraiser.<footnote ref="25">See OCC: 12 CFR Part 34, Subpart C; Board: 12 CFR part 208, subpart E, and 12 CFR part 225, subpart G; FDIC: 12 CFR part 323; and NCUA: 12 CFR part 722.</footnote> 12 U.S.C. 3339, 3350(4).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Agencies' proposal provided that the relevant provisions of FIRREA title XI and its implementing regulations are those selected portions of FIRREA title XI requirements “applicable to appraisers,” in effect at the time the appraiser signs the appraiser's certification. While the Federal financial institutions regulatory agencies' requirements in FIRREA also apply to an institution's ordering and review of an appraisal, the Agencies proposed that the definition of “certified or licensed appraiser” incorporate only FIRREA title XI's minimum standards related to the appraiser's performance of the appraisal. Accordingly, a proposed comment clarified that the relevant standards “applicable to appraisers” are found in regulations prescribed under FIRREA section 1110 (12 U.S.C. 3339) “that relate to an appraiser's development and reporting of the appraisal,” and that paragraph (3) of FIRREA, which relates to the review of appraisals, is not relevant. The Agencies are adopting these proposals as § 1026.35(c)(1)(i) and comment 35(c)(1)(i)-3.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Agencies also noted that FIRREA title XI applies by its terms to “federally related transactions” involving a narrower category of loans and institutions than the group of loans and lenders that fall within TILA's definition of “creditor.”<footnote ref="26">TILA section 103(g), 15 U.S.C. 1602(g) (implemented by § 1026.2(a)(17)). See also 12 U.S.C. 3350(4) and OCC: 12 CFR 34.42(f); Board: 12 CFR 225.62(f); FDIC: 12 CFR 323.2(f); and NCUA: 12 CFR 722.2(e) (defining &#8220;federally related transaction&#8221;).</footnote> For example, the FIRREA title XI regulations do not apply to transactions of $250,000 or less.<footnote ref="27">See OCC: 12 CFR 34.43(a)(1); Board: 12 CFR 225.63(a)(1); FDIC: 12 CFR 323.3(a)(1); and NCUA: 12 CFR 722.3(a)(1).</footnote> They also do not apply to non-depository institutions.<footnote ref="28">See 12 U.S.C. 3339, 3350(4) (defining &#8220;federally related transaction,&#8221; (6) (defining &#8220;federal financial institutions regulatory agencies&#8221;) and (7) (defining &#8220;financial institution&#8221;).</footnote> However, the Agencies believe that Congress, by including the higher-risk mortgage appraisal rules in TILA, which applies to all creditors, demonstrated its intention that all creditors that extend higher-risk mortgage loans, such as independent mortgage companies, should obtain appraisals from appraisers who conform to the standards in FIRREA related to the development and reporting of the appraisal. The Agencies also believe that, by placing this rule in TILA, Congress did not intend to limit its application to loans over $250,000. The Agencies adopt this broader interpretation in the final rule.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In the proposed rule, the Agencies did not identify specific FIRREA regulations that relate to the appraiser's development and reporting of the appraisal. The Agencies requested comment on whether the final rule should address any particular FIRREA requirements applicable to appraisers that related to the development and reporting of the appraisal. Consistent with the proposal, the final rule does not identify specific FIRREA regulations that relate to the appraiser's development and reporting of the appraisal.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Appraiser trade associations, a housing advocate, and a credit union commenter agreed that the rule should apply to all qualifying mortgage loans, and not only the subset of the higher-risk mortgage loans already covered by FIRREA, including those loans with a transaction value of $250,000 or less. The appraiser trade associations and the housing advocate commenters believed that all higher-risk mortgages must be included in the rule to ensure that consumers receive the protections offered by appraisals. The housing advocate commenter also believed that including all higher-risk mortgages would reduce risk to all parties involved in the financing and servicing of mortgages and would ensure equal access to credit. This commenter specifically requested that the Agencies at least require an interior appraisal by licensed appraisers for all residential mortgages above $50,000, regardless of whether they are originated or insured by the private sector, Fannie Mae, Freddie Mac, or the Federal Housing Administration (FHA).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>A banking trade association and a credit union commenter, however, believed that Congress intended the FIRREA requirements to apply only to a subset of higher-risk mortgages that are already covered by FIRREA. The banking trade association commenter believed the Agencies should not require the rule to apply to loans held in portfolio or loans with a value of $250,000 or less, because a bank holding a loan in portfolio has strong incentive to ensure that the property sale is legitimate and the property is properly valued. The commenter also believed the statute intended to apply the rules only to the subset of higher-risk mortgages with a value of over $250,000, as is provided in the Federal financial institutions regulatory agencies' regulations implementing FIRREA. The banking trade association and a bank commenter noted that many community banks, particularly in rural areas, limit costs to consumers by not requiring appraisals on mortgages held in portfolio of $250,000 or less as permitted under FIRREA title XI or by performing cheaper, in-house evaluations of property.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>On whether the final rule should identify specific FIRREA regulations that relate to the development and reporting of the appraisal, the Agencies received one comment letter from appraiser trade associations. These commenters requested that the Agencies specify that creditors must use certified rather than licensed appraisers. The comment is discussed in more detail in the discussion of the use of “certified” versus “licensed” appraisers, below.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the proposal, the Agencies believe that, by referencing FIRREA requirements in the context of defining “certified or licensed appraiser,” the statute intended to limit FIRREA's requirements to those that apply to the appraiser's development and reporting of performance of the appraisal, rather than the FIRREA requirements that apply to a creditor's ordering and review of the appraisal. TILA section 129H(b)(3), 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(3). The Agencies also did not propose to interpret “certified or licensed appraiser” to include requirements related to appraisal review under FIRREA section 1110(3) because these requirements relate to an institution's responsibilities after receiving the appraisal, rather than to how the certified or licensed appraiser performs the appraisal. Comment 35(c)(1)(i)-3 is consistent with the proposal in this regard. Accordingly, as proposed, the final rule includes a comment clarifying that the requirements of FIRREA section 1110(3) that relate to the “appropriate review” of appraisals are not relevant for purposes of whether an appraiser is a certified or licensed appraiser under the proposal. See comment 35(c)(1)(i)-3.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>At the same time and in light of public comments, the Agencies reviewed the relevant statutory provisions and confirmed their conclusion that applying the FIRREA requirements related to an appraiser's performance of an appraisal broadly—to transactions originated by creditors and transaction types not necessarily subject to FIRREA (such as loans of $250,000 or less)—is wholly consistent with the consumer protection purpose of title XIV of the Dodd-Frank Act, as well as specific language of the appraisal provisions. For example, the Agencies believe that if Congress intended to limit application of the FIRREA requirements to mortgage loans covered by FIRREA, such as loans of over $250,000 made by Federally-regulated depositories, Congress would have expressly done so. Instead, Congress placed the appraisal requirements, including the definition of “certified and licensed appraiser” referencing FIRREA, in TILA, which applies to loans made by all types of creditors. Moreover, limiting coverage of the Dodd-Frank Act higher-risk mortgage appraisal rules to loans of over $250,000 would eliminate protections for most higher-risk mortgage consumers.<footnote ref="29">According to HMDA data, mean loan size for purchase-money HPMLs in 2011 was $141,600 (median $109,000) and for refinance HPMLs in 2011, mean loans size was $141,600 (median $104,000). In 2010, mean loan size for purchase-money HPMLs was $140,400 (median $100,000) and for refinance HPMLs, mean loan size was $138,600 (median $95,000). See Robert B. Avery, Neil Bhutta, Kenneth B. Brevoort, and Glenn Canner, &#8220;The Mortgage Market in 2011: Highlights from the Data Reported under the Home Mortgage Disclosure Act,&#8221; FR Bulletin, Vol. 98, no. 6 (Dec. 2012) http://www.federalreserve.gov/pubs/bulletin/2012/PDF/2011_HMDA.pdf.</footnote> From a practical standpoint, the Agencies believe that the most reasonable interpretation of the statute is that all mortgage loans meeting the definition of “higher-risk mortgage” are subject to a uniform set of rules, regardless of the type of creditor. This creates a level playing field and ensures the same protections for all consumers of “higher-risk mortgages.” For these reasons, consistent with the proposal, the final rule applies the FIRREA requirements to appraisals for all HPMLs that are not exempt from the regulation. See § 1026.35(c)(2).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>“Certified” versus “licensed” appraiser. Neither TILA section 129H nor the proposed rule defined the individual terms “certified appraiser” and “licensed appraiser,” or specified when a certified appraiser or a licensed appraiser must be used. Instead, the proposed rule required that creditors obtain an appraisal performed by “a certified or licensed appraiser.” 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(1), (b)(2). The Agencies noted in the proposal that certified appraisers generally differ from licensed appraisers based on the examination, education, and experience requirements necessary to obtain each credential. The proposal also stated that existing State and Federal law and regulations require the use of a certified appraiser rather than a licensed appraiser for certain types of transactions. The Agencies requested comment on whether the final rule should address the issue of when a creditor must use a certified appraiser rather than a licensed appraiser.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Consistent with the proposal, the final rule does not separately define “certified” appraiser or “licensed” appraiser, or specify when a creditor should use a “certified” rather than a “licensed” appraiser.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Several national and State credit union trade associations believed that the Agencies should not specify when a creditor must use a certified appraiser rather than a licensed appraiser and requested that the Agencies provide creditors with flexibility to make that determination. Some of these commenters noted that State requirements for certified or licensed appraisers may vary significantly; some states may not issue licenses for appraisers, and some may issue different certified appraiser credentials based on the type of property. A financial holding company commenter, on the other hand, requested that the Agencies clarify circumstances under which a lender must use a certified or a licensed appraiser to facilitate compliance.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>On the other hand, appraiser trade association commenters believed that creditors should be required to use only certified appraisers, because the certification is more rigorous than licensure. These commenters stated that the FHA requires newly-eligible appraisers to be certified, and noted that many states have phased out, or are in the process of phasing out, the licensing of appraisers rather than certification. The commenters further stated that when collateral property is complex, the Agencies should require a certified appraiser who is also credentialed by a recognized professional appraisal organization. Similarly, a realtor trade association commenter believed that using certified appraisers was preferable. The commenter believed that the rule should define appraisals for higher-risk mortgages as “complex,” thus requiring that only certified appraisers may perform the appraisals.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As noted above, several commenters confirmed the Agencies' concerns that State requirements for certified or licensed appraisers may vary significantly and are evolving. Overall, the Agencies believe that imposing specific requirements in this rule about when a certified or licensed appraiser is required goes beyond the scope of the statutory “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal provisions in TILA section 129h. 15 U.S.C. 1639h. The Agencies do not believe that this rule is an appropriate vehicle for guidance on standards for use of a State certified or licensed appraiser that may change over time and vary by jurisdiction. Although the FIRREA appraisal regulations specifically require a “certified” appraiser for certain types of mortgage transactions, the Agencies do not believe that these FIRREA rules are incorporated into the higher-risk mortgage appraisal rules applicable to all creditors. See section-by-section analysis of § 1026.35(c)(1)(i) (defining “certified or licensed appraiser” to incorporate FIRREA requirements related to the development and reporting of the appraisal, not appraiser selection or review). Thus, the final rule need not clarify these rules for entities not subject to the FIRREA appraisal regulations; entities subject to the FIRREA appraisal regulations are familiar with them.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Appraiser competency. In the proposed rule, the Agencies also noted that, in selecting an appraiser for a particular appraisal assignment, creditors typically consider an appraiser's experience, knowledge, and educational background to determine the individual's competency to appraise a particular property and in a particular market. The proposed rule did not specify competency standards, but the Agencies requested comment on whether the rule should address appraiser competency. In keeping with the proposal, the final rule does not specify competency standards for appraisers.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>A realtor trade association commenter suggested that the rule incorporate guidance from the Interagency Appraisal and Evaluation Guidelines<footnote ref="30">75 FR 77450, 77465-68 (Dec. 10, 2010).</footnote> regarding creditors' criteria for selecting, evaluating, and monitoring the performance of appraisers. However, a banking trade association, a financial holding company, appraiser trade association, and several national and State credit union trade association commenters stated that the Agencies should not require creditors to apply specific competency standards for appraisers. Several commenters asserted that competency standards would result in increased regulatory burden and cost, and a banking trade association expressed concern that requiring creditors to implement subjective competency standards could raise conflict of interest issues with respect to appraiser independence.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Appraiser trade association commenters suggested that instead of setting forth competency standards, the Agencies should require a creditor to ensure that the engagement letter properly lays out the required scope of work, that the appraiser is independent, and that the appraiser possesses the appropriate experience to perform the assignment including, when necessary, geographic competency. The financial holding company commenter suggested that the rule should reference FIRREA and require creditors to ensure that appraisers are in good standing. The banking trade association commenter believed that the Agencies should include a reference to USPAP to create a uniform competency standard. One State credit union association believed that the Agencies should permit creditors to rely on appraisers' representations regarding licensing and certification.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies believe that the many aspects of appraiser competency are beyond the scope of TILA's “higher-risk mortgage” provisions defining “certified or licensed appraiser,” which do not mention competency. Appraiser competency is addressed in a number of regulations and guidelines for Federally-regulated depositories, which are expected to know and follow rules and guidance under FIRREA regarding appraiser competency.<footnote ref="31">See, e.g., id. at 77465-68 (Dec. 10, 2010). Appraiser competency is critical to the quality and accuracy of residential mortgage appraisals. As a commenter noted, the federal banking agencies provide guidance in the Interagency Appraisal and Evaluation Guidelines regarding creditors' criteria for selecting, evaluating, and monitoring the performance of appraisers. See id.</footnote></analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-1-ii" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(1)(ii) Manufactured Home</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii), below, the final rule exempts a transaction secured by a new manufactured home from the appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c). Accordingly, § 1026.35(c)(1)(ii) adds a definition of manufactured home, clarifying that, for the purposes of this section, the term manufactured home has the same meaning as in HUD regulation 24 CFR 3280.2.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-1-iii" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(1)(iii) National Registry</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in § 1026.35(c)(3)(ii)(B) below, to qualify for the safe harbor provided in the final rule, a creditor must verify through the “National Registry” that the appraiser is a certified or licensed appraiser in the State in which the property is located as of the date the appraiser signs the appraiser's certification. Under FIRREA section 1109, the Appraisal Subcommittee of the FFIEC is required to maintain a registry of State certified and licensed appraisers eligible to perform appraisals in connection with federally related transactions. 12 U.S.C. 3338. For purposes of qualifying for the safe harbor, the final rule requires that a creditor must verify that the appraiser holds a valid appraisal license or certification through the registry maintained by the Appraisal Subcommittee. Thus, as proposed, § 1026.35(c)(1)(iii) in the final rule provides that the term “National Registry” means the database of information about State certified and licensed appraisers maintained by the Appraisal Subcommittee of the FFIEC.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-1-iv" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(1)(iv) State Agency</title>
      <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129H(b)(3)(A) provides that, among other things, a certified or licensed appraiser means a person who is certified or licensed by the “State” in which the property to be appraised is located. 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(3)(A). As discussed above, a certified or licensed appraiser means a person certified or licensed by the “State agency” in the State in which the property that secures the transaction is located. Under FIRREA section 1118, the Appraisal Subcommittee of the FFIEC is responsible for recognizing each State's appraiser certifying and licensing agency for the purpose of determining whether the agency is in compliance with the appraiser certifying and licensing requirements of FIRREA title XI. 12 U.S.C. 3347. In addition, FIRREA section 1120(a) prohibits a financial institution from obtaining an appraisal from a person the financial institution knows is not a State certified or licensed appraiser in connection with a federally related transaction. 12 U.S.C. 3349(a). Accordingly, as proposed, § 1026.35(c)(1)(iv) in the final rule defines the term “State agency” as a “State appraiser certifying and licensing agency” recognized in accordance with section 1118(b) of FIRREA and any implementing regulations.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-1" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(1) Definitions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, revised § 1026.35(a) contains the definitions of HPML and APOR, which are used in both the HPML escrow rules in § 1026.35(b) and the HPML appraisal rules in new § 1026.35(c). Definitions specific to the substantive appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c) are segregated in new § 1026.35(c)(1) and described below, along with applicable public comments.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-i" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(i)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Qualified Mortgages</title>
        <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129H(f) expressly excludes from the definition of higher-risk mortgage any loan that is a qualified mortgage as defined in TILA section 129C and a reverse mortgage loan that is a qualified mortgage as defined in TILA section 129C. 15 U.S.C. 1639(f). Rather than implement one exclusion for qualified mortgages and a separate exclusion for any reverse mortgage loans that may be defined by the Bureau as qualified mortgages, the Agencies proposed to provide a single exclusion for a qualified mortgage as that term would be defined in the Bureau's final rule implementing TILA section 129C. 15 U.S.C. 1639c.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Before authority regarding TILA section 129C transferred to the Bureau under the Dodd-Frank Act, the Board issued the 2011 ATR Proposal, which, among other things, would have defined a “qualified mortgage” in a new subsection of Regulation Z. 12 CFR 226.43(e). See 76 FR 27390, 27484-85 (May 11, 2011). During the proposal period for the “higher-risk mortgage” rule, the Bureau had not yet issued final rules implementing TILA section 129C's definition of “qualified mortgage.” Since that time, the Bureau has issued rules defining “qualified mortgage.” See 2013 ATR Final Rule, § 1026.43(e). Consistent with the proposed definition of “qualified mortgage,” the Bureau's final rule defines “qualified mortgage” as generally including loans characterized by the absence of certain features considered risky, such as negative amortization and balloon payments.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies adopt the exemption for “qualified mortgages” as proposed, with a cross-reference to the Bureau's final rules defining this class of loans in 12 CFR 1026.43(e).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>All commenters—including national and State credit union trade associations, as well as national and State banking trade associations—supported this exemption. Some banking trade associations believed the exemption was appropriate because qualified mortgages, by definition, are safe and sound transactions. Other banking and credit union trade associations expressed concern that they could not comment specifically on the exemption, because the term was not yet defined by the Bureau.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The final rule incorporates the exemption for “qualified mortgages” as proposed because the exemption is prescribed by statute and widely supported by commenters. The Agencies note that some commenters requested that the final rule also exempt “qualified residential mortgages,” which the Dodd-Frank Act exempts from the risk retention rules prescribed by the Act. See Dodd-Frank Act section 941, section 15G of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, 15 U.S.C. 780-11(c)(1)(C)(iii). A qualified residential mortgage, however, is by statute to be defined by regulation as “no broader than” the definition of qualified mortgage prescribed by the Bureau in its 2013 ATR Final Rule. See id. at sec. 780-11(e)(4)(C). Therefore, the exemption for qualified mortgages will capture all qualified residential mortgages and a separate exemption is not necessary.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-ii" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(ii)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Transactions Secured by a New Manufactured Home</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies proposed to exclude from coverage of the higher-risk mortgage appraisal rules any loan secured solely by a residential structure, such as a manufactured home.<footnote ref="32">The Agencies proposed to exclude from the definition of “higher-risk mortgage loan” any loans secured solely by a “residential structure,” as that term is used in Regulation Z's definition of “dwelling.” See 12 CFR 1026.2(a)(19). The provision was intended to exclude loans that are not secured in whole or in part by land. Thus, for example, loans secured by manufactured homes that are not also secured by the land on which they are sited were proposed to be excluded from the definition of higher-risk mortgage loan, regardless of whether the manufactured home itself is deemed to be personal property or real property under applicable State law.</footnote> The Agencies believed that requiring appraisals performed by certified or licensed appraisers was not appropriate, because such transactions typically more closely resemble titled vehicle loans. At the same time, based on outreach, the Agencies believed that for loans for residential structures, such as manufactured homes that are secured by both the home and the land to which the home is attached, appraisals performed by certified or licensed appraisers are feasible. Such transactions were therefore covered by the proposed rule. The Agencies believed the exemption for a loan secured solely by a residential structure was appropriate pursuant to the exemption authority under TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B). 15 U.S.C. 1026.35(b)(4)(B).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies requested comment on whether the proposed exclusion was appropriate, and if not, reasonable methods by which creditors could comply with the requirements of this proposed rule when providing loans secured solely by a residential structure. The Agencies also requested comment on whether some alternative standards for valuing residential structures securing higher-risk mortgage loans might be feasible and appropriate to include as part of the final rule, in lieu of an appraisal performed by a certified or licensed appraiser.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Commenters, including national and State credit union trade associations, a manufactured housing industry consultant, manufactured housing trade associations, a realtor trade association, a lender specializing in manufactured housing financing, and national and State banking trade associations, submitted comments regarding the exemption for loans secured “solely by a residential structure,” but limited their comments to the exemption as applied to manufactured homes. The commenters supported exempting loans secured solely by manufactured homes. Banking trade association commenters believed that the statute was intended to apply only to loans secured at least in part by real property. A manufactured housing industry consultant, a manufactured housing lender, and manufactured housing trade association commenters concurred that traditional appraisals were not appropriate for these transactions for a variety of reasons, including: (1) A lack of qualified and trained appraisers to appraise such transactions, especially in rural areas; (2) a lack of comparable sales and limited sales volume; (3) the high expense of appraisals relative to the cost of the transaction; and (4) inaccurate valuations resulting from traditional appraisals. The manufactured housing industry consultant suggested that an exemption was necessary in part because these loans were unlikely to qualify for the qualified mortgage exemption due to their small size, which would in turn increase the likelihood that they would exceed the points and fees thresholds defining qualified mortgages. See § 1026.43(e)(3).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Some of the commenters believed the Agencies should expand the exemption to include financing for both real estate and manufactured homes, known as “land home” financing. Manufactured housing trade association commenters argued that traditional appraisals are not appropriate for these transactions for many of the same reasons cited for excluding loans secured solely by a residential structure. One of these manufactured housing trade associations also expressed the view that appraisals are not appropriate because the cost of the home itself is readily known to consumers through other means. In addition, the commenter stated that in rural areas, the cost of the land is small compared to the overall value of the transaction.<footnote ref="33">Note, however, that another manufactured housing trade association commenter stated that the majority of manufactured homes are not considered an improvement or enhancement of the real property on which they are sited.</footnote> This commenter recommended that if the Agencies did not exclude all land home transactions, the Agencies in the alternative should at least exclude those land home transactions that are under $125,000 or that are in a rural area.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>One commenter also questioned the feasibility of appraisals for such transactions. A lender specializing in manufactured housing financing stated that, in land home transactions, the land on which manufactured homes will be located is often not identified until well after the time appraisals are typically ordered. Moreover, the commenter stated that manufactured homes are typically not available for an interior visit until after closing, regardless of whether the transaction is secured solely by the home itself or by land and home together. As an alternative, the commenter suggested different regulatory language for the exclusion, which would expand the exemption to land home transactions and would incorporate an existing definition of “manufactured home” to clearly eliminate site-built manufactured homes from the exemption.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Public commenters generally confirmed Agencies' concerns regarding the application of the appraisal rules to loans secured by certain manufactured homes. Accordingly, the Agencies are excluding certain manufactured homes from coverage under the final rule. However, in the final rule, the Agencies are modifying the exemption. The proposed rule would have exempted loans “secured solely by a residential structure,” which was intended to exempt manufactured homes and other types of dwellings when the loan was not secured at least in part by land. The language in the final rule is tailored to exempt transactions secured by specific types of dwellings. Accordingly, the final rule exempts transactions secured by a new manufactured home, regardless of whether the structure is attached to land or considered real property, and also exempts transactions secured by a mobile home, boat, or trailer.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies believe that the manufactured home exemption should be based on whether the manufactured home securing the transaction is a new home, regardless of whether land also secures the transaction. Upon further consideration, the Agencies believe that TILA section 129H is intended to apply to certain transactions without regard to whether a transaction is secured by land.<footnote ref="34">The Agencies note that the definition of “higher-risk mortgage loan” in TILA section 129H incorporates the definition of “residential mortgage loan.” TILA section 129H(f). A residential mortgage loan is defined, in part, to include loans involving certain types of dwellings that are non-real estate residences. TILA section 103(cc)(5). For example, cooperatives are specifically described as dwellings under TILA section 103(w). Moreover, although TILA section 129H requires appraisals that conform to FIRREA title XI, the Agencies do not believe that TILA section 129H is limited to transactions subject to FIRREA title XI or other Federal regulations. Thus, the Agencies believe the statute intended to apply the appraisal requirements to some loans that are not secured by land.</footnote> Thus, the approach in the final rule is focused on the feasibility and utility of requiring certified or licensed appraisers to perform appraisals for particular manufactured home transactions.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies believe that an exemption for new manufactured homes regardless of whether the loan for such a home is also secured by land more precisely excludes from the rule those transactions that should not be subject to the new appraisal requirements. Based on further outreach, the Agencies understand that for loans secured by both new manufactured homes and land, a valuation is often performed by combining the manufactured home invoice price with the value of the land, rather than by a traditional appraisal that is based on the collective value of the structure and the land on which it is sited.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies believe that requiring traditional appraisals with interior inspections for transactions secured by a new manufactured home would add very little value to the consumer beyond existing valuation methods. Moreover, because it may be difficult or impossible to retain qualified appraisers to perform such appraisals, the rule could result in some creditors declining to extend loans for manufactured homes. Exempting new manufactured homes from the rule is, therefore, in the public interest. The Agencies believe that such an exemption also promotes the safety and soundness of creditors, because creditors will be able to continue relying on standardized valuations that are more conducive to pricing new manufactured homes than are appraisals performed by a certified or licensed appraiser.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, in § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii), the Agencies are exempting from the appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c) a transaction secured by a new manufactured home. Comment 35(c)(2)(ii)-1 in the final rule clarifies that a transaction secured by a new manufactured home, regardless of whether the transaction is also secured by the land on which it is sited, is not a “higher-priced mortgage loan” subject to the appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-iii" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(iii)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Transaction Secured by Mobile Home, Boat, or Trailer</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.35(c)(2)(iii) of the final rule also specifically exempts transactions secured by a mobile home, boat, or trailer. This is consistent with the proposal, which would have exempted these transactions because they are secured “solely by a residential structure.” The Agencies note that this exemption applies even if the transaction is also secured by land. Comment 35(c)(2)(iii)-1 clarifies that, for purposes of the exemption in § 1026.35(c)(2)(iii), a mobile home does not include a manufactured home, as defined in § 1026.35(c)(1)(ii).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies believe the exemption is in the public interest, because requiring an appraisal with an interior property visit for these transactions would offer limited value due to existing pricing tools, such as new product invoices and publicly-available pricing guides. The Agencies further believe, for purposes of safety and soundness, that creditors would be better served by using other valuation methods geared specifically for mobile homes, boats, and trailers.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-iv" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(iv)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Construction Loans</title>
        <analysisParagraph>In the proposal, the Agencies asked for comment on whether to exempt from the higher-risk mortgage appraisal rules transactions that finance the construction of a new home. The Agencies recognized that for loans that finance the construction of a new home, an interior visit of the property securing the loan is generally not feasible because the homes are proposed to be built or are in the process of being built. At the same time, the Agencies recognized that construction loans that meet the pricing thresholds for higher-risk mortgage loans could pose many of the same risks to consumers as other types of loans meeting those thresholds. The Agencies therefore requested comment on whether to exclude construction loans from the definition of higher-risk mortgage loan. The Agencies also sought comment on whether, if an exemption for initial construction loans were not adopted in the final rule, creditors needed any additional compliance guidance for applying TILA's “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules to construction loans. Alternatively, the Agencies requested comment on whether construction loans should be exempt only from the requirement to conduct an interior visit of the property, and be subject to all other appraisal requirements under the proposed rule.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The final rule adopts an exemption from all of the HPML appraisal requirements for a “transaction that finances the initial construction of a dwelling.” This exemption mirrors an existing exemption from the current HPML rules. See existing § 1026.35(a)(3), also retained in the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(B).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Appraiser trade association commenters believed that new construction loans should not be exempted because consumers needed the protection of the appraisal rules. However, all other commenters—including national and State credit union trade associations, national and State banking trade associations, banks, a mortgage company, a financial holding company, a home builder trade association, and a loan origination software company—supported the proposed exemption.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Commenters that supported an exemption for new construction loans had varying views on the risks associated with these loans, all supporting the commenters' request for an exemption for such loans. A loan origination software company and a bank commenter asserted that new construction loan interest rates and fees are often high because the loans, which are short-term, have inherently greater risk. Thus, the appraisal rules would be over-inclusive because they would apply even when extended to prime borrowers. Similarly, a banking association commenter argued that new construction loans are not those that Congress intended to target in the appraisal rules, which the commenter viewed as loans priced higher due to the relative credit risk of the borrower. The home builder trade association, however, supported an exemption because the commenter believed that new construction loans are not as risky as the loans targeted by Congress in the “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules because these loans require close coordination between a bank, home builder, and consumer.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The financial holding company, mortgage company, banking association, and loan origination software company commenters supported an exemption for new construction loans because they are temporary. One of these commenters noted that most mortgage-related regulations, such as those in Regulation X and Z, make accommodations for temporary loans. Others noted that the property securing the new construction loan ultimately will be subject to an appraisal under TILA's “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules if the permanent financing replacing the new construction loan is a “higher-risk mortgage.”</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Several commenters supporting an exemption cited concerns about the feasibility and utility of performing interior inspection appraisals during the construction phase. A bank commenter stated that an exemption was needed because a home under construction is not available for a physical inspection. Similarly, credit union association and banking association commenters stated that an interior visit would not be feasible during the construction phase. Moreover, the commenter believed an appraisal was unlikely to yield sufficient information about the condition of the property to justify the expense to the consumer. A banking association commenter further asserted that the usual value of a new construction loan is the value “at completion,” so an appraisal performed during construction would not assess the value of a completed home.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>A State banking association commenter asserted that failing to exempt new construction loans from the final rule would result in operational difficulties and that an interior inspection appraisal would be of little value to consumers in these circumstances. A bank commenter requested guidance on how to comply with the rules for these loans, if the Agencies did not exempt them from the rule.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>In § 1026.35(c)(2)(iv), the Agencies are using their exemption authority to exempt from the final rule a “transaction to finance the initial construction of a dwelling.” Unlike the exemption for “bridge” loans that the Agencies are also adopting (see section-by-section analysis of § 1026.35(c)(2)(v), below), the exemption for new construction loans is not limited to loans of twelve months or less. This is because the Agencies recognize that new construction might take longer than twelve months and that therefore new construction loans might be for terms of longer than twelve months. This aspect of the exemption adopted in the final rule also reflects the existing exemption for new construction loans from the current HPML rules. See § 1026.35(a)(3).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies' decision to exempt these types of transactions is consistent with wide support for this exemption received from commenters, which largely confirmed the Agencies' concerns about the drawbacks of subjecting these transactions to the new HPML appraisal requirements, particularly the requirement for an interior inspection, USPAP-compliant appraisal. The Agencies also believe that this exemption is important to ensure consistency across mortgage rules, and thus to facilitate compliance. In addition to noting the existing exemption for new construction loans from the current HPML requirements, the Agencies also note the exemption for these loans from the new Dodd-Frank Act ability-to-repay and “high-cost” mortgage rules issued by the Bureau. See 2013 ATR Final Rule, § 1026.43(a)(3)(ii), and 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, § 1026.32(a)(2)(ii).<footnote ref="35">Moreover, the existing “high-cost” mortgage rules contain a longstanding exemption for construction loans from the limitation on balloon payments. See existing &#167; 1026.32(d)(1)(i).</footnote></analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Due to their temporary nature and for other reasons, these loans tend to have higher rates and thus more of them would be subject to the HPML appraisal rules without an exemption. Applying the HPML appraisal rules to these products might subject them to rules with which creditors might not in fact be able to comply. The Agencies therefore believe that this exemption will help ensure that a useful credit vehicle for consumers remains available to build and revitalize communities. The Agencies also recognize that new construction loans can be an important product for many creditors, enabling them to strengthen and diversify their lending portfolios. The Agencies are also not aware of, and commenters did not offer, evidence of widespread valuation abuses in loans to finance new construction. Thus, the Agencies find that the exemption is both in the public interest and promotes the safety and soundness of creditors. See TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B), 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(4)(B).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies also wished to clarify in the final rule the treatment of “construction to permanent” loans, consisting of a single loan that transforms into permanent financing at the end of the construction phase. For this reason, the commentary of the final rule includes guidance on the application of various rules in Regulation Z to these loans that parallels guidance provided in commentary for the new “high-cost” mortgage rules. See 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, comment 32(a)(2)(ii)-1. Specifically, comment 35(c)(2)(iv)-1 clarifies that the exclusion for loans to finance the initial construction of a dwelling applies to a construction-only loan as well as to the construction phase of a construction-to-permanent loan. The comment further clarifies that the HPML appraisal rules in § 1026.35(c) do apply if the permanent financing qualifies as an HPML under § 1026.35(a)(1) and is not otherwise exempt from the rules under § 1026.35(c)(2).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The comment also provides guidance on the application of Regulation Z's general closed-end mortgage loan disclosure requirements to construction-to-permanent loans. To this end, the comment states that, when a construction loan may be permanently financed by the same creditor, the general disclosure requirements for closed-end credit (§ 1026.17) provide that the creditor may give either one combined disclosure for both the construction financing and the permanent financing, or a separate set of disclosures for each of the two phases as though they were two separate transactions. See § 1026.17(c)(6)(ii) and comment 17(c)(6)-2. The comment explains that § 1026.17(c)(6)(ii) addresses only how a creditor may elect to disclose a construction-to-permanent transaction, and that which disclosure option a creditor elects under § 1026.17(c)(6)(ii) does not affect whether the permanent phase of the transaction is subject to § 1026.35(c). The comment further explains that, when the creditor discloses the two phases as separate transactions, the annual percentage rate for the permanent phase must be compared to the average prime offer rate for a transaction that is comparable to the permanent financing to determine coverage under § 1026.35(c). The comment also explains that, when the creditor discloses the two phases as a single transaction, a single annual percentage rate, reflecting the appropriate charges from both phases, must be calculated for the transaction in accordance with § 1026.35 and appendix D to part 1026. The comment also clarifies that the APR must be compared to the APOR for a transaction that is comparable to the permanent financing to determine coverage under § 1026.35(c). If the transaction is determined to be an HPML that is not otherwise exempt under § 1026.35(c)(2), only the permanent phase is subject to the HPML appraisal requirements of § 1026.35(c).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-v" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(v)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Bridge Loans</title>
        <analysisParagraph>In the proposal, the Agencies also requested comment on whether the appraisal rules of TILA section 129H should apply to temporary or “bridge” loans with a term of 12 months or less. 15 U.S.C. 1639h. If such an exemption were not adopted, the Agencies sought comment on whether any additional compliance guidance would be needed for applying the new appraisal rules to bridge loans. The Agencies stated concerns about the burden to both creditors and consumers of imposing the rule's requirements on such loans and questioned whether such requirements would be useful for many consumers.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As explained in the proposal, bridge loans are short-term loans typically used when a consumer is buying a new home before selling the consumer's existing home. Usually secured by the existing home, a bridge loan provides financing for the new home (often in the form of the down payment) or mortgage payment assistance until the consumer can sell the existing home and secure permanent financing. Bridge loans normally carry higher interest rates, points and fees than conventional mortgages, regardless of the consumer's creditworthiness.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In § 1026.35(c)(2)(v), the final rule adopts an exemption from the new HPML appraisal rules for a “loan with a maturity of 12 months or less, if the purpose of the loan is a `bridge' loan connected with the acquisition of a dwelling intended to become the consumer's principal dwelling.”</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Almost all commenters—including national and State banking associations, national and State credit union associations, a mortgage company, a financial holding company, a loan origination software company, a home builder trade association, and a bank—supported an exemption for bridge loans for many of the same reasons that commenters supported exempting construction loans. Several commenters emphasized that these loans are temporary, and some further pointed out that imposing appraisal requirements was unnecessary because bridge loans are ultimately converted to permanent financing that will be subject to the appraisal rules. Other commenters argued that the protections of the appraisal rules were not needed because bridge loans' higher rates are generally unrelated to a consumer's creditworthiness; they argued that TILA's new “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules were intended for loans made to more vulnerable, less creditworthy consumers without other credit options.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Some commenters asserted that failing to exempt these loans would result in operational difficulties and would be of little value to consumers. In this regard, one commenter discussed the difficulties of comparing an APR to a “comparable” APOR for these loans. One credit union association commenter believed that without an exemption, consumers' access to bridge loans would be reduced. Some commenters requested that the Agencies exempt all types of temporary loans. Appraiser trade association commenters believed that the Agencies should not allow an exemption unless there was a compelling policy reason to do so.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies are adopting an exemption for “bridge” loans of 12 months or less that are connected with the acquisition of a dwelling intended to become the consumer's principal dwelling for several reasons. First, the Agencies believe that with this exemption, the consumer would still be afforded the protection of the appraisal rules. This is because bridge loans used in connection with the acquisition of a new home are typically secured by the consumer's existing home to facilitate the purchase of a new home. Thus, the consumer would be afforded the protections of the appraisal rules on the permanent financing secured by the new home. This would include the protections of § 1026.35(c)(4)(i) regarding properties that are potentially fraudulent flips.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Second, commenters generally confirmed the Agencies' concerns expressed in the proposal about the burden to both creditors and consumers of imposing TILA section 129H's heightened appraisal requirements on short-term financing of this nature. As noted in the proposal, the Agencies recognize that rates on short-term bridge loans are often higher than on long-term home mortgages, so these loans may be more likely to meet the “higher-risk mortgage loan” triggers. As also noted in the proposal and echoed by commenters, “higher-risk mortgages” under TILA section 129H would generally be a credit option for less creditworthy consumers, who may be more vulnerable than others and in need of enhanced consumer protections, such as TILA section 129H's special appraisal requirements. However, a bridge loan consumer could be subject to rates that would exceed the higher-risk mortgage loan thresholds even if the consumer would qualify for a non-higher-risk mortgage loan when seeking permanent financing. The Agencies do not believe that Congress intended TILA section 129H to apply to loans simply because they have higher rates, regardless of the consumer's creditworthiness or the purpose of the loan.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Further, the Agencies recognize that the exemption can help facilitate compliance by generally ensuring consistency across residential mortgage rules. Such consistency can reduce compliance-related burdens and risks, thereby promoting the safety and soundness of creditors. The Agencies also believe that consistency across the rules can reduce operational risk and support a creditor's ability to offer these loans, which can enable creditors to strengthen and diversify their lending portfolios.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In particular, the Agencies note the current exemption for “temporary or `bridge' loans of twelve months or less from the existing HPML rules (retained in the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(C)), but also a similar exemption from TILA's new ability-to-repay requirements. See existing § 1026.35(a)(3). See TILA section 129C(a)(8), 15 U.S.C. 1639c(a)(8); 2013 ATR Final Rule, § 1026.43(a)(3)(ii).<footnote ref="36">The exemption for “temporary or `bridge' loans of twelve months or less” in TILA's ability-to-repay rules codifies an exemption from the current “high-cost” and HPML repayment ability requirements. See existing &#167;&#167; 1026.34(a)(4)(v), 1026.35(a)(3) and (b)(1).</footnote> In addition, longstanding HOEPA rules have included an exception from the balloon payment prohibition for “loans with maturities of less than one year, if the purpose of the loan is a `bridge' loan connected with the acquisition or construction of a dwelling intended to become the consumer's principal dwelling.” § 1026.32(d)(1)(ii). The final HOEPA rules adopted by the Bureau contain the same exception with minor changes for conformity across mortgage rules. See 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, § 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(B) (revising the exception to cover bridge loans of 12 months or less, rather than less than one year).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Like the HOEPA exception from the balloon payment prohibition, the final HPML appraisal rule does not exempt all loans with terms of 12 months or less. Only bridge loans of 12 months or less that are made in connection with the acquisition of a consumer's principal dwelling are exempted. (Construction loans are separately exempted under § 1026.35(c)(2)(iv), discussed in the corresponding section-by-section analysis above.) The Agencies believe that the HPML appraisal rule might be appropriately applied to other types of temporary financing, particularly temporary financing that does not result in the consumer ultimately obtaining permanent financing covered by the appraisal rule.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, as with new construction loans, the Agencies are not aware of, and commenters did not offer, evidence of widespread valuation abuses in bridge loans of twelve months or less used in connection with the acquisition of a consumer's principal dwelling. For all these reasons, the Agencies find that the exemption is both in the public interest and promotes the safety and soundness of creditors. See TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B), 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(4)(B).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2-vi" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2)(vi)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Reverse Mortgage Transactions</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies proposed to exempt reverse mortgage transactions subject to § 1026.33(a) from the definition of “higher-risk mortgage loan.” The Agencies proposed this exemption in part because the proprietary (private) reverse mortgage market is effectively nonexistent, thus the vast majority of reverse mortgage transactions made in the United States today are insured by FHA as part of the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development's (HUD) Home Equity Conversion Mortgage (HECM) Program.<footnote ref="37">See Bureau, Reverse Mortgages: Report to Congress 14, 70-99 (June 28, 2012), available at http://www.consumerfinance.gov/reports/reverse-mortgages-report (Bureau Reverse Mortgage Report).</footnote> The Agencies stated that TILA's new “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules are arguably unnecessary because HECM creditors must adhere to specific standards designed to protect both the creditor and the consumer, including robust appraisal rules.<footnote ref="38">See HUD Handbook 4235.1, ch. 3.</footnote> In addition, a methodology for determining APORs for reverse mortgage transactions does not currently exist, so creditors would be unable to determine whether the APR of a given reverse mortgage transaction exceeded the rate thresholds defining a “higher-risk mortgage loan” (HPML in the final rule).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>At the same time, the Agencies expressed concern that providing a permanent exemption for all reverse mortgage transactions, both private and HECM products, could deny key protections to consumers who rely on reverse mortgages. However, the Agencies proposed the exemption on at least a temporary basis, asserting that avoiding any potential disruption of this segment of the mortgage market in the near term would be in the public interest and promote the safety and soundness of creditors.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies requested comment on the appropriateness of this exemption. The Agencies also sought comment on whether available indices exist that track the APR for reverse mortgages and could be used by the Bureau to develop and publish an APOR for these transactions, or whether such an index could be developed, noting, for example, information published by HUD on HECMs, including the contract rate.<footnote ref="39">See http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/housing/rmra/oe/rpts/hecm/hecmmenu (&#8220;Home Equity Conversion Mortgage Characteristics&#8221;).</footnote></analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed further below, in § 1026.35(c)(2)(vi) of the final rule, the Agencies are adopting the proposed exemption for a “reverse-mortgage transaction subject to § 1026.33(a).”</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Public Comments on the Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>National and State credit union trade associations, as well as a State banking trade association, supported the proposed exemption. However, appraiser trade association commenters generally believed that excluding appraisal protections would harm consumers, particularly senior citizens, and is contrary to public policy. Appraiser trade association, realtor trade association, and reverse mortgage lending trade association commenters suggested that any exemption should be limited to reverse mortgages under the FHA HECM program and not extended to proprietary products, because HECM consumers are afforded a comprehensive and mandatory set of appraisal protections. The reverse mortgage lending trade association also suggested circumstances under which reverse mortgages should be deemed qualified mortgages and, thus, qualify for an exemption on that basis. See section-by-section analysis of § 1026.35(c)(2)(i).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>No commenters offered suggestions on an appropriate approach for developing an APOR for reverse mortgages. Appraiser trade associations, who only supported an exemption for HECMs, believed that the rules should apply to reverse mortgages even though indices do not currently exist. A reverse mortgage lending trade association believed that benchmark indices for reverse mortgages could be developed, but, supporting the proposed exemption, questioned whether one should be.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Discussion</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies are adopting the proposed exemption for a “reverse-mortgage transaction subject to § 1026.33” for the same basic reasons discussed in the proposal, which were affirmed by most commenters. The Agencies share concerns expressed by some commenters about the risks to consumers of reverse mortgages generally, and of proprietary reverse mortgage loans in particular. Proprietary reverse mortgage loans are not insured by FHA or any other government entity, so payments are not guaranteed by the U.S. government to either consumers or creditors. By contrast, HECMs are insured by FHA and subject to a number of rules and restrictions designed to reduce risk to both consumers and creditors, including appraisal rules. See TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B), 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(4)(B).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As noted in the proposal, however, there is little to no market for proprietary reverse mortgages, and prospects for the reemergence of this market in the near-term are remote.<footnote ref="40">Bureau Reverse Mortgage Report at 137-38.</footnote> HECMs comprise virtually the entire reverse mortgage market and are subject to FHA's extensive HECM rules, which include appraisal requirements.<footnote ref="41">See HUD Handbook 4235.1, ch. 3.</footnote> In addition, the Agencies believe that unwarranted creditor liability and operational risk could arise if the rule were applied to loans that a creditor cannot definitively determine are in fact subject to the rule, as is the case here, where no rate benchmark exists for measuring whether a reverse mortgage loan is an HPML. Thus, without an exemption for reverse mortgages, creditors would be susceptible to risks that could negatively affect their safety and soundness.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In reevaluating the proposed exemption, the Agencies also focused more attention on the fact that TILA's “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules apply only to closed-end products. Many (and historically most) reverse mortgages are open-end products. The Agencies are concerned about creating anomalies in the market and compliance confusion among creditors by applying one set of rules to closed-end reverse mortgages and another to open-end reverse mortgages. The Agencies note that compliance confusion among creditors can create burden and operational risk that can have a negative impact on the safety and soundness of the creditors. The Agencies are concerned that this bifurcation of the rule's application could also hinder creditors from offering a range of reverse mortgage product choices that support the creditors' loan portfolios while also benefitting consumers. In short, questions remain for the Agencies about whether this rule is the appropriate vehicle for addressing appraisal issues in the reverse mortgage market.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Agencies remain concerned about the potential for abuse related to appraisals even with HECMs, which are subject to appraisal rules. Indeed, evidence exists that problems of property value inflation and fraudulent flipping occur even in the HECM market.<footnote ref="42">Bureau Reverse Mortgage Report at 154, 157.</footnote> The Agencies plan to continue monitoring the reverse mortgage market closely and address appraisal issues as needed, including through consultations with the Bureau regarding any initiatives to revisit previously-issued reverse mortgage proposals (76 FR 58539, 53638-58659 (Sept. 24, 2012)).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>For all these reasons, the Agencies have concluded that an exemption for all reverse mortgages at this time from this rule is in the public interest and promotes the safety and soundness of creditors.<footnote ref="43">By statute, the term “higher-risk mortgage” excludes any “qualified mortgage” and any “reverse mortgage loan that is a qualified mortgage.” 15 U.S.C. 1639h(f). The Bureau was authorized by the Dodd-Frank Act to define the term “qualified mortgage” and has done so in its 2013 ATR Final Rule. However, the 2013 ATR Final Rule does not define the types of reverse mortgage loans that should be considered “qualified mortgages” because, by statute, TILA's ability-to-repay rules do not apply to reverse mortgages. See TILA section 129C(a)(8), 15 U.S.C. 1639c(a)(8). Thus the Agencies are not able to implement the precise statutory exemption for &#8220;reverse mortgage loans that are qualified mortgages.&#8221; Instead, the exemption for reverse mortgages is based on the Agencies' express authority to exempt from TILA's &#8220;higher-risk mortgage&#8221; appraisal rules &#8220;a class of loans,&#8221; if the exemption &#8220;is in the public interest and promotes the safety and soundness of creditors.&#8221; TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B), 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(4)(B).</footnote></analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-2" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(2) Exemptions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Agencies proposed to exclude from the definition of “higher-risk mortgage loan,” and thus from coverage of TILA's “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules entirely, the following types of loans: (1) Qualified mortgage loans as defined in § 1026.43(e); (2) reverse-mortgage transactions subject to § 1026.33(a); and (3) loans secured solely by a residential structure. These exclusions were proposed consistent with the express language of TILA section 129H(f) and pursuant to the Agencies' exemption authority in TILA section 129H(b)(4)(B), which authorizes the Agencies to exempt from coverage of the appraisal rules a class of loans if the Agencies determine that the exemption is in the public interest and promotes the safety and soundness of creditors. 15 U.S.C. 1639h(b)(4)(B) and (f).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Agencies requested comment on these proposed exemptions. In addition, the Agencies requested comment on whether the final rule should exempt the following types of loans:</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>• Loans to finance new construction of a dwelling;</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>• Temporary or “bridge” loans, typically used to purchase a new dwelling where the consumer plans to sell the consumer's current dwelling; and</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>• Loans secured by properties in “rural” areas. For this last exemption, the Agencies requested comment on how to define “rural”; specifically, whether to define it as the Board did in its proposal to implement Dodd-Frank Act ability-to-repay requirements under TILA section 129C. See 15 U.S.C. 1639c; 76 FR 27390 (May 11, 2011) (2011 ATR Proposal) (and also in the 2011 Escrows Proposal), discussed in more detail below.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Agencies requested comment on whether commenters believed that any other types of loans should be exempt from the final rule.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The final rule adopts two of the proposed exemptions: qualified mortgages and reverse mortgages. See § 1026.35(c)(2)(i) and (vi). The final rule also adopts exemptions for loans secured by new manufactured homes and by mobile homes, boats, or trailers, which replace the proposed exemption for loans secured solely by a residential structure. See § 1026.35(c)(2)(ii) (new manufactured homes) and (iii) (mobile homes, boats, or trailers). In addition, the final rule exempts the two types of loans on which the Agencies specifically requested comment: new construction loans and bridge loans. See § 1026.35(c)(2)(iv) (construction loans) and (v) (bridge loans).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In addition, based on public comments, the Agencies intend to publish a supplemental proposal to request comment on possible exemptions for “streamlined” refinance programs and small dollar loans, as well as to seek comment on whether application of the HPML appraisal rule to loans secured by certain other property types, such as existing manufactured homes, is appropriate.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Exemptions from the HPML appraisal rules of § 1026.35(c) are set out in new § 1026.35(c)(2). The structure of the final rule differs from that of the proposed rule. The proposed rule excluded certain loan types from the definition of “higher-risk mortgage loan” and thereby excluded these loan types from coverage of all of the “higher-risk mortgage” appraisal rules. By contrast, the final rule defines a general term—HPML—and incorporates exemptions from the appraisal rules in a separate subsection, § 1026.35(c)(2). As discussed, the general term HPML applies also to loans covered by the revised escrow rules in § 1026.35(b), with exemptions specific to those rules enumerated separately in § 1026.35(b)(2).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Thus, exemptions that are the same in both the escrow rules in § 1026.35(b) and the appraisal rules in § 1026.35(c) are stated separately in the “exemptions” sections for each set of rules. See § 1026.35(b)(2) and (c)(2). The following exemptions are generally the same for both the HPML escrow rules and the HPML appraisal rules: new construction loans, bridge loans, and reverse mortgages. The intent of this structure is to make clear that the Agencies jointly have authority to exempt transactions from the appraisal rules, whereas only the Bureau has authority to exempt transactions from the escrow rules.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>These exemptions and related public comments are discussed in detail below.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c-6-iv" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>35(c)(6)(iv) No Charge for Copy of Appraisal</title>
      <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129H(c) provides that a creditor shall provide one copy of each appraisal conducted in accordance with this section in connection with a higher-risk mortgage to the applicant without charge. 15 U.S.C. 1639h(c). In the proposal, the Agencies interpreted this provision to prohibit creditors from charging consumers for providing a copy of written appraisals required for higher-risk mortgage loans. Accordingly, the proposal provided that a creditor must not charge the consumer for a copy of a written appraisal required to be provided to the consumer pursuant to new § 1026.35(c)(6)(i).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>A proposed comment clarified that the creditor is prohibited from charging the consumer for any copy of a required appraisal, including by imposing a fee specifically for a required copy of an appraisal or by marking up the interest rate or any other fees payable by the consumer in connection with the higher-risk mortgage loan.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Agencies received no comments on this aspect of the proposal and adopt the proposed regulation text and comment without change in § 1026.35(c)(6)(iv) and comment 35(c)(6)(iv)-1.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35" notice="2013-30108_20140118" date="2014-01-18">
      <title>Section 1026.35 Prohibited Acts or Practices in Connection With Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The final rule is incorporated into Regulation Z's existing section on prohibited acts or practices in connection with HPMLs, § 1026.35. As revised, § 1026.35 will consist of four subsections—(a) Definitions; (b) Escrows for higher-priced mortgage loans; (c) Appraisals for higher-priced mortgage loans; and (d) Evasion; open-end credit. As explained in more detail in the Bureau's final rule on escrow requirements for HPMLs (2013 Escrows Final Rule)<footnote ref="12">The Bureau released the 2013 Escrows Final Rule on January 10, 2013, under Docket No. CFPB-2013-0001, RIN 3170-AA16, at http://consumerfinance.gov/Regulations.</footnote> (finalizing the Board's proposal to implement the Act's escrow account requirements under TILA section 129D, 15 U.S.C. 1639d (2011 Escrows Proposal)<footnote ref="13">76 FR 11598, 11612 (March 2, 2011).</footnote>), the subsections on repayment ability (existing § 1026.35(b)(1)) and prepayment penalties (existing § 1026.35(b)(2)) will be deleted because the Dodd-Frank Act addressed these matters in other ways. Accordingly, repayment ability and prepayment penalties are now addressed in the Bureau's final ability-to-repay rule (2013 ATR Final Rule) and high-cost mortgage rule (2013 HOEPA Final Rule).<footnote ref="14">The Bureau released the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule on January 10, 2013, under Docket No. CFPB-2012-0029, RIN 3170-AA12, at http://consumerfinance.gov/Regulations.</footnote> See §§ 1026.32(d)(6) and 1026.43(c), (d), (f), and (g).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
