<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-10-01</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-22752_20140101</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2014-01-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/articles/2013/10/01/2013-22752/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-equal-credit-opportunity-act-regulation-b-real</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-01503_20140101" rightDocumentNumber="2013-22752_20140101">
    <!-- Effective 1-1-2014: Amendments to §§ 1026.35(b)(2)(iii), 1026.36(a), (b), and (j) -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended more than 50 percent of its total <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by &#167; <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either &#8220;rural&#8221; or &#8220;underserved,&#8221; as set forth in paragraph (b)(2)(iv) of th<ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">is section</ref>;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-1-i-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> who does not take a <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> application or <ref target="1026-58-b-5" reftype="term">offer</ref> or negotiate <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms available from a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to that <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> selected based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>’s financial characteristics, but who performs purely administrative or clerical tasks on behalf of a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> who does engage in such activities.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-1-i-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>An employee of a manufactured home retailer who does not take a <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> application, offer or negotiate <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms available from a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, or advise a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> on <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-36-a-6">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-a-6" marker="(6)">
        <title type="keyterm">Credit terms.</title>
        <content>For purposes of this section, the term &#8220;credit terms&#8221; includes rates, fees, and other costs. <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">Credit</ref> terms are selected based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>’s financial characteristics when those terms are selected based on any factors that may influence a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> decision, such as debts, income, assets, or <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> history.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-b">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-b" marker="(b)">
        <title type="keyterm">Scope.</title>
        <content>Paragraphs <ref target="1026-36-c-1" reftype="internal">(c)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-36-c-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref> of this section apply to closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Paragraph <ref target="1026-36-c-3" reftype="internal">(c)(3)</ref> of this section applies to a <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Paragraphs <ref target="1026-36-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> through <ref target="1026-36-i" reftype="internal">(i)</ref> of this section apply to closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. This section does not apply to a home equity line of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to &#167; <ref target="1026-40" reftype="internal">1026.40</ref>, except that paragraphs <ref target="1026-36-h" reftype="internal">(h)</ref> and <ref target="1026-36-i" reftype="internal">(i)</ref> of this section apply to such <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> when secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Paragraphs <ref target="1026-36-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> through <ref target="1026-36-i" reftype="internal">(i)</ref> of this section do not apply to a loan that is secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s interest in a timeshare plan described in 11 U.S.C. 101(53D).</content></paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-j-2">
      <paragraph label="1026-36-j-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-36-j" reftype="internal">(j)</ref>, &#8220;depository institution&#8221; has the meaning in section 1503(2) of the SAFE Act, <ref target="USC:12-5102" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 5102</ref>(2). For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-36-j" reftype="internal">(j)</ref>, &#8220;subsidiary&#8221; has the meaning in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act, <ref target="USC:12-1813" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 1813</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <!-- Effective 1-1-2014: Interps to §§ 1026.25(c)(2), 1026.35, and 1026.36(a), (b), (d), and (f) -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-25-c-2-Interp-1-i">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-25-c-2-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
        <title>Records sufficient to evidence payment and receipt of compensation.</title>
        <content>Records are sufficient to evidence payment and receipt of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> if they demonstrate the following facts: The nature and amount of the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>; that the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> was paid, and by whom; that the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> was received, and by whom; and when the payment and receipt of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> occurred. The <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreements</ref> themselves are to be retained in all circumstances consistent with &#167; <ref target="1026-25-c-2-i" reftype="internal">1026.25(c)(2)(i)</ref>. The additional records that are sufficient necessarily will vary on a case-by-case basis depending on the facts and circumstances, particularly with regard to the nature of the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>. For example, if the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is in the form of a salary, records to be retained might include copies of required filings under the Internal Revenue Code that demonstrate the amount of the salary. If the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is in the form of a contribution to or a benefit under a designated tax-advantaged plan, records to be maintained might include copies of required filings under the Internal Revenue Code or other applicable Federal law relating to the plan, copies of the plan and <ref target="1026-58-b-2" reftype="term">amendments</ref> thereto in which <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> participate and the names of any <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originators</ref> covered by the plan, or determination letters from the Internal Revenue Service regarding the plan. If the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is in the nature of a commission or bonus, records to be retained might include a settlement agent &#8220;flow of funds&#8221; worksheet or other written record or a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> closing instructions letter directing disbursement of fees at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Where a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> is a mortgage broker, a disclosure of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> or broker <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> required by applicable State law that recites the broker's total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for a transaction is a record of the amount actually paid to the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> in connection with the transaction, unless actual <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> deviates from the amount in the disclosure or <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>. Where <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> has been decreased to defray the cost, in whole or part, of an unforeseen increase in an actual settlement cost over an estimated settlement cost disclosed to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> pursuant to section 5(c) of RESPA (or omitted from that disclosure), records to be maintained are those documenting the decrease in <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> and reasons for it.</content></interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-25-c-2-Interp-1-ii">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-25-c-2-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
        <title>Compensation agreement.</title>
        <content>For purposes of &#167; <ref target="1026-25-c-2" reftype="internal">1026.25(c)(2)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> includes any <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, whether oral, written, or based on a course of conduct that establishes a <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> arrangement between the parties (e.g., a brokerage <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> between a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and a mortgage broker or provisions of employment contracts between a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> employee addressing payment of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>). Where a <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> is oral or based on a course of conduct and cannot itself be maintained, the records to be maintained are those, if any, evidencing the existence or terms of the oral or course of conduct <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> and <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originators</ref> are free to specify what transactions are governed by a particular <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> as they see fit. For example, they may provide, by the terms of the <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, that the <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> governs <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> payable on transactions consummated on or after some future effective date (in which case, a prior <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> governs transactions consummated in the meantime). For purposes of applying the record retention requirement to transaction-specific commissions, the relevant <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> for a given transaction is the <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> pursuant to which <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for that transaction is determined.</content></interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Under &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, except as provided in &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(v)</ref>, a creditor need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a higher-priced mortgage loan, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the higher-priced mortgage loan is consummated:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" subpath="content">
      <content>During any of the three preceding calendar years, more than 50 percent of the creditor's total first-lien covered transactions, as defined in &#167; <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, are secured by properties located in counties that are either &#8220;rural&#8221; or &#8220;underserved,&#8221; as set forth in &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. Pursuant to that section, a creditor may rely as a safe harbor on a list of counties published by the Bureau to determine whether counties in the United States are rural or underserved for a particular calendar year. Thus, for example, if a creditor originated 90 covered transactions, as defined by &#167; <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by a first lien, during 2011, 2012, or 2013, the creditor meets this condition for an exemption in 2014 if at least 46 of those transactions in one of those three calendar years are secured by first liens on properties that are located in such counties.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014, are not counted for purposes of &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. For applications received on and after January 1, 2014, creditors, together with their affiliates, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, do not qualify for the exemption provided under &#167; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii). Creditors, together with their affiliates, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014, still qualify for the exemption provided under &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions for which they received applications on or after January 1, 2014, other than those described in &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, and they otherwise qualify under &#167; <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A" subpath="content">
      <content>Section <ref target="1026-36-a" reftype="internal">1026.36(a)</ref> defines the set of activities or services any one of which, if done for or in the expectation of compensation or gain, makes the person doing such activities orperforming such services a loan originator, unless otherwise excluded. The scope of activities covered by the term loan originator includes:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Referring a consumer to any person who participates in the origination process as a loan originator. Referring is an activity included under each of the activities of offering, arranging, or assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain an extension of credit. Referring includes any oral or written action directed to a consumer that can affirmatively influence the consumer to select a particular loan originator or creditor to obtain an extension of credit when the consumer will pay for such credit. See comment <ref target="1026-36-a-Interp-4" reftype="internal">36(a)-4</ref> with respect to certain activities that do not constitute referring.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-2" subpath="content">
      <content>Arranging a credit transaction, including initially contacting and orienting the consumer to a particular loan originator's or creditor's origination process or particular credit terms that are or may be available to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, assisting the consumer to apply for credit, taking an application, offering particular credit terms to the consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, negotiating credit terms, or otherwise obtaining or making an extension of credit.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-3" subpath="content">
      <content>Assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying for consumer credit by advising on particular credit terms that are or may be available to that consumer based on the consumer's financial characteristics, filling out an application form, preparing application packages (such as a credit application or pre-approval application or supporting documentation), or collecting application and supporting information on behalf of the consumer to submit to a loan originator or creditor. A person who, acting on behalf of a loan originator or creditor, collects information or verifies information provided by the consumer, such as by asking the consumer for documentation to support the information the consumer provided or for the consumer's authorization to obtain supporting documents from third parties, is not collecting information on behalf of the consumer. See also comment 36(a)z4.i through iv with respect to application-related administrative and clerical tasks and comment <ref target="1026-36-a-Interp-1-v" reftype="internal">36(a)-1.v</ref> with respect to third-party advisors.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Presenting particular credit terms for the consumer's consideration that are selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, or communicating with a consumer for the purpose of reaching a mutual understanding about prospective credit terms.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-i" subpath="content">
      <content>The definition of loan originator does not include a loan originator's or creditor's employee who provides a credit application form from the entity for which the person works to the consumer for the consumer to complete or, without assisting the consumer in completing the credit application, processing or analyzing the information, or discussing particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, delivers the credit application from a consumer to a loan originator or creditor. A person does not assist the consumer in completing the application if the person explains to the consumer filling out the application the contents of the application or where particular consumer information is to be provided, or generally describes the credit application process to a consumer without discussing particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-ii-B" subpath="content">
      <content>As employees of a creditor or loan originator, provide loan originator or creditor contact information of the loan originator or creditor entity for which he or she works, or of a person who works for that the same entity to a consumer, provided that the person does not discuss particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics and does not direct the consumer, based on his or her assessment of the consumer's financial characteristics, to a particular loan originator or particular creditor seeking to originate credit transactions to consumers with those financial characteristics;</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-ii-C" subpath="content">
      <content>Describe other product-related services (for example, persons who describe optional monthly payment methods via telephone or via automatic account withdrawals, the availability and features of online account access, the availability of 24-hour customer support, or free mobile applications to access account information); or</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-iii" subpath="content">
      <content>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who, acting on behalf of a loan originator or a creditor:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-iii-C" subpath="content">
      <content>Coordinate consummation of the credit transaction or other aspects of the credit transaction process, including by communicating with a consumer about process deadlines and documents needed at consummation, provided that any communication that includes a discussion about credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics only confirms credit terms already agreed to by the consumer;</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-iv" subpath="content">
      <content>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-4-iv-B" subpath="content">
      <content>Approve particular credit terms or set particular credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics in offer or counter-offer situations, provided that only a loan originator communicates to or with the consumer regarding these credit terms, an offer, or provides or engages in negotiation, a counter-offer, or approval conditions; or</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-5-iv-B" subpath="content">
      <content>Compensation includes any salaries, commissions, and any financial or similar incentive to an individual loan originator, regardless of whether it is labeled as payment for services that are not loan origination activities.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp" parent="1026-36-a-Interp" after="1026-36-a-Interp-5">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp" target="1026-36-a-1-i-B">
        <title>36(a)(1)(i)(B) Employee of a retailer of manufactured homes.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <content>The definition of <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> does not include an employee of a manufactured home retailer that &#8220;assists&#8221; a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in obtaining or applying for <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> as defined in comment 36(a)-1.i.A. 3, provided the employee does not advise the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> on specific <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms, or otherwise engage in <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> activity as defined in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(a)(1)</ref>. The following examples describe activities that, in the absence of other activities, do not define a manufactured home retailer employee as a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref>:</content><interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Generally describing the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> application process to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> without advising on <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms available from a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>Preparing residential <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loan</ref> packages, which means compiling and processing loan application materials and supporting documentation, and providing general application instructions to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> so <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> can complete an application, without interacting or communicating with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> regarding transaction terms, but not filling out a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s application, inputting the information into an online application or other automated system, or taking information from the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> over the phone to complete the application.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>Collecting information on behalf of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> with regard to a residential <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loan</ref>. Collecting information &#8220;on behalf of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>&#8221; would include gathering information or supporting documentation from third parties on behalf of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to provide to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, for the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> then to provide in the application or for the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to submit to the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-1-i-B-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
            <content>Providing or making available general information about <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> or <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originators</ref> that may offer financing for manufactured homes in the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s general area, when doing so does not otherwise amount to &#8220;referring&#8221; as defined in comment 36(a)-1.i.A. 1. This includes making available, in a neutral manner, general brochures or information about the different <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> or <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originators</ref> that may offer financing to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, but does not include recommending a particular <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> or otherwise influencing the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s decision.</content></interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-b-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.36(c)(1) and (c)(2) applies to closed-end consumercredit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Section 1026.36(c)(3) applies to a consumer credit transaction, including home equity lines of credit under &#167; 1026.40, secured by a consumer's dwelling. Paragraphs (h) and (i) of &#167; 1026.36 apply to home equity lines of credit under &#167; 1026.40 secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Paragraphs (d), (e), (f), (g), (h), and (i) of &#167; 1026.36 apply to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling. Closed-end consumer credit transactions include transactions secured by first or subordinate liens, and reverse mortgages that are not home equity lines of credit under &#167; 1026.40. See &#167; 1026.36(b) for additional restrictions on the scope of &#167; 1026.36, and &#167;&#167; 1026.1(c) and 1026.3(a) and corresponding commentary for further discussion of extensions of credit subject to Regulation Z.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-ii">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
        <title>Single or multiple transactions.</title>
        <content>The prohibition on payment and receipt of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref> encompasses <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that directly or indirectly is based on the terms of a single transaction of a single <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>, the terms of multiple transactions by that single <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>, or the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>. <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">Compensation</ref> to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> that is based upon profits determined with reference to a mortgage-related business is considered <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that is based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>. For clarification about the exceptions permitting <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> based upon profits determined with reference to mortgage-related business pursuant to either a designated tax-advantaged plan or a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan, see comment 36(d)(1)-3. For clarification about &#8220;mortgage-related business,&#8221; see comments 36(d)(1)-3.v.B and -3.v.E.</content><interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-ii-A" marker="A.">
          <content>Assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> pays a bonus to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> out of a bonus pool established with reference to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s profits and the profits are determined with reference to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s revenue from origination of closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. In such instance, the bonus is considered <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that is based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>. Therefore, the bonus is prohibited under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref>, unless it is otherwise permitted under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-ii-B" marker="B.">
          <content>Assume that an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s employment contract with a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> guarantees a quarterly bonus in a specified amount conditioned upon the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> meeting certain performance benchmarks (e.g., volume of originations monthly). A bonus paid following the satisfaction of those contractual conditions is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of a transaction by an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>, the terms of multiple transactions by that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>, or the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref> as clarified by this comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii, because the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is obligated to pay the bonus, in the specified amount, regardless of the <ref target="1026-36-d-1-ii" reftype="term">terms of transactions</ref> of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> or multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> and the effect of those terms of multiple transactions on the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s profits. Because this type of bonus is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>, as described in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref> (as clarified by this comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii), it is not subject to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit described in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-iii-D">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-1-iii-D" marker="D.">
        <content>The fees and charges described above in paragraphs B and C can only be a <ref target="1026-36-d-1-ii" reftype="term">term of a transaction</ref> if the fees or charges are required to be disclosed in the Good Faith Estimate, the HUD-1, or the HUD-1A (and subsequently in any integrated disclosures promulgated by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> under TILA section 105(b) (15 U.S.C. 1604(b)) and RESPA section 4 (12 U.S.C. 2603) as amended by sections 1098 and 1100A of the Dodd-Frank Act).</content></interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Interpretation of &#167; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) and (iv). </title>
        <content>Subject to certain restrictions, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref> and &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> permit contributions to or benefits under designated tax-advantaged plans and <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan even if the contributions, benefits, or <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, respectively, are based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>.</content><interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
          <title>Designated tax-advantaged plans.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref> permits an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> to receive, and a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> to pay, <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> in the form of contributions to a defined contribution plan or benefits under a defined benefit plan provided the plan is a designated tax-advantaged plan (as defined in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref>), even if contributions to or benefits under such plans are directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>. In the case of a designated tax-advantaged plan that is a defined contribution plan, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref> does not permit the contribution to be directly or indirectly based on the terms of that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s transactions. A defined contribution plan has the meaning set forth in Internal Revenue Code section 414(i), 26 U.S.C. 414(i). A defined benefit plan has the meaning set forth in Internal Revenue Code section 414(j), 26 U.S.C. 414(j).</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
          <title>Non-deferred profits-based compensation plans.</title>
          <content>As used in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref>, a &#8220;non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan&#8221; is any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> arrangement where an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> may be paid variable, additional <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> based in whole or in part on the mortgage-related business profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> paying the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, any <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, or a business unit within the organizational structure of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> or the <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, as applicable (i.e., depending on the level within the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>'s or <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>'s organization at which the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is established). A non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan does not include a designated tax-advantaged plan or other forms of deferred <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that are not designated tax-advantaged plans, such as those created pursuant to Internal Revenue Code section 409A, 26 U.S.C. 409A. Thus, if contributions to or benefits under a designated tax-advantaged plan or <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under another form of deferred <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan are determined with reference to the mortgage-related business profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> making the contribution, then the contribution, benefits, or other <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, as applicable, are not permitted by &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> (although, in the case of contributions to or benefits under a designated tax-advantaged plan, the benefits or contributions may be permitted by &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref>). Under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan, the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> may, for example, be paid directly in cash, stock, or other non-deferred <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, and the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan may be determined by a fixed formula or may be at the discretion of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> (e.g., the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> may elect not to pay <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan in a given year), provided the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s transactions. As used in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> and this commentary, non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plans include, without limitation, bonus pools, profits pools, bonus plans, and profit-sharing plans. <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">Compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan could include, without limitation, annual or periodic bonuses, or awards of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prizes or incentives where the bonuses, contributions, or awards are determined with reference to the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, business unit, or <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, as applicable. As used in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> and this commentary, a business unit is a division, department, or segment within the overall organizational structure of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> or the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>'s <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> that performs discrete business functions and that the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> or the <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> treats separately for accounting or other organizational purposes. For example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that pays its <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> bonuses at the end of a calendar year based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s average net return on assets for the calendar year is operating a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref>. A bonus that is paid to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> from a source other than a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan (or a deferred <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan where the bonus is determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits), such as a retention bonus budgeted for in advance or a performance bonus paid out of a bonus pool set aside at the beginning of thecompany's annual accounting period as part of the company's operating budget, does not violate the prohibition on payment of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref>, as clarified by comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii; therefore, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> does not apply to such bonuses.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
          <title>Compensation that is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators.</title>
          <content>The <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> arrangements addressed in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref> and (iv) are permitted even if they are directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>. See comment 36(d)(1)-1 for additional interpretation. If a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref>'s revenues are exclusively derived from transactions subject to &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)</ref> (whether paid by <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref>, <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>, or both) and that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> pays its <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> a bonus under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan, the bonus is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> if &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(i)</ref> is otherwise complied with.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-iv" marker="iv.">
          <title>Compensation based on terms of an individual loan originator's transactions.</title>
          <content>Under both &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iii)</ref>, with regard to contributions made to a defined contribution plan that is a designated tax-advantaged plan, and &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A)</ref>, with regard to <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan, the payment of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> may not be directly or indirectly based on the terms of that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s transaction or transactions. Consequently, for example, where an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> makes loans that vary in their interest rate spread, the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> payment may not take into account the average interest rate spread on the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s transactions during the relevant calendar year.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v" marker="v.">
          <title>Compensation under non-deferred profits-based compensation plans.</title>
          <content>Assuming that the conditions in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A)</ref> are met, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> permits certain <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan. Specifically, if the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is determined with reference to the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> from mortgage-related business, <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is permitted provided the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> does not, in the aggregate, exceed 10 percent of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> corresponding to the time period for which <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is paid. The <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> restrictions under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> are sometimes referred to in this commentary as the &#8220;10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit&#8221; or the &#8220;10-percent limit.&#8221;</content><interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-A" marker="A.">
            <title>Total compensation. </title>
            <content>For purposes of &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> consists of the sum total of: (1) All wages and tips reportable for Medicare tax purposes in box 5 on IRS form W-2 (or, if the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> is an independent contractor, reportable <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> on IRS form 1099-MISC) that are actually paid during the relevant time period (regardless of when the wages and tips are earned), except for any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan that is earned during a different time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.C); (2) at the election of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> paying the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, all contributions that are actually made during the relevant time period by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> to the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s accounts in designated tax-advantaged plans that are defined contribution plans (regardless of when the contributions are earned); and (3) at the election of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> paying the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, all <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan that is earned during the relevant time period, regardless of whether the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is actually paid during that time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.C). If an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> has some <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that is reportable on the W-2 and some that is reportable on the 1099-MISC, the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is the sum total of what is reportable on each of the two forms.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-B" marker="B.">
            <title>Profits of the Person.</title>
            <content>Under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref>, a plan is a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan if <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is paid, based in whole or in part, on the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> paying the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>. As used in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref>, &#8220;profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>&#8221; include, as applicable depending on where the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is set, the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, the business unit to which the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> are assigned for accounting or other organizational purposes, or any <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>. Profits from mortgage-related business are profits determined with reference to revenue generated from transactions subject to &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)</ref>. Pursuant to &#167; <ref target="1026-36-b" reftype="internal">1026.36(b)</ref> and comment 36(b)-1, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)</ref> applies to closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transactions secured by <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref>. This revenue includes, without limitation, and as applicable based on the particular sources of revenue of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, business unit, or <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, origination fees and interest associated with <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>-secured transactions for which <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> working for the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> were <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originators</ref>, income from servicing of such transactions, and proceeds of secondary market sales of such transactions. If the amount of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plans paid for a time period does not, in the aggregate, exceed 10 percent of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> corresponding to the same time period, <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plans may be paid under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> regardless of whether or not it was determined with reference to the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> from mortgage-related business.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-C" marker="C.">
            <title>Time period for which the compensation under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is paid and to which the total compensation corresponds.</title>
            <content>Under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref>, determination of whether payment of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan complies with the 10-percent limit requires a calculation of the ratio of the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan (i.e., the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> subject to the 10-percent limit) and the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> corresponding to the relevant time period. For <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> subject to the 10-percent limit, the relevant time period is the time period for which a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> makes reference to profits in determining the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> (i.e., when the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> was earned). It does not matter whether the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is actually paid during that particular time period. For total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, the relevant time period is the same time period, but only certain types of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> may be included in the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> amount for that time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.A). For example, assume that during calendar year 2014 a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> pays an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> in the following amounts: $80,000 in commissions based on the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s performance and volume of loans generated during the calendar year; and $10,000 in an employer contribution to a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan on behalf of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> desires to pay the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> a year-end bonus of $10,000 under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan. The commissions are paid and employer contributions to the designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan are made during calendar year 2014, but the year-end bonus will be paid in January 2015. For purposes of the 10-percent limit, the year-end bonus is counted toward the 10-percent limit for calendar year 2014, even though it is not actually paid until 2015. Therefore, for calendar year 2014 the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that is subject to the 10-percent limit would be $10,000 (i.e., the year-end bonus) and the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> would be $100,000 (i.e., the sum of the commissions, the designated tax-advantaged plan contribution (assuming the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to include it in total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for calendar year 2014), and the bonus (assuming the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to include it in total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for calendar year 2014)); the bonus would be permissible under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> because it does not exceed 10 percent of total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>. The determination of total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> corresponding to 2014 also would not take into account any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> subject to the 10-percent limit that is actually paid in 2014 but is earned during a different calendar year (e.g., an annual bonus determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits for calendar year 2013 that is paid in January 2014). If the employer contribution to the designated tax-advantaged plan is earned in 2014 but actually made in 2015, however, it may not be included in total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for 2014. A company, business unit, or <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, as applicable, may pay <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> subject to the 10-percent limit during different time periods falling within its annual accounting period for keeping records and reporting income and expenses,which may be a calendar year or a fiscal year depending on the annual accounting period. In such instances, however, the 10-percent limit applies both as to each time period and cumulatively as to the annual accounting period. For example, assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> uses a calendar-year accounting period. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> pays an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> a bonus at the end of each quarter under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan, the payment of each quarterly bonus is subject to the 10-percent limit measured with respect to each quarter. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can also pay an annual bonus under the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan that does not exceed the difference of 10 percent of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> corresponding to the calendar year and the aggregate amount of the quarterly bonuses.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-D" marker="D.">
            <title>Awards of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prizes or incentives.</title>
            <content>If any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> paid to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)</ref> consists of an award of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prize or incentive, the cash value of the award is factored into the calculation of the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit. For example, during a given calendar year, <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A and <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B are each employed by a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and paid $40,000 in salary, and $45,000 in commissions. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> also contributes $5,000 to a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan for each <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> during that calendar year, which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to include in the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> amount. Neither <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> is paid any other form of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. In December of the calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> rewards both <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> for their performance during the calendar year out of a bonus pool established with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit. <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A is paid a $10,000 cash bonus, meaning that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A's total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is $100,000 (assuming the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to include the bonus in the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> amount). <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B is paid a $7,500 cash bonus and awarded a vacation package with a cash value of $3,000, meaning that <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B's total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> is $100,500 (assuming the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to include the reward in the total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> amount). Under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref>, <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A's $10,000 bonus is permissible because the bonus would not constitute more than 10 percent of <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A's total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for the calendar year. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may not pay <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B the $7,500 bonus and award the vacation package, however, because the total value of the bonus and the vacation package would be $10,500, which is greater than 10 percent (10.45 percent) of <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B's total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for the calendar year. One way to comply with &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> would be if the amount of the bonus were reduced to $7,000 or less or the vacation package were structured such that its cash value would be $2,500 or less.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-E" marker="E.">
            <title>Compensation determined only with reference to non-mortgage-related business profits.</title>
            <content><ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">Compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is not subject to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> if the non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan is determined with reference only to profits from business other than mortgage-related business, as determined in accordance with reasonable accounting principles. Reasonable accounting principles reflect an accurate allocation of revenues, expenses, profits, and losses among the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, any <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, and any business units within the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> or <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, and are consistent with the accounting principles applied by the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, the <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, or the business unit with respect to, as applicable, its internal budgeting and auditing functions and external reporting requirements. Examples of external reporting and filing requirements that may be applicable to <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> and <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organizations</ref> are Federal income tax filings, Federal securities law filings, or quarterly reporting of income, expenses, loan origination activity, and other information required by government-sponsored enterprises. As used in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref>, profits means positive profits or losses avoided or mitigated.</content></interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-F" marker="F.">
            <title>Additional examples.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-F-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Assume that, during a given calendar year, a loan originator organization pays an individual loan originator employee $40,000 in salary and $125,000 in commissions, and makes a contribution of $15,000 to the individual loan originator's 401(k) plan. At the end of the year, the loan originator organization wishes to pay the individual loan originator a bonus based on a formula involving a number of performance metrics, to be paid out of a profit pool established at the level of the company but that is determined in part with reference to the profits of the company's mortgage origination unit. Assume that the loan originator organization derives revenues from sources other than transactions covered by &#167; 1026.36(d). In this example, the performance bonus would be directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple individual loan originators' transactions as described in &#167; 1026.36(d)(1)(i), because it is being determined with reference to profits from mortgage-related business. Assume, furthermore, that the loan originator organization elects to include the bonus in the total compensation amount for the calendar year. Thus, the bonus is permissible under &#167; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1) if it does not exceed 10 percent of the loan originator's total compensation, which in this example consists of the individual loan originator's salary and commissions, the contribution to the 401(k) plan (if the loan originator organization elects to include the contribution in the total compensation amount), and the performance bonus. Therefore, if the loan originator organization elects to include the 401(k) contribution in total compensation for these purposes, the loan originator organization may pay the individual loan originator a performance bonus of up to $20,000 (i.e., 10 percent of $200,000 in total compensation). If the loan originator organization does not include the 401(k) contribution in calculating total compensation, or the 401(k) contribution is actually made in January of the following calendar year (in which case it cannot be included in total compensation for the initial calendar year), the bonus may be up to $18,333.33. If the loan originator organization includes neither the 401(k) contribution nor the performance bonus in the total compensation amount, the bonus may not exceed $16,500.</title>
              <content/>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-F-2" marker="2.">
              <title/>
              <content>Assume that the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> during a given calendar year of an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> employed by a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> consists of only salary and commissions, and the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> does not participate in a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan. Assume further that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> uses a calendar-year accounting period. At the end of the calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> pays the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> two bonuses: A &#8220;performance&#8221; bonus based on the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s aggregate loan volume for a calendar year that is paid out of a bonus pool determined with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit, and a year-end &#8220;holiday&#8221; bonus in the same amount to all company employees that is paid out of a company-wide bonus pool. Because the performance bonus is paid out of a bonus pool that is determined with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit, it is <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> that is determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits, and the bonus is therefore subject to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit. If the company-wide bonus pool from which the &#8220;holiday&#8221; bonus is paid is derived in part from profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s mortgage origination business unit, then the combination of the &#8220;holiday&#8221; bonus and the performance bonus is subject to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit. The &#8220;holiday&#8221; bonus is not subject to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit if the bonus pool is determined with reference only to the profits of business units other than the mortgage origination business unit, as determined in accordance with reasonable accounting principles. If the &#8220;performance&#8221; bonus and the &#8220;holiday&#8221; bonus in the aggregate do not exceed 10 percent of the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref>, the bonuses may be paid under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> without the necessity of determining from which bonus pool they were paid or whether they were determined with reference to the profits of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s mortgage origination business unit.</content></interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-v-G" marker="G.">
            <title>Reasonable reliance by individual loan originator on accounting or statement by person paying compensation.</title>
            <content>An <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> is deemed to comply with its obligations regarding receipt of <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> if the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> relies in good faith on an accounting or a statement provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> who determined the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref>'s <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan pursuant to &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> and where the statement or accounting is provided within a reasonable time period following the <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>'s determination.</content></interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-36-d-1-Interp-3-vi" marker="vi.">
          <title>Individual loan originators who originate ten or fewer transactions.</title>
          <content>Assuming that the conditions in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A)</ref> are met, &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-2" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(2)</ref> permits <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> to an <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> under a non-deferred profits-based <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> plan even if the payment or contribution is directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref>' transactions if the individual is a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> (as defined in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.36(a)(1)(i)</ref>) for ten or fewer consummated transactions during the 12-month period preceding the <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> determination. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> employs two <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> who originate transactions subject to &#167; 1026.36 during a given calendar year. Both employees are <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> as defined in &#167; <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.36(a)(1)(ii)</ref>, but only one of them (<ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B) acts as a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> in the normal course of business, while the other (<ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A) is called upon to do so only occasionally and regularly performs other duties (such as serving as a manager). In January of the following calendar year, the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> formally determines the financial performance of its mortgage business for the prior calendar year. Based on that determination, the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> on February 1 decides to pay a bonus to the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originators</ref> out of a company bonus pool. Assume that, between February 1 of the prior calendar year and January 31 of the current calendar year, <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A was the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> for eight consummated transactions, and <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B was the <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> for 15 consummated transactions. The <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> may award the bonus to <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> A under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-2" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(2)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-36-a-1-iii" reftype="term">loan originator organization</ref> may not award the bonus to <ref target="1026-36-a-1-ii" reftype="term">individual loan originator</ref> B relying on the exception under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-2" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(2)</ref> because it would not apply, although it could award a bonus pursuant to the 10-percent total <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> limit under &#167; <ref target="1026-36-d-1-iv-B-1" reftype="internal">1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(1)</ref> if the requirements of that provision are complied with.</content></interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-f-3-i-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(i) requires the loan originator organization to obtain, for any of its individual loan originator employees who is not required to be licensed and is not licensed as a loan originator pursuant to the SAFE Act, a criminal background check, a credit report, and information related to any administrative, civil, or criminal determinations by any government jurisdiction. The requirement applies to individual loan originator employees who were hired on or after January 1, 2014 (or whom the loan originator organization hired before this date but for whom there were no applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire or before January 1, 2014, used to screen the individual). A credit report may be obtained directly from a consumer reporting agency or through a commercial service. A loan originator organization with access to the NMLSR can meet the requirement for the criminal background check by reviewing any criminal background check it receives upon compliance with the requirement in 12 CFR 1007.103(d)(1) and can meet the requirement to obtain information related to any administrative, civil, or criminal determinations by any government jurisdiction by obtaining the information through the NMLSR. Loan originator organizations that do not have access to these items through the NMLSR may obtain them by other means. For example, a criminal background check may be obtained from a law enforcement agency or commercial service. Information on any past administrative, civil, or criminal findings (such as from disciplinary or enforcement actions) may be obtained from the individual loan originator.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-f-3-i-Interp-2" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(i) does not require the loan originator organization to obtain the covered information for an individual whom the loan originator organization hired as a loan originator before January 1, 2014, and screened under applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire. However, if the individual subsequently ceases to be employed as a loan originator by that loan originator organization, and later resumes employment as a loan originator by that loan originator organization (or any other loan originator organization), the loan originator organization is subject to the requirements of &#167; 1026.36(f)(3)(i).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-f-3-ii-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(ii) requires the loan originator organization to review the information that it obtains under &#167; 1026.36(f)(3)(i) and other reasonably available information to determine whether the individual loan originator meets the standards in &#167; 1026.36(f)(3)(ii). Other reasonably available information includes any information the loan originator organization has obtained or would obtain as part of a reasonably prudent hiring process, including information obtained from application forms, candidate interviews, other reliable information and evidence provided by a candidate, and reference checks. The requirement applies to individual loan originator employees who were hired on or after January 1, 2014 (or whom the loan originator organization hired before this date but for whom there were no applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire or before January 1, 2014, used to screen the individual).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-f-3-ii-Interp-2" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(ii) does not require the loan originator organization to review the covered information and make the required determinations for an individual whom the loan originator organization hired as a loan originator on or before January 1, 2014 and screened under applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire. However, if the individual subsequently ceases to be employed as a loan originator by that loan originator organization, and later resumes employment as a loan originator by that loan originator organization (or any other loan originator organization), the loan originator organization employing the individual is subject to the requirements of &#167; 1026.36(f)(3)(ii).</content>
    </change>
    <!-- end of notice -->
  </changeset>
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1026-36-j" notice="2013-22752_20140101" date="2014-01-01">
      <title>36(j) Depository Institution Compliance Procedures</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Dodd-Frank Act section 1402(a)(2) added TILA section 129B(b)(2), which provides that the Bureau &#8220;shall prescribe regulations requiring depository institutions to establish and maintain procedures reasonably designed to assure and monitor the compliance of such depository institutions, and subsidiaries of such institutions, and the employees of such institutions or subsidiaries with the requirements of this section and the registration procedures established under section 1507 of the [SAFE Act].&#8221; 15 U.S.C. 1639b(b)(2). The Bureau notes that one week after the Dodd-Frank Act was signed into law, the Federal prudential regulatory agencies for banks, thrifts, and credit unions jointly issued a final rule requiring the institutions they regulate, among other things, to adopt and follow written policies and procedures designed to assure compliance with the registration requirements of the SAFE Act. That final rule was inherited by the Bureau and is designated as Regulation G. The Bureau believes that Regulation G largely satisfies the provision under TILA section 129B(b)(2) for regulations requiring compliance policies and procedures, with regard to mortgage originator qualification requirements. TILA section 129B(b)(2) also requires the Bureau to prescribe regulations requiring depository institutions to establish and maintain procedures reasonable designed to assure and monitor compliance with all of TILA section 129B.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The proposal did not contain specific regulatory language to implement TILA section 129B(b)(2), but the Bureau stated that it might adopt such language in this final rule. Accordingly, it described the language it was considering in detail and solicited comment on the described text.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Specifically, the proposal stated the Bureau's expectation that such a rule would require depository institutions to establish and maintain procedures reasonably designed to ensure and monitor the compliance of themselves, their subsidiaries, and the employees of both with the requirements of &#167; 1026.36(d), (e), (f), and (g). The Bureau stated that the rule would provide further that the required procedures must be appropriate to the nature, size, complexity, and scope of the mortgage credit activities of the depository institution and its subsidiaries. The Bureau solicited public comment on whether it should define &#8220;depository institution&#8221; using the FDIA's definition (which does not include credit unions), the SAFE Act's definition (which includes credit unions), or some other definition.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau further noted that under Regulation G only certain subsidiaries (those that are &#8220;covered financial institutions&#8221;) are required by 12 CFR 1007.104 to adopt and follow written policies and procedures designed to assure compliance with Regulation G. Accordingly, the proposal noted that it may be appropriate to apply the duty to ensure and monitor compliance of subsidiaries and their employees under TILA section 129B(b)(2) only to subsidiaries that are covered financial institutions under Regulation G. Exercising TILA section 105(a) authority to make an adjustment or exception in this way may facilitate compliance by aligning the scope of the subsidiaries covered by the TILA and SAFE Act requirements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Finally, the proposal questioned whether extending the scope of a regulation requiring procedures even further, to apply to other loan originators that are not covered financial institutions under Regulation G (such as independent mortgage companies), would help ensure consistent consumer protections and more equal compliance responsibilities among types of creditor. The Bureau discussed whether exercising TILA section 105(a) authority in this way is necessary or proper to effectuate the purpose stated in TILA section 129B(a)(2) of ensuring that consumers are offered and receive residential mortgage loans that are not unfair, deceptive, or abusive.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau therefore solicited comment on whether a regulation requiring procedures to comply with TILA section 129B should apply only to depository institutions as defined in section 3 of the FDIA, or also to credit unions, other covered financial institutions subject to Regulation G, or any other loan originators such as independent mortgage companies. Additionally, the Bureau solicited comment on whether it should apply the duty to ensure and monitor compliance of subsidiaries and their employees only with respect to subsidiaries that are covered financial institutions under Regulation G. With respect to all of the foregoing, the Bureau also solicited comment on whether any of the potential exercises of TILA section 105(a) authority should apply with respect to procedures concerning only SAFE Act registration, or with respect to procedures for all the duty of care requirements (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> the qualifications and loan document provisions) in TILA section 129B(b)(1), or with respect to procedures for all the requirements of TILA section 129B, including the compensation and steering provisions and those added by section 1402 of the Dodd-Frank Act.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also recognized that a depository institution's failure to establish and maintain the required procedures under the implementing regulation would constitute a violation of TILA, thus potentially resulting in significant civil liability risk to depository institutions under TILA section 130. <em data-original="E-03">See</em> 15 U.S.C. 1640. The Bureau anticipated concerns on the part of depository institutions regarding their ability to avoid such liability risk and therefore sought comment on the appropriateness of establishing a safe harbor that would demonstrate compliance with the rule requiring procedures. It stated that such a safe harbor might provide that a depository institution is presumed to have met the requirement for procedures if it, its subsidiaries, and the employees of it and its subsidiaries do not engage in a pattern or practice of violating &#167; 1026.36(d), (e), (f), or (g).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau did not receive any public comments on the contemplated provision requiring compliance procedures. The Bureau is adopting the contemplated provision to implement TILA section 129B(b)(2) in &#167; 1026.36(j), which requires compliance policies and procedures corresponding only to the substantive requirements of TILA section 129B implemented through this final rule, namely those in &#167; 1026.36(d), (e), (f), and (g). The adopted provision clarifies that the required procedures must be &#8220;written&#8221; to promote transparency, consistency, and accountability. The Bureau is adopting, for purposes of &#167; 1026.36(j), the definition of &#8220;depository institution&#8221; in the SAFE Act, which includes credit unions, because the substantive provisions in &#167; 1026.36(d), (e), (f), and (g) apply to credit unions. The Bureau notes that provisions implicating the contents of the written procedures that a depository institution establishes and maintains pursuant to &#167; 1026.36(j) are included in &#167; 1026.36(f)(3)(ii)(B)(<em data-original="E-03">3</em>)and comment 36(g)(1)(ii)-1.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
