<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-05-03</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-10429</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2013-05-03</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2013/05/03/2013-10429/truth-in-lending-regulation-z</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-07066" rightDocumentNumber="2013-10429">
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i-C"/>
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i-B"/>
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i-A"/>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-2-Interp-2">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title type="keyterm">Independent ability-to-pay standard.</title>
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-51-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)</ref>, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless, at the time of the contemplated increase, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit, consistent with § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>, or a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old assumes liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(ii)</ref>. Thus, when a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is considering whether to increase the credit limit on an existing account, § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-A" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(A)</ref> requires that <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who have not attained the age of 21 and do not have a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is 21 years or older must have an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments as of the time of the contemplated increase. Thus, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may not consider income or assets to which an accountholder, cosigner, or guarantor, in each case who is under the age of 21 and is or will be liable for debts incurred on the account, has only a reasonable expectation of access under § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-A" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(A)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref>, however, may consider income or assets to which an accountholder, cosigner, or guarantor, in each case who is age 21 or older and is or will be liable for debts incurred on the account, has a reasonable expectation of access under § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref>. Information regarding income and assets that satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref> also satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-A" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(A)</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely on the guidance in the commentary to § <ref target="1026-51-b-Interp-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref> for purposes of determining whether an accountholder who is less than 21 years old has the independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments in accordance with § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-A" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(A)</ref>. Information regarding income and assets that satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> also satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely on the guidance in comments 51(a)(1)-4, -5, and -6 for purposes of determining whether a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments in accordance with § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-2-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
      <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>At the time of the contemplated increase, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section; or</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>A cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old agrees in writing to assume liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b-1-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-i" marker="(i)">
      <content>Financial information indicating the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the proposed extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> in connection with the account; or</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iii" marker="iii.">
      <content>Information obtained through third parties (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
      <title type="keyterm">Income and assets of persons liable for debts incurred on account.</title>
      <content>Current or reasonably expected income includes, for example, current or expected salary, wages, bonus pay, tips, and commissions. Employment may be full-time, part-time, seasonal, irregular, military, or self-employment. Other sources of income include interest or dividends, retirement benefits, public assistance, alimony, child support, and separate maintenance payments. Proceeds from student loans may be considered as current or reasonably expected income only to the extent that those proceeds exceed the amount disbursed or owed to an educational institution for tuition and other expenses. Current or reasonably expected income also includes income that is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or joint account). Assets include, for example, savings accounts and investments.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iv">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iv" marker="iv.">
      <title type="keyterm">Examples of considering income.</title>
      <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access, the non-applicant does not regularly use that income to pay for the applicant's expenses, and no Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants the applicant an ownership interest in that income. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is not permitted to consider the non-applicant's income as the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> because the applicant does not have a reasonable expectation of access to the non-applicant's income.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-b-1-Interp-1"/>
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-b-1-Interp"/>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-iii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-iii" marker="iii.">
      <title type="keyterm">Household income and assets.</title>
      <content>Consideration of the income or assets of authorized users, household members, or other <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> who are not liable for debts incurred on the accoun<ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">t does not</ref> satisfy the requirement to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income or assets, unless a Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who is liable for debts incurred on the account an ownership interest in such income and assets (e.g., joint owner<ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">ship grant</ref>ed under <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> community property laws), such income is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or a joint account), or the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access to such income or assets even though the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> does not have a current or expected ownership interest in the income or assets. See comment 51(a)(1)-6 for examples of non-appli<ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">cant incom</ref>e to which a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-ii">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
      <title type="keyterm">Reasonable policies and procedures.</title>
      <content><ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">Card issuers</ref> must establish and maintain reasonable written policies and procedures to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum payments under the terms of the account based on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations. Reasonable policies and procedures include treating any income and assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, or limiting consideration of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s independent income and assets. Reasonable policies and procedures also include consideration of at least one of the following: The ratio of debt obligations to income; the ratio of debt obligations to assets; or the income the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will have after paying debt obligations. It would be unreasonable for a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> not to review any information about a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and current obligations, or to issue a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who does not have any income or assets.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iii" marker="iii.">
      <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly uses a portion of that income to pay for the applicant's expenses. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is used regularly to pay for the applicant's expenses to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> because the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access to that income.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-Interp-7">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-Interp-7" marker="7.">
      <title type="keyterm">Relation to Regulation B.</title>
      <content>In considering an application or <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line increase on the <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who is less than 21 years old, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> must comply with the applicable rules in Regulation B (<ref target="CFR:12-1026" reftype="external">12 CFR part 1026</ref>). A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> does not violate Regulation B by complying with the requirements in § <ref target="1026-51-b" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-Interp-6">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-Interp-6" marker="6.">
      <title type="keyterm">Joint applicants or joint accountholders.</title>
      <content>With respect to the opening of a joint account for two or more <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> under § <ref target="1026-51-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)</ref> or a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line increase on such an account under § <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(2)(i)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the collective ability of all <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> who are or will be liable for debts incurred on the account to make the required payments. See commentary to § <ref target="1026-51-b-Interp-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref> and <ref target="1026-51-b-2-Interp" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref> for information on income and assets that may be considered for joint applicants, joint accountholders, cosigners, or guarantors who are under the age of 21, and commentary to § <ref target="1026-51-b-Interp-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(ii)</ref> for information on income and assets that may be considered for joint applicants, joint accountholders, cosigners, or guarantors who are at least 21 years old.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-Interp-5">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title type="keyterm">Current obligations.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations under § <ref target="1026-51-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-51-b-2-i" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(i)</ref> based on information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or in a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> report. In evaluating a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> need not assume that <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> lines for other obligations are fully utilized.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp" target="1026-51-b-1-i">
      <title>Paragraph 51(b)(1)(i).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Consideration of income and assets for young consumers.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider any current or reasonably expected income or assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are applying for a new account or will be liable for debts incurred on that account, including a cosigner or guarantor. However, because § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref> requires that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who has not attained the age of 21 have an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may only consider the applicant's current or reasonably expected income or assets under § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may not consider income or assets to which an applicant, joint applicant, cosigner, or guarantor, in each case who is under the age of 21 and is or will be liable for debts incurred on the account, has only a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Current or reasonably expected income includes, for example, current or expected salary, wages, bonus pay, tips, and commissions. Employment may be full-time, part-time, seasonal, irregular, military, or self-employment. Other sources of income include interest or dividends, retirement benefits, public assistance, alimony, child support, and separate maintenance payments. Proceeds from student loans may be considered as current or reasonably expected income only to the extent that those proceeds exceed the amount disbursed or owed to an educational institution for tuition and other expenses. Current or reasonably expected income includes income that is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or a joint account). Assets include, for example, savings accounts and investments. Current or reasonably expected income and assets does not include income and assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> only has a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Consideration of the income and assets of authorized users, household members, or other <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> who are not liable for debts incurred on the account does not satisfy the requirement to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income or assets, unless a Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who is liable for debts incurred on the account an ownership interest in such income or assets (e.g., joint ownership granted under <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> community property laws), or the income is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or a joint account). See comment <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3" reftype="internal">51(b)(1)(i)-3</ref> for examples of income that may be relied upon as a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Information regarding income and assets for young consumers.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income and assets based on the following information:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with the account, including information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> through the application process. For example, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely without further inquiry on information provided by applicants in response to a request for “salary,” “income,” “personal income,” “individual income,” “assets,” or other language requesting that the applicant provide information regarding his or her current or reasonably expected income or assets. However, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may not rely solely on information provided in response to a request for “household income.” Nor may they rely solely on information provided in response to a request for “available income,” “accessible income,” or other language requesting that the applicant provide any income or assets to which the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access. In such cases, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> would need to obtain additional information about an applicant's current or reasonably expected income (such as by contacting the applicant). See comments <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-1" reftype="internal">51(b)(1)(i)-1</ref>, <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2" reftype="internal">-2</ref>, and <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3" reftype="internal">-3</ref> for additional guidance on determining the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income under § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>. See comment 51(a)(1)-9 for guidance regarding the use of a single, common application for all <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> applicants, regardless of age.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with any other financial relationship the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> have with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Information obtained through third parties (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-2-iv" marker="iv.">
          <content>Information obtained through any empirically derived, demonstrably and statistically sound model that reasonably estimates a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title type="keyterm">Examples of considering income for young consumers.</title>
        <content>Assume that an applicant is not employed and the applicant is under the age of 21 so § <ref target="1026-51-b" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)</ref> applies.</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
          <content>If a non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited regularly into a joint account shared with the applicant, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being deposited regularly into the account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly transfers a portion of that income into the applicant's individual deposit account. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being transferred regularly into the applicant's account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly uses that income to pay for the applicant's expenses. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is not permitted to consider the non-applicant's income that is used regularly to pay for the applicant's expenses as the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>, unless a Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants the applicant an ownership interest in such income.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-i-Interp-3-iv" marker="iv.">
          <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access, the non-applicant does not regularly use that income to pay for the applicant's expenses, and no Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants the applicant an ownership interest in that income. The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is not permitted to consider the non-applicant's income to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(i)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-1-ii-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-Interp" target="1026-51-b-1-ii">
      <title>Paragraph 51(b)(1)(ii).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Financial information.</title>
        <content>Information regarding income and assets that satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> also satisfies the requirements of § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(ii)(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely on the guidance in comments 51(a)(1)-4, -5, and -6 for purposes of determining whether a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments in accordance with § <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)(1)(ii)(B)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-ii" marker="ii.">
      <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly transfers a portion of that income into the applicant's individual deposit account. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being transferred regularly into the applicant's account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider any current or <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">reasonably</ref> expected income or assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are applying for a new account or will be liable for debts incurred on that account, including a cosigner or guarantor. Similarly, when a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is considering whether to increase the credit limit on an existing account, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider any current or reasonably expected income or assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are accountholders, cosigners, or guarantors, and are liable for debts incurred on that account. In both of these circumstances, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may treat any income and assets to which an applicant, accountholder, joint applicant, cosigner, or guarantor who is or will be liable for debts incurred on the account has a reasonable expectation of access as the applicant's current or reasonably expected income—but is not required to do so. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may instead limit its consideration of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income or assets to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s independent income or assets as discussed in comments 51(b)(1)(i)-1 and 51(b)(2)-2. Although these comments clarify the independent ability-to-pay requirement that governs applications from <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> under 21, they provide guidance regarding the use of “independent income and assets” as an underwriting criterion under § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>. For example, comment 51(b)(1)(i)-1 explains that <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may not consider income or assets to which applicants under 21 have only a reasonable expectation of access. An <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> who chooses to comply with § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> by limiting its consideration to applicants' independent income and assets likewise would not consider income or assets to which applicants 21 or older have only a reasonable expectation of access.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
      <title type="keyterm">Consideration of ability to pay.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must not open a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-ii" reftype="term">credit card account for a consumer under an open-end (not home-secured) consumer credit plan</ref>, or increase any credit limit applicable to such account, unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> considers the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments under the terms of the account based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-a" marker="(a)">
      <title type="keyterm">General rule</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1" marker="(1)">
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <title type="keyterm">Consideration of ability to pay.</title>
          <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must not open a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account for a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> under an open-end (not home-secured) <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> plan, or increase any credit limit applicable to such account, unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> considers the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments under the terms of the account based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title type="keyterm">Reasonable policies and procedures.</title>
          <content><ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">Card issuers</ref> must establish and maintain reasonable written policies and procedures to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum payments under the terms of the account based on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations. Reasonable policies and procedures include treating any income and assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, or limiting consideration of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s independent income and assets. Reasonable policies and procedures also include consideration of at least one of the following: The ratio of debt obligations to income; the ratio of debt obligations to assets; or the income the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will have after paying debt obligations. It would be unreasonable for a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> not to review any information about a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and current obligations, or to issue a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who does not have any income or assets.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2" marker="(2)">
        <title type="keyterm">Minimum periodic payments</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <title type="keyterm">Reasonable method.</title>
          <content>For purposes of paragraph <ref target="1026-51-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must use a reasonable method for estimating the minimum periodic payments the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> would be required to pay under the terms of the account.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title type="keyterm">Safe harbor.</title>
          <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> complies with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> of this section if it estimates required minimum periodic payments using the following method:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> assumes utilization, from the first day of the <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref>, of the full <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line that the <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>; and</content></paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> uses a minimum payment formula employed by the <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> for the product the <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or, in the case of an existing account, the minimum payment formula that currently applies to that account, provided that:</content><paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes interest charges, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> estimates those charges using an interest rate that the <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for purchases or, in the case of an existing account, the interest rate that currently applies to purchases; and</content></paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes mandatory fees, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must assume that such fees have been charged to the account.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b" marker="(b)">
      <title type="keyterm">Rules affecting young consumers</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Applications from young consumers.</title>
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may not open a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account under an open-end (not home-secured) <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> plan for a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> less than 21 years old, unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has submitted a written application and the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> has:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Financial information indicating the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the proposed extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> in connection with the account; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>A signed <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> of a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old to be either secondarily liable for any debt on the account incurred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has attained the age of 21 or jointly liable with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for any debt on the account; and</content></paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Financial information indicating such cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on such debts, consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">(a)</ref> of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2" marker="(2)">
        <title type="keyterm">Credit line increases for young consumers.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>At the time of the contemplated increase, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>A cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old agrees in writing to assume liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless the cosigner, guarantor, or joint accountholder who assumed liability at account opening agrees in writing to assume liability on the increase.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-i" marker="i.">
      <content>If a non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited regularly into a joint account shared with the applicant, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being deposited regularly into the account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6" marker="6.">
      <title type="keyterm">Examples of considering income.</title>
      <content>Assume that an applicant is not employed and that the applicant is age 21 or older so § <ref target="1026-51-b" reftype="internal">1026.51(b)</ref> does not apply.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-i" marker="i.">
        <content>If a non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited regularly into a joint account shared with the applicant, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being deposited regularly into the account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly transfers a portion of that income into the applicant's individual deposit account. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is being transferred regularly into the applicant's account to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access. However, the non-applicant regularly uses a portion of that income to pay for the applicant's expenses. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is permitted to consider the amount of the non-applicant's income that is used regularly to pay for the applicant's expenses to be the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> because the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access to that income.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6-iv" marker="iv.">
        <content>The non-applicant's salary or other income is deposited into an account to which the applicant does not have access, the non-applicant does not regularly use that income to pay for the applicant's expenses, and no Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants the applicant an ownership interest in that income. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is not permitted to consider the non-applicant's income as the applicant's current or reasonably expected income for purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> because the applicant does not have a reasonable expectation of access to the non-applicant's income.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-7">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-7" marker="7.">
      <content>Current obligations. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations based on information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or in a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> report. In evaluating a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> need not assume that <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> lines for other obligations are fully utilized.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title type="keyterm">Consideration of income and assets.</title>
      <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider any current or <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">reasonably</ref> expected income or assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are applying for a new account or will be liable for debts incurred on that account, including a cosigner or guarantor. Similarly, when a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> is considering whether to increase the credit limit on an existing account, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider any current or reasonably expected income or assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are accountholders, cosigners, or guarantors, and are liable for debts incurred on that account. In both of these circumstances, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may treat any income and assets to which an applicant, accountholder, joint applicant, cosigner, or guarantor who is or will be liable for debts incurred on the account has a reasonable expectation of access as the applicant's current or reasonably expected income—but is not required to do so. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may instead limit its consideration of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income or assets to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s independent income or assets as discussed in comments <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">51(b)(1)(i)</ref>-1 and <ref target="1026-51-b-2" reftype="internal">51(b)(2)</ref>-2. Although these comments clarify the independent ability-to-pay requirement that governs applications from <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> under 21, they provide guidance regarding the use of “independent income and assets” as an underwriting criterion under § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>. For example, comment <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">51(b)(1)(i)</ref>-1 explains that <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may not consider income or assets to which applicants under 21 have only a reasonable expectation of access. An <ref target="1026-58-b-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> who chooses to comply with § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> by limiting its consideration to applicants' independent income and assets likewise would not consider income or assets to which applicants 21 or older have only a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>Current or reasonably expected income includes, for example, current or expected salary, wages, bonus pay, tips, and commissions. Employment may be full-time, part-time, seasonal, irregular, military, or self-employment. Other sources of income include interest or dividends, retirement benefits, public assistance, alimony, child support, and separate maintenance payments. Proceeds from student loans may be considered as current or reasonably expected income only to the extent that those proceeds exceed the amount disbursed or owed to an educational institution for tuition and other expenses. Current or reasonably expected income also includes income that is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or joint account). Assets include, for example, savings accounts and investments.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-4-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>Consideration of the income or assets of authorized users, household members, or other <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> who are not liable for debts incurred on the account does not satisfy the requirement to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income or assets, unless a Federal or <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> statute or regulation grants a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who is liable for debts incurred on the account an ownership interest in such income and assets (e.g., joint ownership granted under <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> community property laws), such income is being deposited regularly into an account on which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is an accountholder (e.g., an individual deposit account or a joint account), or the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access to such income or assets even though the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> does not have a current or expected ownership interest in the income or assets. See comment <ref target="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-6" reftype="internal">51(a)(1)-6</ref> for examples of non-applicant income to which a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title type="keyterm">Information regarding income and assets.</title>
      <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income and assets based on the following information:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with the account, including information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> through the application process. For example, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely without further inquiry on information provided by applicants in response to a request for “salary,” “income,” “assets,” “available income,” “accessible income,” or other language requesting that the applicant provide information regarding current or reasonably expected income or assets or any income or assets to which the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access. However, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may not rely solely on information provided in response to a request for “household income.” In that case, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> would need to obtain additional information about an applicant's current or reasonably expected income, including income and assets to which the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access (such as by contacting the applicant). See comments 51(a)(1)-4, -5, and -6 for additional guidance on determining the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income under § <ref target="1026-51-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)(1)</ref>. See comment <ref target="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-9" reftype="internal">51(a)(1)-9</ref> for guidance regarding the use of a single, common application form or process for all <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> applicants, regardless of age.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with any other financial relationship the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> have with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>Information obtained through third parties (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iv" marker="iv.">
        <content>Information obtained through any empirically derived, demonstrably and statistically sound model that reasonably estimates a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, including any income or assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-2">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title type="keyterm">Ability to pay as of application or consideration of increase.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> complies with § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> if it bases its consideration of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the facts and circumstances known to the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> at the time the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> applies to open the <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account or when the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> considers increasing the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line on an existing account.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Consideration of additional factors.</title>
      <content>Section <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> requires a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> to consider a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments under the terms of an account based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and current obligations. The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may also consider <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> reports, <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> scores, and other factors, consistent with Regulation B (12 CFR part 1002).</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b-2">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2" marker="(2)">
      <title type="keyterm">Credit line increases for young consumers.</title>
      <content><ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">Credit</ref> <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>.</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>At the time of the contemplated increase, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old agrees in writing to assume liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless the cosigner, guarantor, or joint accountholder who assumed liability at account opening agrees in writing to assume liability on the increase.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
      <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with the account, including information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> through the application process. For example, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may rely without further inquiry on information provided by applicants in response to a request for “salary,” “income,” “assets,” “available income,” “accessible income,” or other language requesting that the applicant provide information regarding current or reasonably expected income or assets or any income or assets to which the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access. However, <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuers</ref> may not rely solely on information provided in response to a request for “household income.” In that case, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> would need to obtain additional information about an applicant's current or reasonably expected income, including income and assets to which the applicant has a reasonable expectation of access (such as by contacting the applicant). See comments 51(a)(1)-4, -5, and -6 for additional guidance on determining the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current or reasonably expected income under § <ref target="1026-51-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)(1)</ref>. See comment 51(a)(1)-9 for guidance regarding the use of a single, common application form or process for all <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> applicants, regardless of age.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iv">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-iv" marker="iv.">
      <content>Information obtained through any empirically derived, demonstrably and statistically sound model that reasonably estimates a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, including any income or assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-8">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-8" marker="8.">
      <content>Joint applicants and joint accountholders. With respect to the opening of a joint account for two or more <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> or a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line increase on such an account, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may consider the collective ability of all <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">persons</ref> who are or will be liable for debts incurred on the account to make the required payments.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-9">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-9" marker="9.">
      <title type="keyterm">Single application.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may use a single, common application form or process for all <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> applicants, regardless of age. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may rely without further verification on income and asset information provided by applicants through such an application, so long as the application questions gather sufficient information to allow the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> to satisfy the requirements of both § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> and <ref target="1026-51-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref>, depending on whether a particular applicant has reached the age of 21. For example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> might provide two separate line items on its application form, one prompting applicants to provide their “personal income,” and the other prompting applicants for “available income.” A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> might also prompt applicants, regardless of age, using only the term “income” and satisfy the requirements of both § <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">1026.51(a)</ref> and <ref target="1026-51-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="deleted" label="1026-51-b-1-Interp-2"/>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-51-a-1-i-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
      <content>Information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with any other financial relationship the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> have with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> (subject to any applicable information-sharing rules).</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b-1-ii-B">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
      <content>Financial information indicating such cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on such debts, consistent with paragraph (a) of this <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">sec</ref>tion.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b-1-ii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>A signed <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> of a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old to be either secondarily liable for any debt on the account incurred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has attained the age of 21 or jointly liable with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for any debt on the account; and</content></paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-51-b-2-ii">
    <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
      <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section, no increase in the credit limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless the cosigner, guarantor, or joint accountholder who assumed liability at account opening agrees in writing to assume liability on the increase.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
