<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-01-22</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-00734</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2013-06-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/articles/2013/01/22/2013-00734/escrow-requirements-under-the-truth-in-lending-act-regulation-z</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-10429" rightDocumentNumber="2013-00734">
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-b">
      <paragraph label="1026-51-b" marker="(b)">
        <title type="keyterm">Rules affecting young consumers</title>
        <content><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>—</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Applications from young consumers.</title>
          <content><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> may not open a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account under an open-end (not home-secured) <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> plan for a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> less than 21 years old, unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has submitted a written application and the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> has:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Financial information indicating the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the proposed extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> in connection with the account; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>A signed agreement of a cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old to be either secondarily liable for any debt on the account incurred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has attained the age of 21 or jointly liable with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for any debt on the account; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Financial information indicating such cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant has the ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on such debts, consistent with paragraph (a) of this <ref target="1026-51-a" reftype="internal">sec</ref>tion.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Credit line increases for young consumers.</title>
          <content><ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">Credit</ref><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>.</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, no increase in the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>At the time of the contemplated increase, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has an independent ability to make the required minimum periodic payments on the increased limit consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-i" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(i)</ref> of this section; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>A cosigner, guarantor, or joint applicant who is at least 21 years old agrees in writing to assume liability for any debt incurred on the account, consistent with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account has been opened pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-51-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section, no increase in the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> limit may be made on such account before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> attains the age of 21 unless the cosigner, guarantor, or joint accountholder who assumed liability at account opening agrees in writing to assume liability on the increase.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-34-a-4-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-34-a-4-i" marker="(i)">
        <title type="keyterm">Mortgage-related obligations.</title>
        <content>For purposes of this paragraph <ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">(a)(4)</ref>, mortgage-related obligations are expected property taxes, premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)(i)</ref>, and similar expenses.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <content>For purposes of paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> of this section:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for that year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extend covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien five or more times in the county. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-i-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>A transaction to finance the initial construction of a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-i-C">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
        <content>A temporary or “bridge” loan with a loan term of twelve months or less, such as a loan to purchase a new <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> where the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> plans to sell a current <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> within twelve months; or</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-i-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>A transaction secured by shares in a cooperative;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>Insurance premiums described in paragraph (b)(1) of this section need not be included in escrow accounts for loans secured by <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref> in condominiums, planned unit developments, or other common interest communities in which <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> ownership requires participation in a governing association, where the governing association has an obligation to the <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> owners to maintain a master policy insuring all <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-i-D">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-D" marker="(D)">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term">reverse mortgage transaction</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-33-c" reftype="internal">1026.33(c)</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-3-i-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>Receipt no earlier than five years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s request to cancel the escrow account.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-3-i-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>Termination of the underlying debt obligation; or</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-A"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-C"/>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-a-1-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp">
        <title>Paragraph 35(a)(1).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Comparable transaction.</title>
          <content>A <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> is a <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> with an annual percentage rate that exceeds the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> for a comparable transaction as of the date the interest rate is set by the specified margin. The table of <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref> published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> indicates how to identify the comparable transaction.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Rate set.</title>
          <content>A transaction's annual percentage rate is compared to the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set (or “locked”) before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Sometimes a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> sets the interest rate initially and then re-sets it at a different level before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> should use the last date the interest rate is set before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Threshold for “jumbo” loans.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)(1)(ii)</ref> provides a separate threshold for determining whether a transaction is a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> when the principal balance exceeds the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac (a “jumbo” loan). The Federal Housing Finance Agency (FHFA) establishes and adjusts the maximum principal obligation pursuant to rules under <ref target="USC:12-1454" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 1454</ref>(a)(2) and other provisions of federal law. Adjustments to the maximum principal obligation made by FHFA apply in determining whether a mortgage loan is a “jumbo” loan to which the separate coverage threshold in § <ref target="1026-35-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)(1)(ii)</ref> applies.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-3-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp">
        <title>35(b)(3) Cancellation.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Termination of underlying debt obligation.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)(i)</ref> provides that, in general, an escrow account required by § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> may not be cancelled until the underlying debt obligation is terminated or the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> requests cancellation at least five years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Methods by which an underlying debt obligation may be terminated include, among other things, repayment, refinancing, rescission, and foreclosure.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Minimum durations.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-3" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)</ref> establishes minimum durations for which escrow accounts established pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> must be maintained. This requirement does not affect a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s right or obligation, pursuant to the terms of the legal obligation or applicable law, to offer or require an escrow account thereafter.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Less than eighty percent unpaid principal balance.</title>
          <content>The term “original value” in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A)</ref> means the lesser of the sales price reflected in the sales contract for the property, if any, or the appraised value of the property at the time the transaction was consummated. In determining whether the unpaid principal balance has reached less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer shall count any subordinate lien of which it has reason to know. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> certifies in writing that the equity in the property securing the underlying debt obligation is unencumbered by a subordinate lien, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer may rely upon the certification in making its determination unless it has actual knowledge to the contrary.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-Interp">
          <content/>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-iv"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B-Interp"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-C-Interp"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-iii"/>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-v">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>Notwithstanding paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)</ref> of this section, an escrow account must be established pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section for any first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, is subject to a commitment to be acquired by a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> that does not satisfy the conditions in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)</ref> of this section, unless otherwise exempted by this paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-3-ii-A">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
        <content>The unpaid principal balance is less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation; and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Effective date.</title>
        <content>Principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Section 1026.35(b)(1) applies to principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref><ref target="1026-35-b" reftype="internal">ings, incl</ref>uding structures that are classified as personal property under <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> law. For example, an escrow account must be established on a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a manufactured home, boat, or trailer used as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. See the commentary under §§ 1026.2(a)(19) and(24), 1026.15, and 1026.23. Section 1026.35(b)(1) also applies to a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a condominium if it is in fact used as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. But see § 1026.35(b)(2) for exemptions from the escrow requirement that may apply to such transactions.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-Interp">
      <interpSection label="1026-35-Interp" sectionNum="35">
        <title>§ 1026.35—Requirements for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-Interp">
          <title>35(a) Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp">
            <title>Paragraph 35(a)(1).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Comparable transaction.</title>
              <content>A <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> is a <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> with an annual percentage rate that exceeds the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> for a comparable transaction as of the date the interest rate is set by the specified margin. The table of <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref> published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> indicates how to identify the comparable transaction.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Rate set.</title>
              <content>A transaction's annual percentage rate is compared to the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set (or “locked”) before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Sometimes a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> sets the interest rate initially and then re-sets it at a different level before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> should use the last date the interest rate is set before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Threshold for “jumbo” loans.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)(1)(ii)</ref> provides a separate threshold for determining whether a transaction is a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> when the principal balance exceeds the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac (a “jumbo” loan). The Federal Housing Finance Agency (FHFA) establishes and adjusts the maximum principal obligation pursuant to rules under <ref target="USC:12-1454" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 1454</ref>(a)(2) and other provisions of federal law. Adjustments to the maximum principal obligation made by FHFA apply in determining whether a mortgage loan is a “jumbo” loan to which the separate coverage threshold in § <ref target="1026-35-a-1-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)(1)(ii)</ref> applies.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp" target="1026-35-a-2">
            <title>Paragraph 35(a)(2)</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Average prime offer rate.</title>
              <content><ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">Average prime offer rate</ref><ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">Average prime offer rates</ref> are annual percentage rates derived from average interest rates, points, and other loan pricing terms currently offered to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> by a representative sample of <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> for mortgage transactions that have low-risk pricing characteristics. Other pricing terms include commonly used indices, margins, and initial fixed-rate periods for variable-rate transactions. Relevant pricing characteristics include a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s credit history and transaction characteristics such as the loan-to-value ratio, owner-occupant status, and purpose of the transaction. To obtain <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> uses a survey of <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> that both meets the criteria of § <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)(2)</ref> and provides pricing terms for at least two types of variable-rate transactions and at least two types of non-variable-rate transactions. An example of such a survey is the Freddie Mac Primary Mortgage Market Survey®.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Comparable transaction.</title>
              <content><ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> table. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes on the Internet, in table form, <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref> for a wide variety of transaction types. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> calculates an annual percentage rate, consistent with Regulation Z (see § 1026.22 and appendix J), for each transaction type for which pricing terms are available from a survey. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> estimates annual percentage rates for other types of transactions for which direct survey data are not available based on the loan pricing terms available in the survey and other information. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes on the Internet the methodology it uses to arrive at these estimates.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Rate set.</title>
              <content>Additional guidance on determination of <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref>. The <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> has the same meaning in § 1026.35 as in Regulation C, 12 CFR part 1003. See 12 CFR 1003.4(a)(12)(ii). Guidance on the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> under § 1026.35(a)(2), such as when a transaction's rate is set and determination of the comparable transaction, is provided in the official commentary under Regulation C, the publication entitled “A Guide to HMDA Reporting: Getting it Right!”, and the relevant “Frequently Asked Questions” on Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) compliance posted on the FFIEC's Web site at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-Interp" target="1026-35-b">
          <title>35(b) Escrow Accounts.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Effective date.</title>
            <content>Principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Section 1026.35(b)(1) applies to principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref><ref target="1026-35-b" reftype="internal">ings, incl</ref>uding structures that are classified as personal property under <ref target="1026-2-a-26" reftype="term">State</ref> law. For example, an escrow account must be established on a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a manufactured home, boat, or trailer used as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. See the commentary under §§ 1026.2(a)(19) and(24), 1026.15, and 1026.23. Section 1026.35(b)(1) also applies to a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a condominium if it is in fact used as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. But see § 1026.35(b)(2) for exemptions from the escrow requirement that may apply to such transactions.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp">
            <title>35(b)(1) Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Administration of escrow accounts.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> requires <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to establish an escrow account for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> before the <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Section 6 of RESPA, <ref target="USC:12-2605" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 2605</ref>, and Regulation X, <ref target="CFR:12-1024-17" reftype="external">12 CFR 1024.17</ref>, address how escrow accounts must be administered.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Optional insurance items.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> does not require that an escrow account be established for premiums for mortgage-related insurance that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not require in connection with the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> transaction, such as earthquake insurance or <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> life insurance, even if the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> voluntarily obtains such insurance.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Transactions not subject to § 1026.35(b)(1).</title>
              <content><ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> requires a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to establish an escrow account before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>. This requirement does not affect a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s ability, right, or obligation, pursuant to the terms of the legal obligation or applicable law, to offer or require an escrow account for a transaction that is not subject to § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-Interp">
            <title>35(b)(2) Exemptions.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-Interp">
              <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(i).</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                <title type="keyterm">Construction-permanent loans.</title>
                <content>Under § 1026.35(b)(2)(ii)(B), § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> does not apply to a transaction to finance the initial construction of a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref> may apply, however, to permanent financing that replaces a construction loan, whether the permanent financing is extended by the same or a different <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. When a construction loan may be permanently financed by the same <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, § <ref target="1026-17-c-6-ii" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)(ii)</ref> permits the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to give either one combined disclosure for both the construction financing and the permanent financing, or a separate set of disclosures for each of the two phases as though they were two separate transactions. See also comment <ref target="1026-17-c-6-Interp-2" reftype="internal">17(c)(6)-2</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-17-c-6-ii" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)(ii)</ref> addresses only how a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may elect to disclose a construction-permanent transaction. Which disclosure option a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects under § <ref target="1026-17-c-6-ii" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)(ii)</ref> does not affect the determination of whether the permanent phase of the transaction is subject to § <ref target="1026-35" reftype="internal">1026.35</ref>. When the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> discloses the two phases as separate transactions, the annual percentage rate for the permanent phase must be compared to the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> for a transaction that is comparable to the permanent financing to determine whether the transaction is a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> under § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. When the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> discloses the two phases as a single transaction, a single annual percentage rate, reflecting the appropriate charges from both phases, must be calculated for the transaction in accordance with § <ref target="1026-22-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.22(a)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-D" reftype="internal">appendix D</ref> to part 1026. This annual percentage rate must be compared to the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> for a transaction that is comparable to the permanent financing to determine the transaction is a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> under § <ref target="1026-35-a" reftype="internal">1026.35(a)</ref>. If the transaction is determined to be a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>, only the permanent phase is subject to the requirement of § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> to establish and maintain an escrow account, and the period for which the escrow account must remain in place under § <ref target="1026-35-b-3" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)</ref> is measured from the time the conversion to the permanent phase financing occurs.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp">
              <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(ii).</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                <title type="keyterm">Limited exemption.</title>
                <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is required to escrow for payment of property taxes for all first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> secured by condominium, planned unit development, or similar <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref> or units regardless of whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> escrows for insurance premiums for such <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref> or units.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
                <title type="keyterm">Planned unit developments.</title>
                <content>Planned unit developments (PUDs) are a form of property ownership often used in retirement communities, golf communities, and similar communities made up of homes located within a defined geographical area. PUDs usually have a homeowners' association or some other governing association, analogous to a condominium association and with similar authority and obligations. Thus, as with condominiums, PUDs often have master insurance policies that cover all units in the PUD. Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(ii)</ref>, if a PUD's governing association is obligated to maintain such a master insurance policy, an escrow account required by § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> for a transaction secured by a unit in the PUD need not include escrows for insurance. This exemption applies not only to condominiums and PUDs but also to any other type of property ownership arrangement that has a governing association with an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
                <title type="keyterm">More than one governing association associated with a dwelling.</title>
                <content><ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. The limited exemption provided pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(ii)</ref> applies to each master insurance policy for properties with multiple governing associations, to the extent each governing association has an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii">
              <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii).</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                <title type="keyterm">Requirements for exemption.</title>
                <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(v)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> is consummated:</content>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
                  <content>During the preceding calendar year, more than 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s total first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), on properties located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. Pursuant to that section, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> determines annually which counties in the United States are rural or underserved and publishes a list of those counties to enable <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to determine whether they meet this condition for the exemption. Thus, for example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> originated 90 first-lien covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), during 2013, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for an exemption in 2014 if at least 46 of those transactions are secured by first liens on properties that are located in counties that are on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s lists of rural or underserved counties for 2013.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
                  <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together originated 500 or fewer first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), during the preceding calendar year.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
                  <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> had total assets that are less than the asset threshold for the relevant calendar year. For calendar year 2013, the asset threshold is $2,000,000,000. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> that had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000 on December 31, 2012, satisfy this criterion for purposes of the exemption during 2013. This asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will publish notice of the asset threshold each year by amending this comment.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
                  <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> do not maintain an escrow account for any mortgage transaction being serviced by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> at the time the transaction is consummated, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>. Thus, the exemption applies, provided the other conditions of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> are satisfied, even if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> previously maintained escrow accounts for mortgage loans, provided it no longer maintains any such accounts except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>. Once a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> begins escrowing for loans currently serviced other than those addressed in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, however, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> become ineligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> on <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> they make while such escrowing continues. Thus, as long as a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) services and maintains escrow accounts for any mortgage loans, other than as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will not be eligible for the exemption for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> it may make. For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> “maintains” an escrow account only if it services a mortgage loan for which an escrow account has been established at least through the due date of the second periodic payment under the terms of the legal obligation.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-Interp">
                <content/>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1">
                  <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1).</title>
                  <content/>
                  <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                    <title type="keyterm">Exception for certain accounts.</title>
                    <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013, are not counted for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. On and after June 1, 2013, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, do not qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established between April 1, 2010, and June 1, 2013, still qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions consummated on or after June 1, 2013, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, and they otherwise qualify under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>.</content>
                  </interpParagraph>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2">
                  <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2).</title>
                  <content/>
                  <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                    <title type="keyterm">Exception for post-consummation escrow accounts for distressed consumers.</title>
                    <content><ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> escrow accounts for distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>. An escrow account established after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> for a distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> does not count for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. Distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> are <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are working with the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer to attempt to bring the loan into a current status through a modification, deferral, or other accommodation to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establishes escrow accounts after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as a regular business practice, regardless of whether <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> are in distress, does not qualify for the exception described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>.</content>
                  </interpParagraph>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iv">
              <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iv).</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                <title type="keyterm">Requirements for “rural” or “underserved” status.</title>
                <content>A county is considered to be “rural” or “underserved” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> if it satisfies either of the two tests in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> applies both tests to each county in the United States and, if a county satisfies either test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will include the county on a published list of “rural” or “underserved” counties for a particular calendar year. To facilitate compliance with § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> also creates a list of only those counties that are “rural” but not also “underserved.” The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will post on its public Web site the applicable lists for each calendar year by the end of that year. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor, pursuant to section 130(f) of the Truth in Lending Act, on the lists of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” or “underserved” for a particular calendar year. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s originations of covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), in such counties during that year are considered in determining whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the condition in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> and therefore will be eligible for the exemption during the following calendar year.</content>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
                  <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, a county is rural during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. These areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). Specifically, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> classifies a county as “rural” if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
                <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
                  <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, a county is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for that year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extend first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien five or more times in the county. These areas are defined by reference to the specific calendar year's HMDA data. Specifically, a county is “underserved” if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien covered transactions with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only covered transactions are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
                </interpParagraph>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-v-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-v">
              <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(v).</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
                <title type="keyterm">Forward commitments.</title>
                <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may make a mortgage loan that will be transferred or sold to a purchaser pursuant to an agreement that has been entered into at or before the time the loan is consummated. Such an agreement is sometimes known as a “forward commitment.” Even if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is otherwise eligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, a first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that will be acquired by a purchaser pursuant to a forward commitment is subject to the requirement to establish an escrow account under § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> unless the purchaser is also eligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> or the transaction is otherwise exempt under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)</ref>. The escrow requirement applies to any such transaction, whether the forward commitment provides for the purchase and sale of the specific transaction or for the purchase and sale of mortgage obligations with certain prescribed criteria that the transaction meets. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that qualifies for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> makes a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that meets the purchase criteria of an investor with which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has an agreement to sell such mortgage obligations after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. If the investor is ineligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, an escrow account must be established for the transaction before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> in accordance with § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> unless the transaction is otherwise exempt (such as a reverse mortgage or home equity line of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref>).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp">
            <title>35(b)(3) Cancellation.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Termination of underlying debt obligation.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)(i)</ref> provides that, in general, an escrow account required by § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> may not be cancelled until the underlying debt obligation is terminated or the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> requests cancellation at least five years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. Methods by which an underlying debt obligation may be terminated include, among other things, repayment, refinancing, rescission, and foreclosure.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Minimum durations.</title>
              <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-3" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)</ref> establishes minimum durations for which escrow accounts established pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> must be maintained. This requirement does not affect a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s right or obligation, pursuant to the terms of the legal obligation or applicable law, to offer or require an escrow account thereafter.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Less than eighty percent unpaid principal balance.</title>
              <content>The term “original value” in § <ref target="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A)</ref> means the lesser of the sales price reflected in the sales contract for the property, if any, or the appraised value of the property at the time the transaction was consummated. In determining whether the unpaid principal balance has reached less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer shall count any subordinate lien of which it has reason to know. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> certifies in writing that the equity in the property securing the underlying debt obligation is unencumbered by a subordinate lien, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer may rely upon the certification in making its determination unless it has actual knowledge to the contrary.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-Interp">
              <content/>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-i-Interp"/>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-1-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp">
        <title>35(b)(1) Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Administration of escrow accounts.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> requires <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to establish an escrow account for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> before the <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first lien on a principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. Section 6 of RESPA, <ref target="USC:12-2605" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 2605</ref>, and Regulation X, <ref target="CFR:12-1024-17" reftype="external">12 CFR 1024.17</ref>, address how escrow accounts must be administered.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Optional insurance items.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> does not require that an escrow account be established for premiums for mortgage-related insurance that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not require in connection with the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> transaction, such as earthquake insurance or <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> life insurance, even if the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> voluntarily obtains such insurance.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Transactions not subject to § 1026.35(b)(1).</title>
          <content><ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> requires a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to establish an escrow account before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>. This requirement does not affect a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s ability, right, or obligation, pursuant to the terms of the legal obligation or applicable law, to offer or require an escrow account for a transaction that is not subject to § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii">
        <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Requirements for exemption.</title>
          <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(v)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref>, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> is consummated:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>During the preceding calendar year, more than 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s total first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), on properties located in counties that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. Pursuant to that section, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> determines annually which counties in the United States are rural or underserved and publishes a list of those counties to enable <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to determine whether they meet this condition for the exemption. Thus, for example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> originated 90 first-lien covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), during 2013, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for an exemption in 2014 if at least 46 of those transactions are secured by first liens on properties that are located in counties that are on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s lists of rural or underserved counties for 2013.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together originated 500 or fewer first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), during the preceding calendar year.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> had total assets that are less than the asset threshold for the relevant calendar year. For calendar year 2013, the asset threshold is $2,000,000,000. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> that had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000 on December 31, 2012, satisfy this criterion for purposes of the exemption during 2013. This asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will publish notice of the asset threshold each year by amending this comment.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
            <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> do not maintain an escrow account for any mortgage transaction being serviced by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> at the time the transaction is consummated, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>. Thus, the exemption applies, provided the other conditions of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> are satisfied, even if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> previously maintained escrow accounts for mortgage loans, provided it no longer maintains any such accounts except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>. Once a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> begins escrowing for loans currently serviced other than those addressed in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, however, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> become ineligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> on <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> they make while such escrowing continues. Thus, as long as a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) services and maintains escrow accounts for any mortgage loans, other than as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will not be eligible for the exemption for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> it may make. For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> “maintains” an escrow account only if it services a mortgage loan for which an escrow account has been established at least through the due date of the second periodic payment under the terms of the legal obligation.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-Interp">
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1">
            <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Exception for certain accounts.</title>
              <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013, are not counted for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. On and after June 1, 2013, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, do not qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established between April 1, 2010, and June 1, 2013, still qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions consummated on or after June 1, 2013, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, and they otherwise qualify under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2">
            <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Exception for post-consummation escrow accounts for distressed consumers.</title>
              <content><ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> escrow accounts for distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>. An escrow account established after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> for a distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> does not count for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. Distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> are <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are working with the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer to attempt to bring the loan into a current status through a modification, deferral, or other accommodation to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establishes escrow accounts after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as a regular business practice, regardless of whether <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> are in distress, does not qualify for the exception described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> currently is not delinquent o<ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">r in defa</ref>ult on the underlying debt obligation.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-iv">
        <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iv).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Requirements for “rural” or “underserved” status.</title>
          <content>A county is considered to be “rural” or “underserved” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> if it satisfies either of the two tests in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> applies both tests to each county in the United States and, if a county satisfies either test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will include the county on a published list of “rural” or “underserved” counties for a particular calendar year. To facilitate compliance with § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> also creates a list of only those counties that are “rural” but not also “underserved.” The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will post on its public Web site the applicable lists for each calendar year by the end of that year. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor, pursuant to section 130(f) of the Truth in Lending Act, on the lists of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” or “underserved” for a particular calendar year. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s originations of covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), in such counties during that year are considered in determining whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the condition in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> and therefore will be eligible for the exemption during the following calendar year.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, a county is rural during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. These areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). Specifically, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> classifies a county as “rural” if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, a county is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for that year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extend first-lien covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien five or more times in the county. These areas are defined by reference to the specific calendar year's HMDA data. Specifically, a county is “underserved” if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien covered transactions with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only covered transactions are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Planned unit developments.</title>
        <content>Planned unit developments (PUDs) are a form of property ownership often used in retirement communities, golf communities, and similar communities made up of homes located within a defined geographical area. PUDs usually have a homeowners' association or some other governing association, analogous to a condominium association and with similar authority and obligations. Thus, as with condominiums, PUDs often have master insurance policies that cover all units in the PUD. Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(ii)</ref>, if a PUD's governing association is obligated to maintain such a master insurance policy, an escrow account required by § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> for a transaction secured by a unit in the PUD need not include escrows for insurance. This exemption applies not only to condominiums and PUDs but also to any other type of property ownership arrangement that has a governing association with an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title type="keyterm">More than one governing association associated with a dwelling.</title>
        <content><ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>. The limited exemption provided pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(ii)</ref> applies to each master insurance policy for properties with multiple governing associations, to the extent each governing association has an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-20">
      <section label="1026-20" sectionNum="20">
        <subject>§ 1026.20 Subsequent disclosure requirements.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Refinancings.</title>
          <content>A refinancing occurs when an existing obligation that was subject to this subpart is satisfied and replaced by a new obligation undertaken by the same <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. A refinancing is a new transaction requiring new disclosures to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. The new finance charge shall include any unearned portion of the old finance charge that is not credited to the existing obligation. The following shall not be treated as a refinancing:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>A renewal of a single payment obligation with no change in the original terms.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>A reduction in the annual percentage rate with a corresponding change in the payment schedule.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>An agreement involving a court proceeding.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>A change in the payment schedule or a change in collateral requirements as a result of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s default or delinquency, unless the rate is increased, or the new amount financed exceeds the unpaid balance plus earned finance charge and premiums for continuation of insurance of the types described in § <ref target="1026-4-d" reftype="internal">1026.4(d)</ref>.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-a-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The renewal of optional insurance purchased by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and added to an existing transaction, if disclosures relating to the initial purchase were provided as required by this subpart.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Assumptions.</title>
          <content>An assumption occurs when a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> expressly agrees in writing with a subsequent <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to accept that <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> as a primary obligor on an existing <ref target="1026-2-a-24" reftype="term">residential mortgage transaction</ref>. Before the assumption occurs, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall make new disclosures to the subsequent <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, based on the remaining obligation. If the finance charge originally imposed on the existing obligation was an add-on or discount finance charge, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> need only disclose:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The unpaid balance of the obligation assumed.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The total charges imposed by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> in connection with the assumption.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>The information required to be disclosed under § <ref target="1026-18-k" reftype="internal">1026.18(k)</ref>, <ref target="1026-18-l" reftype="internal">(l)</ref>, <ref target="1026-18-m" reftype="internal">(m)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-18-n" reftype="internal">(n)</ref>.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The annual percentage rate originally imposed on the obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-b-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The payment schedule under § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> and the total of payments under § <ref target="1026-18-h" reftype="internal">1026.18(h)</ref> based on the remaining obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-c" marker="(c)">
          <title type="keyterm">Variable-rate adjustments.</title>
          <content>Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-20-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> of this section, an adjustment to the interest rate with or without a corresponding adjustment to the payment in a variable-rate transaction subject to § <ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal">1026.19(b)</ref> is an event requiring new disclosures to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. At least once each year during which an interest rate adjustment is implemented without an accompanying payment change, and at least 25, but no more than 120, calendar days before a payment at a new level is due, the following disclosures, as applicable, must be delivered or placed in the mail:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The current and prior interest rates.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The index values upon which the current and prior interest rates are based.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>The extent to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has foregone any increase in the interest rate.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The contractual effects of the adjustment, including the payment due after the adjustment is made, and a statement of the loan balance.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-20-c-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>The payment, if different from that referred to in paragraph <ref target="1026-20-c-4" reftype="internal">(c)(4)</ref> of this section, that would be required to fully amortize the loan at the new interest rate over the remainder of the loan term.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-20-d" marker="(d)">
          <content>Information provided in accordance with variable-rate subsequent disclosure regulations of other Federal agencies may be substituted for the disclosure required by paragraph <ref target="1026-20-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title type="keyterm">Rate set.</title>
        <content>Additional guidance on determination of <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref>. The <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> has the same meaning in § 1026.35 as in Regulation C, 12 CFR part 1003. See 12 CFR 1003.4(a)(12)(ii). Guidance on the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> under § 1026.35(a)(2), such as when a transaction's rate is set and determination of the comparable transaction, is provided in the official commentary under Regulation C, the publication entitled “A Guide to HMDA Reporting: Getting it Right!”, and the relevant “Frequently Asked Questions” on Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) compliance posted on the FFIEC's Web site at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Comparable transaction.</title>
        <content><ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> table. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes on the Internet, in table form, <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rates</ref> for a wide variety of transaction types. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> calculates an annual percentage rate, consistent with Regulation Z (see § 1026.22 and appendix J), for each transaction type for which pricing terms are available from a survey. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> estimates annual percentage rates for other types of transactions for which direct survey data are not available based on the loan pricing terms available in the survey and other information. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes on the Internet the methodology it uses to arrive at these estimates.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-a-2-Interp-4"/>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19">
      <section label="1026-19" sectionNum="19">
        <subject>§ 1026.19 Certain mortgage and variable-rate transactions.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage transactions subject to RESPA</title>
          <content>—</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1" marker="(1)">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
              <title type="keyterm">Time of disclosures.</title>
              <content>In a mortgage transaction subject to the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (<ref target="USC:12-2601" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 2601</ref> et seq.) that is secured by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, other than a home equity line of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-40" reftype="internal">1026.40</ref> or mortgage transaction subject to paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-5" reftype="internal">(a)(5)</ref> of this section, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall make good faith estimates of the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref> and shall deliver or place them in the mail not later than the third business day after the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> receives the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s written application.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <title type="keyterm">Imposition of fees.</title>
              <content>Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-iii" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(iii)</ref> of this section, neither a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> nor any other <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> may impose a fee on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in connection with the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s application for a mortgage transaction subject to paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has received the disclosures required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section. If the disclosures are mailed to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is considered to have received them three <ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term">business days</ref> after they are mailed.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <title type="keyterm">Exception to fee restriction.</title>
              <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or other <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> may impose a fee for obtaining the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s credit history before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has received the disclosures required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section, provided the fee is bona fide and reasonable in amount.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2" marker="(2)">
            <title type="keyterm">Waiting periods for early disclosures and corrected disclosures.</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall deliver or place in the mail the good faith estimates required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section not later than the seventh <ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term">business day</ref> before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of the transaction.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>If the annual percentage rate disclosed under paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1-i" reftype="internal">(a)(1)(i)</ref> of this section becomes inaccurate, as defined in § <ref target="1026-22" reftype="internal">1026.22</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall provide corrected disclosures with all changed terms. The <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> must receive the corrected disclosures no later than three <ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term">business days</ref> before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. If the corrected disclosures are mailed to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or delivered to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> by means other than delivery in person, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is deemed to have received the corrected disclosures three <ref target="1026-2-a-6" reftype="term">business days</ref> after they are mailed or delivered.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-3" marker="(3)">
            <title type="keyterm">Consumer's waiver of waiting period before consummation.</title>
            <content><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">Consumer</ref><ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> determines that the extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> is needed to meet a bona fide personal financial emergency, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may modify or waive the seven-business-day waiting period or the three-business-day waiting period required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> of this section, after receiving the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref>. To modify or waive a waiting period, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> shall give the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> a dated written statement that describes the emergency, specifically modifies or waives the waiting period, and bears the signature of all the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> who are primarily liable on the legal obligation. Printed forms for this purpose are prohibited.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-4" marker="(4)">
            <title type="keyterm">Notice.</title>
            <content>Disclosures made pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> or paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> of this section shall contain the following statement: “You are not required to complete this agreement merely because you have received these disclosures or signed a loan application.” The disclosure required by this paragraph shall be grouped together with the disclosures required by paragraphs <ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> or <ref target="1026-19-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5" marker="(5)">
            <title type="keyterm">Timeshare plans.</title>
            <content>In a mortgage transaction subject to the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (<ref target="USC:12-2601" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 2601</ref> et seq.) that is secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s interest in a timeshare plan described in <ref target="USC:11-101" reftype="external">11 U.S.C. 101</ref>(53(D)):</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The requirements of paragraphs <ref target="1026-19-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> through <ref target="1026-19-a-4" reftype="internal">(a)(4)</ref> of this section do not apply;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall make good faith estimates of the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref> before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, or shall deliver or place them in the mail not later than three business days after the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> receives the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s written application, whichever is earlier; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-a-5-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>If the annual percentage rate at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> varies from the annual percentage rate disclosed under paragraph <ref target="1026-19-a-5-ii" reftype="internal">(a)(5)(ii)</ref> of this section by more than 1/8 of 1 percentage point in a regular transaction or more than 1/4 of 1 percentage point in an irregular transaction, as defined in § <ref target="1026-22" reftype="internal">1026.22</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall disclose all the changed terms no later than <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> or settlement.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Certain variable-rate transactions.</title>
          <content>Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-19-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> of this section, if the annual percentage rate may increase after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> in a transaction secured by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> with a term greater than one year, the following disclosures must be provided at the time an application form is provided or before the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> pays a non-refundable fee, whichever is earlier (except that the disclosures may be delivered or placed in the mail not later than three business days following receipt of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s application when the application reaches the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> by telephone, or through an intermediary agent or broker):</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The booklet titled <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> Handbook on Adjustable Rate Mortgages, or a suitable substitute.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>A loan program disclosure for each variable-rate program in which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> expresses an interest. The following disclosures, as applicable, shall be provided:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>The fact that the interest rate, payment, or term of the loan can change.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>The index or formula used in making adjustments, and a source of information about the index or formula.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>An explanation of how the interest rate and payment will be determined, including an explanation of how the index is adjusted, such as by the addition of a margin.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
              <content>A statement that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> should ask about the current margin value and current interest rate.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
              <content>The fact that the interest rate will be discounted, and a statement that the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> should ask about the amount of the interest rate discount.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-vi" marker="(vi)">
              <content>The frequency of interest rate and payment changes.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-vii" marker="(vii)">
              <content>Any rules relating to changes in the index, interest rate, payment amount, and outstanding loan balance including, for example, an explanation of interest rate or payment limitations, negative amortization, and interest rate carryover.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii" marker="(viii)">
              <content>At the option of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, either of the following:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>A historical example, based on a $10,000 loan amount, illustrating how payments and the loan balance would have been affected by interest rate changes implemented according to the terms of the loan program disclosure. The example shall reflect the most recent 15 years of index values. The example shall reflect all significant loan program terms, such as negative amortization, interest rate carryover, interest rate discounts, and interest rate and payment limitations, that would have been affected by the index movement during the period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-viii-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>The maximum interest rate and payment for a $10,000 loan originated at the initial interest rate (index value plus margin, adjusted by the amount of any discount or premium) in effect as of an identified month and year for the loan program disclosure assuming the maximum periodic increases in rates and payments under the program; and the initial interest rate and payment for that loan and a statement that the periodic payment may increase or decrease substantially depending on changes in the rate.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix" marker="(ix)">
              <content>An explanation of how the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may calculate the payments for the loan amount to be borrowed based on either:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>The most recent payment shown in the historical example in paragraph <ref target="1026-19-b-2-viii-A" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(viii)(A)</ref> of this section; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-ix-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>The initial interest rate used to calculate the maximum interest rate and payment in paragraph <ref target="1026-19-b-2-viii-B" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(viii)(B)</ref> of this section.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-x" marker="(x)">
              <content>The fact that the loan program contains a demand feature.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-xi" marker="(xi)">
              <content>The type of information that will be provided in notices of adjustments and the timing of such notices.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-19-b-2-xii" marker="(xii)">
              <content>A statement that disclosure forms are available for the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s other variable-rate loan programs.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-c" marker="(c)">
          <title type="keyterm">Electronic disclosures.</title>
          <content>For an application that is accessed by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in electronic form, the disclosures required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> of this section may be provided to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in electronic form on or with the application.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-d" marker="(d)">
          <content>Information provided in accordance with variable-rate regulations of other Federal agencies may be substituted for the disclosures required by paragraph <ref target="1026-19-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <content>Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(v)</ref> of this section, an escrow account need not be established for a transaction if, at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties designated either “rural” or “underserved” by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, as set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iv)</ref> of this section;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together originated 500 or fewer covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal">35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii</ref> for the current threshold); and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>Neither the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> nor its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section for any extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> secured by real property or a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> currently services, other than:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>Escrow accounts established after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as an accommodation to distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> to assist such <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-v-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-v-Interp" target="1026-35-b-2-v">
        <title>Paragraph 35(b)(2)(v).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Forward commitments.</title>
          <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may make a mortgage loan that will be transferred or sold to a purchaser pursuant to an agreement that has been entered into at or before the time the loan is consummated. Such an agreement is sometimes known as a “forward commitment.” Even if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is otherwise eligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, a first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that will be acquired by a purchaser pursuant to a forward commitment is subject to the requirement to establish an escrow account under § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> unless the purchaser is also eligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> or the transaction is otherwise exempt under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)</ref>. The escrow requirement applies to any such transaction, whether the forward commitment provides for the purchase and sale of the specific transaction or for the purchase and sale of mortgage obligations with certain prescribed criteria that the transaction meets. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that qualifies for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> makes a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that meets the purchase criteria of an investor with which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has an agreement to sell such mortgage obligations after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. If the investor is ineligible for the exemption in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, an escrow account must be established for the transaction before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> in accordance with § <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(1)</ref> unless the transaction is otherwise exempt (such as a reverse mortgage or home equity line of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref>).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35">
      <section label="1026-35" sectionNum="35">
        <subject>§ 1026.35 Requirements for higher-priced mortgage loans.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Higher-priced mortgage loans.</title>
          <content>Definitions. For purposes of this section:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>“<def term="higher-priced mortgage loan">Higher-priced mortgage loan</def>” means a closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref><ref target="1026-35-b-3-v" reftype="internal">it transa</ref>ction secured by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> with an annual percentage rate that exceeds the <ref target="1026-35-a-2" reftype="term">average prime offer rate</ref> for a comparable transaction as of the date the interest rate is set:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>By 1.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a first lien with a principal obligation at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> that does not exceed the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>By 2.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a first lien with a principal obligation at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> that exceeds the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's interest rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-a-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>By 3.5 or more percentage points for loans secured by a subordinate lien.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-a-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>“<def term="average prime offer rate">Average prime offer rate</def>” means an annual percentage rate that is derived from average interest rates, points, and other loan pricing terms currently offered to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> by a representative sample of <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> for mortgage transactions that have low-risk pricing characteristics. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes average prime offer rates for a broad range of types of transactions in a table updated at least weekly as well as the methodology the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> uses to derive these rates.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Rules for higher-priced mortgage loans.</title>
          <content>Escrow accounts—</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
            <content>Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(2) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may not extend a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first li<ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">en on a consu</ref><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> unless an escrow account is established before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, such as insurance against loss of or damage to property, or against liability arising out of the ownership or use of the property, or insurance protecting the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> against the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s default or other <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> loss. For purposes of this paragraph (b), the term “escrow account” has the same meaning as under Regulation X (24 CFR 3500.17(b)), as amended.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
            <content>Exemptions. Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(1) of this section:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i" marker="(i)">
              <content>An escrow account need not be established for:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>A transaction secured by shares in a cooperative;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>A transaction to finance the initial construction of a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
                <content>A temporary or “bridge” loan with a loan term of twelve months or less, such as a loan to purchase a new <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> where the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> plans to sell a current <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> within twelve months; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-i-D" marker="(D)">
                <content>A <ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term">reverse mortgage transaction</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-33-c" reftype="internal">1026.33(c)</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <content>Insurance premiums described in paragraph (b)(1) of this section need not be included in escrow accounts for loans secured by <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref> in condominiums, planned unit developments, or other common interest communities in which <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> ownership requires participation in a governing association, where the governing association has an obligation to the <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> owners to maintain a master policy insuring all <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwellings</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
              <content>Except as provided in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(v)</ref> of this section, an escrow account need not be established for a transaction if, at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties designated either “rural” or “underserved” by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, as set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iv)</ref> of this section;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>During the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together originated 500 or fewer covered transactions, as defined by § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
                <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal">35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii</ref> for the current threshold); and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
                <content>Neither the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> nor its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section for any extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> secured by real property or a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> currently services, other than:</content>
                <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
                  <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013; or</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
                  <content>Escrow accounts established after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as an accommodation to distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> to assist such <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
              <content>For purposes of paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> of this section:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>A county is “rural” during a calendar year if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “rural” for a particular calendar year.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>A county is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for that year, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extend covered transactions, as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien five or more times in the county. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may rely as a safe harbor on the list of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> to determine whether a county qualifies as “underserved” for a particular calendar year.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-v" marker="(v)">
              <content>Notwithstanding paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)</ref> of this section, an escrow account must be established pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section for any first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> that, at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, is subject to a commitment to be acquired by a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> that does not satisfy the conditions in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iii)</ref> of this section, unless otherwise exempted by this paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3" marker="(3)">
            <title type="keyterm">Escrows</title>
            <content>Cancellation—</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i" marker="(i)">
              <title type="keyterm">Failure to escrow for property taxes and insurance.</title>
              <content>General. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(3)(ii) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or s<ref target="1026-35-b-3-ii" reftype="internal">ervicer ma</ref>y cancel an escrow account required in paragraph (b)(1) of this section only upon the earlier of:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>Termination of the underlying debt obligation; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>Receipt no earlier than five years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s request to cancel the escrow account.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
              <title type="keyterm">Exemptions for loans secured by shares in a cooperative and for certain condominium units.</title>
              <content>Delayed cancellation. Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer shall not cancel an escrow account pursuant to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s request described in paragraph (b)(3)(i)(B) of this section unless the following conditions are satisfied:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
                <content>The unpaid principal balance is less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
                <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> currently is not delinquent o<ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">r in defa</ref>ult on the underlying debt obligation.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-c" marker="(c)">
          <content>[Reserved]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-d" marker="(d)">
          <title type="keyterm">Evasion; open-end credit.</title>
          <content><ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="term">open-end credit</ref>. In connection with <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that does not meet the definition of <ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="term">open-end credit</ref> in § <ref target="1026-2-a-20" reftype="internal">1026.2(a)(20)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> shall not structure a home-secured loan as an open-end plan to evade the requirements of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-v-Interp"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-2-ii-B"/>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1026-35-b-3-v"/>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Repayment ability.</title>
        <content>Requirement to escrow for property taxes and insurance. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(2) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may not extend a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> secured by a first li<ref target="1026-34-a-4" reftype="internal">en on a consu</ref><ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> unless an escrow account is established before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> for payment of property taxes and premiums for mortgage-related insurance required by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, such as insurance against loss of or damage to property, or against liability arising out of the ownership or use of the property, or insurance protecting the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> against the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s default or other <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> loss. For purposes of this paragraph (b), the term “escrow account” has the same meaning as under Regulation X (24 CFR 3500.17(b)), as amended.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-3">
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Escrows</title>
        <content>Cancellation—</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i" marker="(i)">
          <title type="keyterm">Failure to escrow for property taxes and insurance.</title>
          <content>General. Except as provided in paragraph (b)(3)(ii) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or s<ref target="1026-35-b-3-ii" reftype="internal">ervicer ma</ref>y cancel an escrow account required in paragraph (b)(1) of this section only upon the earlier of:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Termination of the underlying debt obligation; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Receipt no earlier than five years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s request to cancel the escrow account.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title type="keyterm">Exemptions for loans secured by shares in a cooperative and for certain condominium units.</title>
          <content>Delayed cancellation. Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or servicer shall not cancel an escrow account pursuant to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s request described in paragraph (b)(3)(i)(B) of this section unless the following conditions are satisfied:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The unpaid principal balance is less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-35-b-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> currently is not delinquent o<ref target="1026-35-b-3-i" reftype="internal">r in defa</ref>ult on the underlying debt obligation.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-51-a">
      <paragraph label="1026-51-a" marker="(a)">
        <title type="keyterm">General rule</title>
        <content>—</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1" marker="(1)">
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <title type="keyterm">Consideration of ability to pay.</title>
            <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must not open a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> account for a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> under an open-end (not home-secured) <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> plan, or increase any <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> limit applicable to such account, unless the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> considers the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum periodic payments under the terms of the account based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Reasonable policies and procedures.</title>
            <content><ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">Card issuers</ref> must establish and maintain reasonable written policies and procedures to consider the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s ability to make the required minimum payments under the terms of the account based on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s current obligations. Reasonable policies and procedures include treating any income and assets to which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> has a reasonable expectation of access as the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets, or limiting consideration of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s independent income and assets. Reasonable policies and procedures also include consideration of at least one of the following: The ratio of debt obligations to income; the ratio of debt obligations to assets; or the income the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> will have after paying debt obligations. It would be unreasonable for a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> not to review any information about a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s income or assets and current obligations, or to issue a <ref target="1026-2-a-15-i" reftype="term">credit card</ref> to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> who does not have any income or assets.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Minimum periodic payments</title>
          <content>—</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <title type="keyterm">Reasonable method.</title>
            <content>For purposes of paragraph <ref target="1026-51-a-1" reftype="internal">(a)(1)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must use a reasonable method for estimating the minimum periodic payments the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> would be required to pay under the terms of the account.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Safe harbor.</title>
            <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> complies with paragraph <ref target="1026-51-a-2-i" reftype="internal">(a)(2)(i)</ref> of this section if it estimates required minimum periodic payments using the following method:</content>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> assumes utilization, from the first day of the <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref>, of the full <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> line that the issuer is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> uses a minimum payment formula employed by the issuer for the product the issuer is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or, in the case of an existing account, the minimum payment formula that currently applies to that account, provided that:</content>
              <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes interest charges, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> estimates those charges using an interest rate that the issuer is considering offering to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for purchases or, in the case of an existing account, the interest rate that currently applies to purchases; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1026-51-a-2-ii-B-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>If the applicable minimum payment formula includes mandatory fees, the <ref target="1026-2-a-7" reftype="term">card issuer</ref> must assume that such fees have been charged to the account.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1026-20" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>Section 1026.20 Subsequent Disclosure Requirements</title>
      <analysisParagraph>In the 2011 Escrows Proposal, the Board proposed a new § 226.20(d) to implement the disclosure requirements of TILA sections 129D(j)(1)(B) and 129D(j)(2), as enacted by section 1462 of the Dodd-Frank Act. TILA section 129D(j)(1)(B) requires a creditor or servicer to provide the disclosures set forth in TILA section 129D(j)(2) when a consumer requests closure of an escrow account that was established in connection with a transaction secured by real property. Proposed § 226.20(d) would have directed the creditor or servicer to disclose the information about escrow accounts in accordance with certain format and timing requirements. As previously noted, the Bureau has delayed the implementation of certain disclosure requirements contained in title XIV of the Dodd-Frank Act, including those contained in sections 1461 and 1462. <em data-original="E-03">See</em> 77 FR 70105 (Nov. 23, 2012). Consequently, the Bureau will not be adopting a new § 1026.20(d) in this rule.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-19" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>Section 1026.19 Certain Mortgage and Variable-Rate Transactions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>In the 2011 Escrows Proposal, the Board proposed a new § 226.19(f) to implement the account disclosure requirements of TILA section 129D, as enacted by Sections 1461 and 1462 of the Dodd- Frank Act. Proposed § 226.19(f)<footnote ref="24">This section-by-section analysis discusses the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal by reference to the Board's Regulation Z, 12 CFR part 226, which the Board proposed to amend, and discusses this final rule by reference to the Bureau's Regulation Z, 12 CFR part 1026, which this final rule amends.</footnote> would have required disclosures for the establishment or non-establishment of an escrow account in connection with consummation of a transaction secured by a first lien, but not a subordinate lien. As discussed above, on November 23, 2012, the Bureau published in the <em data-original="E-04">Federal Register</em> a rule that delays the implementation of certain disclosure requirements contained in title XIV of the Dodd-Frank Act, including those contained in sections 1461 and 1462. <em data-original="E-03">See</em> 77 FR 70105 (Nov. 23, 2012). Consequently, the Bureau will not be adopting a new § 1026.19(f) in this rule.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-34-a-4-i" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>34(a)(4)(i) Mortgage-Related Obligations</title>
      <analysisParagraph>In the 2011 Escrows Proposal, the Board proposed amendments to the definition of mortgage-related obligations in § 226.34(a)(4)(i) and comment 34(a)(4)(i)-1, which contained cross-references to the definition of mortgage-related insurance in § 226.35(b)(3)(i). Because the Board proposed removing and reserving § 226.35(b)(3)(i) and preserving the substance of that provision in the proposed new § 226.45(b)(1), the Board made conforming amendments to § 226.34(a)(4)(i) and staff comment 34(a)(4)(i))-1 to reflect the new cross-reference. Section 1026.34(a)(4)(i) and staff comment 34(a)(4)(i)-1 are being amended under the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule to remove the cross-reference to § 1026.35(b)(3)(i). Consequently, the Bureau will not be adopting conforming amendments in this rule.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-a-1" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(a)(1)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As noted above, the Dodd-Frank Act substantially codified the Board's escrow requirement for higher-priced mortgage loans, but with certain differences. One of those differences is the higher threshold above the average prime offer rate established by the Dodd-Frank Act for determining when escrow accounts are required for transactions that exceed the maximum principal balance eligible for sale to Freddie Mac (“jumbo” transactions). In general, the coverage thresholds are 1.5 percentage points above the average prime offer rate for first-lien transactions and 3.5 percentage points above the average prime offer rate for subordinate-lien transactions. Under section 1461 of the Dodd-Frank Act, however, Congress established a new threshold of 2.5 percentage points above the average prime offer rate for “jumbo” transactions. Under an interim final rule published concurrently with the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal, the Board implemented this special coverage test for “jumbo” transactions by amending its existing escrow requirement for higher-priced mortgage loans in § 226.35(b)(3).See76 FR 11319 (Mar. 2, 2011) (the Board's 2011 “Jumbo” Final Rule).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Under the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal, proposed § 226.45(a)(1) would have provided that a higher-priced mortgage loan is a consumer credit transaction secured by the consumer's principal dwelling that exceeds the applicable pricing threshold as of the date the transaction's rate is set. The Board's proposed § 226.45(a)(1) incorporated the special, separate coverage threshold for “jumbo” transactions, as provided by the Dodd-Frank Act. In addition, as discussed above, the Board's proposed § 226.45(a)(1) would have based “higher-priced mortgage loan” status on a comparison of the transaction's“transaction coverage rate,” rather than its APR, to the average prime offer rate.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>A few commenters suggested that the proposed thresholds should be reconsidered. However, the Bureau believes the current thresholds capture the expansion intended by Congress and is therefore generally adopting proposed § 226.45(a)(1) as § 1026.35(a)(1). As discussed above, however, the Bureau is suspending consideration of the transaction coverage rate until it considers the proposed expansion of the definition of finance charge in connection with the TILA-RESPA Final Rule. Accordingly, the final rule continues to base the definition of higher-priced mortgage loans on a comparison of the transaction's APR to the average prime offer rate. The Bureau will consider comments received concerning the transaction coverage rate proposal in connection with the TILA-RESPA Final Rule. Comment 35(a)(1)-1 clarifies how to determine if a transaction is a higher-priced mortgage loan by comparing the annual percentage rate to the average prime offer rate. Comment 35(a)(1)-2 clarifies when the comparison between the annual percentage rate and the average prime offer rate should occur. Comment 35(a)(1)-3 clarifies how to determine whether a transaction is a higher-priced mortgage loan when the principal balance exceeds the limit in effect as of the date the transaction's rate is set for the maximum principal obligation eligible for purchase by Freddie Mac.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-a-2" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(a)(2)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is not altering current § 1026.35(a)(2), which defines the “average prime offer rate” as the annual percentage rate derived from average interest rates, points, and other transaction pricing terms currently offered to consumers by a representative sample of creditors for mortgage transactions that have low-risk pricing characteristics. The Bureau is, however, adding comment 35(a)(2)-3 to clarify that the average prime offer rate in § 1026.35 has the same meaning as in Regulation C, 12 CFR part 1003.See12 CFR 1003.4(a)(12)(ii).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-1" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(1)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As amended by the Dodd-Frank Act, TILA section 129D(a) contains the general requirement that an escrow account be established for any consumer credit transaction secured by a first lien on a consumer's principal dwelling. TILA section 129D(b), however, restricts that general requirement to four specified circumstances: (1) Where an escrow account is required by Federal or State law; (2) where the transaction is made, guaranteed, or insured by a State or Federal agency; (3) where the transaction's annual percentage rate exceeds the average prime offer rate by prescribed amounts; and (4) where an escrow account is “required pursuant to regulation.”</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(1) implemented only the third of the four circumstances, pursuant to TILA section 129D(b)(3), because the other three either are self-effectuating or are effectuated by other agencies' regulations. Nonetheless, the Bureau recognizes that those other three provisions may have implications for existing State and Federal credit programs, under which the applicable agencies may need to revise their own underlying guidelines to accommodate or otherwise reflect the statutory changes. Moreover, the Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(1) would have stated that, for purposes of § 226.45(b), “escrow account” has the same meaning as under Regulation X. This proposed provision paralleled existing § 226.35(b)(3)(iv).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>No comments were received on the scope and structure of § 226.45(b)(1). The Bureau is adopting the proposed language with certain technical changes as § 1026.35(b)(1).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2) Exemptions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Under existing regulations, certain categories of transactions are exempt from the escrow requirement. The Board proposed § 226.45(a)(3) and (b)(2)(i) and (ii) to reflect these provisions. The Board's proposed § 226.45(a)(3) would have provided that a “higher-priced mortgage loan” does not include a transaction to finance the initial construction of a dwelling, a temporary or “bridge” transaction with a term of twelve months or less, a reverse mortgage transaction, or a home equity line of credit. This provision is identical to existing § 1026.35(a)(3) (adopted as § 226.35(a)(3) in the 2008 HOEPA Final Rule), which provides that the term “higher-priced mortgage loan” does not include a transaction to finance the initial construction of a dwelling, a temporary or “bridge” transaction with a term of twelve months or less, a reverse mortgage transaction, or a home equity line of credit. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(i) would have provided that escrow accounts need not be established for transactions secured by shares in a cooperative. This provision would track existing § 1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A). It also is consistent with new TILA section 129D(e), as added by section 1461 of the Dodd-Frank Act.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In light of the way in which the Dodd-Frank Act has expanded on various elements of the 2008 HOEPA Final Rule, the Bureau believes that a more tailored approach is appropriate to specify what types of transactions are exempt from specific substantive requirements in Regulation Z. Accordingly, with the exception of home equity lines of credit (HELOCs), the Bureau is using its exemption authority under TILA section 129D<footnote ref="25">The Bureau may prescribe rules that revise, add to, or subtract from the criteria of section 129D(b) of TILA if the Bureau determines that such rules are in the interest of consumers and the public interest.See15 U.S.C. 1639d note. These exceptions are also justified by section 105(a) of TILA which provides that the Bureau in its regulations to carry out the purposes of TILA may provide for such adjustments and exceptions for all or any class of transactions that the Bureau judges are necessary or proper to effectuate the purposes of TILA, to prevent circumvention or evasion thereof, or to facilitate compliance therewith.See15 U.S.C. 1604(a).</footnote>
            to recodify the exemptions that were formerly located in § 1026.35(a)(3) and § 1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A) in the exemptions from coverage of the escrow requirement under new § 1026.35(b)(2). The separate exemption for HELOCs is no longer necessary because § 1026.35(a)(1) has been modified to apply only to closed-end consumer credit transactions.<footnote ref="26">The Bureau notes that open-end credit transactions are excluded from section 129D(a) of TILA under Dodd-Frank Act section 1461.See15 U.S.C. 1639d.</footnote>
            The Bureau believes that the use of its exemption authority is appropriate given the nature of the transactions at issue and would benefit consumers and industry alike. Given that reverse mortgages are unique transactions that are currently addressed by § 1026.33,<footnote ref="27">Reverse mortgages are also excluded from section 129D(a) of TILA under Dodd-Frank Act section 1461.See15 U.S.C. 1639d.</footnote>
            the Bureau believes it is in the interest of consumers and the public interest to pursue a course involving further review of § 1026.33 and to consider whether new or different protections would be appropriate for reverse mortgages at a later date.<footnote ref="28">See, e.g.,Consumer Financial Protection Bureau,Reverse Mortgages: Report to Congress(June 28, 2012) available at:http://files.consumerfinance.gov/a/assets/documents/201206_cfpb_Reverse_Mortgage_Report.pdf.</footnote>

            In addition, because of the nature of construction-only and bridge loan transactions, the Bureau believes that exempting these transactions is in the interest of consumers and the public interest. In both cases, the payments and amounts of property taxes and hazard insurance will depend on various time-sensitive factors for loan transactions that generally do not exist for more than one or two years, making maintainingan escrow account for a minimum of five years impractical. The recodification of the other exemptions from the escrows requirements is purely for organizational purposes and has no substantive effect. Exemptions from the new appraisal requirements are being finalized separately by the 2013 Interagency Appraisals Final Rule, in § 1026.35(c).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-i" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(i)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(i) would have provided that escrow accounts need not be established for transactions secured by shares in a cooperative, tracking the existing regulation, which is now located at § 1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A). The Bureau is adopting this proposal with certain conforming changes as § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(A). The Bureau is adopting the Board's proposed exemption for transactions to finance the initial construction of a dwelling as § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(B). The Bureau is adopting the Board's proposed exemption for “bridge” loan transactions as § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(C). Finally, the Bureau is adopting the Board's proposed exemption for reverse mortgage transactions as § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(D) with certain conforming changes. Comment 35(b)(2)(i)-1 clarifies the operation of the exemption for transactions to finance the initial construction of a dwelling under § 1026.35(b)(2)(i)(B) in relation to a construction-to-permanent mortgage transaction, noting that where a transaction is determined to be a higher-priced mortgage loan, only the permanent phase of the transaction is subject to § 1026.35.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-ii" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(ii)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As added by section 1461 of the Dodd- Frank Act, new TILA section 129D(e) codifies the current provision stating that escrow accounts that are established in connection with transactions secured by condominium units need not reserve funds to cover mortgage-related insurance, found in existing § 1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(B), and expands it to other, similar ownership arrangements involving governing associations that have an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(ii) would have provided that insurance premiums need not be included in escrow accounts for transactions secured by dwellings in condominiums, planned unit developments (PUDs), or similar arrangements in which ownership requires participation in a governing association, where the governing association has an obligation to the dwelling owners to maintain a master policy insuring all dwellings.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Several commenters suggested that even with this expanded definition other ownership structures might not be captured by the Board's proposed exemption. The Bureau is responding to these comments by revising the proposed language to adopt the umbrella term “common interest community,” which one commenter had suggested would be sufficiently broad to capture the various arrangements under which a governing association has an obligation to the dwelling owners to maintain a master policy insuring all dwellings. The Bureau is adopting the Board's proposed comment 45(b)(2)(ii)-1 as comment 35(b)(2)(ii)-1, which parallels existing comment 35(b)(3)(ii)(B)-1, but with conforming amendments to reflect the expanded scope of the exemption. The Bureau also is adopting the Board's proposed comment 45(b)(2)(ii)-2 as comment A22b)(2)(ii)-2 to provide details about the nature of PUDs and to clarify that the exemption is available for not only condominiums and PUDs but also any other type of property ownership arrangement that has a governing association with an obligation to maintain a master insurance policy. Following a request from one commenter, the Bureau additionally adds comment 35(b)(2)(ii)-3 to clarify that properties with multiple governing associations would also qualify for the limited exemption provided in § 1026.35(b)(2)(ii).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iii" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iii)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As adopted by Dodd-Frank Act section 1461, TILA section 129D(c) authorizes the Bureau to exempt from the higher-priced mortgage loan escrow requirement a creditor that: (1) Operates predominantly in rural or underserved areas; (2) together with all affiliates, has total annual mortgage loan originations that do not exceed a limit set by the Bureau; (3) retains its mortgage obligations in portfolio; and (4) meets any asset-size threshold and any other criteria as the Bureau may establish. As discussed above, Dodd-Frank Act section 1412 ability-to-repay provisions contain a similar set of criteria with regard to certain balloon-payment mortgages originated and held in portfolio by creditors that operate predominantly in rural or underserved areas. The statute authorizes the Bureau to issue regulations permitting certain balloon-payment mortgages issued by the specified creditors to receive a presumption of compliance with the ability-to-repay requirements as “qualified mortgages,” even though the general qualified mortgage criteria prohibit balloon-payment features. Specifically, in addition to having to meet certain transaction-specific features and underwriting requirements, balloon-payment qualified mortgages may be made only by a creditor that: (1) Operates predominantly in rural or underserved areas; (2) together with all affiliates, has total annual residential mortgage transaction originations that do not exceed a limit set by the Bureau; (3) retains the balloon-payment mortgages in portfolio; and (4) meets any asset-size threshold and any other criteria as the Bureau may establish.SeeTILA section 129C(b)(2)(E), 15 U.S.C. 1639c(b)(2)(E).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board interpreted the two provisions as serving similar but not identical purposes, and thus varied certain aspects of the proposals to implement the balloon qualified mortgage and escrow provisions. Specifically, the Board interpreted the escrow provision as being designed to exempt creditors that do not possess economies of scale to offset cost-effectively the burden of establishing escrow accounts by maintaining a certain minimum portfolio size from being required to establish escrow accounts on higher-priced mortgage loans, and the balloon-payment qualified mortgage provision to ensure access to credit in rural and underserved areas where consumers may be able to obtain credit only from community banks offering balloon-payment mortgages. Accordingly, the two Board proposals would have used similar definitions of “rural” and “underserved,” but did not provide uniformity in calculating and defining various other elements. Specifically, the Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(iii) would have implemented the escrow exemption in TILA section 129D(c) by requiring that the creditor have (1) in the prior year made more than 50 percent of its first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans in rural or underserved areas, (2) together with all affiliates, originated and retained servicing rights to no more than 100 first-lien mortgage obligations in either the current or prior calendar year, and (3) together with all affiliates, not maintained an escrow account on any consumer credit transaction secured by real property or a dwelling that is currently serviced by the creditor or its affiliates. The Board also sought comment on whether to add a requirement for the creditor to meet an asset-size limit and what that size should be.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In contrast, the Board's proposal for balloon qualified mortgages would have required that the creditor (1) in thepreceding calendar year, have made more than 50 percent of its balloon-payment mortgages in rural or underserved areas; and (2) have assets that did not exceed $2 billion. The Board proposed two alternatives for qualifications relating to (1) the total annual originations limit; and (2) the retention of balloon-payment mortgages in portfolio.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In both cases, the Board proposed to use a narrow definition of rural based on the Economic Research Service (ERS) of the United States Department of Agriculture's (USDA) “urban influence codes” (UICs). The UICs are based on the definitions of “metropolitan” and “micropolitan” as developed by the Office of Management and Budget, along with other factors reviewed by the ERS that place counties into twelve separately defined UICs depending on the size of the largest city and town in the county. The Board's proposal would have limited the definition of rural to certain “non-core” counties, which are areas outside of any metropolitan or micropolitan area, excluding those adjacent to a metropolitan area of at least one million residents or adjacent to a micropolitan area with a town of at least 2,500 residents. This definition corresponded with UICs of 7, 10, 11, and 12, which would have covered areas in which only 2.3 percent of the nation's population lives.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In light of the overlap in criteria between the escrow exemption and balloon qualified mortgage provisions, the Bureau considered comments responding to both proposals in determining how to finalize the particular elements of each rule as discussed further below. With regard to exercising the Bureau's authority to create an escrows exemption in general, the bulk of the comments received asserted that the Bureau should exercise such authority but that the scope of the proposal was too limited and would lead to reduced access to credit or increased costs for consumers in rural areas because of increased compliance costs for creditors. Two industry commenters suggested a blanket exemption for community banks, but did not identify any criteria to define a community bank. Five industry commenters suggested the exemption should be based solely on loan-to-value ratio of the transaction being originated, ranging from 50 percent to 80 percent, without using any of the statutory requirements. Four trade association commenters suggested that the exemption should be based solely on whether the debt obligation was being kept in the creditor's portfolio. One consumer advocacy group stated that the exemption was too broad because, under its reading of section 1461 of the Dodd-Frank Act, the exemption was not meant to protect access to credit but, rather, to protect communities that need credit but cannot find credit with terms better than the terms of higher-priced mortgage loans.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes that escrows generally provide meaningful consumer protections, as consumers may not incorporate recurring costs related to the ownership of a dwelling to their monthly mortgage payments to anticipate the total costs associated with the dwelling. For consumers who struggle with their monthly mortgage payments, there is a higher probability of foreclosure as a result. Based on recent research,<footnote ref="29">Nathan B. Anderson and Jane B. Dokko,Liquidity Problems and Early Payment Default Among Subprime Mortgages,Finance and Economics Discussion Series, Federal Reserve Board (2011), available at:http://www.federalreserve.gov/pubs/feds/2011/201109/201109pap.pdf.</footnote>
            consumers that do not have an escrow account in the first year after consummation result in 0.35 percent more foreclosures per year for first-lien, higher-priced mortgages. However, in rural and underserved areas where there are fewer creditors that may be willing to extend higher-priced mortgage loans, the number of providers could be further reduced when additional costs associated with establishing and maintaining escrow accounts are taken into account. The reduction in the number of providers could lead to some consumers being unable to obtain higher-priced mortgage loans, or to increase the costs of the higher-priced mortgage loans as a result of a concentrated market with limited competition to a point where the consumer would be unable to repay the higher-priced mortgage loan.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>There are also substantial data suggesting that the small portfolio creditors that are most likely to have difficulty maintaining escrow accounts (or to rely on balloon loan transactions to manage their interest rate risks) have a significantly better track record than larger creditors with regard to the performance of their mortgage transactions. As discussed in more depth in the 2013 ATR Concurrent Proposal, because small portfolio creditors retain a higher percentage of their transactions on their own books, they have strong incentives to engage in thorough underwriting. To minimize performance risk, small community creditors have developed underwriting standards that differ from those employed by larger institutions. Small creditors generally engage in “relationship banking,” in which underwriting decisions rely at least in part on qualitative information gained from personal relationships between creditors and consumers. This qualitative information focuses on subjective factors such as consumer character and reliability which “may be difficult to quantify, verify, and communicate through the normal transmission channels of banking organization.”<footnote ref="30">SeeAllen N. Berger and Gregory F. Udell,Small Business Credit Availability and Relationship Lending: The Importance of Bank Organizational Structure,Economic Journal (2002).</footnote>
            While it is not possible to disaggregate the impact of each of the elements of the community banking model, the combined effect is highly beneficial. Moreover, where consumers have trouble paying their mortgage obligations, small portfolio creditors have stronger incentives to work with the consumers to get them back on track, to protect both the creditors' balance sheets and their reputations in their local communities. Market-wide data demonstrate that mortgage delinquency and charge-off rates are significantly lower at smaller banks than at larger banks.<footnote ref="31">See2013 ATR Concurrent Proposal; FDIC, Community Banking Study, December 2012, available at:http://www.fdic.gov/regulations/resources/cbi/report/cbi-full.pdf.</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes that Congress carefully weighed these considerations in authorizing the Bureau to establish an exemption in TILA section 129D(c) to ensure access to credit in rural and underserved areas where consumers may be able to obtain credit only from community banks that cannot maintain escrow accounts on a cost-effective basis. Thus, the Bureau concludes that exercising its authority is appropriate, but also that the exemption should implement the statutory criteria to ensure it effectuates Congress's intent. Accordingly, as discussed in more detail below, the Bureau is adopting § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) largely as proposed, but with certain changes described below, to implement TILA section 129D(c).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In particular, the Bureau has concluded that it is appropriate to make the specific creditor qualifications much more consistent between the balloon-payment qualified mortgage and escrow exemptions than originally proposed by the Board.<footnote ref="32">The Bureau has similarly attempted to maintain consistency between the asset-size limit, annual originations threshold, and requirements concerning portfolio transactions as between the final rules that it is adopting with regard to balloon qualified mortgages and the escrow exemption and its separate proposal to create a new type of qualified mortgage originated and held by smallportfolio creditors. The Bureau is seeking comment in that proposal on these elements and on whether other adjustments are appropriate to the existing rules to maintain continuity and reduce compliance burden.Seethe 2013 ATR Concurrent Proposal.</footnote>
            The Bureau believes thatthis approach is justified by several considerations, including the very similar statutory language, the similar congressional intents underlying the two provisions, and the fact that requiring small creditors operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas to track overlapping but not identical sets of technical criteria for each separate provision could create unwarranted compliance burden that itself would frustrate the intent of the statutes. Although the Bureau has recast and loosened some of the criteria to promote consistency, the Bureau has carefully calibrated the changes to further the purpose of each rulemaking. Further, the Bureau believes that any risk to consumers from the modifications is minimal given the nature of the small creditors' operations and in particular the fact that they are required to hold the affected transactions in portfolio (in this final rule's case, indirectly, by virtue of the requirement that a transaction originated under the escrow exemption not be subject to a forward commitment at consummation). As discussed in more detail below and in the 2013 ATR Concurrent Proposal, which also proposes to adopt several of the criteria to define a new type of qualified mortgage, the creditors at issue have strong motivations to provide vigorous underwriting and high levels of customer service to protect their balance sheets and reputations in their local communities. This motivation is manifest in the fact that they have demonstrably lower credit losses on their mortgage originations than larger institutions.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>For the foregoing reasons, the Bureau is adopting § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) to implement TILA section 129D(c) by providing that a transaction is exempt from the escrow account requirement otherwise applicable to a higher-priced mortgage loan if the creditor: (1) In the preceding calendar year made more than 50 percent of its first-lien covered transactions in counties designated by the Bureau as “rural” or “underserved”; (2) together with all affiliates extended 500 or fewer first-lien covered transactions in the preceding calendar year; and (3) has total assets that are less than $2 billion, adjusted annually for inflation. The final rule also creates greater parallelism with the balloon qualified mortgage provision with regard to the requirement that the affected transactions be held in portfolio by requiring in both rules that the transactions not be subject to a “forward commitment” agreement at the time of consummation. These qualifications and the other requirements under the final rule are discussed in more detail below.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>“Operates Predominantly in Rural or Underserved Areas”</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Under TILA section 129D(c)(1), to qualify for the exemption, a creditor must “operate predominantly in rural or underserved areas.” The Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal would have required a creditor to have made during the preceding calendar year more than 50 percent of its first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans in “rural or underserved” counties. One industry commenter agreed with the Board's proposal. Numerous commenters to the Board's proposal in this rule and the Board's 2011 ATR Proposal objected to the proposed definition of “rural or undeserved” as discussed below, but commenters did not generally dispute the definition of “predominantly” as meaning more than 50 percent of originations of its first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans in rural or underserved counties.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes Congress enacted the exemption in TILA section 129D(c)(1) to ensure access to credit in rural and underserved areas where consumers may be able to obtain credit only from community banks or other small creditors serving those areas. The “operates predominantly in” requirement serves to limit the exemption to these institutions. To remove this portion of the qualifications of the creditor would be to circumvent Congress's stated requirement that the exemption was intended for creditors operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas. The Bureau believes that “predominantly” indicates a portion greater than half, hence the regulatory requirement of more than 50 percent.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Upon further analysis of the differences in the proposals for the escrows exemption and the balloon-payment qualified mortgage provisions, however, the Bureau believes that further harmonization between the two sets of requirements is warranted. The Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal would have required creditors to track first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans by county, while the qualified mortgage proposal would have required creditors to track balloon-payment mortgages. Given that the underlying statutory language regarding “operates predominantly” is the same in each instance and that tracking each type of mortgage separately would increase administrative burden, the Bureau believes it is appropriate to base the threshold for both rules on the distribution of all first-lien “covered transactions” as defined in § 1026.43(b)(1). As provided in the 2013 ATR Final Rule, a covered transaction is defined in § 1026.43(b)(1) as a consumer credit transaction that is secured by a dwelling, as defined in § 1026.2(a)(19), other than a transaction exempt from coverage under § 1026.43(a). The Bureau believes that counting only first-lien transactions will facilitate compliance, as well as promote consistency in applying to creditors the two exemptions under both rulemakings, since both exemptions relate to first-lien transactions. Balloon-payment mortgages that will meet the qualifications of the balloon-payment qualified mortgage exemption will be first-lien covered transactions, as having subordinate financing along with the balloon-payment mortgage would be rare since it further constrains a consumers' ability to build equity in the property and to refinance the balloon-payment mortgage when it becomes due. Subordinate-lien, higher-priced mortgage loans are not required to establish escrow accounts, as only first-lien higher priced mortgage loans must establish escrow accounts under § 1026.35(b)(1).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) provides that, during the preceding calendar year, a creditor must have made more than 50 percent of its total first-lien covered transactions in counties designated “rural” or “underserved” as defined by § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv), discussed below. Comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.i states that the Bureau publishes annually a list of counties that qualify as rural or underserved.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Total Annual Mortgage Originations</title>
        <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129D(c)(3) provides that, to qualify for the exemption, a creditor together with its affiliates must have total annual mortgage originations that do not exceed a limit set by the Bureau. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(iii)(B) required that the creditor and its affiliates, during either of the preceding two calendar years, have originated and retained servicing rights to 100 or fewer mortgage obligations secured by a first lien on real property or a dwelling. Although the Dodd-Frank Act requirement to establish escrow accounts applies onlyto higher-priced mortgage loans that are secured by first liens, the Board reasoned that it was appropriate to base the threshold on all first-lien originations because creditors are free to establish escrow accounts for all of their first-lien mortgages voluntarily to achieve the scale necessary to escrow cost-effectively. The Board estimated that a minimum servicing portfolio size of 500 is necessary to escrow cost-effectively, and assumed that the average life expectancy of a mortgage loan is about five years. Based on this reasoning, the Board believed that creditors would no longer need the benefit of the exemption if they originated and serviced more than 100 first-lien transactions per year. In contrast, the Board did not propose a specific annual originations threshold in connection with the balloon-payment qualified mortgages, but rather sought comment on whether to adopt a threshold based on the number of transactions or dollar volume and what numeric threshold would be appropriate.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In connection with the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal, trade association and industry commenters generally said that the proposed maximum annual volume of originations would be insufficient to make the escrow accounts cost effective for creditors. No commenters provided information to support their suggestions for alternative thresholds or to refute the Board's analysis that creditors can provide escrow accounts cost-effectively when they annually originate and retain servicing rights to more than 100 mortgage obligations secured by a first lien on real property or a dwelling. Suggestions for higher thresholds ranged from 200 to 1,000 mortgage obligations per year originated and serviced. One consumer advocacy commenter suggested the proposed threshold was too high because it counted only first-lien mortgage transactions, instead of all mortgage obligations, but offered no specific alternative amount. Two industry commenters also suggested that the origination limit should measure only the number of higher-priced mortgage loans originated and serviced by the creditor and its affiliates.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In response to the Board's 2011 ATR Proposal, two trade associations and one group of State bank regulators, argued that other criteria, such as the asset-size limit or portfolio requirement, were sufficient and that neither a volume nor a total annual originations limit would be necessary. One industry trade association suggested combining the proposed alternatives and permitting creditors to elect under which limit they would operate. Other trade group and industry commenters indicated that the total annual originations limit would be preferable because of the varying dollar amount of transactions originated, which would constrain the number of consumers with limited credit options who could obtain balloon-payment mortgages in rural or underserved areas. Four trade group and industry commenters suggested a range for the total annual originations limit of 250 to 1,000 transactions.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes that the requirement of TILA section 129D(c)(2) reflects a recognition that larger creditors have the systems capability and operational scale to establish cost-efficient escrow accounts. Similarly, the Bureau believes the requirement of TILA section 129C(b)(2)(E)(iv)(II) reflects Congress's recognition that larger creditors who operate in rural or underserved areas should be able to make credit available without resorting to balloon-payment mortgages. In light of the strong concerns expressed in both rulemakings about the potential negative impacts on small creditors in rural and underserved areas, the Bureau conducted further analysis to try to determine the most appropriate thresholds, although it was significantly constrained by the fact that data are limited with regard to mortgage originations in rural and underserved areas generally and in particular with regard to originations of balloon-payment mortgages.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau started with the premise that it would be preferable to use the same annual originations threshold in both rules to reflect the consistent language in both statutory provisions focusing on total annual mortgage loan originations, to facilitate compliance by not requiring institutions to track multiple metrics and to promote consistent application of the two exemptions. This approach requires significant reconciliation between the two proposals, however, because the escrows proposal focused specifically on transactions originated and serviced to gauge creditors' ability to maintain escrow accounts over time, while retention of servicing is not directly relevant to the balloon-payment qualified mortgage. However, to the extent that creditors chose to offer balloon-payment mortgages to manage their interest rate risk without having to undertake the compliance burdens involved in administering adjustable rate mortgages over time, the Bureau believes that both provisions are focused in a broad sense on accommodating creditors whose systems constraints might otherwise cause them to exit the market.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>With this in mind, the Bureau ultimately decided to adopt a threshold of 500 or fewer annual originations of first-lien transactions for both rules. The Bureau believes that this threshold will provide greater flexibility and reduce concerns that the specific threshold that had been proposed in the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal (100 higher-priced mortgage loans originated and serviced annually in either of the preceding two years) would reduce access to credit by excluding creditors that need special accommodations in light of their capacity constraints. At the same time, the increase is not as dramatic as it may first appear because the Bureau's analysis of HMDA data suggests that even small creditors are likely to sell a significant number of their originations in the secondary market. Assuming that most mortgage transactions that are retained in portfolio are also serviced in house, the Bureau estimates that a creditor originating no more than 500 first-lien transactions per year would maintain and service a portfolio of about 670 mortgage obligations over time, assuming an average obligation life expectancy of five years.<footnote ref="33">A review of 2011 HMDA data shows creditors that otherwise meet the criteria of § 1026.43(f)(1)(vi) and originate between 200 and 500 or fewer first-lien covered transactions per year average 134 transactions per year retained in portfolio. Over a five year period, the total portfolio for these creditors would average 670 mortgage obligations.</footnote>
          Thus, the higher threshold will help to ensure that creditors that are subject to the escrow requirement do in fact maintain portfolios of sufficient size to maintain the escrow accounts on a cost efficient basis over time, in the event that the Board's estimate of a minimum portfolio of 500 transactions was too low. However, the Bureau believes that the 500 annual originations threshold in combination with the other requirements will still ensure that the balloon-payment qualified mortgage and escrow exemptions are available only to small creditors that focus primarily on a relationship-lending model and face significant systems constraints.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also believes that it is appropriate to focus the annual originations threshold on all first-lien originations. Given that escrow accounts are typically not maintained for transactions secured by subordinate liens, the Bureau does not believe that it makes sense to count such transactions toward the threshold because they would not contribute to a creditor's ability to achieve cost-efficiency. At the same time, the Bureau believes it is appropriate to count allfirst-lien transactions toward the threshold because creditors can voluntarily establish escrow accounts for such transactions to increase the cost-effectiveness of their program even though the mandatory account requirements under the Dodd-Frank Act apply only to first-lien, higher-priced mortgage loans. Focusing on all first-lien originations also provides a metric that is useful for gauging the relative scale of creditors' operations for purposes of the balloon-payment qualified mortgages, while focusing solely on the number of higher-priced mortgage loan originations would not. Accordingly, the Bureau adopts § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B) requiring to creditor and its affiliates to have originated 500 or fewer covered transactions secured by a first lien.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Asset-Size Threshold</title>
        <analysisParagraph>TILA section 129D(c)(4) provides that, to qualify for the exemption, a creditor must meet any asset-size threshold established by the Bureau. The Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal did not establish an asset-size threshold but did request comment on whether one should be added and, if so, what threshold level would be appropriate. In contrast, the Board proposed a $2 billion threshold for the balloon qualified mortgage exception. This number was based on the limited data available to the Board at the time of the proposal. Based on that limited information, the Board reasoned that none of the entities it identified as operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas had total assets as of the end of 2009 greater than $2 billion, and therefore, the limitation should be set at $2 billion. The Board expressly proposed setting the asset-size threshold at the highest level currently held by any of the institutions that appear to be smaller institutions that served areas with otherwise limited credit options.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In response to the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal, a group of State bank regulators and a trade association advocated including an asset-size prerequisite in the exemption. The group of State bank regulators suggested that the asset-size prerequisite be the sole requirement to obtain the exemption but did not propose a specific dollar threshold. The industry commenter suggested the asset-size be $1 billion in assets, but did not provide a rationale for the amount.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Based on the Board's 2011 ATR Proposal, one group of State bank regulators suggested that the asset-size threshold be included and be the only requirement for a creditor to qualify for the balloon-mortgage qualified mortgage exemption. Two trade association commenters suggested that a $2 billion asset-size threshold was appropriate, with one also suggesting that the asset-size threshold be the only requirement for a creditor to qualify for the balloon-payment qualified mortgage exemption. One industry commenter suggested that the asset-size threshold be $10 billion.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>For reasons discussed above, the Bureau is adopting an annual originations limit as contemplated by the statute. Given that limitation, restricting the asset size of institutions that can claim the exemption is of limited importance. Nonetheless, the Bureau believes that an asset-size limitation is still helpful because very large institutions should have sufficient resources to adapt their systems to make mortgages without a balloon payment and to establish and maintain escrow accounts even if the scale of their mortgage operations is relatively modest. A very large institution with a relatively modest mortgage operation also does not have the same type of reputational and balance-sheet incentives to maintain the same kind of relationship-banking model as a smaller community-based creditor. An asset-size limitation can guard against circumvention of the rule if a larger institution were to elect to enter a rural area to make a limited number of higher-priced mortgage loans or balloon-payment mortgages. Therefore, the Bureau believes that the $2 billion asset limitation proposed by the Board in the Board's 2011 ATR Proposal remains an appropriate limitation and should be adopted in both this final rule and the 2013 ATR Final Rule.<footnote ref="34">The $2 billion threshold reflects the purposes of the exemption and the structure of the mortgage servicing industry. The Bureau's choice of $2 billion in assets as a threshold for purposes of TILA section 129D(c)(4) does not imply that a threshold of that type or of that magnitude would be an appropriate way to distinguish small firms for other purposes or in other industries.</footnote>

        </analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the Bureau adopts § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C) to require creditors to have total assets as of the end of the preceding calendar year that are less than $2 billion and is effectively adopting the same threshold by cross-reference to § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) for purposes of the balloon-payment qualified mortgage exemption in the 2013 ATR Final Rule. As provided in § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C), this threshold dollar amount will adjust automatically each year based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers (CPI-W), not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars. Comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii recites this initial threshold and further clarifies that a creditor that had total assets below the threshold on December 31 of the preceding year satisfies this criterion for purposes of the exemption during the current calendar year. The comment also notes that the Bureau will publish notice of each year's asset threshold by amending the comment.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Creditor and Affiliates Do Not Maintain Escrows</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As adopted by section 1461 of the Dodd-Frank Act, TILA section 129D(c)(4) provides that, to qualify for the exemption, a creditor must meet any other criteria established by the Bureau consistent with the provisions of TILA. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(iii)(C) would have required that, to obtain the exemption, the creditor and its affiliates not maintain an escrow account for any mortgage they currently service through at least such mortgage obligation's second installment due date. The Board used the second installment due date as a cutoff point because it recognized that a creditor may sometimes hold a mortgage obligation for a short period after consummation to take steps necessary before transferring and assigning the mortgage debt obligation to the intended investor. The Board recognized that the process of transferring and assigning the mortgage obligation could extend beyond the mortgage obligation's first payment due date, especially when the first payment is due shortly after consummation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Board believed this additional condition was necessary to effectuate the purpose of the exemption. The Board reasoned that, if a creditor already establishes and maintains escrow accounts, it has the capacity to escrow and therefore has no need for the exemption. Moreover, the Board concluded that a creditor's capacity to escrow should reflect not only its own activities but those of any affiliate because it assumed that a creditor could rely on its affiliate to help meet the escrow requirement. The Board sought comment, however, on three aspects: first, whether affiliates' capacities to escrow should be considered; second, whether the second payment due date is the appropriate cutoff point for whether a creditor has established an escrow account for purposes of the exemption; and third, whether the proposal should allow somede minimisnumber ofmortgage obligations for which escrows are maintained and, if so, what that number should be.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Six trade association commenters, five industry commenters and a Federal agency submitted comments noting that many creditors had only begun to establish escrow accounts for mortgage transactions after the Board adopted the 2008 HOEPA Final Rule, which took effect for most transactions in April 2010. Many of the same commenters argued that it would be unfair to deny the exemption in TILA section 129D(c) to those creditors that established escrow accounts only to comply with the current escrow requirements. Two trade association commenters and one industry commenter suggested ade minimisnumber of mortgage obligations ranging from 10 to 50 mortgage obligations to address the exclusion of creditors currently escrowing that would otherwise qualify for the exemption. In addition, one industry commenter suggested that a creditor that establishes escrow accounts for distressed mortgage obligations should still be eligible for the exemption, as these creditors are doing so as an accommodation to the consumer to attempt to avoid foreclosure. No comments were received as to whether the second payment due date is the appropriate cutoff point for whether a creditor has established an escrow account for purposes of the exemption.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting the Board's proposal in § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D), with the addition of two exceptions based on comments received. The Bureau agrees with the Board generally that creditors that currently provide escrow accounts can afford to establish and maintain escrow accounts for higher-priced mortgage loans. Thus, to qualify for the exemption, a creditor and its affiliates must not maintain escrow accounts for any extensions of consumer credit secured by real property or a dwelling that the creditor, or its affiliates, currently services through at least the second installment due date. However, the Bureau agrees with commenters that those creditors that would otherwise qualify for the exemption but for their compliance with the current regulation, and creditors that establish escrow accounts as an accommodation to distressed consumers, should still be able to qualify for the exemption in TILA section 129D(c). In particular, the Bureau notes that Congress's decision to codify and expand upon the escrow requirement from the 2008 HOEPA Final Rule while simultaneously providing authority to exempt certain mortgage transactions by creditors operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas suggests that Congress intended to provide relief to creditors that were struggling to meet the existing requirements. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1) and (2) to provide exceptions to the exemption's general prerequisite that a creditor and its affiliates not maintain an escrow account.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iv clarifies that the limitation excluding creditors and their affiliates who currently maintain escrow accounts for other mortgage obligations they service applies only to mortgage obligations serviced at the time a transaction purporting to invoke the escrows exemption is consummated. Thus, the exemption still could apply even if the creditor or its affiliates previously established and maintained escrows for mortgage obligations it no longer services. However, if a creditor or an affiliate escrows for mortgage obligations currently serviced, those institutions are ineligible to invoke the escrows exemption until the escrow accounts are no longer maintained. The comment also clarifies that a creditor or its affiliate “maintains” an escrow account for a mortgage obligation only if it services the mortgage obligation at least through the due date of the second periodic payment under the terms of the legal obligation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Comment 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1)-1 clarifies that escrow accounts created by a creditor and its affiliates established between April 1, 2010, and June 1, 2013 are not counted for purposes of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D). In addition, the comment clarifies that creditors that continue to maintain escrow accounts that were established between April 1, 2010, and June 1, 2013 until the termination of those escrow accounts will still qualify for the exemption, so long as they or their affiliates do not establish escrow accounts for other mortgage obligations that the creditor and its affiliates service after June 1, 2013 and they otherwise qualify under § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii). Comment 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)-1 clarifies that escrow accounts established after consummation for distressed consumers are not considered to be maintaining escrow accounts for purposes of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D), although creditors that establish escrow accounts after consummation as a regular business practice are considered to be maintaining escrow accounts and cannot qualify for the exception under  § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii).
        </analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-iv" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(iv)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>“Rural” and “Underserved” Defined</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As adopted in the Dodd-Frank Act, TILA section 129D(c)(1) requires, among other criteria for the escrows exemption, that the creditor operate predominantly in “rural” and “underserved” areas, but does not define either term. As discussed above, the Board proposed separate definitions for “rural” and “underserved,” respectively, in both the Board's 2011 Escrows Proposal and the 2011 ATR Proposal, and the definitions for the two terms were similar across the two proposals.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Commenters on the two proposals addressed the specific definitions themselves but not the necessity of creating a definition for “rural” that is separate from “underserved.” The Bureau is adopting the Board's approach in § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv) which establishes a definition of rural that is separate from underserved. Thus, creditors' activity in either type of area will count toward their eligibility for the escrows exemption and for making balloon-payment qualified mortgages.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>“Rural.”As described above, the Board's proposed definition of rural for purposes of both the balloon-payment qualified mortgage and escrows exemptions would have relied upon the ERS's “urban influence codes” (UICs), which in turn are based on the definitions of “metropolitan statistical area” and “micropolitan statistical area.”<footnote ref="35">The ERS places counties into twelve separately defined UICs depending on the size of the largest city or town in the county or in adjacent counties. Descriptions of UICs can be found on the ERS Web site athttp://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx.</footnote>

          The Board's proposal would have limited the definition of rural to certain “non-core” counties, which are areas outside of any metropolitan or micropolitan area that are not adjacent to a metropolitan area with at least one million residents or to a micropolitan area with a town of at least 2,500 residents. This definition corresponded to UICs 7, 10, 11, and 12. The counties that would have been covered under the Board's proposed definition contain 2.3 percent of the United States population under the 2000 census. The Board believed this approach limited the definition of “rural” to those properties most likely to have only limited sources of mortgage credit because of their remoteness from urban centers and their resources. However, the Board sought comment on all aspects of this approach to defining rural, including whether the definition should be broader ornarrower or based on information other than UIC codes.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Many commenters to both the 2011 ATR Proposal and the 2011 Escrows Proposal, including more than a dozen trade group commenters, several individual industry commenters, one association of State banking regulators, and a United States Senator, stated that the rural definition was too narrow. The trade association and industry commenters, and the group of State banking regulators, had various proposals to broaden the definition, from the addition of other UICs and a combination of county population and asset size to the adoption of other regulatory definitions of “rural,” such as those governing credit unions. The comment from a United States Senator suggested using the eligibility of a property to secure a single-family mortgage under the USDA's Rural Housing Loan program as the definition of a rural property.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau agrees that a broader definition of “rural” is appropriate to ensure access to credit with regard to both the escrows and balloon-payment qualified mortgage exemptions. In particular, the Bureau believes that all “non-core” counties should be encompassed in the definition of rural, including counties adjacent to a metropolitan area of at least one million residents or a county with a town of at least 2,500 residents (i.e.,counties with a UIC of 4, 6, or 9 in addition to the counties with the UICs included in the Board's definition). The Bureau also believes that micropolitan areas that are not adjacent to a metropolitan area should be included within the definition of rural (i.e.,counties with a UIC of 8), as these areas are not located adjacent to metropolitan areas that are served by many creditors. These counties have significantly fewer creditors originating higher-priced mortgage loans and balloon-payment mortgages than other counties.<footnote ref="36">A review of data from HMDA reporters indicates that there were 700 creditors in 2011 that otherwise meet the requirements of new § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii), of which 391 originate higher-priced mortgage loans in counties that meet the definition of rural, compared to 2,110 creditors that otherwise meet the requirements of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) that originate balloon-payment mortgages in counties that would not be rural. The 391 creditors originated 12,921 higher-priced mortgage loans, representing 30 percent of their 43,359 total mortgage loan originations. A review of data from credit unions indicates that there were 830 creditors in 2011 that otherwise meet the requirements of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii), of which 415 originate balloon-payment and hybrid mortgages in counties that meet the definition of rural, compared to 3,551 creditors that otherwise meet the requirements of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) that originate balloon-payment mortgages in counties that would not be rural. The 415 creditors originated 4,980 balloon-payment mortgage originations, representing 20 percent of their 24,968 total mortgage loan originations.</footnote>
          Including these counties within the definition of rural would result in 9.7 percent of the U.S. population being located within rural areas. Under this definition, only counties in metropolitan areas or in micropolitan areas adjacent to metropolitan areas would be excluded from the definition of rural.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also considered adopting the definition of rural used to determine the eligibility of a property to secure a single-family mortgage under the USDA's Rural Housing Loan program. This definition subdivides counties into rural and non-rural areas based upon whether certain areas are open country, or contain a town, village, city or place, with certain population criteria, and excludes areas associated with an urban area. Given the size of some counties, particularly in western States, this approach may provide a more nuanced measure of access to credit in some areas than a county-by-county metric. However, use of the Rural Housing Loan metrics would incorporate such significant portions of metropolitan and micropolitan counties that 37 percent of the United States population would be within areas defined as rural. Based on a review of HMDA data and the location of mortgage transactions originated by HMDA reporting entities, the average number of creditors in the areas that would meet the USDA's Rural Housing Loan program definition of rural is ten. The Bureau believes that a wholesale adoption of the Rural Housing Loan definitions would therefore expand the definition of rural beyond the intent of the escrow and balloon-payment qualified mortgage exemptions under sections 1412 and 1461 of the Dodd-Frank Act by incorporating areas in which there is robust access to credit.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the final rule implements § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A) to provide that a county is rural if it is neither in a metropolitan statistical area, nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area. The Bureau intends to continue studying over time the possible selective use of the Rural Housing Loan program definitions and tools provided on the USDA Web site to determine whether a particular property is located within a “rural” area. For purposes of initial implementation, however, the Bureau believes that defining “rural” to include more UIC categories creates an appropriate balance to preserve access to credit and create a system that is easy for creditors to implement.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>“Underserved.”The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(iv)(B) would have defined a county as “underserved” during a calendar year if no more than two creditors extend credit secured by a first lien on real property or a dwelling five or more times in that county. The definition was based on the Board's judgment that, where no more than two creditors are significantly active, the inability of one creditor to offer a higher-priced mortgage loan would be detrimental to consumers who would have limited credit options because only one creditor, or no creditors, would be left to provide the higher-priced mortgage loan. Essentially, a consumer who could only qualify for a higher-priced mortgage loan would be required to obtain credit from the remaining creditor in that area or would be left with no credit options at all. Most of the same commenters that stated that the proposed definition of rural was too narrow, as discussed above, also stated that this definition of underserved was too narrow. The commenters proposed various different standards, including standards that considered the extent to which the property was in a rural area, as an alternate definition of underserved.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau agrees with the Board that the purpose of the exemption is to permit creditors to continue to offer credit to consumers, rather than to refuse to make higher-priced mortgage loans if such creditors' withdrawal would significantly limit consumers' ability to obtain mortgage credit. In light of this rationale, the Bureau believes that “underserved” should be implemented in a way that protects consumers from losing meaningful access to mortgage credit and that it is appropriate to focus the definition on identifying areas where the withdrawal of a creditor from the market could leave no meaningful competition for consumers' mortgage business. The Bureau notes that the final rule's expanded definition of “rural,” as discussed above, will also address concerns about access to credit in many areas. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B) to define a property as “underserved” if it is located in a county where no more than two creditors extend covered transactions secured by a first lien five or more times in that county during a calendar year, substantially consistent with the Board's proposal. As adopted, § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B) also expressly states that the numbers of creditors and of their originations in counties for purposes of this definition is as reported in HMDA data for the year in question.
        </analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau adopted this definition based on HMDA data to provide an objective, easily administered rule and one that is consistent with the purpose of preserving credit access in underserved areas. Given that many smaller creditors may not be subject to HMDA reporting requirements, the Bureau recognizes that many counties may be underserved under the definition being adopted, because it is based on HMDA data, yet additional information (if it were available) could reveal that more than two creditors are significantly active in such counties. The Bureau may examine further whether a refinement to the underserved definition is warranted.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Commentary guidance on “rural” and “underserved” definitions.Comment 35(b)(2)(iv)-1 clarifies that the Bureau will annually update on its Web site a list of counties deemed rural or underserved under the definitions of rural and underserved in § 1026.35(b)(2)(iv). It also clarifies that the definition of rural corresponds to UICs 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12, as determined by the Economic Research Service of the USDA. It further clarifies that the definition of underserved counties is based on HMDA data. Finally, the comment provides that the Bureau also publishes a list of only those counties that are rural but not also underserved, to facilitate compliance with § 1026.35(c).<footnote ref="37">Section 1026.35(c) is being adopted separately by the Bureau jointly with other Federal agencies, to implement the new appraisal requirements in TILA section 129H, in the 2013 Interagency Appraisals Final Rule, as discussed in part III.C, above. That new section provides an exemption for creditors operating in rural, but not underserved, areas. Consequently, the single, combined list of all counties that are either rural or underserved that the Bureau will publish annually for purposes of the exemption from this final rule's escrow requirement is inadequate for the analogous purpose under the new appraisal requirements in § 1026.35(c).</footnote>
          As this final rule takes effect on June 1, 2013, the Bureau expects to publish lists applicable for the current year within approximately four to six weeks after publication of this final rule, but in any event before this final rule takes effect.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-2-v" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(2)(v)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As established by the Dodd-Frank Act, TILA section 129D(c)(3) requires that the exemption from the escrow requirements apply only where a creditor “retains its mortgage loan originations in portfolio” and meets the other statutory requirements. Because the escrow requirements must be applied at the time that a transaction is consummated, while qualified mortgage status may continue for the life of the mortgage obligation, the Board did not propose to implement this requirement consistently with the 2011 ATR Proposal. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(v) would have provided that the escrow exemption is not available for certain transactions that, at consummation, are subject to “forward commitments.” Forward commitments are agreements entered into at or before consummation of a transaction under which a purchaser is committed to acquire the mortgage obligation from the creditor after consummation. In addition, the Board included a proposed comment to § 226.45(b)(2)(v) which would have clarified that the forward commitment provision would have applied whether the forward commitment refers to the specific transaction or the higher-priced mortgage loan meets prescribed criteria of the forward commitment in order to address a potential method to avoid compliance. The Board's 2011 ATR Proposal, in contrast, proposed two alternatives for comment, either prohibiting a creditor to qualify if it has sold any balloon-payment qualified mortgages at any time or prohibiting a creditor to qualify if it has sold any balloon-payment qualified mortgages in the current or prior calendar year.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board considered requiring that a transaction be held in portfolio after consummation as a condition of the escrows exemption, but concluded that this approach would have raised operational problems. Whether a mortgage obligation is held in portfolio can be determined only after consummation, but a creditor making a higher-priced mortgage loan must know by consummation whether it is subject to the escrow requirement. The Board expressed concern that requiring an escrow account to be established sometime after consummation if the creditor in fact sells the mortgage obligation could put a significant burden on consumers, who may not have the money available to make a significant advance payment. In contrast, the Board reasoned that the forward commitment test would be easy to apply at consummation, and would be unlikely to be circumvented by small creditors because they would be reluctant to extend credit for transactions they do not intend to keep in portfolio unless they have the assurance of a committed buyer before extending the credit. Thus, proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(v) would have served as a means of indirectly limiting the exemption to mortgage obligations that are to be held in portfolio. The Board sought comment, however, on whether institutions could easily evade the escrow requirement by making higher-priced mortgage loans without a forward commitment in place and thereafter selling them to non-exempt purchasers and how to address this possibility without relying on post-consummation events.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Among the commenters, there was a divergence of opinion on how this provision would work in practice. One trade association commenter stated that the forward commitment requirement would prevent creditors from selling portfolio mortgage obligations in the future. This appears to be a misreading of the Board's proposal, as it would not have restricted the sale of higher-priced mortgage loans. The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(2)(v) instead merely provided that, so long as the higher-priced mortgage loan was not subject to a forward commitment at the time of consummation, the higher-priced mortgage loan could later be sold on the secondary market without requiring an escrow account to be established at that time. One consumer advocacy group, concerned about the possibility that creditors would use the provision to skirt the escrow requirements, suggested a blanket rule that higher-priced mortgage loans that are exempt must be maintained in the portfolio of the creditor or, alternatively, that upon sale secondary market purchasers be required to establish escrow accounts for such mortgage obligations.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>After reviewing the comments received, the Bureau believes that the Board's proposal is an appropriate method to implement the requirements of TILA section 129D(c)(3), as both creditor and consumer benefit if an escrow account is established at consummation of the transaction, rather than months or years later. Indeed, allowing a consumer to avoid having to make a single large lump-sum payment after consummation is part of the basic purpose of establishing an escrow account. Accordingly, the Bureau is following the approach in the Board's proposal by adopting § 1026.35(b)(2)(v) to require that for a higher-priced mortgage loan to be exempt from the requirements under § 1026.35(b)(1), the higher-priced mortgage loan must not be subject to a forward commitment to be acquired by a creditor that does not satisfy the conditions of § 1026.35(b)(2)(iii). Comment 35(b)(2)(v)-1 clarifies that a higher-priced mortgage loan that is subject to a forward commitment is subject to the escrow requirement under § 1026.35(b)(1), whether the forward commitment refers to the specific transaction or the higher-pricedmortgage loan meets prescribed criteria of the forward commitment, along with an example. As discussed separately in the Bureau's 2013 ATR Final Rule, the Bureau is also adopting language in § 1026.43(f) to provide that qualified mortgage status is not available to balloon-payment mortgages that would otherwise qualify for the exemption if the transactions are subject to a forward commitment at the time of consummation.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-b-3" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(b)(3) Cancellation</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Under TILA section 129D(d), a creditor or servicer of a higher-priced mortgage loan must maintain an escrow account for a minimum of five years following consummation, unless the underlying debt obligation is terminated earlier under certain prescribed circumstances. In addition, even after five years have elapsed, TILA section 129D(d) provides that an escrow account shall remain in existence unless and until the consumer is current on the obligation and has accrued sufficient equity in the dwelling securing the consumer credit transaction “so as to no longer be required to maintain private mortgage insurance.”</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board's proposed § 226.45(b)(3) would have implemented TILA section 129D(d) by permitting cancellation of the escrow account only upon the earlier of termination of the legal obligation or five years after consummation, provided that at least 20 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation is unencumbered and the consumer currently is not delinquent or in default on the underlying debt obligation. The Board modeled its proposal after the prerequisites for cancellation of private mortgage insurance coverage under the Homeowners Protection Act of 1998 (HPA), 12 U.S.C. 4901-4910. Under the HPA, the consumer may initiate cancellation of private mortgage insurance (PMI) once the outstanding balance of the mortgage obligation is first scheduled to reach 80 percent of the original value of the property, regardless of the outstanding balance, based on the amortization schedule or actual payments. In addition, servicers must automatically terminate PMI for residential mortgage transactions on the earliest date that the principal balance of the mortgage is first scheduled to reach 78 percent of the original value of the secured property securing the mortgage obligation, where the consumer is current. The Board sought comment on this proposal, as well as whether TILA section 129D(d)(1) should be interpreted narrowly to mean that, among consumers with escrow accounts required pursuant to proposed § 226.45(b)(1), only those that in fact have private mortgage insurance must meet the minimum equity requirement under the HPA as a prerequisite for cancelling their escrow accounts.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Commenters generally agreed with the Board's approach of requiring the 80 percent loan-to-value (LTV) ratio for consumer-requested PMI termination, rather than the 78 percent LTV ratio for automatic PMI termination. Several commenters remarked, however, that the proposed language defining the equity cancellation requirement as “at least 20% of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation is unencumbered” was confusing, if not misleading.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The final rule follows the general approach in the Board's proposal by adopting § 1026.35(b)(3) to establish the cancellation criteria for escrow accounts as provided by TILA section 129D(d). In response to comments, § 1026.35(b)(3) contains revised language describing the equity necessary for cancellation as an unpaid principal balance that is less than 80 percent of the original value of the property securing the underlying debt obligation. Additionally, the Bureau is adopting the Board's proposed comment 45(b)(3)-1 as comment 35(b)(3)-1 to clarify that termination of the underlying credit obligation could include, among other things, repayment, refinancing, rescission, and foreclosure. Comment 35(b)(3)-2 clarifies that § 1026.35(b)(3) does not affect the right or obligation of a creditor or servicer, pursuant to the terms of the legal obligation or applicable law, to offer or require an escrow account after the minimum period dictated by § 1026.35(b)(3). Finally, comment 35(b)(3)-3 notes that the term “original value” in § 1026.35(b)(3)(ii)(A), as adopted from section 2(12) of the HPA, 12 U.S.C. 4901(12), means the lesser of the sales price reflected in the sales contract for the property, if any, or the appraised value of the property at the time the transaction was consummated.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-c" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(c)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board proposed to reserve § 226.45(c) for future use in implementing section 1471 of the Dodd- Frank Act, which creates new TILA section 129H to establish certain appraisal requirements applicable to “higher-risk mortgages.” Consistent with that proposal, the Bureau is reserving § 1026.35(c) in this final rule, thus permitting that section to be finalized separately in the 2013 Interagency Appraisals Final Rule, discussed above. As discussed in part III.C, the 2013 Interagency Appraisals Final Rule will take effect subsequent to this final rule.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1026-35-d" notice="2013-00734" date="2013-06-01">
      <title>35(d) Evasion; Open-End Credit</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board's proposed § 226.45(d) would have paralleled existing § 1026.35(b)(4) in prohibiting a creditor from structuring a home-secured transaction as an open-end plan to evade the requirements of proposed § 226.45 in connection with credit secured by a consumer's principal dwelling that does not meet the definition of open-end credit in § 226.2(a)(20). No comments were received regarding the scope or substance of this proposal. The Bureau has adopted the Board's proposal in § 1026.35(d), with certain technical edits.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
