<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2015-12-24</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2015-32463</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2015-12-24</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2015/12/24/2015-32463/2013-integrated-mortgage-disclosures-rule-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2015-18239" rightDocumentNumber="2015-32463">
  <!-- Section 1026.22 is amended by revising paragraph (a)(5) to read as follows: -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-22-a-5">
    <paragraph label="1026-22-a-5" marker="(5)">
      <title type="keyterm">Additional tolerance for mortgage loans.</title>
      <content>In a transaction secured by real property or a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, in addition to the tolerances applicable under paragraphs <ref target="1026-22-a-2" reftype="internal">(a)(2)</ref> and <ref target="1026-22-a-3" reftype="internal">(3)</ref> of this section, if the disclosed finance charge is calculated incorrectly but is considered accurate under § <ref target="1026-18-d-1" reftype="internal">1026.18(d)(1)</ref> or § <ref target="1026-23-g" reftype="internal">1026.38(o)</ref>(2),<ref target="1026-23-h" reftype="internal"> as</ref> applicable, or § <ref target="1026-23-g" reftype="internal">1026.23(g)</ref> or (h), the disclosed annual percentage rate shall be considered accurate:</content><paragraph label="1026-22-a-5-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>If the disclosed finance charge is understated, and the disclosed annual percentage rate is also understated but it is closer to the actual annual percentage rate than the rate that would be considered accurate under paragraph <ref target="1026-22-a-4" reftype="internal">(a)(4)</ref> of this section;</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-22-a-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>If the disclosed finance charge is overstated, and the disclosed annual percentage rate is also overstated but it is closer to the actual annual percentage rate than the rate that would be considered accurate under paragraph <ref target="1026-22-a-4" reftype="internal">(a)(4)</ref> of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <!-- In Supplement I to Part 1026 Official Interpretations, under Subpart C Closed-End Credit: -->
  <!-- A. In Section 1026.17 General Disclosure Requirements: -->
  <!-- i. Under 17(c) Basis of Disclosures and Use of Estimates: -->
  <!-- a. Under Paragraph 17(c)(1), paragraphs 2,4,10,11, and 12 are revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-2">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title type="keyterm">Modification of obligation.</title>
      <content>The legal obligation normally is presumed to be contained in the note or contract that evidences the <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> between the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. But this presumption is rebutted if another <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> between the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> legally modifies that note or contract. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> informally agree to a modification of the legal obligation, the modification should not be reflected in the disclosures unless it rises to the level of a change in the terms of the legal obligation. For example:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
        <content>If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> <ref target="1026-58-b-5" reftype="term">offers</ref> a preferential rate, such as an employee preferred rate, the disclosures should reflect the terms of the legal obligation. (See the commentary to § <ref target="1026-19-b-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.19(b)</ref> for an example of a preferred-rate transaction that is a variable-rate transaction.)</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>If the contract provides for a certain monthly payment schedule but payments are made on a voluntary payroll deduction plan or an informal principal-reduction <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, the disclosures should reflect the schedule in the contract.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>If the contract provides for regular monthly payments but the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> informally permits the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to defer payments from time to time, for instance, to take account of holiday seasons or seasonal employment, the disclosures should reflect the regular monthly payments.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title type="keyterm">Consumer buydowns.</title>
      <content>In certain transactions, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may pay an amount to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to reduce the payments on the transaction. <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">Consumer</ref> buydowns must be reflected as an <ref target="1026-58-b-2" reftype="term">amendment</ref> to the contract's interest rate provision in the disclosure of the finance charge and other disclosures affected by it given for that transaction. To illustrate, in a mortgage transaction, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> agree to a note specifying a 14 percent interest rate. However, in a separate document, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> agrees to pay an amount to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> in return for lower payments for a portion of the mortgage term. The amount paid by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may be deposited in an escrow account or may be retained by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. Depending upon the buydown plan, the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s prepayment of the obligation may or may not result in a portion of the amount being credited or refunded to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. In the disclosure of the finance charge and other disclosures affected by it given for the mortgage, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must reflect the terms of the buydown <ref target="1026-58-b-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
        <content>For example:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4-i-A" marker="A.">
          <content>The amount paid by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is a <ref target="1026-2-a-23" reftype="term">prepaid finance charge</ref> (even if deposited in an escrow account).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4-i-B" marker="B.">
          <content>A composite annual percentage rate must be calculated, taking into account both interest rates, as well as the effect of the <ref target="1026-2-a-23" reftype="term">prepaid finance charge</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4-i-C" marker="C.">
          <content>The disclosures under §§ <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> and (s), <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, as applicable, must reflect the multiple rate and payment levels resulting from the buydown, except as otherwise provided in those sections. Further, for example, the disclosures must reflect that the transaction is a step rate product under §§ <ref target="1026-37-a-10-i-B" reftype="internal">1026.37(a)(10)(i)(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-a-5-iii" reftype="internal">1026.38(a)(5)(iii)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>The rules regarding <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> buydowns do not apply to transactions known as “lender buydowns.” In lender buydowns, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> pays an amount (either into an account or to the party to whom the obligation is sold) to reduce the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s payments or interest rate for all or a portion of the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> term. Typically, these transactions are structured as a buydown of the interest rate during an initial period of the transaction with a higher than usual rate for the remainder of the term. The disclosure of the finance charge and other disclosures affected by it for lender buydowns should be based on the terms of the legal oblig<ref target="1026-17-c-1-Interp-3" reftype="internal">ation betw</ref>een the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. See comment 17(c)(1)-3 for the analogous rules concerning third-party buydowns.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10" marker="10.">
      <title>Discounted and premium variable-rate transactions.</title>
      <content>In some variable-rate transactions, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> may set an initial interest rate that is not determined by the index or formula used to make later interest rate adjustments. Typically, this initial rate charged to <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> is lower than the rate would be if it were calculated using the index or formula. However, in some cases the initial rate may be higher. In a discounted transaction, for example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may calculate interest rates according to a formula using the six-month Treasury bill rate plus a 2 percent margin. If the Treasury bill rate at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> is 10 percent, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may forgo the 2 percent spread and charge only 10 percent for a limited time, instead of setting an initial rate of 12 percent.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-i" marker="i.">
        <content>When <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> use an initial interest rate that is not calculated using the index or formula for later rate adjustments, the disclosures should reflect a composite annual percentage rate based on the initial rate for as long as it is charged and, for the remainder of the term, the rate that would have been applied using the index or formula at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>. The rate at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> need not be used if a contract provides for a delay in the implementation of changes in an index value. For example, if the contract specifies that rate changes are based on the index value in effect 45 days before the change date, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> may use any index value in effect during the 45 day period before <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> in calculating a composite annual percentage rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>The effect of the multiple rates must also be reflected in the calculation and disclosure of the finance charge, total of payments, and the disclosures required under §§ <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> and (s), <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-l-1" reftype="internal">1026.37(l)(1)</ref> and (3), <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-o-5" reftype="internal">1026.38(o)(5)</ref>, as applicable.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>If a loan contains a rate or payment cap that would prevent the initial rate or payment, at the time of the first adjustment, from changing to the rate determined by the index or formula at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, the effect of that rate or payment cap should be reflected in the disclosures.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-iv" marker="iv.">
        <content>Because these transactions involve irregular payment amounts, an annual percentage rate tolerance of 1/4 of 1 percent applies, in accordance with § <ref target="1026-22-a-3" reftype="internal">1026.22(a)(3)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-v" marker="v.">
        <content>Examples of discounted variable-rate transactions include:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-v-A" marker="A.">
            <content>A 30-year loan for $100,000 with no <ref target="1026-2-a-23" reftype="term">prepaid finance charges</ref> and rates determined by the Treasury bill rate plus two percent. Rate and payment adjustments are made annually. Although the Treasury bill rate at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> is 10 percent, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> sets the interest rate for one year at 9 percent, instead of 12 percent according to the formula. The disclosures should reflect a composite annual percentage rate of 11.63 percent based on 9 percent for one year and 12 percent for 29 years. Reflecting those two rate levels, the payment schedule disclosed pursuant to § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> should show 12 payments of $804.62 and 348 payments of $1,025.31. Similarly, the disclosures required by §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-l-1" reftype="internal">1026.37(l)(1)</ref> and (3), <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-o-5" reftype="internal">1026.38(o)(5)</ref> should reflect the effect of this calculation. The finance charge should be $266,463.32 and, for transactions subject to § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref>, the total of payments should be $366,463.32.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-v-B" marker="B.">
            <content>Same loan as above, except with a two-percent rate cap on periodic adjustments. The disclosures should reflect a composite annual percentage rate of 11.53 percent based on 9 percent for the first year, 11 percent for the second year, and 12 percent for the remaining 28 years. Reflecting those three rate levels, the payment schedule disclosed pursuant to § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> should show 12 payments of $804.62, 12 payments of $950.09, and 336 payments of $1,024.34. Similarly, the disclosures required by §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-l-1" reftype="internal">1026.37(l)(1)</ref> and (3), <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-o-5" reftype="internal">1026.38(o)(5)</ref> should reflect the effect of this calculation. The finance charge should be $265,234.76 and, for transactions subject to § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref>, the total of payments should be $365,234.76.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-v-C" marker="C.">
            <content>Same loan as above, except with a 7 1/2 percent cap on payment adjustments. The disclosures should reflect a composite annual percentage rate of 11.64 percent, based on 9 percent for one year and 12 percent for 29 years. Because of the payment cap, five levels of payments should be reflected. The payment schedule disclosed pursuant to § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> should show 12 payments of $804.62, 12 payments of $864.97, 12 payments of $929.84, 12 payments of $999.58, and 312 payments of $1,070.04. Similarly, the disclosures required by §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-l-1" reftype="internal">1026.37(l)(1)</ref> and (3), <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-o-5" reftype="internal">1026.38(o)(5)</ref> should reflect the effect of this calculation. The finance charge should be $277,040.60, and, for transactions subject to § <ref target="1026-18" reftype="internal">1026.18</ref>, the total of payments should be $377,040.60.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-10-vi" marker="vi.">
        <content>A loan in which the initial interest rate is set according to the index or formula used for later adjustments but is not set at the value of the index or formula at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> is not a discounted variable-rate loan. For example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> commits to an initial rate based on the formula on a date prior to <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, but the index has moved during the period between that time and <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> should base its disclosures on the initial rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11" marker="11.">
      <title>Examples of variable-rate transactions.</title>
      <content>Variable-rate transactions include:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Renewable balloon-payment instruments where the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is both unconditionally obligated to renew the balloon-payment loan at the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s option (or is obligated to renew subject to conditions within the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control) and has the option of increasing the interest rate at the time of renewal. Disclosures must be based on the payment amortization (unless the specified term of the obligation with renewals is shorter) and on the rate in effect at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> of the transaction. (Examples of conditions within a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control include requirements that a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> be current in payments or continue to reside in the mortgaged property. In contrast, setting a limit on the rate at which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> would be obligated to renew or reserving the right to change the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> standards at the time of renewal are examples of conditions outside a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control.) If, however, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is not obligated to renew as described above, disclosures must be based on the term of the balloon-payment loan. Disclosures also must be based on the term of the balloon-payment loan in balloon-payment instruments in which the legal obligation provides that the loan will be renewed by a “refinancing” of the obligation, as that term is defined by § <ref target="1026-20-a" reftype="internal">1026.20(a)</ref>. If it cannot be determined from the legal obligation that the loan will be renewed by a “refinancing,” disclosures must be based either on the term of the balloon-payment loan or on the payment amortization, depending on whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is unconditionally obligated to renew the loan as described above. (This discussion does not apply to construction loans subject to § <ref target="1026-17-c-6" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)</ref>.)</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>“Shared-equity” or “shared-appreciation” mortgages that have a fixed rate of interest and an appreciation share based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s equity in the mortgaged property. The appreciation share is payable in a lump sum at a specified time. Disclosures must be based on the fixed interest rate. (As discussed in the commentary to § <ref target="1026-2-Interp" reftype="internal">1026.2</ref>, other types of shared-equity arrangements are not considered “credit” and are not subject to Regulation Z.)</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>Preferred-rate loans where the terms of the legal obligation provide that the initial underlying rate is fixed but will increase upon the occurrence of some event, such as an employee leaving the employ of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, and the note reflects the preferred rate. The disclosures are to be based on the preferred rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11-iv" marker="iv.">
        <content>Graduated-payment mortgages and step-rate transactions without a variable-rate feature are not considered variable-rate transactions.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-11-v" marker="v.">
        <content>“Price level adjusted mortgages” or other indexed mortgages that have a fixed rate of interest but provide for periodic adjustments to payments and the loan balance to reflect changes in an index measuring prices or inflation. Disclosures are to be based on the fixed interest rate, except as otherwise provided in §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, 1026.37, and 1026.38, as applicable.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12" marker="12.">
      <title type="keyterm">Graduated payment adjustable rate mortgages.</title>
      <content>These mortgages involve both a variable interest rate and scheduled variations in payment amounts during the loan term. For example, under these plans, a series of graduated payments may be scheduled before rate adjustments affect payment amounts, or the initial scheduled payment may remain constant for a set period before rate adjustments affect the payment amount. In any case, the initial payment amount may be insufficient to cover the scheduled interest, causing <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> from the outset of the transaction. In these transactions, except as otherwise provided in §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, the disclosures should treat these features as follows:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12-i" marker="i.">
        <content>The finance charge includes the amount of <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref> based on the assumption that the rate in effect at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> remains unchanged.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>The amount financed does not include the amount of <ref target="1026-18-s-7-v" reftype="term">negative amortization</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>As in any variable-rate transaction, the annual percentage rate is based on the terms in effect at <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-1-Interp-12-iv" marker="iv.">
        <content>The disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> and (s) reflect the amount of any scheduled initial payments followed by an adjusted level of payments based on the initial interest rate. Since some mortgage plans contain limits on the amount of the payment adjustment, the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> and (s) may require several different levels of payments, even with the assumption that the original interest rate does not increase. For transactions subject to § <ref target="1026-19-e" reftype="internal">1026.19(e)</ref> and (f), see § <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and its commentary for a discussion of different rules for graduated payment adjustable rate mortgages.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- b. Under Paragraph 17(c)(4), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-4-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Payment schedule irregularities.</title>
      <content>When one or more payments in a transaction differ from the others because of a long or short first period, the variations may be ignored in disclosing the payment schedule pursuant to § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref>, the disclosures required pursuant to §§ <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>, <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref>, or <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, or the finance charge, annual percentage rate, and other terms. For example:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-4-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
        <content>A 36-month auto loan might be consummated on June 8 with payments due on July 1 and the first of each succeeding month. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may base its calculations on a payment schedule that assumes 36 equal intervals and 36 equal installment payments, even though a precise computation would produce slightly different amounts because of the shorter first period.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-c-4-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>By contrast, in the same example, if the first payment were not scheduled until August 1, the irregular first period would exceed the limits in § <ref target="1026-17-c-4" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(4)</ref>; the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> could not use the special rule and could not ignore the extra days in the first period in calculating its disclosures.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- ii. Under 17(g) Mail or Telephone Orders Delay in Disclosures, paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-g-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-17-g-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Conditions for use.</title>
      <content>Except for extensions of <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-19-a" reftype="internal">1026.19(a)</ref> or (e) and (f), when the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> receives a mail or telephone request for <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may delay making the disclosures until the first payment is due if the following conditions are met:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-g-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
        <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> request is initiated without face-to-face or direct telephone <ref target="1026-46-d-1-i" reftype="term">solicitation</ref>. (<ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may, however, use the special rule when <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> requests are solicited by mail.)</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-g-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> has supplied the specified <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> information about its <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms either to the individual <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or to the public generally. That information may be distributed through <ref target="1026-2-a-2" reftype="term">advertisements</ref>, catalogs, brochures, special mailers, or similar means.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- B. In Section 1026.18 Content of Disclosures, under 18(g) Payment Schedule, paragraph 4 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-g-Interp-4-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-18-g-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
      <title>General rule.</title>
      <content>Section <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> requires <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> to disclose the timing of payments. To meet this requirement, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> may list all of the payment due dates. They also have the option of specifying the “period of payments” scheduled to repay the obligation. As a general rule, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> that choose this option must disclose the payment intervals or frequency, such as “monthly” or “bi-weekly,” and the calendar date that the beginning payment is due. For example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may disclose that payments are due “monthly beginning on July 1, 1998.” This information, when combined with the number of payments, is necessary to define the repayment period and enable a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to determine all of the payment due dates.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-g-Interp-4-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-18-g-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
      <title type="keyterm">Exception.</title>
      <content>In a limited number of circumstances, the beginning-payment date is unknown and difficult to determine at the time disclosures are made. For example, a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> may become obligated on a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> contract that contemplates the delayed disbursement of funds based on a contingent event, such as the completion of repairs. Disclosures may also accompany loan checks that are sent by mail, in which case the initial disbursement and repayment dates are solely within the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s control. In such cases, if the beginning-payment date is unknown the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may use an estimated date and label the disclosure as an estimate pursuant to § <ref target="1026-17-c" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)</ref>. Alternatively, the disclosure may refer to the occurrence of a particular event, for example, by disclosing that the beginning payment is due “30 days after the first loan disbursement.” This information also may be included with an estimated date to explain the basis for the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s estimate. See comment 17(a)<ref target="1026-17-a-1-Interp-5-iii" reftype="internal">(1)-5.iii.</ref></content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- C. In Appendix D Multiple-Advance Construction Loans, paragraph 7 is added. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-D-Interp-7">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-D-Interp-7" marker="7.">
      <title type="keyterm">Relation to §§ 1026.37 and 1026.38.</title>
      <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must disclose a projected payments table for certain transactions secured by real property, pursuant to §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, instead of the general payment schedule required by § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref> or the interest rate and payments summary table required by § <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>. Accordingly, some home construction loans that are secured by real property are subject to §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref> and not § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref>. See comment app. <ref target="1026-D-Interp-6" reftype="internal">D-6</ref> for a discussion of transactions that are subject to § <ref target="1026-18-s" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)</ref>. Under § <ref target="1026-17-c-6-ii" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)(ii)</ref>, when a multiple-advance construction loan may be permanently financed by the same <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, the construction phase and the permanent phase may be treated as either one transaction or more than one transaction. Following are illustrations of the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> of appendix <ref target="1026-D" reftype="internal">D</ref> to transactions subject to §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, under each of these two alternatives:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-D-Interp-7-i" marker="i.">
        <content>If a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> uses appendix <ref target="1026-D" reftype="internal">D</ref> and elects pursuant to § <ref target="1026-17-c-6-ii" reftype="internal">1026.17(c)(6)(ii)</ref> to disclose the construction and permanent phases as separate transactions, the construction phase must be disclosed according to the rules in §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>. Under §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must disclose the periodic payments during the construction phase in a projected payments table. The provision in appendix <ref target="1026-D-I-A-3" reftype="internal">D, part I.A.3</ref>, which allows the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to omit the number and amounts of any interest payments “in disclosing the payment schedule under § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref>” does not apply because the transaction is governed by §§ <ref target="1026-37-c" reftype="internal">1026.37(c)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-c" reftype="internal">1026.38(c)</ref> rather than § <ref target="1026-18-g" reftype="internal">1026.18(g)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> determines the amount of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-iv" reftype="term">interest-only</ref> payment to be made during the construction phase using the assumption in appendix <ref target="1026-D-I-A-1" reftype="internal">D, part I.A.1</ref>. Also, because the construction phase is being disclosed as a separate transaction and its terms do not repay all principal, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must disclose the construction phase transaction as a product with a balloon payment feature, pursuant to §§ <ref target="1026-37-a-10-ii-D" reftype="internal">1026.37(a)(10)(ii)(D)</ref> and <ref target="1026-38-a-5-iii" reftype="internal">1026.38(a)(5)(iii)</ref>, in addition to reflecting the balloon payment in the projected payments table.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-D-Interp-7-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> elects to disclose the construction and permanent phases as a single transaction, the repayment schedule must be disclosed pursuant to appendix <ref target="1026-D-II-C-2" reftype="internal">D, part II.C.2</ref>. Under appendix <ref target="1026-D-II-C-2" reftype="internal">D, part II.C.2</ref>, the projected payments table must reflect the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-iv" reftype="term">interest-only</ref> payments during the construction phase in a first column, followed by the appropriate column(s) reflecting the amortizing payments for the permanent phase. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> determines the amount of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-iv" reftype="term">interest-only</ref> payment to be made during the construction phase using the assumption in appendix <ref target="1026-D-II-A-1" reftype="internal">D, part II.A.1</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
