<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2015-10-02</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2015-24362</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2016-01-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2015/10/02/2015-24362/amendments-relating-to-small-creditors-and-rural-or-underserved-areas-under-the-truth-in-lending-act</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2015-22987" rightDocumentNumber="2015-24362">
  <!-- Section 1026.35 is amended by revising paragraphs (b)(2)(iii)(A) through (D)(1) and (b)(2)(iv)(A) and (B) and adding paragraph (b)(2)(iv)(C) to read as follows: -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, during either of the two preceding calendar years, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended more than 50 percent of its total <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens on properties that are located in areas that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(iv)</ref> of this section;</content></paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" marker="(B)">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, during either of the two preceding calendar years, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together extended no more than 2,000 <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>;</content></paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" marker="(C)">
      <content>As of the preceding December 31st, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, as of either of the two preceding December 31sts, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, together, had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000; this asset threshold shall adjust automatically each year, based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars (see comment <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" reftype="internal">35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii</ref> for the applicable threshold); and</content></paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" marker="(D)">
      <content>Neither the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> nor its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> maintains an escrow account of the type described in paragraph <ref target="1026-35-b-1" reftype="internal">(b)(1)</ref> of this section for any extension of <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> secured by real property or a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> currently services, other than:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2016; or</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>Escrow accounts established after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> as an accommodation to distressed <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> to assist such <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> in avoiding default or foreclosure.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>An area is “rural” during a calendar year if it is:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS); or</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>A census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census Bureau using the latest decennial census of the United States.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" marker="(B)">
      <content>An area is “underserved” during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, it is a county in which no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens on properties in the county five or more times.</content></paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-C" after="1026-35-b-2-iv-B">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-C" marker="(C)">
      <content>A property shall be deemed to be in an area that is rural or underserved in a particular calendar year if the property is:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-C-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>Located in a county that appears on the lists published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> of counties that are rural or underserved, as defined by § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref> or § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, for that calendar year,</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-C-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>Designated as rural or underserved for that calendar year by any automated tool that the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> provides on its public Web site, or</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-C-3" marker="(3)">
        <content>Not designated as located in an urban area, as defined by the most recent delineation of urban areas announced by the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, by any automated address search tool that the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> provides on its public Web site for that purpose and that specifically indicates the urban or rural designations of properties.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change><!-- Section 1026.43 is amended by revising paragraph (e)(6) to read as follows: -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-e-6">
    <paragraph label="1026-43-e-6" marker="(6)">
      <title type="keyterm">Qualified mortgage defined temporary balloon-payment qualified mortgage rules.</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-43-e-6-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>Notwithstanding paragraph <ref target="1026-43-e-2" reftype="internal">(e)(2)</ref> of this section, a qualified mortgage is a <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref>:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-43-e-6-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>That satisfies the requirements of paragraph <ref target="1026-43-f" reftype="internal">(f)</ref> of this section other than the requirements of paragraph <ref target="1026-43-f-1-vi" reftype="internal">(f)(1)(vi)</ref>; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-43-e-6-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>For which the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the requirements stated in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">(C)</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-43-e-6-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>The provisions of this paragraph <ref target="1026-43-e-6" reftype="internal">(e)(6)</ref> apply only to <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> for which the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received before April 1, 2016.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <!-- In Supplement I to Part 1026   Official Interpretations: -->
  <!-- A. Under Section 1026.35 Requirements for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans: -->
  <!-- i. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii), paragraphs 1 introductory text and 1.i through iii are revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1" subpath="content">
    <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>, except as provided in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-v" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(v)</ref>, a creditor need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a higher-priced mortgage loan, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the higher-priced mortgage loan is consummated:</content>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or during either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, more than 50 percent of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s total first-lien cove<ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">red transactions,</ref> as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, are secured by properties located in areas that are either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-A" marker="A.">
        <content>In general, whether this condition (the more than 50 percent test) is satisfied depends on the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s activity during the preceding calendar year. However, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan in question was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may instead meet the more than 50 percent test based on its activity during the next-to-last calendar year. This provides <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> with a <ref target="1026-54-a-2" reftype="term">grace period</ref> if their activity meets the more than 50 percent test (in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>) in one calendar year but fails to meet it in the next calendar year.</content></interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B" marker="B.">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets the more than 50 percent test for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during a calendar year if a majority of its first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in the preceding calendar year are secured by properties located in rural or underserved areas. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s transactions in the preceding calendar year do not meet the more than 50 percent test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during the current calendar year only if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year and a majority of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during the next-to-last calendar year are secured by properties located in rural or underserved areas. The following examples are illustrative:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B-1" marker="1.">
          <content>Assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended 180 first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2016 and that 91 of these are secured by properties located in rural or underserved areas. Because a majority of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2016 are secured by properties located in rural or underserved areas, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can meet this condition for exemption for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2017.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B-2" marker="2.">
          <content>Assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended 180 first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2016, including 90 transactions secured by properties that are located in rural or underserved areas. Assume further that the same <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended 200 first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2015, including 101 transactions secured by properties that are located in rural or underserved areas. Assume further that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> consummates a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> in 2017 for which the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received in November 2017. Because the majority of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2016 are not secured by properties that are located in rural or underserved areas, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received on or after April 1, 2017, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not meet this condition for exemption. However, assume instead that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> consummates a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> in 2017 based on an <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> received in February 2017. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for exemption for this loan because the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received before April 1, 2017, and the majority of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in 2015 are secured by properties that are located in areas that were rural or underserved.</content></interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
      <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together extended no more than 2,000 <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, during the preceding calendar year or during either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year. For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref>, a transfer of a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> to “another person” includes a transfer by a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> to its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii-A" marker="A.">
        <content>In general, whether this condition is satisfied depends on the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s activity during the preceding calendar year. However, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan in question is received before April 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may instead meet this condition based on activity during the next-to-last calendar year. This provides <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> with a <ref target="1026-54-a-2" reftype="term">grace period</ref> if their activity falls at or below the threshold in one calendar year but exceeds it in the next calendar year.</content></interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii-B" marker="B.">
        <content>For example, assume that in 2015 a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together extended 1,500 loans that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, and 2,500 such loans in 2016. Because the 2016 transaction activity exceeds the threshold but the 2015 transaction activity does not, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies this condition for exemption for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2017 if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> received the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan before April 1, 2017, but does not satisfy this condition for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2017 if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received on or after April 1, 2017.</content></interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-ii-C" marker="C.">
        <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref>, extensions of first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, during the applicable time period, by all of a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, as “affiliate” is defined in § <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(5)</ref>, are counted toward the threshold in this section. “Affiliate” is defined in § <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(5)</ref> as “any company that controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with another company, as set forth in the Bank Holding Company Act of 1956 (<ref target="USC-12-1841" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 1841</ref> et seq.).” Under the Bank Holding Company Act, a company has control over a bank or another company if it “directly or indirectly or acting through one or more persons owns, controls, or has power to vote 25 per centum or more of any class of voting securities of the bank or company”; it “controls in any manner the election of a majority of the directors or trustees of the bank or company”; or the Federal Reserve Board “determines, after notice and opportunity for hearing, that the company directly or indirectly exercises a controlling influence over the management or policies of the bank or company.” <ref target="USC-12-1841" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 1841</ref>(a)(2).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
      <content>As of the end of the preceding calendar year, or as of the end of either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens, together, had total assets that are less than the applicable annual asset threshold.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-A" marker="A.">
        <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</ref>, in addition to the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s assets, only the assets of a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s “affiliate” (as defined by § <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(5)</ref>) that regularly extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> (as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>) secured by first liens, are counted toward the applicable annual asset threshold. See comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.ii.C for discussion of definition of “<ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-B" marker="B.">
        <content>Only the assets of a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during the applicable period are included in calculating the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s assets. The meaning of “regularly extended” is based on the number of times a <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> extends <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> for purposes of the definition of “creditor” in § <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="internal">1026.2(a)(17)</ref>. Because <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> are “transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>,” consistent with § <ref target="1026-2-a-17-v" reftype="internal">1026.2(a)(17)(v)</ref>, an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> regularly extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> if it extended more than five <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in a calendar year. Also consistent with § <ref target="1026-2-a-17-v" reftype="internal">1026.2(a)(17)(v)</ref>, because a <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> may be a high-cost mortgage subject to § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref>, an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> regularly extends <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> if, in any 12-month period, it extends more than one <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is subject to the requirements of § <ref target="1026-32" reftype="internal">1026.32</ref> or one or more such transactions through a mortgage broker. Thus, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s assets as of the end of the preceding calendar year, for purposes of the asset limit, take into account the assets of that <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, exceeded the asset limit in the preceding calendar year to be eligible to operate as a small <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> for transactions with applications received before April 1 of the current calendar year the assets of the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in the year before the preceding calendar year are included in calculating the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s assets.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-C" marker="C.">
        <content>If multiple <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> share ownership of a company that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, the assets of the company count toward the asset limit for a co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> if the company is an “<ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>,” as defined in § <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(5)</ref>, of the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. Assuming the company is not an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> by virtue of any other aspect of the definition (such as by the company and co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> being under common control), the company's assets are included toward the asset limit of the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> only if the company is controlled by the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, “as set forth in the Bank Holding Company Act.” If the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and the company are <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> (by virtue of any aspect of the definition), the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> counts all of the company's assets toward the asset limit, regardless of the co-owner <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s ownership share. Further, because the co-owner and the company are mutual <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> the company also would count all of the co-owner's assets towards its own asset limit. See comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.ii.C for discussion of the definition of “<ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-D" marker="D.">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the criterion in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</ref> for purposes of any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2016, for example, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>) had total assets of less than the applicable asset threshold on December 31, 2015. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that (together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>) did not meet the applicable asset threshold on December 31, 2015 satisfies this criterion for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2016 if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1, 2016 and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>) had total assets of less than the applicable asset threshold on December 31, 2014.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-E" marker="E.">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</ref>, the $2,000,000,000 asset threshold adjusts automatically each year based on the year-to-year change in the average of the Consumer Price Index for Urban Wage Earners and Clerical Workers, not seasonally adjusted, for each 12-month period ending in November, with rounding to the nearest million dollars. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will publish notice of the asset threshold each year by amending this comment. For historical purposes:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-E-1" marker="1.">
          <content>For calendar year 2013, the asset threshold was $2,000,000,000. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> that had total assets of less than $2,000,000,000 on December 31, 2012, satisfied this criterion for purposes of the exemption during 2013.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-E-2" marker="2.">
          <content>For calendar year 2014, the asset threshold was $2,028,000,000. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> that had total assets of less than $2,028,000,000 on December 31, 2013, satisfied this criterion for purposes of the exemption during 2014.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-iii-E-3" marker="3.">
          <content>For calendar year 2015, the asset threshold was $2,060,000,000. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> that had total assets of less than $2,060,000,000 on December 31, 2014, satisfied this criterion for purposes of any loan consummated in 2015 and, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s assets together with the assets of its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during calendar year 2014 were less than that amount, for purposes of any loan consummated in 2016 for which the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received before April 1, 2016.</content></interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- ii. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Exception for certain accounts.</title>
      <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2016, are not counted for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. For applications received on and after January 1, 2016, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35 (b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, do not qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2016, still qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions for which they received applications on or after January 1, 2016, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, and they otherwise qualify under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- iii. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iv), paragraphs 1 and 2 are revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Requirements for “rural” or “underserved” status.</title>
      <content>An area is considered to be “rural” or “underserved” during a calendar year for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> if it satisfies either the definition for “rural” or the definition for “underserved” in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s extensions of <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens on properties located in such areas are considered in determining whether the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies the condition in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>. See comment <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">35(b)(2)(iii)-1</ref>.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, an area is rural during a calendar year if it is: A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area; or a census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> using the latest decennial census of the United States. Metropolitan statistical areas and micropolitan statistical areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref>, “adjacent” has the meaning applied by the USDA-ERS in determining a county's UIC; as so applied, “adjacent” entails a county not only being physically contiguous with a metropolitan statistical area but also meeting certain minimum population commuting patterns. A county is a “rural” area if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx. A county for which there is no currently applicable UIC (because the county has been created since the USDA-ERS last categorized counties) is a rural area only if all counties from which the new county's land was taken are themselves rural under currently applicable UICs.</content></interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref>, an area is underserved during a calendar year if, according to Home Mortgage Disclosure Act (HMDA) data for the preceding calendar year, it is a county in which no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, five or more times on properties in the county. Specifically, a county is an “underserved” area if, in the applicable calendar year's public HMDA aggregate dataset, no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> have reported five or more first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, with HMDA geocoding that places the properties in that county. For purposes of this determination, because only <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> are counted, all first-lien originations (and only first-lien originations) reported in the HMDA data are counted except those for which the owner-occupancy status is reported as “Not owner-occupied” (HMDA code 2), the property type is reported as “Multifamily” (HMDA code 3), the applicant's or co-applicant's race is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 7), or the applicant's or co-applicant's sex is reported as “Not applicable” (HMDA code 4). The most recent HMDA data are available at http://www.ffiec.gov/hmda.</content></interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-iii-A" marker="A.">
          <content>Each calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> applies the “underserved” area test and the “rural” area test to each county in the United States. If a county satisfies either test, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will include the county on a published list of counties that are rural or underserved as defined by § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref> or § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref> for a particular calendar year, even if the county contains census blocks that are designated by the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> as urban. To facilitate compliance with appraisal requirements in § <ref target="1026-35-c" reftype="internal">1026.35(c)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> also creates a list of those counties that are rural under the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s definition without regard to whether the counties are underserved. To the extent that U.S. territories are treated by the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> as counties and are neither metropolitan statistical areas nor micropolitan statistical areas adjacent to metropolitan statistical areas, such territories will be included on these lists as rural areas in their entireties. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will post on its public Web site the applicable lists for each calendar year by the end of that year and publish such lists in the Federal Register, to assist <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> in ascertaining the availability to them of the exemption during the following year. Any county that the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> includes on its published lists of counties that are rural or underserved under the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s definitions for a particular year is deemed to qualify as a rural or underserved area for that calendar year for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, even if the county contains census blocks that are designated by the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> as urban. A property located in such a listed county is deemed to be located in a rural or underserved area, even if the census block in which the property is located is designated as urban.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-iii-B" marker="B.">
          <content>A property is deemed to be in a rural or underserved area according to the definitions in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref> during a particular calendar year if it is identified as such by an automated tool provided on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site. A printout or electronic copy from the automated tool provided on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site designating a particular property as being in a rural or underserved area may be used as “evidence of compliance” that a property is in a rural or underserved area, as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">(B)</ref>, for purposes of the record retention requirements in § <ref target="1026-25" reftype="internal">1026.25</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-iii-C" marker="C.">
          <content>The U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> may provide on its public Web site an automated address search tool that specifically indicates if a property is located in an urban area for purposes of the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s most recent delineation of urban areas. For any calendar year that began after the date on which the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> announced its most recent delineation of urban areas, a property is deemed to be in a rural area if the search results provided for the property by any such automated address search tool available on the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site do not designate the property as being in an urban area. A printout or electronic copy from such an automated address search tool available on the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site designating a particular property as not being in an urban area may be used as “evidence of compliance” that the property is in a rural area, as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, for purposes of the record retention requirements in § <ref target="1026-25" reftype="internal">1026.25</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-iii-D" marker="D.">
          <content>For a given calendar year, a property qualifies for a safe harbor if any of the enumerated safe harbors affirms that the property is in a rural or underserved area or not in an urban area. For example, the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s automated address search tool may indicate a property is in an urban area, but the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s rural or underserved counties list indicates the property is in a rural or underserved county. The property in this example is in a rural or underserved area because it qualifies under the safe harbor for the rural or underserved counties list. The lists of counties published by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, the automated tool on its public Web site, and the automated address search tool available on the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site, are not the exclusive means by which a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can demonstrate that a property is in a rural or underserved area as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">(B)</ref>. However, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> are required to retain “evidence of compliance” in accordance with § <ref target="1026-25" reftype="internal">1026.25</ref>, including determinations of whether a property is in a rural or underserved area as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">(B)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
      <content>An area is considered “rural” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available UIC designations by the USDA-ERS and the most recent available delineations of urban areas by the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> that are available at the beginning of the calendar year. These designations and delineations are updated by the USDA-ERS and the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> respectively once every ten years. As an example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in Census Block X that is located in County Y during calendar year 2017. As of January 1, 2017, the most recent UIC designations were published in the second quarter of 2013, and the most recent delineation of urban areas was announced in the Federal Register in 2012, see U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, Qualifying Urban Areas for the 2010 Census, 77 FR 18652 (Mar. 27, 2012). To determine whether County Y is rural under the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s definition during calendar year 2017, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can use USDA-ERS's 2013 UIC designations. If County Y is not rural, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can use the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s 2012 delineation of urban areas to determine whether Census Block X is rural and is therefore a “rural” area for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
      <content>A county is considered an “underserved” area for a given calendar year based on the most recent available HMDA data. For example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in County Y during calendar year 2016, and the most recent HMDA data are for calendar year 2015, published in the third quarter of 2016. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> will use the 2015 HMDA data to determine “underserved” area status for County Y in calendar year 2016 for the purposes of qualifying for the “rural or underserved” exemption for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> consummated in calendar year 2017 or for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2018 for which the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received before April 1, 2018.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- B. Under Section 1026.36 Prohibited Acts or Practices and Certain Requirements for Credit Secured by a Dwelling, subheading 36(a) Definitions, paragraph 1.i.A. 3 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-3">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-a-Interp-1-i-A-3" marker="3.">
      <content>Assisting a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in obtaining or applying for <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> by advising on particular <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> terms that are or may be available to that <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> based on the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s financial characteristics, filling out an <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> form, preparing <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> packages (such as a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> or pre-approval <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> or supporting documentation), or collecting <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> and supporting information on behalf of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to submit to a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. A <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> who, acting on behalf of a <ref target="1026-36-a-1-i" reftype="term">loan originator</ref> or <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, collects information or verifies information provided by the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, such as by asking the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> for documentation to support the information the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> provided or for the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s authorization to obtain supporting documents from third parties, is not collecting<ref target="1026-36-a-Interp-4-i" reftype="internal"> informat</ref>ion on behalf of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>. See also comment 36(a)-4.i through .iv with respect to applicat<ref target="1026-36-a-Interp-1-v" reftype="internal">ion-relat</ref>ed administrative and clerical tasks and comment 36(a)-1.v with respect to third-party advisors.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- i. Under Paragraph 43(e)(5), paragraphs 4 and 8 are revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-e-5-Interp-4">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-e-5-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title type="keyterm">Creditor qualifications.</title>
      <content>To be eligible to make qualified mortgages under § <ref target="1026-43-e-5" reftype="internal">1026.43(e)(5)</ref>, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must satisfy the requirements stated in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">(C)</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref> requires that, during the preceding calendar year, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, during either of the two preceding calendar years, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> together extended no more than 2,000 <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>. Section <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</ref> requires that, as of the preceding December 31st, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, as of either of the two preceding December 31sts, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended, during the applicable period, <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, together, had total assets of less than $2 billion, adjusted annually by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> for inflation.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-e-5-Interp-8">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-e-5-Interp-8" marker="8.">
      <title type="keyterm">Transfer to another qualifying creditor.</title>
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-43-e-5-ii-B" reftype="internal">1026.43(e)(5)(ii)(B)</ref>, a qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-e-5" reftype="internal">1026.43(e)(5)</ref> may be sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred at any time to another <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that meets the requirements of § <ref target="1026-43-e-5-i-D" reftype="internal">1026.43(e)(5)(i)(D)</ref>. That section requires that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> together with all its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, extended no more than 2,000 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>; and have, together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens, total assets less than $2 billion (as adjusted for inflation). These tests are assessed based on transactions and assets from the calendar year preceding the current calendar year or from either of the two calendar years preceding the current calendar year if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year. A qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-e-5" reftype="internal">1026.43(e)(5)</ref> transferred to a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that meets these criteria would retain its qualified mortgage status even if it is transferred less than three years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- ii. Under Paragraph 43(f)(1)(vi), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1-vi" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)(vi)</ref>, to make a qualified mortgage that provides for a balloon payment, the creditor must satisfy three criteria that are also required under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>, <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">(B)</ref> and <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">(C)</ref>, which require:</content>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year or during either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was recei<ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">ved before Ap</ref>ril 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended over 50 percent of its total first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, on properties that are located in areas that are designated either “rural” or “underserved,” as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, to satisfy the requirement of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>. Pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, an area is considered to be rural if it is: A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area, nor a micropolitan statistical area adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget; or a census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> using the latest decennial census of the United States. An area is considered to be underserved during a calendar year if, according to HMDA data for the preceding calendar year, it is a county in which no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens on properties in the county five or more times.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-A" marker="A.">
        <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> determines annually which counties in the United States are rural or underserved as defined by § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref> or § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref> and publishes on its public Web site lists of those counties to assist <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> in determining whether they meet the criterion at § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may also use an automated tool provided on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site to determine whether specific properties are located in areas that qualify as “rural” or “underserved” according to the definitions in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref> for a particular calendar year. In addition, the U.S. Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> may also provide on its public Web site an automated address search tool that specifically indicates if a property address is located in an urban area for purposes of the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s most recent delineation of urban areas. For any calendar year that begins after the date on which the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> announced its most recent delineation of urban areas, a property is located in an area that qualifies as “rural” according to the definitions in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref> if the search results provided for the property by any such automated address search tool available on the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site do not identify the property as being in an urban area.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-B" marker="B.">
        <content>For example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended 100 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2016 and 90 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> during 2017, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this element of the exception for any transaction consummated during 2018 if at least 46 of its 2017 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> are secured by properties that are located in one or more counties on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s lists for 2017 or are located in one or more census blocks that are not in an urban area, as defined by the Census <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-C" marker="C.">
        <content>Alternatively, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s 2017 transactions do not meet the over 50 percent test (see comment <ref target="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i" reftype="internal">43(f)(1)(vi)-1.i</ref>), the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies this criterion for any transaction consummated during 2018 for which it received the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> before April 1, 2018, if at least 51 of its 2016 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> are secured by properties that are located in one or more counties on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s lists for 2016 or are located in one or more census blocks that are not in an urban area.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-ii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, during either <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">of the two pr</ref>eceding calendar years, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> extended no more than 2,000 <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by first liens, that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, to satisfy the requirement of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-iii">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
      <content>As of the preceding December 31st, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, as of either of the two preceding December 31st, the creditor and <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens, together, had total assets that do not exceed the applicable asset threshold established by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>, to satisfy the requirement of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-C" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(C)</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> publishes notice of the asset threshold each year by amending comment 35(b)(2)(iii)-1.iii.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- iii. Under Paragraph 43(f)(2), paragraph 2 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-2-Interp-2">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title type="keyterm">Application to subsequent transferees.</title>
      <content>The exceptions contained in § <ref target="1026-43-f-2" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(2)</ref> apply not only to an initial sale, assignment, or other transfer by the originating <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> but to subsequent sales, assignments, and other transfers as well. For example, assume <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditor</ref> A originates a qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)</ref>. Six months after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditor</ref> A sells the qualified mortgage to <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditor</ref> B pursuant to § <ref target="1026-43-f-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(2)(ii)</ref> and the loan retains its qualified mortgage status because <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditor</ref> B complies with the conditions relating to operating in rural or underserved areas, asset size, and number of transactions. If <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditor</ref> B sells the qualified mortgage, it will lose its qualified mortgage status under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1) </ref>unless the sale qualifies for one of the § <ref target="1026-43-f-2" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(2)</ref> exceptions for sales three or more years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>, to another qualifying institution, as required by supervisory action, or pursuant to a merger or acquisition.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- iv. Under Paragraph 43(f)(2)(ii), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-2-ii-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title type="keyterm">Transfer to another qualifying creditor.</title>
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-43-f-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(2)(ii)</ref>, a balloon-payment qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)</ref> may be sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred at any time to another <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that meets the requirements of § <ref target="1026-43-f-1-vi" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)(vi)</ref>. That section requires that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>: (1) Extended over 50 percent of its total first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, on properties located in rural or underserved areas; (2) together with all <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, extended no more than 2,000 first-lien <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred by the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> to another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>, or that were subject at the time of <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref> to a commitment to be acquired by another <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>; and (3) have, together with its <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> that regularly extended <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens, total assets less than $2 billion (as adjusted for inflation). These tests are assessed based on transactions and assets from the calendar year preceding the current calendar year or from either of the two calendar years preceding the current calendar year if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year. A balloon-payment qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)</ref> transferred to a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that meets these criteria would retain its qualified mortgage status even if it is transferred less than three years after <ref target="1026-2-a-13" reftype="term">consummation</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
