<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2017-10-19</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>Z</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-18901</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2017-10-19</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/10/19/2016-18901/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation-x</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2017-15764" rightDocumentNumber="2016-18901">
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-2-a-11">
    <paragraph label="1026-2-a-11" marker="(11)">
      <content><def term="consumer">Consumer</def> means a cardholder or natural <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> to whom <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> is offered or extended. However, for purposes of rescission under §§ <ref target="1026-15" reftype="internal">1026.15</ref> and <ref target="1026-23" reftype="internal">1026.23</ref>, the term also includes a natural <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> in whose principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> a <ref target="1026-2-a-25" reftype="term">security interest</ref> is or will be retained or acquired, if that <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>'s ownership interest in the <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> is or will be subject to the <ref target="1026-2-a-25" reftype="term">security interest</ref>.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-27" parent="1026-2-a">
    <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27" marker="(27)">
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i" marker="(i)">
        <content><def term="successor in interest">Successor in interest</def> means a person to whom an ownership interest in a dwelling securing a closed-end consumer credit transaction is transferred from a consumer, provided that the transfer is:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A transfer by devise, descent, or operation of law on the death of a joint tenant or tenant by the entirety;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A transfer to a relative resulting from the death of the consumer;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>A transfer where the spouse or children of the consumer become an owner of the property;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>A transfer resulting from a decree of a dissolution of marriage, legal separation agreement, or from an incidental property settlement agreement, by which the spouse of the consumer becomes an owner of the property; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-E" marker="(E)">
          <content>A transfer into an inter vivos trust in which the consumer is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a transfer of rights of occupancy in the property.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content><def term="confirmed successor in interest">Confirmed successor in interest</def> means a successor in interest once a servicer has confirmed the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-20-f" parent="1026-20" after="1026-20-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-20-f" marker="(f)">
      <title>Successor in interest.</title>
      <content>If, upon confirmation, a servicer provides a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the mortgage loan obligation with a written notice and acknowledgment form in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1) of this chapter, the servicer is not required to provide to the confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by paragraphs (c), (d), and (e) of this section unless and until the confirmed successor in interest either assumes the mortgage loan obligation under State law or has provided the servicer an executed acknowledgment in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv) of this chapter, that the confirmed successor in interest has not revoked.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-c-1">
    <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1" marker="(1)">
      <title>Payment processing.</title>
      <content>In connection with a closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>:</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-c-2">
    <paragraph label="1026-36-c-2" marker="(2)">
      <title>No pyramiding of late fees.</title>
      <content>In connection with a closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, a servicer shall not impose any late fee or delinquency charge for a payment if:</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-d-8-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-d-8-i" marker="(i)">
      <content>The length of the consumer's delinquency;</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-e-4-iii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>Mortgage loans voluntarily serviced by the servicer for a non-affiliate of the servicer and for which the servicer does not receive any compensation or fees.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-4-iii-D" parent="1026-41-e-3-iii">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-D" marker="(D)">
      <content>Transactions serviced by the servicer for a seller financer that meets all of the criteria identified in § 1026.36(a)(5).</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-6" parent="1026-41-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6" marker="(6)">
      <title>Charged-off loans.</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>A servicer is exempt from the requirements of this section for a mortgage loan if the servicer:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Has charged off the loan in accordance with loan-loss provisions and will not charge any additional fees or interest on the account; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>Provides, within 30 days of charge-off or the most recent periodic statement, a periodic statement, clearly and conspicuously labeled “Suspension of Statements &amp; Notice of Charge Off-Retain This Copy for Your Records.” The periodic statement must clearly and conspicuously explain that, as applicable, the mortgage loan has been charged off and the servicer will not charge any additional fees or interest on the account; the servicer will no longer provide the consumer a periodic statement for each billing cycle; the lien on the property remains in place and the consumer remains liable for the mortgage loan obligation and any obligations arising from or related to the property, which may include property taxes; the consumer may be required to pay the balance on the account in the future, for example, upon sale of the property; the balance on the account is not being canceled or forgiven; and the loan may be purchased, assigned, or transferred.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title>Resuming compliance.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>If a servicer fails at any time to treat a mortgage loan that is exempt under paragraph (e)(6)(i) of this section as charged off or charges any additional fees or interest on the account, the obligation to provide a periodic statement pursuant to this section resumes.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii-B" marker="(B)">
          <title>Prohibition on retroactive fees.</title>
          <content>A servicer may not retroactively assess fees or interest on the account for the period of time during which the exemption in paragraph (e)(6)(i) of this section applied.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-4(C)">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="6" label="1026-H-4(C)">
      <subject>H-4(C)—Variable-Rate Model Clauses</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p31" marker="">
        <content>This disclosure describes the features of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-i" reftype="term">adjustable-rate mortgage</ref> (ARM) program you are considering. Information on other ARM programs is available upon request.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p32" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate and Payment Are Determined</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p33" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will be based on [an index plus a margin] [a formula].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p34" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment will be based on the interest rate, loan balance, and <ref target="1026-43-b-6" reftype="term">loan term</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p35" marker="">
          <content>—[The interest rate will be based on (identification of index) plus our margin. Ask for our current interest rate and margin.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p36" marker="">
          <content>—[The interest rate will be based on (identification of formula). Ask us for our current interest rate.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p37" marker="">
          <content>—Information about the index [formula for rate adjustments] is published [can be found] ______.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p38" marker="">
          <content>—[The initial interest rate is not based on the (index) (formula) used to make later adjustments. Ask us for the amount of current interest rate discounts.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate Can Change</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p39" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate can change (frequency).</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p40" marker="">
          <content>• [Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than __ percentage points at each adjustment.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p41" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase [or decrease] more than __ percentage points over the term of the loan.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4" marker="">
        <title>How Your Payment Can Change</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p42" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment can change (frequency) based on changes in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p43" marker="">
          <content>• [Your payment cannot increase more than (amount or percentage) at each adjustment.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p44" marker="">
          <content>• You will be notified in writing ____ days before the due date of a payment at a new level. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount, and loan balance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p45" marker="">
          <content>• [You will be notified once each year during which interest rate adjustments, but no payment adjustments, have been made to your loan. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount, and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p46" marker="">
          <content>• [For example, on a $10,000 [term] loan with an initial interest rate of ____ [(the rate shown in the interest rate column below for the year 19 ____)] [(in effect (month) (year)], the maximum amount that the interest rate can rise under this program is ____ percentage points, to ____%, and the monthly payment can rise from a first-year payment of $____ to a maximum of $____ in the _____ year. To see what your payments would be, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 would be: $60,000 ÷ $10,000 = 6; 6 × ____ = $____ per month.)]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p47" marker="">
        <title>Example</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p48" marker="">
          <content>The example below shows how your payments would have changed under this ARM program based on actual changes in the index from 1982 to 1996. This does not necessarily indicate how your index will change in the future.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p49" marker="">
          <content>The example is based on the following assumptions:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p50" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.036)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.036.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.036.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p51" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.037)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.037.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.037.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p52" marker="">
          <content>Note: To see what your payments would have been during that period, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, in 1996 the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 taken out in 1982 would be: $60,000÷$10,000=6; 6x____=$____per month.)</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-14">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="27" label="1026-H-14">
      <subject>H-14—Variable-Rate Mortgage Sample</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-p94" marker="">
        <content>This disclosure describes the features of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-i" reftype="term">adjustable-rate mortgage</ref> (ARM) program you are considering. Information on other ARM programs is available upon request.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate and Payment Are Determined</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p95" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will be based on an index rate plus a margin.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p96" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment will be based on the interest rate, loan balance, and <ref target="1026-43-b-6" reftype="term">loan term</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p97" marker="">
          <content>—The interest rate will be based on the weekly average yield on United States Treasury securities adjusted to a constant maturity of 1 year (your index), plus our margin. Ask us for our current interest rate and margin.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p98" marker="">
          <content>—Information about the index rate is published weekly in the Wall Street Journal.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p99" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will equal the index rate plus our margin unless your interest rate “caps” limit the amount of change in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate Can Change</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p100" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate can change yearly.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p101" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than 2 percentage points per year.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p102" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than 5 percentage points over the term of the loan.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11" marker="">
        <title>How Your Monthly Payment Can Change</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p103" marker="">
          <content>• Your monthly payment can increase or decrease substantially based on annual changes in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p104" marker="">
          <content>• [For example, on a $10,000, 30-year loan with an initial interest rate of 12.41 percent in effect in July 1996, the maximum amount that the interest rate can rise under this program is 5 percentage points, to 17.41 percent, and the monthly payment can rise from a first-year payment of $106.03 to a maximum of $145.34 in the fourth year. To see what your payment is, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 would be: $60,000 ÷ $10,000 = 6; 6 × 106.03 = $636.18 per month.)</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p105" marker="">
          <content>• You will be notified in writing 25 days before the annual payment adjustment may be made. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p106" marker="">
        <title>Example</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p107" marker="">
          <content>The example below shows how your payments would have changed under this ARM program based on actual changes in the index from 1982 to 1996. This does not necessarily indicate how your index will change in the future. The example is based on the following assumptions:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p108" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.046)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.046.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.046.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p109" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.047)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.047.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.047.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p110" marker="">
          <content>
            <callout type="note">
              <line>Note:</line>
              <line>To see what your payments would have been during that period, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, in 1996 the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 taken out in 1982 would be: $60,000÷$10,000=6; 6×$106.73=$640.38.)</line>
            </callout>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p111" marker="">
          <content>• [You will be notified at least 210, but no more than 240, days before first payment at the adjusted level is due after the initial interest rate adjustment of the loan. This notice will contain information about the adjustment, including the interest rate, payment amount, and loan balance.]
   </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p112" marker="">
          <content>[You will be notified at least 60, but no more than 120, days before first payment at the adjusted level is due after any interest rate adjustment resulting in a corresponding payment change. This notice will contain information about the adjustment, including the interest rate, payment amount, and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-30(C)">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="40" label="1026-H-30(C)">
      <subject>H-30(C) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for a Payment-Option Loan</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(C)-p7" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER14FE13.010-1)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER14FE13.010-1.png</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER14FE13.010-1.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-H-30(E)" parent="1026-H">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="42" label="1026-H-30(E)">
      <subject>H-30(E) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 7 or Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(E)-p1" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER19OC16.001)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.001.png</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.001.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-H-30(F)" parent="1026-H">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="43" label="1026-H-30(F)">
      <subject>H-30(F) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 12 or Chapter 13 Bankruptcy</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(F)-p1" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER19OC16.001)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.002.png</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.002.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4" parent="1026-2-a-11-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Successors in interest.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
        <title>Assumption of the mortgage loan obligation.</title>
        <content>A servicer may not require a confirmed successor in interest to assume the mortgage loan obligation to be considered a consumer for purposes of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41. If a successor in interest assumes a mortgage loan obligation under State law or is otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, the protections the successor in interest enjoys under this part are not limited to §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
        <title>Communications with confirmed successors in interest.</title>
        <content>Communications in compliance with this part to a confirmed successor in interest as defined in § 1026.2(a)(27)(ii) do not violate section 805(b) of the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) because consumer for purposes of FDCPA section 805 includes any person who meets the definition in this part of confirmed successor in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-iii" marker="iii.">
        <title>Treatment of transferor consumer.</title>
        <content>Even after a servicer's confirmation of a successor in interest, the servicer is still required to comply with all applicable requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref> with respect to the consumer who transferred an ownership interest to the successor in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-iv" marker="iv.">
        <title>Multiple notices unnecessary.</title>
        <content>Except as required by Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.36, a servicer is not required to provide to a confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 if the servicer is providing the same specific disclosure to another consumer on the account. For example, a servicer is not required to provide a periodic statement required by § 1026.41 to a confirmed successor in interest if the servicer is providing the same periodic statement to another consumer; a single statement may be sent in that billing cycle. If a servicer confirms more than one successor in interest, the servicer need not send any disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 to more than one of the confirmed successors in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-27-Interp" parent="1026-2-a-Interp" after="1026-2-a-25-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-Interp">
      <title>Paragraph 2(a)(27)</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp" target="1026-2-a-27-i">
        <title>2(a)(27)(i) Successor in interest</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Joint tenants and tenants by the entirety.</title>
          <content>If a consumer who has an ownership interest as a joint tenant or tenant by the entirety in a dwelling securing a closed-end consumer credit transaction dies, a surviving joint tenant or tenant by the entirety with a right of survivorship in the property is a successor in interest as defined in § 1026.2(a)(27)(i).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Beneficiaries of inter vivos trusts.</title>
          <content>In the event of a transfer into an inter vivos trust in which the consumer is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a transfer of rights of occupancy in the property, the beneficiaries of the inter vivos trust rather than the inter vivos trust itself are considered to be the successors in interest for purposes of § 1026.2(a)(27)(i). For example, assume Consumer A transfers her home into such an inter vivos trust for the benefit of her spouse and herself. As of the transfer date, Consumer A and her spouse are considered successors in interest and, upon confirmation, are consumers for purposes of certain provisions of this part. If the creditor has not released Consumer A from the loan obligation, Consumer A also remains a consumer more generally for purposes of this part.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-20-e-4-Interp-4" parent="1026-20-e-4-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-20-e-4-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Modifications of disclosures.</title>
      <content>The requirements of § 1026.20(e)(4) to provide the § 1026.20(e) disclosures with the headings, content, order, and format substantially similar to model form H-29 in appendix H to this part do not preclude creditors and servicers from modifying the disclosures to accommodate particular consumer circumstances or transactions not addressed by the form or from adjusting the statement required by § 1026.20(e)(2)(ii)(A), concerning consequences if the consumer fails to pay property costs, to the circumstances of the particular consumer.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-4" parent="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
      <content>If a loan contract has not been permanently modified but the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is the amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, regardless of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-5" parent="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title>Permanent loan modifications.</title>
      <content>If a loan contract has been permanently modified, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the modified loan contract.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-a-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-a-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title>Recipient of periodic statement.</title>
      <content>When two consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling subject to § 1026.41, the periodic statement may be sent to either one of them. For example, if spouses jointly own a home, the servicer need not send statements to both spouses; a single statement may be sent.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-c-Interp-5" parent="1026-41-c-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title>Permissible changes.</title>
      <content>Servicers may modify the sample forms for periodic statements provided in appendix H-30 of this part to remove language that could suggest liability under the mortgage loan agreement if such language is not applicable. For example, in the case of a confirmed successor in interest who has not assumed the mortgage loan obligation under State law and is not otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, a servicer may modify the forms to:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Use “this mortgage” or “the mortgage” instead of “your mortgage.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>Use “The payments on this mortgage are late” instead of “You are late on your mortgage payments.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>Use “This is the amount needed to bring the loan current” instead of “You must pay this amount to bring your loan current.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-d-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title>Close proximity.</title>
      <content>Section 1026.41(d) requires several disclosures to be provided in close proximity to one another. To meet this requirement, the items to be provided in close proximity must be grouped together, and set off from other groupings of items. This may be accomplished in a variety of ways, for example, by presenting the information in boxes, or by arranging the items on the document and including spacing between the groupings. Items in close proximity may not have any unrelated text between them. Text is unrelated if it does not explain or expand upon the required disclosures.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-d-Interp-4" parent="1026-41-d-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
      <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2), (3), and (5) regarding how payments were and will be applied must identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract, regardless of the temporary loss mitigation program.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-d-Interp-5" parent="1026-41-d-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title>First statement after exemption terminates.</title>
      <content>Section 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) requires the disclosure of the total sum of any fees or charges imposed since the last statement, the total of all payments received since the last statement, including a breakdown of how payments were applied, and a list of all transaction activity since the last statement. For purposes of the first periodic statement provided to the consumer following termination of an exemption under § 1026.41(e), the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) may be limited to account activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. For example, if mortgage loan payments are due on the first of each month and the servicer's exemption under § 1026.41(e) terminated on January 15, the first statement provided to the consumer after January 15 may be limited to the total sum of any fees or charges imposed, the total of all payments received, a breakdown of how the payments were applied, and a list of all transaction activity since January 1.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-d-1-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp" after="1026-41-d-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp" target="1026-41-d-1">
      <title>41(d)(1) Amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Acceleration.</title>
        <content>If the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan. The periodic statement must be accurate when provided and should indicate, if applicable, that the amount due is accurate only for a specified period of time. For example, the statement may include language such as “as of [date]” or “good through [date]” and provide an amount due that will reinstate the loan as of that date or good through that date, respectively.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
        <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) may identify either the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program or the amount due according to the loan contract.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Permanent loan modifications.</title>
        <content>If the loan contract has been permanently modified, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must identify only the amount due under the modified loan contract.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-d-2-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp" after="1026-41-d-1-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp" target="1026-41-d-2">
     <title>41(d)(2) Explanation of amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Acceleration.</title>
        <content>If the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must list both the reinstatement amount that is disclosed as the amount due and the accelerated amount but not the monthly payment amount that would otherwise be required under § 1026.41(d)(2)(i). The periodic statement must also include an explanation that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan through the “as of [date]” or “good through [date],” as applicable, along with any special instructions for submitting the payment. The explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement. The explanation may include related information, such as a statement that the amount disclosed is “not a payoff amount.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
        <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program and the amount due identifies the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must include both the amount due according to the loan contract and the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. The statement must also include an explanation that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount because of the temporary loss mitigation program. The explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-d-8-Interp" parent="1026-41-d-Interp" after="1026-41-d-4-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp" target="1026-41-d-8">
      <title>41(d)(8) Delinquency information.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Length of delinquency.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(d)(8), the length of a consumer's delinquency is measured as of the date of the periodic statement or the date of the written notice provided under § 1026.41(e)(3)(iv). A consumer's delinquency begins on the date an amount sufficient to cover a periodic payment of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, becomes due and unpaid, even if the consumer is afforded a period after the due date to pay before the servicer assesses a late fee. A consumer is delinquent if one or more periodic payments of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, are due and unpaid.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Application of funds.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(d)(8), if a servicer applies payments to the oldest outstanding periodic payment, a payment by a delinquent consumer advances the date the consumer's delinquency began. For example, assume a mortgage loan obligation under which a consumer's periodic payment is due on the first of each month. A consumer fails to make a payment on January 1 but makes a periodic payment on February 3. The servicer applies the payment received on February 3 to the outstanding January payment. On February 4, the consumer is three days delinquent, and the next periodic statement should disclose the length of the consumer's delinquency using February 2 as the first day of delinquency.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <!-- it's hard to insert a heading right into the middle of the flow as the notice demands -->
  <!-- so instead we'll just mod the entire paragraph from the previous reg and add the title in -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-Interp">
      <title>41(e) Exemptions.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp" target="1026-41-e-3">
        <title>41(e)(3) Coupon book exemption.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Fixed rate.</title>
          <content>For guidance on the meaning of “fixed rate” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-41-e-3" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(3)</ref>, see § <ref target="1026-18-s-7-iii" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)(7)(iii)</ref> and its commentary.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Coupon book.</title>
          <content>A coupon book is a booklet provided to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> with a page for each <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref> during a set period of time (often covering one year). These pages are designed to be torn off and returned to the servicer with a payment for each <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref>. Additional information about the loan is often included on or inside the front or back cover, or on filler pages in the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Information location.</title>
          <content>The information required by paragraph <ref target="1026-41-e-3-ii" reftype="internal">(e)(3)(ii)</ref> need not be provided on each coupon, but should be provided somewhere in the coupon book. Such information could be located, e.g., on or inside the front or back cover, or on filler pages in the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title type="keyterm">Outstanding principal balance.</title>
          <content>Paragraph <ref target="1026-41-e-3-ii-A" reftype="internal">(e)(3)(ii)(A)</ref> requires the information listed in paragraph <ref target="1026-41-d-7" reftype="internal">(d)(7)</ref> to be included in the coupon book. Paragraph <ref target="1026-41-d-7-i" reftype="internal">(d)(7)(i)</ref> requires the disclosure of the outstanding principal balance. If the servicer makes use of a coupon book and the exemption in § <ref target="1026-41-e-3" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(3)</ref>, the servicer need only disclose the principal balance at the beginning of the time period covered by the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-Interp">
        <title>41(e)(4) Small servicers.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-4-ii">
          <title>41(e)(4)(ii) Small servicer defined.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Mortgage loans considered.</title>
            <content>Pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.41(a)(1)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> considered in determining status as a small servicer are closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, subject to the exclusions in § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Services, together with affiliates, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>Services, together with <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans. To qualify as a small servicer, under § <ref target="CFR:12-1024-31" reftype="external">1026.41(e)(4)(</ref>ii)(A), a servicer must service, together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, for all of which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee. There are two elements to satisfying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref>. First, a servicer, together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, must service 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans. Second, a servicer must service only mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee. To be the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee of a mortgage loan, the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) must either currently own the mortgage loan or must have been the entity to which the mortgage loan obligation was initially payable (that is, the originator of the mortgage loan). A servicer is not a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> if it services any mortgage loans for which the servicer or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee (that is, for which the servicer or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> is not the owner or was not the originator). The following two examples demonstrate circumstances in which a servicer would not qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> because it did not meet both requirements under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> for determining a servicer's status as a small servicer:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>A servicer services 3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> owns or originated. An <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the servicer services 4,000 other <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> owns or originated. Because the number of <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> serviced by a servicer is determined by counting the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> serviced by a servicer together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, both of these servicers are considered to be servicing 7,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> and neither servicer is a small servicer.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>A service services 3,100 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>—3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it owns or originated and 100 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it neither owns nor originated, but for which it owns the mortgage servicing rights. The servicer is not a small servicer because it services <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> for which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee, notwithstanding that the servicer services fewer than 5,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Master servicer and subservicing.</title>
              <content>A servicer that qualifies as a small servicer does not lose its small servicer status if it retains a subservicer, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.31, to service any of its <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. A subservicer can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption only if (1) the master servicer, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.31, is a small servicer and (2) the subservicer is a small servicer. A subservicer generally will not qualify as a small servicer because it does not own or did not originate the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it subservices—unless it is an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of a master servicer that qualifies as a small servicer. The following examples demonstrate the application of the small servicer exemption for different forms of servicing relationships:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
                <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union services 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it originated or owns. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union retains a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization, that is not an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, to subservice 1,000 of the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union is a small servicer and, thus, can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption for the 3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union services itself. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization is not a small servicer because it services <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it does not own or did not originate. Accordingly, the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization does not gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption and, thus, must comply with any applicable mortgage servicing requirements for the 1,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it subservices.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>A bank holding company, through a lender subsidiary, owns or originated 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. All mortgage servicing rights for the 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> are owned by a wholly owned master servicer subsidiary. Servicing for the 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> is conducted by a wholly owned subservicer subsidiary. The bank holding company controls all of these subsidiaries and, thus, they are <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> of the bank holding company pursuant 12 CFR <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(2)</ref>. Because the master servicer and subservicer service 5,000 or fewer <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, and because all the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> are owned or originated by an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, the master servicer and the subservicer both qualify for the small servicer exemption for all 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>A nonbank servicer services 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it originated or owns. The servicer retains a “component servicer” to assist it with servicing functions. The component servicer is not engaged in “servicing” as defined in 12 CFR 1024.2; that is, the component servicer does not receive any scheduled periodic payments from a borrower pursuant to the terms of any <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loan</ref>, including amounts for <ref target="1026-35-b-3-iv" reftype="term">escrow accounts</ref>, and does not make the payments to the owner of the loan or other third parties of principal and interest and such other payments with respect to the amounts received from the borrower as may be required pursuant to the terms of the mortgage servicing loan documents or servicing contract. The component servicer is not a subservicer pursuant to 12 CFR 1024.31 because it is not engaged in servicing, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.2. The nonbank servicer is a small servicer and, thus, can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption with regard to all 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it services.</content></interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
              <title type="keyterm">Nonprofit entity that services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>To qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>, a servicer must be a nonprofit entity that services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities, for all of which the servicer or an associated nonprofit entity is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. There are two elements to satisfying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>. First, a nonprofit entity must service 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities. For each associated nonprofit entity, the small servicer determination is made separately, without consideration of the number of loans serviced by another associated nonprofit entity. Second, a nonprofit entity must service only mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. To be the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) must have been the entity to which the mortgage loan obligation was initially payable (that is, the originator of the mortgage loan). A nonprofit entity is not a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> if it services any mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (that is, for which the servicer or an associated nonprofit entity was not the originator). The first of the following two examples demonstrates circumstances in which a nonprofit entity would qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> because it meets both requirements for determining a nonprofit entity's status as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>. The second example demonstrates circumstances in which a nonprofit entity would not qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> because it does not meet both requirements under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>.</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Nonprofit entity A services 3,000 of its own mortgage loans, and 1,500 mortgage loans on behalf of associated nonprofit entity B. All 4,500 mortgage loans were originated by A or B. Associated nonprofit entity C services 2,500 mortgage loans, all of which it originated. Because the number of mortgage loans serviced by a nonprofit entity is determined by counting the number of mortgage loans serviced by the nonprofit entity (including mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities) but not counting any mortgage loans serviced by an associated nonprofit entity, A and C are both small servicers.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>A nonprofit entity services 4,500 mortgage loans—3,000 mortgage loans it originated, 1,000 mortgage loans originated by associated nonprofit entities, and 500 mortgage loans neither it nor an associated nonprofit entity originated. The nonprofit entity is not a small servicer because it services mortgage loans for which neither it nor an associated nonprofit entity is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, notwithstanding that it services fewer than 5,000 mortgage loans.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-4-iii">
          <title>41(e)(4)(iii) Small servicer determination.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Loans obtained by merger or acquisition.</title>
            <content>Any mortgage loans obtained by a servicer or an affiliate as part of a merger or acquisition, or as part of the acquisition of all of the assets or liabilities of a branch office of a creditor, should be considered mortgage loans for which the servicer or an affiliate is the creditor to which the mortgage loan is initially payable. A branch office means either an office of a depository institution that is approved as a branch by a Federal or State supervisory agency or an office of a for-profit mortgage lending institution (other than a depository institution) that takes applications from the public for mortgage loans.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Timing for small servicer exemption.</title>
            <content>The following examples demonstrate when a servicer either is considered or is no longer considered a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> and (C):</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on October 1, and services more than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer would no longer be considered a small servicer on January 1 of the following year and would have to comply with any requirements from which it is no longer exempt as a small servicer on April 1 of the following year.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on February 1, and services more than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer would no longer be considered a small servicer on January 1 of the following year and would have to comply with any requirements from which it is no longer exempt as a small servicer on that same January 1.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on February 1, but services fewer than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer is considered a small servicer for the following year.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage loans not considered in determining whether a servicer is a small servicer.</title>
          <content>Mortgage loans that are not considered pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref> in applying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> are not considered either for determining whether a servicer (together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>) services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans or whether a servicer is servicing only mortgage loans that it (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) owns or originated. For example, assume a servicer services 5,400 mortgage loans. Of these mortgage loans, the servicer owns or originated 4,800 mortgage loans, voluntarily services 300 mortgage loans that neither it (nor an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) owns or originated and for which the servicer does not receive any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> or fees, and services 300 <ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term">reverse mortgage transactions</ref>. The voluntarily serviced mortgage loans and reverse mortgage loans are not considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A)</ref>. Thus, because only the 4,800 mortgage loans owned or originated by the servicer are considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer, the servicer satisfies § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> with regard to all 5,400 mortgage loans it services.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage loans not considered in determining whether a nonprofit entity is a small servicer.</title>
          <content>Mortgage loans that are not considered pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref> in applying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> are not considered either for determining whether a nonprofit entity services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities, or whether a nonprofit entity is servicing only mortgage loans that it or an associated nonprofit entity originated. For example, assume a servicer that is a nonprofit entity services 5,400 mortgage loans. Of these mortgage loans, the nonprofit entity originated 2,800 mortgage loans and associated nonprofit entities originated 2,000 mortgage loans. The nonprofit entity receives <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for servicing the loans originated by associated nonprofits. The nonprofit entity also voluntarily services 600 mortgage loans that were originated by an entity that is not an associated nonprofit entity, and receives no <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> or fees for servicing these loans. The voluntarily serviced mortgage loans are not considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer. Thus, because only the 4,800 mortgage loans originated by the nonprofit entity or associated nonprofit entities are considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer, the servicer satisfies § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> with regard to all 5,400 mortgage loans it services.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
          <title type="keyterm">Limited role of voluntarily serviced mortgage loans.</title>
          <content>Reverse mortgages and mortgage loans secured by <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>' interests in timeshare plans, in addition to not being considered in determining small servicer qualification, are also exempt from the requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>. In contrast, although voluntarily serviced mortgage loans, as defined by § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A)</ref>, are likewise not considered in determining small servicer status, they are not exempt from the requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>. Thus, a servicer that does not qualify as a small servicer would not have to provide periodic statements for reverse mortgages and timeshare plans because they are exempt from the rule, but would have to provide periodic statements for mortgage loans it voluntarily services.</content></interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5">
        <title>41(e)(5) Consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Commencing a case.</title>
          <content>The requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref> do not apply once a petition is filed under Title 11 of the United States Code, commencing a case in which the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> is a debtor.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Obligation to resume sending periodic statements.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
            <content>With respect to any portion of the mortgage debt that is not discharged, a servicer must resume sending periodic statements in compliance with § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref> within a reasonably prompt time after the next payment due date that follows the earliest of any of three potential outcomes in the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s bankruptcy case: the case is dismissed, the case is closed, or the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> receives a discharge under 11 U.S.C. 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328. However, this requirement to resume sending periodic statements does not require a servicer to communicate with a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> in a manner that would be inconsistent with applicable bankruptcy law or a court order in a bankruptcy case. To the extent permitted by such law or court order, a servicer may adapt the requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref> in any manner believed necessary.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>The periodic statement is not required for any portion of the mortgage debt that is discharged under applicable provisions of the U.S. Bankruptcy Code. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s bankruptcy case is revived—for example if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case, reopens the case, or revokes a discharge—the servicer is again exempt from the requirement in § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Joint obligors.</title>
          <content>When two or more <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> are joint obligors with primary liability on a closed-end <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> subject to § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>, the exemption in § <ref target="1026-41-e-5" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)</ref> applies if any of the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref> is in bankruptcy. For example, if a husband and wife jointly own a home, and the husband files for bankruptcy, the servicer is exempt from providing periodic statements to both the husband and the wife.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change label="1026-41-e-5-Interp" operation="modified">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5">
      <title>41(e)(5) Certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Consumer's representative.</title>
        <content>If an agent of the consumer, such as the consumer's bankruptcy counsel, submits a request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii), the request is deemed to be submitted by the consumer.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Multiple requests.</title>
        <content>A consumer's most recent written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) that the service cease or continue, as applicable, providing a periodic statement or coupon book determines whether the exemption in § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) applies.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Effective upon receipt.</title>
        <content>A consumer's written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) is effective as of the date of receipt by the servicer.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Bankruptcy case revived.</title>
        <content>If a consumer's bankruptcy case is revived, for example, if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case or reopens a case, § 1026.41(e)(5) may apply again, including the timing requirements in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-5-i-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i">
      <title>41(e)(5)(i) Exemption.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Multiple obligors.</title>
        <content>When two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41, § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) applies if any one of the consumers meets its criteria. For example, assume that two spouses jointly own a home and are primary obligors on the mortgage loan. One spouse files for chapter 13 bankruptcy and has a bankruptcy plan that provides for surrendering the dwelling that secures the mortgage loan. In part, § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) exempts the servicer from providing a periodic statement with regard to that mortgage loan, unless one of the spouses requests in writing that the servicer provide a periodic statement or coupon book pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(ii). If either spouse, including the one who is not a debtor in bankruptcy, submits a written request to receive a periodic statement or coupon book, the servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for that mortgage loan account.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2">
      <title>Paragraph 41(e)(5)(i)(B)(2).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Bankruptcy plan.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(2), bankruptcy plan refers to the consumer's most recently filed bankruptcy plan under the applicable provisions of title 11 of the United States Code, regardless of whether the court overseeing the consumer's bankruptcy case has confirmed or approved the plan.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4">
      <title>Paragraph 41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Statement of intention.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4), the statement of intention refers to the consumer's most recently filed statement of intention. For example, if a consumer files a statement of intention on June 1 identifying an intent to surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan but files an amended statement of intention on June 15 identifying an intent to retain the dwelling, the consumer's June 15 statement of intention is the relevant filing for purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-5-ii-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-ii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-ii">
      <title>41(e)(5)(ii) Reaffirmation or consumer request to receive statement or coupon book.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Form of periodic statement or coupon book.</title>
        <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-5-ii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)(ii)</ref> generally requires a servicer, notwithstanding § 1026.41(e)(5)(i), to resume providing a periodic statement or coupon book if the consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan or any consumer on the mortgage loan requests in writing that the servicer provide a periodic statement or coupon book. Whether a servicer provides a periodic statement or coupon book as modified by § 1026.41(f) or an unmodified periodic statement or coupon book depends on whether or not § 1026.41(f) applies to that mortgage loan at that time. For example, § 1026.41(f) does not apply with respect to a mortgage loan once the consumer has reaffirmed personal liability; therefore, following a consumer's reaffirmation, a servicer generally would provide a periodic statement or coupon book that complies with § 1026.41 but without the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f). See comment 41(f)-6. Section 1026.41(f) does apply, however, with respect to a mortgage loan following a consumer's written request to receive a periodic statement or coupon book, so long as any consumer on the mortgage loan remains in bankruptcy or has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan; accordingly, following that written request, a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book that includes the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-5-iv-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-Interp">
      <title>41(e)(5)(iv) Timing of compliance following transition.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-A">
        <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(A) Triggering events for transitioning to modified and unmodified periodic statements.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Section 1026.41(f) becomes applicable or ceases to apply.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-5-iv" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)(iv)</ref> sets forth the time period in which a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for the first time after a mortgage loan either becomes subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) or ceases to be subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f). A mortgage loan becomes subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) when, for example, any consumer on the mortgage loan becomes a debtor in bankruptcy or discharges personal liability for the mortgage loan. A mortgage loan may cease to be subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) when, for example, the consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for a mortgage loan or the consumer's bankruptcy case is closed or dismissed without the consumer having discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan. See comment 41(f)-6.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-5-iv" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)(iv)</ref> sets forth the time period in which a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for the first time after a servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) with respect to a mortgage loan. A servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) with respect to a mortgage loan when, for example:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
            <content>The consumer's bankruptcy case is dismissed or closed without the consumer having discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>The consumer files an amended bankruptcy plan or statement of intention that provides, as applicable, for the maintenance of payments due under the mortgage loan and the payment of pre-petition arrearage or that the consumer will retain the dwelling securing the mortgage loan;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>A consumer makes a partial or periodic payment on the mortgage loan despite the consumer in bankruptcy having filed a statement of intention identifying an intent to surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan, thus making § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4) inapplicable;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-iv" marker="iv.">
            <content>The consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan; or</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-v" marker="v.">
            <content>The consumer submits a written request pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(ii) that the servicer resume providing a periodic statement or coupon book.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-B-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-B">
        <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(B) Transitional single-billing-cycle exemption.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <content>An exemption under § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv) applies for only the first billing cycle that occurs after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. If a servicer is required to provide a periodic statement or coupon book, the servicer must do so beginning with the next billing cycle in accordance with the timing provisions of § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-C">
        <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(C) Timing of first modified or unmodified statement or coupon book after transition.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Reasonably prompt time.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-5-iv-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C)</ref> requires that, when one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs, a servicer must provide the next periodic statement or coupon book by delivering or placing it in the mail within a reasonably prompt time after the next payment due date, or the end of any courtesy period for the payment's corresponding billing cycle, that is more than 14 days after the date on which the applicable event listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. Delivering, emailing, or placing the periodic statement or coupon book in the mail within four days after the payment due date or the end of the courtesy period generally would be considered reasonably prompt. See comment 41(b)-1.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Subsequent periodic statements or coupon books.</title>
          <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-5-iv-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C)</ref> applies to the timing of only the first periodic statement or coupon book a servicer provides after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. For subsequent billing cycles, a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book in accordance with the timing requirements of § 1026.41(a)(2) and (b), as applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Duplicate coupon books not required.</title>
          <content>With respect to coupon books, § 1026.41 requires a servicer to provide a new coupon book after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs only to the extent the servicer has not previously provided the consumer with a coupon book that covered the upcoming billing cycle.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-6-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp" after="1026-41-e-5-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp" target="1026-41-e-6">
      <title>41(e)(6) Charged-off loans.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Change in ownership.</title>
        <content>If a charged-off mortgage loan is subsequently purchased, assigned, or transferred, § 1026.39(b) requires a covered person, as defined in § 1026.39(a)(1), to provide mortgage transfer disclosures. See § 1026.39.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Change in servicing.</title>
        <content>A servicer may take advantage of the exemption in § 1026.41(e)(6)(i), subject to the requirements of that paragraph, and may rely on a prior servicer's provision to the consumer of a periodic statement pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(6)(i)(B) unless the servicer provided the consumer a periodic statement pursuant to § 1026.41(a).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-6-i-B-Interp" parent="1026-41-e-Interp" after="1026-41-e-6-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B-Interp" marker="1.">
      <title>Paragraph 41(e)(6)(i)(B).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Clearly and conspicuously.</title>
        <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-e-6-i-B" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(6)(i)(B)</ref> requires that the periodic statement be clearly and conspicuously labeled “Suspension of Statements &amp; Notice of Charge Off—Retain This Copy for Your Records” and that it clearly and conspicuously provide certain explanations to the consumer, as applicable, but no minimum type size or other technical requirements are imposed. The clear and conspicuous standard generally requires that disclosures be in a reasonably understandable form and readily noticeable to the consumer. See comment 41(c)-1.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp" target="1026-41-f">
      <title>41(f) Modified periodic statements and coupon books for certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Compliance after the bankruptcy case ends.</title>
        <content>Except as provided in § 1026.41(e)(5), § 1026.41(f) applies with regard to a mortgage loan for which any consumer with primary liability is a debtor in a case under title 11 of the United States Code. After the debtor exits bankruptcy, § 1026.41(f) continues to apply if the consumer has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan, but § 1026.41(f) does not apply if the consumer has reaffirmed personal liability for the mortgage loan or otherwise has not discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Terminology.</title>
        <content>With regard to a periodic statement provided under § 1026.41(f), a servicer may use terminology other than that found on the sample periodic statements in appendix H-30, so long as the new terminology is commonly understood. See comment 41(d)-3. For example, a servicer may take into account terminology appropriate for consumers in bankruptcy and refer to the “amount due” identified in § 1026.41(d)(1), as the “payment amount.” Similarly, a servicer may refer to an amount past due identified in § 1026.41(d)(2)(iii) as “past unpaid amount.” Additionally, a servicer may refer to the delinquency information required by § 1026.41(d)(8) as an “account history,” and to the amount needed to bring the loan current, referred to in § 1026.41(d)(8)(vi) as “the total payment amount needed to bring the account current,” as “unpaid amount.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Other periodic statement requirements continue to apply.</title>
        <content>The requirements of § 1026.41, including the content and layout requirements of § 1026.41(d), apply unless modified expressly by § 1026.41(e)(5) or (f). For example, the requirement under § 1026.41(d)(3) to disclose a past payment breakdown applies without modification with respect to a periodic statement provided to a consumer in bankruptcy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Further modifications.</title>
        <content>A periodic statement or coupon book provided under § 1026.41(f) may be modified as necessary to facilitate compliance with title 11 of the United States Code, the Federal Rules of Bankruptcy Procedure, court orders, and local rules, guidelines, and standing orders. For example, a periodic statement or coupon book may include additional disclosures or disclaimers not required under § 1026.41(f) but that are related to the consumer's status as a debtor in bankruptcy or that advise the consumer how to submit a written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1). See comment 41(f)(3)-1.ii for a discussion of the treatment of a bankruptcy plan that modifies the terms of the mortgage loan, such as by reducing the outstanding balance of the mortgage loan or altering the applicable interest rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Commencing compliance.</title>
        <content>A servicer must begin to provide a periodic statement or coupon book that complies with paragraph (f) of this section within the timeframe set forth in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-6" marker="6.">
        <title>Reaffirmation.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f), a consumer who has reaffirmed personal liability for a mortgage loan is not considered to be a debtor in bankruptcy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3">
      <title>41(f)(3) Chapter 12 and chapter 13 consumers.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Pre-petition payments and post-petition payments.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3), pre-petition payments are payments made to cure the consumer's pre-bankruptcy defaults, and post-petition payments are payments made to satisfy the mortgage loan's periodic payments as they come due after the bankruptcy case is filed. For example, assume a consumer is $3,600 in arrears as of the bankruptcy filing date on a mortgage loan requiring monthly periodic payments of $2,000. The consumer's most recently filed bankruptcy plan requires the consumer to make payments of $100 each month for 36 months to pay the pre-bankruptcy arrearage, and $2,000 each month to satisfy the monthly periodic payments. Assuming the consumer makes the payments according to the plan, the $100 payments are the pre-petition payments and the $2,000 payments are the post-petition payments for purposes of the disclosures required under § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>If a consumer is a debtor in a case under chapter 12 or if a consumer's bankruptcy plan modifies the terms of the mortgage loan, such as by reducing the outstanding balance of the mortgage loan or altering the applicable interest rate, the disclosures under § 1026.41(d)(1) and (2) and (f)(3)(ii) and (iii) may disclose either the amount payable under the original terms of the mortgage loan, the amount payable under the remaining secured portion of the adjusted mortgage loan, or a statement that the consumer should contact the trustee or the consumer's attorney with any questions about the amount payable. In such cases, the remaining disclosures under § 1026.41(d) or (f)(3), as applicable, may be limited to how payments are applied to the remaining secured portion of the adjusted mortgage loan.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Post-petition fees and charges.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3), post-petition fees and charges are those fees and charges imposed after the bankruptcy case is filed. To the extent that the court overseeing the consumer's bankruptcy case requires such fees and charges to be included as an amendment to a servicer's proof of claim, a servicer may include such fees and charges in the balance of the pre-petition arrearage under § 1026.41(f)(3)(v)(C) rather than treating them as post-petition fees and charges for purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>First statement after exemption terminates.</title>
        <content>Section § 1026.41(f)(3)(iii) through (v) requires, in part, the disclosure of certain information regarding account activity that has occurred since the last statement. For purposes of the first periodic statement provided to the consumer following termination of an exemption under § 1026.41(e), those disclosures regarding account activity that has occurred since the last statement may be limited to account activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. See comment 41(d)-5.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-41-f-3-ii">
      <title>41(f)(3)(ii) Amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Amount due.</title>
        <content>The amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) is not required to include any amounts other than post-petition payments the consumer is required to make under the terms of a bankruptcy plan, including any past due post-petition payments, and post-petition fees and charges that a servicer has imposed. The servicer is not required to include in the amount due any pre-petition payments due under a bankruptcy plan or other amounts payable pursuant to a court order. The servicer is not required to include in the amount due any post-petition fees and charges that the servicer has not imposed. A servicer that defers collecting a fee or charge until after complying with the Federal Rule of Bankruptcy Procedure 3002.1 procedures, and thus after a potential court determination on whether the fee or charge is allowed, is not required to disclose the fee or charge until complying with such procedures. However, a servicer may include in the amount due other amounts due to the servicer that are not post-petition payments or fees or charges, such as amounts due under an agreed order, provided those other amounts are also disclosed in the explanation of amount due and transaction activity.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3-iii">
      <title>41(f)(3)(iii) Explanation of amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Explanation of amount due.</title>
        <content>The explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) is not required to include any amounts other than the post-petition payments, including the amount of any past due post-petition payments and post-petition fees and charges that a servicer has imposed. Consistent with § 1026.41(d)(3)(i), the post-petition payments must be broken down by the amount, if any, that will be applied to principal, interest, and escrow. The servicer is not required to disclose, as part of the explanation of amount due, any pre-petition payments or the amount of the consumer's pre-bankruptcy arrearage. However, a servicer may identify other amounts due to the servicer provided those amounts are also disclosed in the amount due and transaction activity. See comment 41(d)-4.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3-v">
      <title>41(f)(3)(v) Pre-petition arrearage.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Pre-petition arrearage.</title>
        <content>If the pre-petition arrearage is subject to dispute, or has not yet been determined by the servicer, the periodic statement may include a statement acknowledging the unresolved amount of the pre-petition arrearage. A servicer may omit the information required by § 1026.41(f)(3)(v) from the periodic statement until such time as the servicer has had a reasonable opportunity to determine the amount of the pre-petition arrearage. The servicer may not omit the information required by § 1026.41(f)(3)(v) from the periodic statement after the date that the bankruptcy court has fixed for filing proofs of claim in the consumer's bankruptcy case.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-4-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp" target="1026-41-f-4">
      <title>41(f)(4) Multiple obligors.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Modified statements.</title>
        <content>When two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41, a servicer may send the periodic statement to any one of the primary obligors. See comment 41(a)-1. Section 1026.41(f)(4) provides that a servicer may provide a modified statement under § 1026.41(f), if applicable, to any or all of the primary obligors, even if a primary obligor to whom the servicer provides the modified statement is not a debtor in bankruptcy. The servicer need not provide an unmodified statement to any of the primary obligors. For example, assume that two spouses jointly own a home and are both primarily liable on the mortgage loan. One spouse files for chapter 13 bankruptcy, and that spouse's chapter 13 bankruptcy plan provides that the same spouse will retain the home by making pre-petition and post-petition payments. The servicer complies with § 1026.41 by providing the modified periodic statement under § 1026.41(f) to either spouse.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Obligors in different chapters of bankruptcy.</title>
        <content>If two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41 and are debtors under different chapters of bankruptcy, only one of which is subject to § 1026.41(f)(3), a servicer may, but need not, include the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(3). For example, assume one joint obligor is a debtor in a case under chapter 7 and another joint obligor is a debtor in a case under chapter 13, and that the servicer is not exempt from the periodic statement requirement under § 1026.41(e)(5). The periodic statement or coupon book is subject to the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(1) and (2), but the servicer may determine whether it is appropriate to include the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
  <analysis>
  <analysisSection target="1026-36-c-1-iii" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>36(c)(1)(iii) Non-Conforming Payments</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.36(c) includes requirements relating to prompt crediting of payments, pyramiding of late fees, and payoff statements. In the proposal, the Bureau solicited comment on whether certain parts of § 1026.36(c) should apply with respect to successors in interest even if the servicer has not confirmed the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling. The Bureau received a variety of comments on this issue, including some that asked the Bureau to clarify how servicers should handle payments by potential successors in interest.<footnote ref="296">Some commenters also addressed whether § 1026.36(c) and other mortgage servicing requirements should apply to confirmed successors in interest. Those comments are addressed in part V.A. and the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.2(a)(11).</footnote>
      For the reasons explained in part V.A. and in this discussion, the final rule clarifies the operation of § 1026.36(c) with respect to potential successors in interest by amending comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-2.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several consumer advocacy groups stated that a servicer should always be required to credit payments promptly and to refrain from improper pyramiding of late fees. These groups noted that it could take potential successors in interest several months or longer to obtain and provide documentation of their status as a successor in interest. Consumer advocacy group commenters also indicated that successors in interest continue to have difficulties getting their payments credited. A local government commenter noted the importance of assisting successors in making payments on a loan if the loan is current at the time the servicer is notified of the borrower's death.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>A number of industry commenters urged the Bureau not to apply protections or regulations including § 1026.36(c) to unconfirmed successors in interest. A trade association stated that successors in interest can and should make payments while successorship claims and loss mitigation applications are being prepared or pending. It indicated that servicers accept payments made prior to confirmation if the servicers have enough confirming information. This commenter suggested that it would be helpful for the Bureau to clarify the treatment of a payment that a successor in interest sends before confirmation and raised a number of questions relating to how the error resolution procedures of § 1024.35 apply to payments received from potential and confirmed successor in interest. This commenter indicated that servicers should have the ability to accept or reject payments from potential successors in interest and that servicers need to be able to reject payments in certain circumstances, citing the Patriot Act.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For the reasons stated in part V.A. and the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.2(a)(11), the Bureau has decided not to define unconfirmed successors in interest as consumers for purposes of the Mortgage Servicing Rules, including § 1026.36(c). However, the Bureau agrees with commenters that potential successors in interest should be able to make payments during the confirmation process, in order to ensure that mortgage loans do not become delinquent or, if already delinquent, do not become more delinquent while potential successors in interest await confirmation. Both industry commenters and consumer advocacy groups emphasized the importance of payments by potential successors in interest. The Bureau encourages servicers to continue to work with potential successors in interest to facilitate payments during the confirmation process in order to help prevent delinquency. The Bureau also notes that there may be circumstances where State law provides additional protections for potential successors in interest as to payment acceptance and crediting.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Additionally, the Bureau notes that the mere fact that a payment comes from someone who is not a consumer does not obviate the servicer's obligations to handle it properly under § 1026.36(c)(1) and (2).<footnote ref="297">For example, comment 36(c)(1)(i)-3 addresses how servicers should calculate the date of receipt for payments made by third-party payors such as a financial institution through a preauthorized payment or telephone bill-payment arrangement.</footnote>
      In connection with consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling, section 129F(a) of TILA generally requires servicers to credit a payment to the consumer's loan account as of the date of receipt, with certain limited exceptions.<footnote ref="298">15 U.S.C. 1639f(a).</footnote>
      In establishing this requirement, Congress did not specify by whom the payment must be made. Consistent with section 129F(a), § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) provides, with specified exceptions, that, in connection with such transactions, no servicer shall fail to credit a periodic payment to the consumer's loan account as of the date of receipt, without limiting the requirement to payments received from a consumer. There may be many circumstances in which a third party makes mortgage payments on behalf of the consumer or as a successor in interest to the transferor consumer. In those cases, as well as when the consumer makes the payment directly, the Bureau expects servicers to follow the payment processing requirements in § 1026.36(c)(1) and to adhere to the prohibition on pyramiding of late fees in § 1026.36(c)(2), to the extent those provisions are otherwise applicable.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Current comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-1 explains that a servicer may specify reasonable requirements for making payments in writing, such as requiring that payments be accompanied by the account number or payment coupon. Current comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-2 also explains that it should not be difficult for most consumers to make conforming payments. Pursuant to the final rule, consumers, as used in comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-2, includes confirmed successors in interest. In light of the importance of keeping loans current, it would not be reasonable for a servicer to impose payment requirements that prevent a potential successor in interest from making payments on the account during the confirmation process. The final rule accordingly amends comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-2 to clarify that it should not be difficult for most consumers or potential successors in interest to make payments that conform to a servicer's payment requirements. The Bureau believes that this clarification serves TILA's purpose of protecting consumers against inaccurate and unfair credit billing practices by ensuring that servicers properly process payments received on an account.<footnote ref="299">15 U.S.C. 1601(a).</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-d-8" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(d)(8)</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.41(d)(8) requires a servicer to include a so-called “delinquency box” containing certain prescribed information in periodic statements sent to consumers who are more than 45 days delinquent.<footnote ref="307">12 CFR 1026.41(d)(8).</footnote>
      The Bureau proposed certain revisions to § 1026.41(d)(8) to align the requirements of that section with the proposed definition of delinquency under Regulation X § 1024.31. The Bureau proposed to revise § 1026.41(d)(8) and add commentary to mirror the language in proposed § 1024.31 (Delinquency) and its related comments.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Current § 1026.41(d)(8) requires a servicer to include in each periodic statement certain information about a consumer's delinquency when the consumer is more than 45 days delinquent, including the date on which the consumer became delinquent. However, Regulation Z currently does not include an explanation of how a servicer must determine the length of a consumer's delinquency. The Bureau explained that it may confuse consumers if a servicer calculates the length of delinquency pursuant to § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) differently from the length of delinquency for purposes of the servicing requirements in subpart C of Regulation X. As such, the Bureau proposed Regulation Z comment 41(d)(8)-1, which mirrored the proposed Regulation X definition of delinquency in § 1024.31 and accompanying comment 31 (Delinquency)-1. Proposed Regulation Z comment 41(d)(8)-1 would have clarified that delinquency begins on the date a consumer misses a payment of principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable), notwithstanding any grace period the servicer affords the consumer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>In addition, the Bureau proposed to add comment 41(d)(8)-2 to address how a creditor must disclose the length of a consumer's delinquency as required by § 1026.41(d)(8) if a servicer applies a consumer's payment to the oldest outstanding delinquency first. As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1024.31, the Bureau proposed a comment to the definition of delinquency to clarify that, if a servicer applies a borrower's payment to the oldest outstanding delinquency, the servicer must advance the date of the borrower's delinquency for purposes of calculating the length of a borrower's delinquency under the various applicable provisions of Regulation X's mortgage servicing rules. To ensure that a servicer's method of calculating the length of the consumer's delinquency for purposes of Regulation Z § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) was consistent with the method for doing the same under the proposed definition of delinquency in Regulation X, the Bureau proposed to include the same commentary in proposed Regulation Z comment 41(d)(8)-2.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau proposed to revise § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) to harmonize its language with the notion that the date a consumer's delinquency begins advances if the servicer applies payments to the oldest outstanding delinquency. Current § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) requires servicers to include the date on which the consumer became delinquent on a delinquent consumer's periodic statement. The Bureau believed that including that date could lead to consumer uncertainty if related proposed comment 41(d)(8)-2 was adopted. Accordingly, the Bureau proposed to revise § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) to require servicers to instead disclose the length of a consumer's delinquency as of the date of the periodic statement.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>A consumer advocacy group expressed support for the proposed revisions to § 1026.41(d)(8) and stated that consumers will benefit from the disclosure of the length of the delinquency.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) and comments 41(d)(8)-1 and -2 substantially as proposed. Final § 1026.41(d)(8)(i) explains that servicers must disclose on the periodic statement the length of the consumer's delinquency. It omits proposed language regarding “as of the date of the periodic statement,” as the Bureau is incorporating this statement into final comment 41(d)(8)-1.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(8)-1 explains that, for purposes of § 1026.41(d)(8), the length of a consumer's delinquency is measured as of the date of the periodic statement or the date of the written notice provided under § 1026.41(e)(3)(iv). A consumer's delinquency begins on the date an amount sufficient to cover a periodic payment of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, becomes due and unpaid, even if the consumer is afforded a period after the due date to pay before the servicer assesses a late fee. It further explains that a consumer is delinquent if one or more periodic payments of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, are due and unpaid. Final comment 41(d)(8)-1 includes a change from the proposal to address a situation where a servicer provides the consumer a coupon book under § 1026.41(e)(3) and is exempt from the periodic statement requirements under § 1026.41(a)(2). Section § 1026.41(e)(3)(iv) requires the servicer to provide the consumer the information listed in § 1026.41(d)(8) in writing for any billing cycle during which the consumer is more than 45 days delinquent. Proposed § 1026.41(d)(8)(i), which would have referred to the length of the consumer's delinquency only as of the date of the periodic statement, did not account for situations where the servicer provides a coupon book under § 1026.41(e)(3). Accordingly, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(8)-1 to also clarify how the length of a consumer's delinquency is determined when a servicer provides a written notice under § 1026.41(e)(3)(iv).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(8)-2 provides that, for purposes of § 1026.41(d)(8), if a servicer applies payments to the oldest outstanding periodic payment, a payment by a delinquent consumer advances the date the consumer's delinquency began. It provides an illustrative example.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisSection>
      <title>Legal Authority</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The amendments to § 1026.41(d) implement section 128(f)(1)(H) of TILA, which requires inclusion in periodic statements of any information that the Bureau may prescribe by regulation.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-d-2" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(d)(2)</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.41(d)(2)(i) provides that the explanation of amount due on periodic statements required by § 1026.41 must include the monthly payment amount, including a breakdown showing how much, if any, will be applied to principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) and, if a mortgage loan has multiple payment options, a breakdown of each of the payment options along with information on whether the principal balance will increase, decrease, or stay the same for each option listed. The Bureau proposed § 1026.41(d)(2) commentary to clarify how acceleration and temporary loss mitigation programs affect disclosure of the explanation of amount due on the periodic statement. The Bureau's rules and commentary do not currently address this issue. The Bureau proposed this § 1026.41(d)(2) commentary in conjunction with proposed § 1026.41(d)(1) commentary, as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(d)(1). The Bureau is finalizing the proposed § 1026.41(d)(2) commentary with revisions.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(d)(2)-1 would have provided that, if the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) should omit the monthly payment amount that would generally be required under § 1026.41(d)(2)(i) and should include both the reinstatement amount and the accelerated amount. The proposed comment would have provided that the statement must also include an explanation that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan. The proposed comment would have required that this explanation be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed comment 41(d)(2)-1 because, given that the amount due will reflect the reinstatement amount, the Bureau believed that the periodic statement should elsewhere identify the accelerated balance, which is the amount that the consumer technically owes under the loan contract. The Bureau believed that the explanation of amount due is where this disclosure is most appropriate. The Bureau proposed that the monthly payment amount be omitted from the explanation of amount due after acceleration because the Bureau believed that, once a loan has been accelerated, the monthly payment obligation is not relevant to the consumer, as the servicer will no longer accept this amount.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Because identification of both the reinstatement amount and the accelerated amount in the explanation of amount due may present some possibility of misleading consumers, the Bureau believed that the periodic statement should also include an explanation indicating that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan. Consistent with the requirement under § 1026.41(d)(5) that partial payment information must be on the front page of the periodic statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the statement or in a separate letter, the Bureau believed it was appropriate that this explanation should be on the front page of the periodic statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the statement or in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several industry commenters expressed concern with proposed comment 41(d)(2)-1. These commenters stated that including both the reinstatement amount and the accelerated loan balance in the explanation of amount due could lead to consumer confusion. Many of these industry commenters asserted that, where a servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, there is no need to disclose the accelerated loan balance on the periodic statement. One industry commenter stated that there is often a significant difference between the reinstatement amount and the accelerated amount, and that disclosing the accelerated amount could be overwhelming to consumers.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several industry commenters requested that servicers not be required to disclose this amount or be permitted to disclose that this amount was an estimate. One industry commenter stated that it was unclear how the accelerated amount should be accurately disclosed on the periodic statement, and that programing systems to include the accelerated amount on the periodic statement could be complicated. Another industry commenter expressed concern that the proposal might have required servicers to provide a payoff amount in the periodic statement, and stated that payoff statements are difficult to produce because the amount required to pay off a loan can change daily. Some industry commenters requested that the final rule permit servicers to include language explaining that the payoff amount is distinct from the accelerated amount and reinstatement amount.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several consumer advocacy groups stated that, after acceleration, many servicers have specific requirements as to how the reinstatement amount must be paid that are distinct from the requirements pertaining to periodic payments. These commenters expressed that, for example, servicers may require that the reinstatement amount be submitted in the form of a certified check to the attorney handling the foreclosure on behalf of the servicer. These commenters recommended that the rule require that the periodic statement include an explanation of any requirements the consumer must follow in paying the reinstatement amount. Another consumer advocacy group stated that information regarding the accelerated balance should be clearly located to avoid confusing the consumer, whether on the periodic statement or in the same enclosure as the periodic statement.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(d)(2)-2 would have provided that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program and the amount due on the periodic statement identifies the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) should include both the amount due according to the loan contract and the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. The proposed comment would have provided that the statement should also include an explanation that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount because of the temporary loss mitigation program. The proposed comment would have also provided that this explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believed that, when the amount due is disclosed on the periodic statement as the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, the periodic statement should elsewhere identify the amount due according to the loan contract, as this amount is significant information that the consumer should have. For example, under proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4, the amount due according to the loan contract would be the amount promptly credited by the servicer. The Bureau believed that the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) is where this disclosure is most appropriate.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Because identification of both the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program and the amount due according to the loan contract could present some possibility of consumer confusion, the Bureau believed that the statement should also include an explanation indicating that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount than the amount due under the loan contract because of the temporary loss mitigation program. Again, consistent with the requirement under § 1026.41(d)(5) that partial payment information must be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter, the Bureau believed it was appropriate that this explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comments regarding the disclosure of the amount due on the periodic statement when a consumer is participating in a temporary loss mitigation program are discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(d)(1).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing comments 41(d)(2)-1 and -2 with changes from the proposal. The Bureau understands that proposed comment 41(d)(2)-1 could have caused consumer uncertainty as to the meaning of the accelerated amount or the reinstatement amount. The Bureau continues to believe that consumers will benefit if the periodic statement includes both the reinstatement amount and the accelerated amount in the explanation of amount due. However, consumers may further benefit if servicers are permitted to include additional, relevant information in the explanation of amount due. Accordingly, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(2)-1 with changes.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(2)-1 explains that, if the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must list both the reinstatement amount that is disclosed as the amount due and the accelerated amount, but not the monthly payment amount that would otherwise be required under § 1026.41(d)(2)(i). Comment 41(d)(2)-1 further provides that the periodic statement must also include an explanation that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan through the “as of [date]” or “good through [date],” as applicable, along with any special instructions for submitting the payment. It provides that the explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement. Finally, comment 41(d)(2)-1 provides that the explanation may include related information, such as a statement that the amount disclosed is “not a payoff amount.”</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As the Bureau has previously explained, the accelerated amount is the amount that the consumer technically owes under the loan contract and is significant information that the consumer should have. Additionally, the Bureau believes the burden on servicers associated with providing the accelerated amount should be limited. The Bureau notes that some industry commenters requested that the final rule permit servicers to disclose an estimate of the accelerated amount because of the difficulty associated with disclosing an accurate accelerated amount. However, as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(d)(1), if any information necessary for an accurate disclosure is unknown to the servicer, the servicer must make the disclosure based on the best information reasonably available at the time the disclosure is provided and shall state clearly that the disclosure is an estimate, consistent with Regulation Z's provisions for the disclosure of estimates.<footnote ref="306">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; §§ 1026.17(c)(1) and 1026.31(d)(2).</footnote>
      The Bureau believes this provision accounts for situations where a servicer may not have sufficient information to calculate the accelerated amount accurately. Final comment 41(d)(2)-1 also clarifies that the reinstatement amount listed in the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must be the reinstatement amount that is disclosed as the amount due.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Additionally, as discussed in the section-by-section-analysis of § 1026.41(d)(1), the Bureau understands that reinstatement amounts may change with some frequency. Consistent with final comment 41(d)(1)-1, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(2)-1 to explain that the periodic statement must include language stating that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan through the “as of [date]” or “good through [date],” as applicable.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also understands from comments received that servicers may place certain conditions on the acceptance of the reinstatement amount, for example, requiring payment by certified check or to a specific address. Final comment 41(d)(2)-1 addresses this possibility by requiring that any special instructions for submitting the payment be included in the periodic statement. This explanation should prevent consumers from missing an opportunity to reinstate the loan simply because they are unaware of the specific form or manner in which the reinstatement amount must be remitted. Additionally, consumers may benefit if the explanation of the reinstatement amount is included on the periodic statement or enclosed with the periodic statement. Accordingly, final comment 41(d)(2)-1 does not permit this explanation to be provided in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(2)-1 also provides that the explanation on the periodic statement regarding the reinstatement amount may also include related information, such as a statement that the amount disclosed is “not a payoff amount.” This provision enables servicers to provide further clarification and relevant, additional information to consumers in the explanation of amount due required by § 1026.41(d)(2). For example, servicers could include information on the periodic statement regarding the distinction between the payoff amount and the reinstatement and accelerated amounts. Permitting this additional information addresses concerns about consumer uncertainty as to the meaning of the reinstatement or accelerated amounts as compared to the payoff amount. Additionally, servicers disclosing an estimated accelerated amount may include in the explanation of amount due relevant information regarding, for example, circumstances under which the estimate may change.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(2)-2 substantially as proposed. Comment 41(d)(2)-2 explains that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program and the amount due identifies the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must include both the amount due according to the loan contract and the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. It further explains that the statement must also include an explanation that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount because of the temporary loss mitigation program. Finally, it states that the explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(2)-2 clarifies that the explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) must, rather than should, include both the amount due according to the loan contract and the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. The final rule also explains that the statement must, rather than should, include an explanation that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount because of the temporary loss mitigation program. Under these circumstances, requiring servicers to include this information in the explanation of amount due will benefit consumers. Additionally, as servicers will already know the amount due under the loan contract and be aware that the consumer is participating in a temporary loss mitigation program, requiring this additional information provides an important consumer protection without imposing a significant additional burden on servicers.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-d-1" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(d)(1)</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.41(d)(1)(iii) provides that the periodic statement required by § 1026.41(d) must include the amount due, shown more prominently than other disclosures on the page. The Bureau proposed § 1026.41(d)(1) commentary to clarify how acceleration, temporary loss mitigation programs, and permanent loan modification affect disclosure of the amount due on the periodic statement. Currently, the Bureau's rules and commentary do not address this issue. The Bureau is finalizing proposed comment 41(d)(1)-1 regarding acceleration with revisions. The Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(1)-2 regarding temporary loss mitigation programs as proposed and comment 41(d)(1)-3 regarding permanent loan modifications substantially as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(d)(1)-1 would have provided that, if the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due disclosed on the periodic statement under § 1026.41(d)(1) should identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan, not the entire accelerated balance.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is aware that, after accelerating a mortgage loan, a servicer may accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan and may sometimes be required to do so by State law. The Bureau believed that receiving a periodic statement indicating that the amount due is the reinstatement amount rather than the full accelerated balance would make the consumer more likely to pay the reinstatement amount, thereby possibly preventing foreclosure. The Bureau believed it may confuse consumers to receive a periodic statement indicating that the amount due is the full accelerated balanced when, in fact, the consumer is informed elsewhere that the consumer may pay only the reinstatement amount. The consumer may be deterred from reading other disclosures or documents if the consumer sees the full accelerated balance as the amount due and believes payment of that amount is impossible. In that case, the consumer may not become aware that reinstatement is available, possibly leading to unnecessary foreclosure.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(d)(1)-2 would have provided that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) may identify either the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program or the amount due according to the loan contract. The Bureau believed that it may be confusing for consumers who have agreed to a loss mitigation program to receive a periodic statement identifying the amount due under the loan contract when that amount is different from the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. Accordingly, the Bureau proposed that servicers may, but are not required to, identify the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, instead of the amount due according to the loan contract.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau did not propose to require that the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program must be identified as the amount due for two primary reasons. First, because a temporary loss mitigation program does not change the underlying legal obligation, the Bureau believed it may be inappropriate to require a servicer to modify periodic statements whenever a consumer agrees to a temporary loss mitigation program. Second, the Bureau was concerned that imposing additional requirements on servicers when a consumer agrees to a temporary loss mitigation program could deter servicers from offering temporary loss mitigation programs.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau solicited comment on whether, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, servicers should be required, rather than permitted, to identify the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) as the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, rather than the amount due according to the loan contract.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(d)(1)-3 would have provided that, if the loan contract has been permanently modified, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) should identify only the amount due under the modified loan contract. The Bureau believed that the periodic payment should reflect the contractual obligation; once the loan contract has been permanently modified, the terms of the modified loan contract govern the periodic payment determination, not the terms of the contract pre-modification.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received a number of comments in response to the proposed § 1026.41(d)(1) commentary. The majority of industry commenters expressed concern over the explanation in proposed comment 41(d)(1)-1 that, if the balance of the mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan. Several of these commenters stated that disclosing the reinstatement amount on the periodic statement as proposed would not be feasible, as this value changes frequently, even daily. They stated that servicers could not be expected to disclose a reinstatement amount that would remain accurate until the periodic payment due date disclosed on the periodic statement. One industry commenter stated that reinstatement amounts are often manually calculated and that the proposal would necessitate implementation of expensive, automated systems. This commenter also said that the proposal was unclear as to whether a servicer would be required to accept the disclosed reinstatement amount after it is no longer accurate. Another industry commenter expressed that the reinstatement amount depends on the expenses incurred by third parties on behalf of servicers and stated that servicers would have no cause to stop such third-party activities unless they had received an indication from the consumer that the consumer sought to reinstate the loan.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>A few industry commenters recommended that the Bureau address concerns over frequent changes to the reinstatement amount by permitting servicers to disclose a reinstatement amount that is “good through” a specified date. These commenters stated that disclosing the good through date would clarify that the disclosed reinstatement amount may only be available for a specified period of time, and that this specified period of time may not coincide with the consumer's payment due date.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Some industry commenters urged the Bureau to require only that servicers provide a general disclosure when a loan is accelerated. One commenter expressed support for the Bureau's goal of making the periodic statement seem less daunting for delinquent consumers. It stated, however, that this goal would be more effectively carried out if servicers provided a generic clarification on the periodic statement that, although the fully accelerated balance is the total amount owed on the loan, the consumer may have the right to request a quote for a lower reinstatement amount. This commenter recommended that the periodic statement include contact information for the mortgage servicer's payoff and reinstatement departments.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several consumer advocacy groups expressed support for proposed comment 41(d)(1)-1. These commenters stated that otherwise disclosing the amount due on the periodic statement as the fully accelerated amount may cause consumer confusion.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>A few industry commenters expressed concern with proposed comment 41(d)(1)-2. These commenters stated that identifying an amount due other than what is legally required under the loan contract could lead to consumer confusion. They further expressed that disclosing this amount would provide little benefit to consumers, as consumers would already be aware of the terms of the loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>In contrast, several consumer advocacy groups stated that, when a consumer and servicer have entered into a contract for temporary loss mitigation, the consumer may be confused if the periodic statement discloses the contractual amount due. These commenters stated that consumers may believe the contractual amount is the amount they are required to pay and may also believe that the servicer has terminated or will not comply with the terms of the temporary loss mitigation program. Some consumer advocacy groups expressed that the costs to servicers associated with changing the amount due on the periodic statement to reflect the terms of the temporary loss mitigation program would be minimal. These commenters further stated that any such costs would not deter servicers from offering temporary loss mitigation programs to consumers, as many servicers must extend such offers pursuant to investor requirements. One consumer advocacy group suggested that servicers identify the amount due under the loan contract if the loss mitigation program is expected to be 90 days or less and otherwise identify the amount due under the temporary loss mitigation plan. It stated that the proposal may lead to consumer confusion as to the validity of the loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For the reasons discussed below, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(1)-1 with changes from the proposal. It is finalizing comment 41(d)(1)-2 as proposed and is finalizing comment 41(d)(1)-3 substantially as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau understands that proposed comment 41(d)(1)-1 could have posed compliance difficulties. As noted by commenters, the reinstatement amount may frequently change, which could make it difficult to disclose a reinstatement amount on the periodic statement that will remain accurate until the consumer's payment due date. Accordingly, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)(1)-1 with changes from the proposal.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Final comment 41(d)(1)-1 provides that, if the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan. It further explains that the periodic statement must be accurate when provided and should indicate, if applicable, that the amount due is accurate only for a specified period of time. It provides that, for example, the statement may include language such as “as of [date]” or “good through [date]” and provide an amount due that will reinstate the loan as of that date or good through that date, respectively.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comment 41(d)(1)-1 provides a flexible standard for disclosing the reinstatement amount. Servicers may disclose that the reinstatement amount is accurate for only a specified time, thus reducing concerns about consumer confusion when a reinstatement amount changes between the date the amount is disclosed on the periodic statement and the date the consumer's payment is due. For example, if the servicer discloses that the reinstatement amount is “good through” a specific date, the reinstatement amount must be accepted through that date to reinstate the loan, even if that date is different from the date on which the consumer's payment is due. Additionally, consumers should benefit by having information on the statement indicating that the reinstatement amount is accurate, or will remain accurate, for only a specified time. A general disclosure, as suggested by some commenters, would be less effective in helping consumers understand the specific amount that the consumer can pay to reinstate the loan and possibly avoid unnecessary foreclosure. The Bureau understands that calculating the reinstatement amount for purposes of this disclosure may increase costs to servicers, as suggested by one commenter. However, the Bureau believes that final comment 41(d)(1)-1 may alleviate some of the costs that the proposal could have imposed, and that there are benefits to consumers associated with disclosure of the reinstatement amount. The Bureau also understands that servicers may already be required to disclose this information to consumers under State law.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Permitting servicers to disclose an “as of [date]” enables servicers to disclose a reinstatement amount that accurately captures the amount of fees that have actually been incurred as of the date the periodic statement is provided. It avoids servicers having to make an estimate of future fees. If servicers instead disclose a “good through [date],” the reinstatement amount may include an estimate of future fees that have not yet been incurred at the time the periodic statement is provided. If any information necessary for an accurate disclosure under subpart E of Regulation Z is unknown to the servicer, the servicer must make the disclosure based on the best information reasonably available at the time the disclosure is provided.<footnote ref="304">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 1026.17(c)(1) and 1026.31(d)(2).</footnote>
      The disclosure shall state clearly that the disclosure is an estimate and describe the circumstances under which the disclosure may change.<footnote ref="305">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau recognizes that, where servicers are estimating future fees, servicers may overestimate or underestimate the actual amount of these unincurred fees. The Bureau understands that, under applicable State and Federal law, consumers would have a right to recover any fees that are paid based on the disclosed reinstatement amount but that the servicer does not actually incur during the time between when the periodic statement is provided and the “good through” date. Alternatively, any bona fide charges from third parties incurred during the time between when the periodic statement is provided and the “good through” date could still be accepted from the consumer after reinstatement, where permitted by applicable State law.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Additionally, final comment 41(d)(1)-1 explains that, if the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must, rather than should, identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan. As the Bureau has explained, in these situations consumers will benefit from a periodic statement indicating that the amount due is the reinstatement amount. Additionally, the changes adopted in the final rule should facilitate servicers' compliance with comment 41(d)(1)-1.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting comment 41(d)(1)-2 as proposed. Comment 41(d)(1)-2 provides that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) may identify either the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program or the amount due according to the loan contract. Industry commenters generally stated that the disclosed amount due should reflect the amount due under the loan contract, while most consumer advocacy groups stated that the disclosed amount due should reflect the amount required to be paid pursuant to the temporary loss mitigation program. The Bureau continues to believe, as explained in the proposal, that it may be confusing for consumers who have agreed to a loss mitigation program to receive a periodic statement identifying the amount due under the loan contract when that amount is different from the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. At the same time, requiring servicers to modify periodic statements whenever a consumer agrees to a temporary loss mitigation program may be costly for servicers. Accordingly, where a consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the Bureau believes that permitting, but not requiring, servicers to disclose the amount due under the temporary loss mitigation program appropriately balances consumer and servicer interests.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau did not receive any comments on proposed comment 41(d)(1)-3 and is finalizing the comment substantially as proposed. Comment 41(d)(1)-3 provides that, if the loan contract has been permanently modified, the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must identify only the amount due under the modified loan contract. Comment 41(d)(1)-3 clarifies the proposed language by explaining that the amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) must, rather than should, identify only the amount due under the modified loan contract. As the Bureau has explained, once a loan has been permanently modified, the obligation under the unmodified loan contract is not relevant to the periodic statement.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-2-a-11" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>2(a)(11)</title>
    <analysisParagraph>As noted in part V.A., the Bureau proposed to apply certain mortgage servicing rules to confirmed successors in interest. Similar to the definition in proposed § 1024.30(d) with respect to the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation X,<footnote ref="279">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; section-by-section analysis of § 1024.30(d), &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;supra.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
      proposed § 1026.2(a)(11) would have revised the definition of the term consumer to include a successor in interest once a servicer confirms the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling for the purposes of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), and 1026.41. For the reasons described in part V.A. and in this discussion, the Bureau is finalizing this proposed definition with a substantive change to add the mortgage transfer disclosure requirements of § 1026.39 and technical changes to incorporate the new definition of confirmed successor in interest. The final rule thus amends the definition of consumer for purposes of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41 to include a confirmed successor in interest. As in the proposal, confirmed successors in interest covered by § 1026.2(a)(11) will not necessarily have assumed the mortgage loan obligation (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> legal liability for the mortgage debt) under State law or otherwise be liable on it.<footnote ref="280">As indicated in part V.A., &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;supra,&lt;/em&gt; the Bureau understands that whether a successor in interest has assumed a mortgage loan obligation (&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;i.e.,&lt;/em&gt; legal liability for the mortgage debt) under State law is a fact-specific question.</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As described in part V.A., successors in interest face many of the challenges that the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z were designed to prevent. Because a confirmed successor in interest is a homeowner whose dwelling is subject to foreclosure if the mortgage loan obligation is not satisfied, the same reasons supporting the Bureau's adoption of the 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule support the changes that the Bureau is making to § 1026.2(a)(11).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau has considered each of the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z and has concluded that each rule should apply to confirmed successors in interest. The Bureau generally believes that it would add unnecessary complexity to the rules to require servicers to apply some but not all of the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z to confirmed successors in interest. After reviewing the comments, the Bureau has not identified any compelling reasons not to apply a particular rule and therefore concludes that it is preferable to apply all of the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z to confirmed successors in interest.<footnote ref="281">As explained in part V.A., &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;supra,&lt;/em&gt; and in the section-by-section analyses of §§ 1026.20(f), 1026.39(f), and 1026.41(g), &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;infra,&lt;/em&gt; the final rule includes additional provisions governing how the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z apply to confirmed successors in interest.</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The new definition of consumer in § 1026.2(a)(11) entitles confirmed successors in interest to receive ARM disclosures under § 1026.20(c) and (d) and escrow account cancellation notices under § 1026.20(e).<footnote ref="282">Section 1026.20(c) and (d) generally applies with respect to a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by the consumer's principal dwelling in which the annual percentage rate may increase after consummation, and § 1026.20(e) generally applies with respect to a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a first lien on real property or a dwelling.</footnote>
      The disclosures required by § 1026.20(c) through (e) will provide confirmed successors in interest with important information to allow the confirmed successor in interest to keep the mortgage loan current, which in turn will help the confirmed successor in interest avoid unnecessary foreclosure.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau anticipates that § 1026.36(c)'s protections will help confirmed successors in interest maintain ownership of their homes.<footnote ref="283">Section 1026.36(c)(1) and (2) apply in connection with a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a consumer's principal dwelling, and § 1026.36(c)(3) applies in connection with a consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling.</footnote>
      As noted in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.36(c)(1)(iii), even in the absence of the final rule, existing § 1026.36(c) imposes certain obligations on servicers with respect to payments from successors in interest. However, consumer advocacy groups reported in their comments, as they had in earlier reports, that some servicers are refusing to accept payments from successors in interest, which in turn may lead to delinquency on the mortgage loan and, eventually, foreclosure. Applying § 1026.36(c)'s prompt crediting requirements explicitly to confirmed successors in interest may help alleviate this problem. The Bureau also believes that providing confirmed successors in interest with access to the loan's payoff balance will help keep them informed about the mortgage loan secured by the dwelling and prevent unnecessary foreclosure.<footnote ref="284">For the reasons discussed in part V.A., &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;supra,&lt;/em&gt; the Bureau believes that providing confirmed successors in interest with payoff balances does not present privacy concerns.</footnote>
      Access to this information could also facilitate refinancing by the confirmed successor in interest. Because successors in interest, as owners of a dwelling securing a mortgage loan, may be required to make payments on the loan to avoid foreclosure, applying the prohibition on pyramiding of late fees explicitly to confirmed successors in interest serves TILA's purpose of protecting consumers against inaccurate and unfair credit billing practices.<footnote ref="285">78 FR 10901, 10914 (Feb. 14, 2013) (quoting 15 U.S.C. 1601(a)).</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The new definition of consumer in § 1026.2(a)(11) also ensures that confirmed successors in interest can receive ongoing periodic statements required under § 1026.41.<footnote ref="286">Section 1026.41 generally applies with respect to a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling.</footnote>
      As the Bureau recognized in issuing the periodic statement requirement in the 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule, the periodic statement serves a variety of important purposes, including informing consumers of their payment obligations, providing information about the mortgage loan, creating a record of transactions that increase or decrease the outstanding balance, providing information needed to identify and assert errors, and providing information when consumers are delinquent.<footnote ref="287">78 FR 10901, 10959 (Feb. 14, 2013).</footnote>
      Receiving periodic statements serves these same purposes for confirmed successors in interest who, as homeowners of a dwelling securing a mortgage loan, may be required to make payments on the loan to avoid foreclosure.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As explained in part V.A., a trade association commenter suggested that a confirmed successor in interest should be treated as a consumer for purposes of the mortgage transfer disclosure requirement in § 1026.39. The mortgage transfer disclosure notifies consumers of valuable information regarding certain transfers of ownership of a mortgage loan, including the name and contact information for the new owner of the mortgage loan and an agent or party authorized to resolve issues concerning the consumer's payments on the loan (if the owner's information cannot be used for that purpose). Information of this nature can assist confirmed successors in interest who seek to engage in loss mitigation, to ensure that payments on the account are properly applied, or to identify who has a security interest in their property. For the reasons set forth in part V.A. and below, the final rule defines consumer in § 1026.2(a)(11) to also include confirmed successors in interest for purposes of § 1026.39.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As explained in part V.A., some industry commenters expressed concern that the proposal would require servicers to communicate about the loan with parties that are not obligated on the loan in ways. An industry commenter suggested that such communications might be considered abusive or harassing and might be found to violate FDCPA section 806, 15 U.S.C. 1692d, if done by a servicer subject to the FDCPA. The Bureau does not believe that providing this important information about the property at issue in a notice that is required by Regulation X will be abusive or harassing absent other conduct making the overall effect of the communication abusive or harassing, as explained in part V.A. Additionally, the final rule gives servicers the option not to send Mortgage Servicing Rule notices to a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the loan obligation until the confirmed successor in interest requests them through a written acknowledgment, as long as the servicer sends an initial written notice and acknowledgment form to the confirmed successor in interest upon confirmation in compliance with the requirements of § 1024.32(c)(1) through (3).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>A number of industry commenters also expressed concern that subjecting servicers to the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z might prove costly for servicers. However, as explained in part V.A., many of the specific cost concerns that industry commenters raised relate to requirements that are not part of the final rule. For example, many industry commenters expressed concern about the potential burden of having to provide duplicative copies of notices to confirmed successors in interest if the servicer had already provided the same notice to another consumer on the account. To address this concern, the final rule clarifies that servicers generally do not have to send Regulation Z disclosures to a confirmed successor in interest if the disclosure is provided to another consumer on the account. Because servicers already must comply with §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36, 1026.39, and 1026.41 with respect to the transferor consumer, the Bureau believes that the additional cost to servicers to apply these requirements to confirmed successors in interest will be relatively minimal. The Bureau believes that the additional cost imposed by extending the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z to confirmed successors in interest will largely be limited to updating servicer systems initially, adding individual successors in interest to the system on an ongoing basis, and printing and mailing costs, if any.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As discussed in more detail in part V.A., the Bureau received a variety of comments on whether mortgage servicing protections should apply with respect to successors in interest even if the servicer has not confirmed the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling. Industry commenters generally opposed extending such protections, asserting that doing so could violate the privacy of the transferor consumer and any other consumers on the account and could result in unauthorized persons obtaining access to loan information or taking action with respect to a loan. Some consumer advocacy groups encouraged the Bureau to apply certain servicing protections prior to confirmation. For example, consumer advocacy groups indicated that, even before a successor in interest is confirmed, a servicer should be required to credit payments promptly and refrain from improper pyramiding of late fees pursuant to § 1026.36(c).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For the reasons stated in part V.A. and in this discussion, the Bureau has decided not to add successors in interest who have not been confirmed to the Regulation Z definition of consumer in § 1026.2(a)(11).<footnote ref="288">However, a successor in interest may be a consumer under the Regulation Z definition of consumer (both currently and as amended by the final rule), even if the successor in interest has not been confirmed, if the successor in interest has assumed the mortgage loan obligation under State law or is otherwise obligated on the mortgage loan obligation.</footnote>
      Because some people representing themselves as successors in interest may not actually have an ownership interest in the dwelling, requiring servicers to apply Regulation Z's mortgage servicing communication and disclosure requirements to successors in interest before servicers have confirmed the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling may present privacy and other concerns, as various commenters noted. For the same reason, the Bureau also believes it is inappropriate to require servicers to incur substantial costs before confirming the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling. However, as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.36(c), § 1026.36(c)(1) and (2) imposes certain obligations relating to payment crediting and processing that apply even if a payment is received from a successor in interest prior to confirmation.<footnote ref="289">For example, the Bureau is clarifying in comment 36(c)(1)(iii)-2 that, when a servicer specifies requirements for payments, those requirements should not make it difficult for most confirmed and potential successors in interest to make conforming payments.</footnote>
      Moreover, as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of Regulation X §§ 1024.36(i) and 1024.38(b)(1)(vi), the Bureau is creating a new request for information procedure and imposing certain policies and procedures requirements on servicers under Regulation X with respect to potential successors in interest.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The final rule includes commentary to § 1026.2(a)(11) in comment 2(a)(11)-4.i, .ii, and .iv, which was not part of the proposal. It also includes a substantially revised version of proposed comment 2(a)(11)-4 as comment 2(a)(11)-4.iii. New comment 2(a)(11)-4.i clarifies that confirmation of a successor in interest is different from assumption of the mortgage loan under State law. It explains that a servicer may not require a confirmed successor in interest to assume the mortgage loan obligation to be considered a consumer for purposes of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41. It also explains that, if a successor in interest assumes a mortgage loan obligation under State law or is otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, the protections the successor in interest enjoys under Regulation Z are not limited to §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41. The Bureau believes that this comment will help prevent confusion about the consequences of confirmation and of assumption of the loan obligation under State law.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>New comment 2(a)(11)-4.ii explains that communications in compliance with Regulation Z to a confirmed successor in interest as defined in § 1026.2(a)(27)(ii) do not violate FDCPA section 805(b) because the term consumer for purposes of FDCPA section 805 includes any person who meets the definition in Regulation Z of confirmed successor in interest. As explained in parts IV.C. and V.A., this is consistent with an interpretive rule that the Bureau is issuing concurrently with this final rule.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comment 2(a)(11)-4.iii addresses the treatment of transferor consumers, a subject that was addressed in proposed comment 2(a)(11)-4. Proposed comment 2(a)(11)-4 would have provided that, even after a servicer confirms a successor in interest's status, the servicer would still generally be required to comply with the requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), and 1026.41 with respect to the prior consumer. The proposed comment indicated, however, that a servicer would not be required to comply with the requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e) and 1026.41 if the prior consumer also either had died or had been released from the obligation on the mortgage loan and a servicer would not be required to comply with the requirements of § 1026.36(c) if the prior consumer also had been released from the obligation on the mortgage loan. The proposed comment also would have provided that the prior consumer would retain any rights under §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), and 1026.41 that accrued prior to the confirmation of the successor in interest to the extent those rights would otherwise survive the prior consumer's death or release from the obligation. For the reasons stated in part V.A. and in this discussion, the Bureau has substantially revised this comment to make it clear that confirmation of a successor in interest does not strip the consumer who transferred the ownership interest to the successor in interest of any protections under Regulation Z. The revised comment appears as comment 2(a)(11)-4.iii in the final rule.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>In the proposal, the Bureau solicited comment on whether a servicer should not be required to comply with §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), and 1026.41 with respect to prior consumers after a successor in interest is confirmed. The Bureau also solicited comment on whether other circumstances exist, beyond death and release of the obligation on the mortgage loan, in which some or all of the requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), and 1026.41 should not apply with respect to the prior consumer after a successor in interest is confirmed. The Bureau also solicited comment on whether § 1026.41 should provide that, in the case of consumer death, the servicer should continue providing periodic statements to the consumer's estate until a successor in interest's status has been confirmed.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As explained in part V.A., the Bureau received many comments objecting to the use of the term prior consumer. A number of commenters also expressed concern that the Bureau's proposal would not provide adequate protection to the estates of transferor consumers. Some consumer advocacy groups suggested that estates and their representatives should always be able to obtain information regarding the mortgage loan and have payments applied correctly. A trade association agreed with two caveats: It indicated that (1) the servicer needs to verify that a person purporting to act as administrator or executor is properly acting in that capacity, and (2) if the estate is released from the loan obligation, Regulation P may limit the estate's ability to access future loan information. Another trade association indicated that the executor of an estate may ultimately be legally obligated to dispose of property and needs information in order to fulfill the executor's responsibilities.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The final rule uses the term transferor consumer rather than prior consumer because a transferor consumer typically remains a consumer for purposes of Regulation Z after the transfer. As many commenters indicated, transferor consumers may remain liable on the mortgage loan obligation and can have significant legal interests at stake even after a successor in interest is confirmed. The Bureau also recognizes that, when a consumer dies, the consumer's estate and its representative have an important role to play and that Regulation Z can provide valuable information and protections to transferor consumers and their estates even after confirmation of a successor in interest. The Bureau does not intend for the final rule to diminish any protections that TILA and Regulation Z currently provide for living transferor consumers or for estates and their representatives, and the Bureau has significantly revised proposed comment 2(a)(11)-4 accordingly. As finalized, comment 2(a)(11)-4.iii provides that, even after a servicer's confirmation of a successor in interest, the servicer is still required to comply with all applicable requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41 with respect to the consumer who transferred an ownership interest to the successor in interest.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau acknowledges that, under the final rule, servicers will sometimes be required to comply with the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z with respect to more than one person—such as the transferor consumer or a representative of the transferor consumer's estate and the confirmed successor in interest, as well as, in some cases, multiple confirmed successors in interest who each acquire an ownership interest in a dwelling. Although some commenters expressed concern about this, the Bureau notes that, under the Mortgage Servicing Rules, the rules already may apply with respect to more than one consumer for a particular mortgage loan. It is quite common for more than one consumer (for example, spouses) to be obligated on the mortgage note, and the Mortgage Servicing Rules apply with respect to each consumer in such cases. Accordingly, the Bureau does not believe that applying the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z to confirmed successors in interest will present novel challenges for servicers in this regard.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The final rule also includes new comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv, which makes clear that servicers generally do not need to send Regulation Z notices to confirmed successors in interest if the notices would be duplicative of notices sent to another consumer on the account. A number of commenters asked the Bureau to clarify whether servicers must send multiple copies of required servicing notices after a successor in interest is confirmed. One industry commenter explained that most servicing platforms only allow for automated delivery of correspondence to one address. It indicated that a requirement to send items to multiple addresses or through differing communication channels would create significant operational and systems challenges with concomitant costs.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For the reasons set forth in part V.A. and in this discussion, the Bureau agrees that it would be unnecessarily burdensome to require servicers to send additional copies of notices required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 to confirmed successors in interest if another consumer is already receiving them. Proposed comment 41(a)-5.ii addressed this issue with respect to periodic statements, but, in light of the comments received, the Bureau believes it is clearest and most efficient to address questions regarding duplication of notices for confirmed successors in interest in a uniform, centralized way in comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv for all of the Mortgage Servicing Rules in Regulation Z. Comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv clarifies that, except as required by Regulation X 12 CFR 1024.36, in response to an information request, a servicer is not required to provide to a confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 if the servicer is providing the same specific disclosure to another consumer on the account. Comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv also explains that, if a servicer confirms more than one successor in interest, the servicer need not send any disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 to more than one of the confirmed successors in interest.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Requiring only one periodic statement is consistent with current comment 41(a)-1, which provides that, when two consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling, subject to § 1026.41, the periodic statement may be sent to either one of them. New comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv is also consistent with § 1026.17(d), comment 17(d)-2, and § 1026.31(e), which generally provide that, if there is more than one consumer, the disclosures required by Regulation Z subparts C and E may be made to any consumer who is primarily liable on the obligation.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-H-30(C)" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>Appendix H-30(C) to Part 1026</title>
    <analysisParagraph>This proposal would have made a minor technical revision to the entry for H-30(C) in the table of contents at the beginning of this appendix and republishes sample form H-30(C). The technical change amends “Sample Form of Periodic Statement for a Payment-Options Loan (§ 1026.41)” to “Sample Form of Periodic Statement for a Payment-Option Loan (§ 1026.41).” The Bureau is adopting this technical change as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-36-c-2" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>36(c)(2) No Pyramiding of Late Fees</title>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed a technical change to § 1026.36(c)(2). Section 1026.36(b) provides that § 1026.36(c)(2) applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. However, current § 1026.36(c)(2) refers to consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling without referring to closed-end transactions. Consistent with § 1026.36(b), proposed § 1026.36(c)(2) modified the existing language to refer directly to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau did not receive comments addressing the proposed technical change to § 1024.36(c)(2) and is finalizing as proposed. Accordingly, final § 1024.36(c)(2) refers directly to a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a consumer's principal dwelling.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-36-c-1" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>36(c)(1) Payment Processing</title>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed a technical change to § 1026.36(c)(1) for clarity. Section 1026.36(b) provides that § 1026.36(c)(1) applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. However, current § 1026.36(c)(1) refers to consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling, without referring to closed-end transactions. Proposed § 1026.36(c)(1) added language relating to closed-end consumer credit transactions.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also proposed commentary to § 1026.36(c)(1) to clarify how servicers must treat periodic payments made by consumers who are performing under either temporary loss mitigation programs or permanent loan modifications. Proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4 would have provided that, if the loan contract has not been permanently modified but the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) remains an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, irrespective of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. Accordingly, if a consumer submits a payment under a temporary loss mitigation program that is less than an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, the servicer should generally treat the payment as a partial payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i), even though the consumer may have made the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed this comment in response to several inquiries regarding payment processing for payments under temporary loss mitigation programs. In the proposal, the Bureau acknowledged that its statement in the 2013 TILA Final Servicing Rule, “if a consumer makes a payment sufficient to cover the principal, interest, and escrow due under a trial modification plan, these funds should be applied,” <footnote ref="294">78 FR 10901, 10954 (Feb. 14, 2013).</footnote>
      may have suggested that, when a temporary loss mitigation program is in effect, the periodic payment is the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, rather than the amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract. In the proposal, the Bureau reiterated that the periodic payment, even under a temporary loss mitigation program, remains the amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract. A consumer may continue to accumulate a delinquency according to the loan contract during the duration of a temporary loss mitigation program. If a consumer fails to comply with the terms of a temporary loss mitigation program, the servicer will typically revert back to the terms of the loan contract, with the result that the consumer may be facing acceleration or an immediate demand for payment in full of the accumulated delinquency. Accordingly, the Bureau believed that it would be appropriate to require servicers to credit payments in a way that reflects the continuing contractual obligations between the parties and any accumulating delinquency. Moreover, the Bureau believed it could be burdensome for servicers to treat the payment due under a temporary loss mitigation program as the periodic payment, only to revert to the contractual payment if the consumer fails to comply with the terms of the temporary loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For loans that have been permanently modified, proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-5 would have provided that the periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the modified loan contract. The periodic payment should reflect the contractual obligation; once the loan contract has been permanently modified, the terms of the modified loan contract govern the periodic payment determination and not the terms of the contract pre-modification.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Several consumer advocacy groups commented on proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4. Consumer advocacy group commenters expressed concern that the proposed comment would cause servicers to believe that payments made under a temporary loss mitigation program are treated differently than other partial payments. One consumer advocacy group stated that a temporary loss mitigation program is a contract that the consumer has the legal right to enforce. It suggested that treating payments made under a temporary plan as partial payments under proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4 conflicts with this principle.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing the technical change to § 1026.36(c)(1) and the revisions to comments 36(c)(1)(i)-4 and -5 as proposed. Accordingly, final § 1026.36(c)(1) refers directly to a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4 explains that, if a loan contract has not been permanently modified but the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is the amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, regardless of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. Comment 36(c)(1)(i)-5 provides that, if a loan contract has been permanently modified, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the modified loan contract.<footnote ref="295">As described in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(d), the Bureau is also finalizing commentary to § 1026.41(d) clarifying certain periodic statement disclosures relating to temporary loss mitigation programs and permanent loan modifications.</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As explained in the proposal, the servicer should generally treat a payment due under a temporary loss mitigation program as a partial payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i). Although a temporary loss mitigation program is a contract, as noted by one commenter, and may be enforceable as such, the temporary loss mitigation program does not remove the obligations of the existing mortgage loan contract. Servicers must credit payments in a way that reflects the continuing contractual obligations between the parties. The Bureau notes that its commentary here is confined to clarifying how servicers must credit payments received and ensuring that those payments are credited according to the terms of the loan contract; the Bureau is not addressing other legal requirements the servicer may have to the borrower relating to the temporary loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-e-4-iii" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(e)(4)(iii) Small Servicer Determination</title>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend certain criteria for determining whether a servicer qualifies for the small servicer exemption under § 1026.41(e)(4). For purposes of determining whether a servicer qualifies as a small servicer, current § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii) excludes from consideration certain types of mortgage loans, including mortgage loans voluntarily serviced by the servicer for a creditor or assignee that is not an affiliate of the servicer and for which the servicer does not receive any compensation or fees. The proposal would have removed the requirement from § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) that the non-affiliate be a creditor or assignee and would have added a new provision § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(D) to exclude from the small servicer determination transactions serviced by a servicer for a seller financer that meet all of the criteria identified in § 1026.36(a)(5).
      <footnote ref="308">Section 1026.36(a)(5) provides that, to be considered a seller financer, a person must (1) provide financing for the sale of only one property in any 12-month period, (2) not have constructed a residence on the property in the ordinary course of business, and (3) provide financing that meets certain interest rate criteria and does not result in negative amortization. See the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(D) for additional details.</footnote>
      For the reasons discussed below, the Bureau is adopting, as proposed, § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau's mortgage servicing rules exempt small servicers from certain mortgage servicing requirements. Regulation Z exempts small servicers, defined in § 1026.41(e)(4)(ii), from the requirement to provide periodic statements for residential mortgage loans.<footnote ref="309">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; § 1026.41(a), (e)(4). For loans serviced by a small servicer, a creditor or assignee is also exempt from the Regulation Z periodic statement requirements. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; § 1026.41(e)(4)(i).</footnote>
      Regulation X incorporates this same definition by reference to § 1026.41(e)(4) <footnote ref="310">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 1024.17(k)(5); 1024.30(b)(1); 1024.41(j).</footnote>
      and thereby exempts small servicers from: (1) Certain requirements relating to obtaining force-placed insurance; <footnote ref="311">12 CFR 1024.17(k)(5) (prohibiting purchase of force-placed insurance in certain circumstances).</footnote>
      (2) the general servicing policies, procedures, and requirements; <footnote ref="312">12 CFR 1024.30(b)(1) (exempting small servicers from §§ 1024.38 through 1024.41, except as otherwise provided under § 1024.41(j), as discussed in note 313, &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;infra&lt;/em&gt;). Sections 1024.38 through 1024.40 respectively impose general servicing policies, procedures, and requirements; early intervention requirements for delinquent borrowers; and policies and procedures to maintain continuity of contact with delinquent borrowers.</footnote>
      and (3) certain requirements and restrictions relating to communicating with borrowers about, and evaluation of applications for, loss mitigation options.<footnote ref="313">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 CFR 1024.41 (loss mitigation procedures). Though exempt from most of the rule, small servicers are subject to the prohibition of foreclosure referral before the loan obligation is more than 120 days delinquent and may not make the first notice or filing for foreclosure if a borrower is performing pursuant to the terms of an agreement on a loss mitigation option. 12 CFR 1024.41(j).</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Under § 1026.41(e)(4)(ii), a small servicer is a servicer that: (1) Services, together with any affiliates,<footnote ref="314">Affiliate is defined in § 1026.32(b)(5) as any company that controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with another company, as set forth in the Bank Holding Company Act of 1956, 12 U.S.C. 1841 &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;et seq.&lt;/em&gt; (BHCA). Under the BHCA, a company has control over another company if it (i) “directly or indirectly . . . owns, controls, or has power to vote 25 per centum or more of any class of voting securities” of the other company; (ii) “controls . . . the election of a majority of the directors or trustees” of the other company; or (iii) “directly or indirectly exercises a controlling influence over the management or policies” of the other company (based on a determination by the Board). 12 U.S.C. 1841(a)(2).</footnote>
      5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, for all of which the servicer (or an affiliate) is the creditor or assignee; (2) is a Housing Finance Agency, as defined in 24 CFR 266.5; or (3) is a nonprofit entity that services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities, for all of which the servicer or an associated nonprofit entity is the creditor. Generally, under § 1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A), a servicer cannot be a small servicer if it services any loan for which the servicer or its affiliate is not the creditor or assignee. As noted above, current § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii) excludes from the small servicer determination certain mortgage loans voluntarily serviced by the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>In the 2012 RESPA Servicing Proposal, the Bureau proposed the exclusion from the small servicer determination for voluntarily serviced mortgage loans <footnote ref="315">78 FR 25638, 25644 (May 2, 2013).</footnote>
      and received one comment from a national trade association requesting guidance regarding certain depository services some of its bank members provide for depositors who “owner-finance” the sale of residential real estate. At that time, the Bureau did not have sufficient information about the described service.<footnote ref="316">78 FR 44685, 44697-98 (July 24, 2013).</footnote>
      Since that time, the Bureau learned that certain depository institutions, which may otherwise qualify for the small servicer exemption, service for their depository customers seller-financed sales of residential real estate.<footnote ref="317">For ease of review, the section-by-section analyses of § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii), (e)(4)(iii)(A), and (e)(4)(iii)(D) discuss the concept of seller financing and the practice of seller-financed sales of residential real estate in general terms, except when specifying that the analyses refer directly to the term seller financer as defined under § 1026.36(a)(4) or (5).</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau understands that certain banks, particularly in small or remote communities, provide their customers this service when there may not be an alternative service provider in the state. The Bureau understands that, under these arrangements, depository institutions typically receive scheduled periodic payments from the purchaser of the property pursuant to the terms of the sale and deposit into the account of the seller (the depository institution's customer) the payments of principal and interest and such other payments with respect to the amounts received from the purchaser as may be required pursuant to the terms of the sale.<footnote ref="318">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; 12 U.S.C. 2605(i)(3) (definition of servicing applicable to TILA, as amended by section 1401 of the Dodd-Frank Act).</footnote>
      The Bureau understands that these arrangements typically involve small seller financers who are not affiliates of the servicer, do not regularly extend consumer credit, and would not qualify as a creditor <footnote ref="319">To be considered a creditor under TILA, a person generally must extend consumer credit for transactions secured by a dwelling more than five times in the preceding calendar year. § 1026.2(a)(17)(v). However, the Bureau notes that the threshold is lower for high-cost mortgages subject to § 1026.32; a person regularly extends credit if, in any 12-month period, the person originates more than one credit extension that is subject to § 1026.32, or one or more such credit extensions through a mortgage broker. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
      or an assignee in their own right. The Bureau understands that depository institutions typically charge a fee for servicing these seller-financed transactions. The Bureau further understands that in some cases, however, depository institutions may elect to service voluntarily these seller-financed sales of residential real estate on behalf of their depository customers without receiving any compensation or fees. In either scenario, under the current rule, a depository institution that services even a single seller-financed sale of residential real estate would likely no longer qualify for the small servicer exemption and would be subject to all of the applicable mortgage servicing rules for all of the mortgage loans that it services, including those that would otherwise be exempt as being owned or originated by the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>To address these scenarios, in issuing the proposal, the Bureau sought comment on whether it would be appropriate to exclude from the small servicer determination mortgage loans voluntarily serviced by the servicer for a non-affiliate that is not a creditor or assignee, or transactions serviced by a servicer for a seller financer that meet all of the criteria identified in the definition of seller financer under § 1026.36(a)(5). The Bureau also sought comment on whether to exclude from the small servicer determination existing mortgage loans that meet the criteria of proposed § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D).</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received several comments supporting the proposed amendments to § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D). The commenters included credit union associations, trade associations, a nationwide association of State regulators, and a community bank. No commenters opposed these proposed amendments.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Some commenters recommended that the Bureau adopt additional revisions, beyond those contemplated in the proposal, to expand the reach of the small servicer exemption. Several commenters recommended including additional types of transactions that could be exempt from the small servicer determination. One trade association suggested that the small servicer exemption apply for all institutions that are community banks, a term that the rule would define. Several commenters also recommended that the Bureau raise the small servicer threshold under § 1026.41(e)(4)(ii) from 5,000 loans to 10,000 loans. One trade association recommended that the Bureau introduce a de minimis standard for servicing loans not owned or originated by the servicer. The Bureau declines to adopt these recommended approaches and considers these comments to be outside of the scope of the proposal, which did not contemplate altering the 5,000 loan threshold or exempting additional types of transactions.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>One commenter suggested that the servicing rules do not apply to long-term escrow companies or contract collection companies because such companies are not considered servicers and their activities should not be considered mortgage loan servicing. In part, the commenter predicated this assertion upon the nature of these companies, arguing that they are not in control of the loan, do not represent the lender in foreclosure matters, and cannot force-place insurance. The Bureau notes that the presence or absence of these factors is not determinative as to whether an entity qualifies as a servicer. TILA section 103(cc)(7) defines servicer to have the same meaning as in RESPA section 6(i)(2), which defines a servicer as, subject to certain exceptions, the person responsible for servicing of a loan (including the person who makes or holds a loan if such person also services the loan).<footnote ref="320">15 U.S.C. 1602(cc)(7); &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; 12 U.S.C. 2605(i)(2).</footnote>
      Further, RESPA section 6(i)(3) defines servicing as receiving any scheduled periodic payments from a borrower pursuant to the terms of any loan.<footnote ref="321">12 U.S.C. 2605(i)(3).</footnote>
      Thus, the mortgage servicing rules apply to any person who receives scheduled periodic payments from a borrower pursuant to the terms of any loan, even a person not typically considered to be a servicer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Two commenters recommended that the Bureau exclude from the small servicer determination existing mortgage loans that meet the criteria of proposed § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D), irrespective of when the servicing relationship began. A national trade association stated that excluding existing contract collection activities would afford banks the opportunity to make an informed business decision as to how they prefer to handle this activity going forward. And a community bank stated that, without excluding existing seller-financed loans, the new exemption would lose its value, as it would be impossible to impose new parameters on existing contracts with seller-financers.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the section-by-section analyses of § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D), the final rule excludes from the small servicer determination both mortgage loans voluntarily serviced for a non-affiliate that is not a creditor or assignee and also transactions serviced for a seller financer that meet all of the criteria identified in the definition of seller financer under § 1026.36(a)(5). The Bureau believes that, to the extent servicing cost savings are passed on to consumers, consumers may benefit from having a depository institution that otherwise qualifies for the small servicer exemption service voluntarily mortgage loans for a non-affiliate that is not a creditor or assignee without losing its small servicer status. Similarly, consumers benefit from having a depository institution service transactions for a seller financer that meet all of the criteria identified in the definition of seller financer under § 1026.36(a)(5) without losing its small servicer status. Financial institutions may be better equipped than individual seller financers to service loans. The Bureau believes that consumers may benefit from a depository institution receiving their scheduled periodic payments and providing an independent accounting as a third party to the transaction, even if the servicer is exempt from some servicing regulations as a small servicer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Under the final rule, a small servicer will now be able to service mortgage loans on behalf of certain seller financers, even if they do not meet TILA's definition of creditor, without jeopardizing the servicer's exemption. The Bureau will continue to monitor this market to determine if the small servicer exemption is being manipulated to evade TILA's requirements or otherwise cause consumer harm.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also determines that it is appropriate to exclude from the small servicer determination all loans that meet the criteria identified in § 1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A) and (D), regardless of whether the small servicer began servicing the loan before the effective date of this final rule. The Bureau believes that requiring servicers to review their entire portfolios to determine whether they already service such loans and, if so, how many would unnecessarily increase burden on servicers. Therefore, a servicer may continue to service existing loans that meet these criteria and exclude them from consideration in determining whether a servicer qualifies for the small servicer exemption.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-H-14" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>Appendix H-14 to Part 1026</title>
    <analysisParagraph>The 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule changed the commentary to § 1026.19(b) to reflect the revised § 1026.20(c) and revised § 1026.20(d) ARM notices. This proposal would have modified the Variable-Rate Mortgage Sample form in appendix H-14 to reflect the language in the revised commentary. The Bureau is adopting these modifications as proposed. No change to the table of contents of appendix H is necessary.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-d" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(d) Content and Layout of the Periodic Statement</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Section 1026.41(d) specifies the disclosures that must be provided on the periodic statement and requires that several of those disclosures be provided in close proximity to one another. The Bureau proposed to amend current comment 41(d)-1 and add new comments 41(d)-4 and -5 relating to the requirements in § 1024.41(d). The Bureau is finalizing comments 41(d)-1 and -4 substantially as proposed. The Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)-5 as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend current comment 41(d)-1, which states that items in close proximity may not have any intervening text between them. The close proximity standard is found in other parts of Regulation Z, including §§ 1026.24(b) and 1026.48. The proposed amendment would have relaxed this requirement for purposes of § 1026.41(d) and instead would have provided that items in close proximity may not have any unrelated text between them. This proposal mirrored the standard for open-end credit plans secured by a consumer's dwelling found in § 1026.40(a) and its corresponding comment 40(a)(1)-3, which explain that while most of the disclosures required by § 1026.40(d) must be grouped together and segregated from all unrelated information, a creditor is permitted to include information that explains or expands upon the required disclosures.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The proposed amendment to comment 41(d)-1 would have provided that items in close proximity may not have any unrelated text between them and explained that text is unrelated if it does not explain or expand upon the required disclosures. Text that explains or expands upon the required disclosures may include, for example, an additional explanation of the amount due when: A fee has been charged to the consumer but will not be collected until payoff (<em data-original="E-03">e.g.</em>, attorney's fees); the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program (as discussed further in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41(d)(2)); the consumer makes an advance payment; or the servicer reverses a fee. The Bureau believed that the proposed amendment to comment 41(d)-1 would provide servicers with additional flexibility to clarify or explain information on the periodic statement and may enable servicers to address circumstances not expressly provided for in § 1026.41(d). The Bureau sought comment generally on this proposal to amend comment 41(d)-1 to relax the prohibition on intervening text to include only related text that explains or expands upon the required disclosures.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed additional § 1026.41(d) commentary clarifying certain periodic statement disclosure requirements relating to temporary loss mitigation programs. Proposed comment 41(d)-4 would have provided that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2), (3), and (5) regarding how payments will be and were applied should nonetheless identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract, irrespective of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. The Bureau proposed this commentary in response to several inquiries regarding how temporary loss mitigation programs affect certain disclosures on the periodic statement. Currently, the Bureau's rules and commentary do not address this issue.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>As described in the section-by-section analysis of § 1024.36(c)(1), proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4 would have provided that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) remains an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, irrespective of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. Accordingly, the Bureau believed that it was appropriate for the disclosures on the periodic statement required by § 1026.41(d)(2), (3), and (5) to identify how payments will be and are applied according to the loan contract, irrespective of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, because this is how servicers would actually be applying the payments under proposed comment 36(c)(1)(i)-4. The Bureau believed that this treatment would have been appropriate so that the consumer is kept apprised of how payments are being applied, including being notified of any delinquency that may be accumulating during a temporary loss mitigation program.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also proposed comment 41(d)-5 to address the disclosures that servicers must make on the first periodic statement provided to a consumer after an exemption under § 1026.41(e) terminates. Section 1026.41(d) requires that a periodic statement include three disclosures concerning account activity that occurred “since the last statement.” First, § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii) requires the explanation of amount due to identify the total sum of any fees or charges imposed since the last statement. Second, § 1026.41(d)(3)(i) requires the past payment breakdown to disclose all payments received since the last statement, including a breakdown showing the amount, if any, that was applied to principal, interest, escrow, fees and charges, and the amount, if any, sent to any suspense or unapplied funds account. Finally, § 1026.41(d)(4) requires the transaction activity to include a list of all transaction activity that occurred since the last statement.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>In advance of the proposal, the Bureau had received inquiries regarding a servicer's disclosure obligations under § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) for purposes of the first periodic statement provided after an exemption under § 1026.41(e) terminates. The Bureau understood that such circumstances might arise when a servicer provided periodic statements, became exempt from the requirements for one of the reasons under § 1026.41(e), and the exemption subsequently terminated, thereby requiring the servicer to resume providing statements. For example, a servicer may have been exempt from providing periodic statements for the duration of a consumer's bankruptcy case, may have provided coupon books but has now decided to begin providing periodic statements, or may have been exempt from the periodic statement requirement as a small servicer but no longer qualifies for that exemption. Alternatively, a mortgage loan might be transferred from a servicer that provides coupon books or was an exempt small servicer to a servicer that provides periodic statements.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Sections 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) could be interpreted as requiring the periodic statement to include information about account activity for the duration of the exemption period—literally “since the last statement.” The Bureau recognized that there may be benefits to providing a consumer with information regarding all fees and charges imposed, all payments received and applied, and all transaction activity that occurred during the exemption period. A consumer could review this information to determine if a servicer imposed any erroneous fees, failed to properly credit payments, or made other mistakes with respect to the consumer's mortgage loan while the exemption applied. The § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) disclosures, however, generally cover a time period equivalent to a billing cycle, and the first post-exemption periodic statement should arguably cover a similar time period. The proposal would therefore have clarified that the first post-exemption periodic statement may be limited to disclosing the fees and charges imposed, payments received and applied, and transaction activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believed that consumers and servicers may be better served if the first post-exemption periodic statement includes account activity only since the final payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. The Bureau understood that servicers' systems are generally not equipped to provide months' or years' worth of account activity on a single periodic statement. Requiring the disclosure of all fees and charges imposed, payments received, and transaction activity during an exemption period, which could have spanned several months or years, would impose costs on servicers. Similarly, consumers could be confused or overwhelmed by the receipt of a periodic statement listing all account activity during a lengthy exemption period. For example, consumers might believe that listed fees and charges were presently due, even if the consumer had already paid them.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Moreover, including account activity for the duration of the exemption period would have undermined, in part, the rationale for the exemptions. For example, § 1026.41(e)(3) recognizes the value of a coupon book as striking a balance between ensuring consumers receive important information and providing a low-burden method for servicers to comply with the periodic statement requirements.<footnote ref="302">78 FR 10901, 10973 (Feb. 14, 2013).</footnote>
      Requiring the first post-exemption periodic statement to include the disclosures required under § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) for the duration of the exemption arguably would have upset the balance struck by the coupon book exemption. Servicers might be forced to maintain the functional ability to produce periodic statements to account for the possibility of a change from coupon books to periodic statements or a loss of the exemption, thus obviating any burden-reduction features of the exemption.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Consumers either receive, or have alternative methods of obtaining, much of the account information that, under the proposal, would not have been included in the first post-exemption periodic statement. For example, consumers who receive coupon books have a right to request the information set forth in § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4). Similarly, for servicers subject to Regulation X's servicing requirements, a consumer may obtain this information by submitting a written information request. In addition, even if the first post-exemption periodic statement does not include the past payment breakdown since the last pre-exemption periodic statement, § 1026.41(d) requires the statement to identify the total of all payments received since the beginning of the current calendar year. This year-to-date information, while not necessarily covering the entire exemption period, provides consumers with a broad overview of the costs of their mortgage loan and how their payments are being allocated to interest or fees as opposed to principal.<footnote ref="303">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt; at 10966.</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the Bureau proposed comment 41(d)-5, which would have provided that, for purposes of the first periodic statement following termination of an exemption under § 1026.41(e), the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) may be limited to the period since the final payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. Proposed comment 41(d)-5 also provided an illustrative example. The Bureau sought comment on proposed comment 41(d)-5, including whether to disclose account activity since a date other than the final payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>One industry commenter expressed support for the proposed clarifications to the periodic statement requirements generally, while another expressed concern over the costs associated with updating the periodic statements. A few consumer advocacy groups expressed support for proposed comment 41(d)-4 and stated that the proposal accurately reflects the fact that a temporary loss mitigation program does not change the terms of the loan contract.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>For the reasons discussed below, the Bureau is finalizing comments 41(d)-1 through -5 substantially as proposed. Comment 41(d)-1 explains that § 1026.41(d) requires several disclosures to be provided in close proximity to one another. It provides that, to meet this requirement, the items to be provided in close proximity must be grouped together, and set off from other groupings of items. It further provides that this may be accomplished in a variety of ways, for example, by presenting the information in boxes, or by arranging the items on the document and including spacing between the groupings. It clarifies that items in close proximity may not have any unrelated text between them and explains that text is unrelated if it does not explain or expand upon the required disclosures.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comment 41(d)-4 explains that, if the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2), (3), and (5) regarding how payments were and will be applied must identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract, regardless of the temporary loss mitigation program. Final comment 41(d)-4 clarifies the proposed language by explaining that a servicer must, rather than should, identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract, regardless of the temporary loss mitigation program. The Bureau is finalizing this change because it is mandatory that the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2), (3), and (5) identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract. Additionally, the Bureau is finalizing comment 41(d)-4 so that it discusses only temporary loss mitigation programs, rather than referring to both temporary loss mitigation programs and loss mitigation programs.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comment 41(d)-5 explains that § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) require the disclosure of the total sum of any fees or charges imposed since the last statement, the total of all payments received since the last statement, including a breakdown of how payments were applied, and a list of all transaction activity since the last statement. It explains that, for purposes of the first periodic statement provided to the consumer following termination of an exemption under § 1026.41(e), the disclosures required by § 1026.41(d)(2)(ii), (d)(3)(i), and (d)(4) may be limited to account activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. It provides an illustrative example.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-c" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(c) Form of the Periodic Statement</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Current section 1026.41(c) requires servicers to make periodic statement disclosures clearly and conspicuously and in a form the consumer may keep. It provides that proper use of sample forms provided in appendix H-30 complies with these requirements. For the reasons stated in part V.A. and in this discussion, the Bureau is adding new comment 41(c)-5, which explains that servicers may modify the sample forms for periodic statements provided in appendix H-30 to remove language that could suggest liability under the mortgage loan agreement if such language is not applicable.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The sample periodic statement forms in appendix H-30 include language that could suggest liability under the mortgage loan, such as: “You are late on your mortgage payments. Failure to bring your loan current may result in fees and foreclosure—the loss of your home . . . . You must pay this amount to bring your loan current.” Including these statements in notices sent to a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the loan obligation under State law could potentially result in confusion if the servicer has not otherwise clarified that the confirmed successor in interest is not in fact liable on the loan obligation.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Comment 41(c)-5 notes that, for example, in the case of a confirmed successor in interest who has not assumed the mortgage loan obligation and is not otherwise liable on it, a servicer may modify the forms to use “this mortgage” or “the mortgage” instead of “your mortgage”; “The payments on this mortgage are late” instead of “You are late on your mortgage payments”; and “This is the amount needed to bring the loan current” instead of “You must pay this amount to bring your loan current.” As explained in part V.A., the adjustments authorized by comment 41(c)-5 represent one of several options that servicers may use to ensure that their notices and other communications do not confuse or deceive successors in interest who have not assumed the mortgage loan obligation under State law and are not otherwise liable on it regarding whether they are liable on the mortgage loan obligation.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-41-a" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>41(a) In General</title>
    <analysisParagraph>Although the Bureau did not propose to amend comment 41(a)-1, the Bureau is revising the example provided in comment 41(a)-1 to substitute “spouses” for “husband and wife,” in order to align the language with other examples in Regulation Z.<footnote ref="300">Pursuant to the Bureau's Same-Sex Married Couple Policy, &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;see supra&lt;/em&gt; note 39, the Bureau interprets “spouse” to include married same-sex spouses.</footnote>
      Thus, as revised, comment 41(a)-1 explains that, if spouses jointly own a home, a servicer need not send statements to both spouses; a single statement may be sent.<footnote ref="301">Section 1026.41 defines servicers to mean creditors, assignees, or servicers for the purposes of § 1026.41. The Bureau, therefore, also uses the term servicer to mean a creditor, assignee, or servicer in the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.41, except as otherwise noted.</footnote>
    </analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(a)-5.i reiterated for clarity that a servicer must provide a confirmed successor in interest with a periodic statement meeting the requirements of § 1026.41. The Bureau proposed this comment to ensure that the effect of proposed § 1026.2(a)(11) with respect to providing periodic statements to confirmed successors in interest would be clear. However, the Bureau believes that the effect of the final version of § 1026.2(a)(11) with respect to periodic statements is clear from § 1026.2(a)(11) and its commentary and § 1026.41(g), and the Bureau therefore has not included a comment similar to proposed comment 41(a)-5.i in the final rule. Pursuant to § 1026.2(a)(11), comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv, and § 1026.41(g), a servicer must provide a confirmed successor in interest with periodic statements, unless: (1) The servicer is providing the specific periodic statements to another consumer on the account, or (2) the confirmed successor in interest is not liable on the mortgage loan obligation, the servicer has provided a written notice and acknowledgment form in accordance with Regulation X § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv), and the confirmed successor in interest has not provided the servicer an executed acknowledgment that has not been revoked.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(a)-5.ii would have provided that, if a servicer sends a periodic statement meeting the requirements of § 1026.41 to another consumer, the servicer need not also send a periodic statement to a successor in interest; a single statement may be sent. The proposed comment also would have provided that, if a servicer confirms more than one successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling, the servicer need not send periodic statements to more than one of the successors in interest. For the reasons stated in part V.A. and the section-by-section analysis of § 1026.2(a)(11) and in this discussion, the Bureau has decided not to finalize proposed comment 41(a)-5.ii and is instead addressing in comment 2(a)(11)-4.iv whether duplicative periodic statements and other Regulation X disclosures must be sent to confirmed successors in interest.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau solicited comment on whether only one successor in interest should receive a periodic statement or whether instead each successor in interest should receive a periodic statement. A number of industry commenters stated that the rule of joint obligors should apply, such that only one periodic statement is required, and urged the Bureau not to require multiple periodic statements. Some noted that a requirement to provide periodic statements to multiple successors in interest would be extremely burdensome and require significant systems changes. As explained above, various commenters also suggested that the Bureau clarify what is expected with regard to other Mortgage Servicing Rule notices when there are multiple borrowers and suggested that only one notice should be required. In contrast, a consumer advocacy group suggested that anyone with an ownership interest should receive a copy of the periodic statement, provided they have given their contact information to the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
    <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes that servicers should not be required to send more than one periodic statement with respect to a mortgage loan. This is consistent with how periodic statements for multiple obligors are treated in current comment 41(a)-1, which provides that, when two consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling, the periodic statement may be sent to either one of them. Due to the constraints of current systems platforms and other factors, the Bureau recognizes that requiring servicers to send multiple copies of the same periodic statement would impose additional costs. In light of commenters' requests for clarification regarding other notices required by the Mortgage Servicing Rules, the Bureau has decided to address this issue through a more general comment to § 1026.2(a)(11), as explained in the section-by-section analysis of that section. The Bureau is therefore not finalizing proposed comment 41(a)-5.ii.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  <analysisSection target="1026-H-4(C)" notice="2016-18901" date="2016-10-19">
    <title>Appendix H-4(C) to Part 1026</title>
    <analysisParagraph>The 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule revised the commentary to § 1026.19(b) to reflect the revised § 1026.20(c) and revised § 1026.20(d) ARM notices. The proposal would have modified the Variable-Rate Model Clauses in appendix H-4(C) to reflect the language in the revised commentary. The Bureau is adopting these modifications as proposed. No change to the table of contents of appendix H is necessary.</analysisParagraph>
  </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
