<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2016-03-25</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-06834</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2016-03-31</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/03/25/2016-06834/operations-in-rural-areas-under-the-truth-in-lending-act-regulation-z-interim-final-rule</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2015-32293" rightDocumentNumber="2016-06834">
  <!-- Section 1026.35 is amended by revising paragraphs (b)(2)(iii)(A), (b)(2)(iii)(D)(1), and (b)(2)(iv)(A) to read as follows: -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, during either of the two preceding calendar years, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended a <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref>, as defined by § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by a first lien on a property that is located in an area that is either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in paragraph <ref target="1026-43-b-2" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref>(iv) of this section;</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1" marker="(1)">
      <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before May 1, 2016; or</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>An area is “rural” during a calendar year if it is:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget and as they are applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS);</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>A census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census Bureau using the latest decennial census of the United States; or</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-3" marker="(3)">
        <content> county or a census block that has been designated as rural by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> pursuant to the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> process established under section 89002 of the Helping Expand Lending Practices in Rural Communities Act, Public Law 114-94, title LXXXIX (2015). The provisions of this paragraph (b)(2)(iv)(A)(3) shall cease to have any force or effect on December 4, 2017.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change><!-- i. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii), paragraph 1.i is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year, or during either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, secured by a property located in an area that is either “rural” or “underserved,” as set forth in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-A" marker="A.">
        <content>In general, whether the rural-or-underserved test is satisfied depends on the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s activity during the preceding calendar year. However, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan in question was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may instead meet the rural-or-underserved test based on its activity during the next-to-last calendar year. This provides <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> with a <ref target="1026-54-a-2" reftype="term">grace period</ref> if their activity meets the rural-or-underserved test (in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>) in one calendar year but fails to meet it in the next calendar year.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B" marker="B.">
        <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets the rural-or-underserved test for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during a calendar year if it extended a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> in the preceding calendar year secured by a property located in a rural-or-underserved area. If the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not meet the rural-or-underserved test in the preceding calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during the current calendar year only if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the loan was received before April 1 of the current calendar year and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> during the next-to-last calendar year that is secured by a property located in a rural or underserved area. The following examples are illustrative:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B-1" marker="1.">
          <content>Assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended during 2016 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is secured by a property located in a rural or underserved area. Because the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> during 2016 that is secured by a property located in a rural or underserved area, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can meet this condition for exemption for any <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> consummated during 2017.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-Interp-1-i-B-2" marker="2.">
          <content>Assume that a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> did not extend during 2016 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> secured by a property that is located in a rural or underserved area. Assume further that the same <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended during 2015 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is located in a rural or underserved area. Assume further that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> consummates a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> in 2017 for which the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received in November 2017. Because the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> did not extend during 2016 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> secured by a property that is located in a rural or underserved area, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received on or after April 1, 2017, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not meet this condition for exemption. However, assume instead that the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> consummates a <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loan</ref> in 2017 based on an <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> received in February 2017. The <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this condition for exemption for this loan because the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> was received before April 1, 2017, and the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended during 2015 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is located in a rural or underserved area.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- ii. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)( 1 ), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title>Exceptions for certain accounts.</title>
    <content>Escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before May 1, 2016, are not counted for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)</ref>. For applications received on and after May 1, 2016, <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, do not qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref>, together with their <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established for first-lien <ref target="1026-35-a-1" reftype="term">higher-priced mortgage loans</ref> for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before May 1, 2016, still qualify for the exemption provided under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref> so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions for which they received applications on or after May 1, 2016, other than those described in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-D-2" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(2)</ref>, and they otherwise qualify under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)</ref>.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- iii. Under Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iv), paragraphs 1.i and 2.i are revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>, an area is rural during a calendar year if it is: A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area nor in a micropolitan statistical area that is adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area; a census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census Bureau using the latest decennial census of the United States; or a county or a census block that has been designated as “rural” by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> pursuant to the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> process established in 2016. See Application Process for Designation of Rural Area under Federal Consumer Financial Law; Procedural Rule, 81 FR 11099 (Mar. 3, 2016). Metropolitan statistical areas and micropolitan statistical areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget and applied under currently applicable Urban Influence Codes (UICs), established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service (USDA-ERS). For purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref>, “adjacent” has the meaning applied by the USDA-ERS in determining a county's UIC; as so applied, “adjacent” entails a county not only being physically contiguous with a metropolitan statistical area but also meeting certain minimum population commuting patterns. A county is a “rural” area under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref> if the USDA-ERS categorizes the county under UIC 4, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, or 12. Descriptions of UICs are available on the USDA-ERS Web site at http://www.ers.usda.gov/data-products/urban-influence-codes/documentation.aspx. A county for which there is no currently applicable UIC (because the county has been created since the USDA-ERS last categorized counties) is a rural area only if all counties from which the new county's land was taken are themselves rural under currently applicable UICs.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-35-b-2-iv-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
      <content>An area is considered “rural” for a given calendar year based on the most recent available UIC designations by the USDA-ERS and the most recent available delineations of urban areas by the U.S. Census Bureau that are available at the beginning of the calendar year. These designations and delineations are updated by the USDA-ERS and the U.S. Census Bureau respectively once every ten years. As an example, assume a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> in Census Block X that is located in County Y during calendar year 2017. As of January 1, 2017, the most recent UIC designations were published in the second quarter of 2013, and the most recent delineation of urban areas was announced in the Federal Register in 2012, see U.S. Census Bureau, Qualifying Urban Areas for the 2010 Census, 77 FR 18652 (Mar. 27, 2012). To determine whether County Y is rural under the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s definition during calendar year 2017, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can use USDA-ERS's 2013 UIC designations. If County Y is not rural, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> can use the U.S. Census Bureau's 2012 delineation of urban areas to determine whether Census Block X is rural and is therefore a “rural” area for purposes of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)</ref>. In addition, an area is considered “rural” if it is a county or a census block that has been designated as rural by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> using the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> process established in 2016. See Application Process for Designation of Rural Area under Federal Consumer Financial Law; Procedural Rule, 81 FR 11099 (Mar. 3, 2016). Designations under this process are time-limited and expire on December 4, 2017.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- i. Under Paragraph 43(f)(1)(vi), paragraph 1.i is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
      <content>During the preceding calendar year or during either of the two preceding calendar years if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref>, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, on a property that is located in an area that is designated either “rural” or “underserved,” as defined in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, to satisfy the requirement of § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref> (the rural-or-underserved test). Pursuant to § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, an area is considered to be rural if it is: A county that is neither in a metropolitan statistical area, nor a micropolitan statistical area adjacent to a metropolitan statistical area, as those terms are defined by the U.S. Office of Management and Budget; a census block that is not in an urban area, as defined by the U.S. Census Bureau using the latest decennial census of the United States; or a county or a census block that has been designated as “rural” by the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> pursuant to the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> process established in 2016. See Application Process for Designation of Rural Area under Federal Consumer Financial Law; Procedural Rule, 81 FR 11099 (Mar. 3, 2016). An area is considered to be underserved during a calendar year if, according to HMDA data for the preceding calendar year, it is a county in which no more than two <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> extended <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transactions</ref> secured by first liens on properties in the county five or more times.</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-A" marker="A.">
        <content>The <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> determines annually which counties in the United States are rural or underserved as defined by § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-1" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(1)</ref> or § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-B" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(B)</ref> and publishes on its public Web site lists of those counties to assist <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditors</ref> in determining whether they meet the criterion at § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</ref>. <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">Creditors</ref> may also use an automated tool provided on the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref>'s public Web site to determine whether specific properties are located in areas that qualify as “rural” or “underserved” according to the definitions in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref> for a particular calendar year. In addition, the U.S. Census Bureau may also provide on its public Web site an automated address search tool that specifically indicates if a property address is located in an urban area for purposes of the Census Bureau's most recent delineation of urban areas. For any calendar year that begins after the date on which the Census Bureau announced its most recent delineation of urban areas, a property is located in an area that qualifies as “rural” according to the definitions in § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref> if the search results provided for the property by any such automated address search tool available on the Census Bureau's public Web site do not identify the property as being in an urban area. A property is also located in an area that qualifies as “rural,” if the <ref target="1026-2-a-5" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> has designated that area as rural under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv-A-3" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)(A)(3)</ref> and published that determination in the Federal Register. See Application Process for Designation of Rural Area under Federal Consumer Financial Law; Procedural Rule, 81 FR 11099 (Mar. 3, 2016).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-B" marker="B.">
        <content>For example, if a <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> extended during 2017 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is secured by a property that is located in an area that meets the definition of rural or underserved under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> meets this element of the exception for any transaction consummated during 2018.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-43-f-1-vi-Interp-1-i-C" marker="C.">
        <content>Alternatively, if the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> did not extend in 2017 a transaction that meets the definition of rural or underserved test under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> satisfies this criterion for any transaction consummated during 2018 for which it received the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> before April 1, 2018, if it extended during 2016 a first-lien <ref target="1026-42-b-2" reftype="term">covered transaction</ref> that is secured by a property that is located in an area that meets the definition of rural or underserved under § <ref target="1026-35-b-2-iv" reftype="internal">1026.35(b)(2)(iv)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change><!-- ii. Under Paragraph 43(f)(2)(ii), paragraph 1 is revised. -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-2-ii-Interp-1" subpath="title">
    <title>Transfer to another qualifying creditor.</title>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-43-f-2-ii-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Under § <ref target="1026-43-f-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(2)(ii)</ref>, a balloon-payment qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)</ref> may be sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred at any time to another creditor that meets the requirements of § <ref target="1026-43-f-1-vi" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)(vi)</ref>. That section requires that a creditor: (1) Extended a first-lien covered transaction, as defined in § <ref target="1026-43-b-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(b)(1)</ref>, on a property located in a rural or underserved area; (2) together with all affiliates, extended no more than 2,000 first-lien covered transactions that were sold, assigned, or otherwise transferred by the creditor or its affiliates to another person, or that were subject at the time of consummation to a commitment to be acquired by another person; and (3) have, together with its affiliates that regularly extended covered transactions secured by first liens, total assets less than $2 billion (as adjusted for inflation). These tests are assessed based on transactions and assets from the calendar year preceding the current calendar year or from either of the two calendar years preceding the current calendar year if the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> for the transaction was received before April 1 of the current calendar year. A balloon-payment qualified mortgage under § <ref target="1026-43-f-1" reftype="internal">1026.43(f)(1)</ref> transferred to a creditor that meets these criteria would retain its qualified mortgage status even if it is transferred less than three years after consummation.</content>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
