<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2016-10-19</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>TRUTH IN LENDING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>Z</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-18901</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2018-04-19</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/10/19/2016-18901/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation-x</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2017-15764" rightDocumentNumber="2016-18901">
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-2-a-11">
    <paragraph label="1026-2-a-11" marker="(11)">
      <content><def term="consumer">Consumer</def> means a cardholder or natural <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> to whom <ref target="1026-2-a-12" reftype="term">consumer credit</ref> is offered or extended. However, for purposes of rescission under §§ <ref target="1026-15" reftype="internal">1026.15</ref> and <ref target="1026-23" reftype="internal">1026.23</ref>, the term also includes a natural <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref> in whose principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> a <ref target="1026-2-a-25" reftype="term">security interest</ref> is or will be retained or acquired, if that <ref target="1026-2-a-22" reftype="term">person</ref>'s ownership interest in the <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref> is or will be subject to the <ref target="1026-2-a-25" reftype="term">security interest</ref>. For purposes of §§ <ref target="1026-20-c" reftype="internal">1026.20(c)</ref> through <ref target="1026-20-e" reftype="internal">(e)</ref>, <ref target="1026-36-c" reftype="internal">1026.36(c)</ref>, <ref target="1026-39" reftype="internal">1026.39</ref>, and <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>, the term includes a confirmed successor in interest.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-27" parent="1026-2-a">
    <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27" marker="(27)">
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i" marker="(i)">
        <content><def term="successor in interest">Successor in interest</def> means a person to whom an ownership interest in a dwelling securing a closed-end consumer credit transaction is transferred from a consumer, provided that the transfer is:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A transfer by devise, descent, or operation of law on the death of a joint tenant or tenant by the entirety;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A transfer to a relative resulting from the death of the consumer;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>A transfer where the spouse or children of the consumer become an owner of the property;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>A transfer resulting from a decree of a dissolution of marriage, legal separation agreement, or from an incidental property settlement agreement, by which the spouse of the consumer becomes an owner of the property; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-E" marker="(E)">
          <content>A transfer into an inter vivos trust in which the consumer is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a transfer of rights of occupancy in the property.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-2-a-27-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content><def term="confirmed successor in interest">Confirmed successor in interest</def> means a successor in interest once a servicer has confirmed the successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the dwelling.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-20-f" parent="1026-20" after="1026-20-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-20-f" marker="(f)">
      <title>Successor in interest.</title>
      <content>If, upon confirmation, a servicer provides a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the mortgage loan obligation with a written notice and acknowledgment form in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1) of this chapter, the servicer is not required to provide to the confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by paragraphs (c), (d), and (e) of this section unless and until the confirmed successor in interest either assumes the mortgage loan obligation under State law or has provided the servicer an executed acknowledgment in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv) of this chapter, that the confirmed successor in interest has not revoked.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-c-1">
    <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1" marker="(1)">
      <title>Payment processing.</title>
      <content>In connection with a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1-i" marker="(i)">
        <title>Periodic payments.</title>
        <content>No servicer shall fail to <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> a periodic payment to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s loan account as of the date of receipt, except when a delay in crediting does not result in any charge to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> or in the reporting of negative information to a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> reporti<ref target="1026-36-c-2" reftype="internal">ng age</ref>ncy, or except as provided in paragraph (c)(1)(iii) of this section. A periodic payment, as used in this paragraph (c), is an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref>. A payment qualifies as a periodic payment even if it does not include amounts required to cover late fees, other fees, or non-escrow payments a servicer has advanced on a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s behalf.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title>Partial payments.</title>
        <content>Any servicer that retains a partial payment, meaning any payment less than a periodic payment, in a suspense or unapplied funds account shall:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Disclose to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> the total amount of funds held in such suspense or unapplied funds account on the periodic statement as required by § <ref target="1026-41-d-3" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(3)</ref>, if a periodic statement is required; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>On accumulation of sufficient funds to cover a periodic payment in any suspense or unapplied funds account, treat such funds as a periodic payment received in accordance with paragraph <ref target="1026-36-c-1-i" reftype="internal">(c)(1)(i)</ref> of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-36-c-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <title>Non-conforming payments.</title>
        <content>If a servicer specifies in writing requirements for the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to follow in making payments, but accepts a payment that does not conform to the requirements, the servicer shall <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> the payment as of five days after receipt.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-c-2">
    <paragraph label="1026-36-c-2" marker="(2)">
      <title>No pyramiding of late fees.</title>
      <content>In connection with a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s principal <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, a servicer shall not impose any late fee or delinquency charge for a payment if:</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-d-8-i">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-d-8-i" marker="(i)">
      <content>The length of the consumer's delinquency;</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-e-4-iii-A">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" marker="(A)">
      <content>Mortgage loans voluntarily serviced by the servicer for a non-affiliate of the servicer and for which the servicer does not receive any compensation or fees.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-4-iii-D" parent="1026-41-e-4-iii">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-D" marker="(D)">
      <content>Transactions serviced by the servicer for a seller financer that meets all of the criteria identified in § <ref target="1026-36-a-5" reftype="internal">1026.36(a)(5)</ref>.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-e-5" parent="1026-41-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5" marker="(5)">
      <title>Certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i" marker="(i)">
        <title>Exemption.</title>
        <content>Except as provided in paragraph (e)(5)(ii) of this section, a servicer is exempt from the requirements of this section with regard to a mortgage loan if:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Any consumer on the mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code or has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>With regard to any consumer on the mortgage loan:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The consumer requests in writing that the servicer cease providing a periodic statement or coupon book;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The consumer's bankruptcy plan provides that the consumer will surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan, provides for the avoidance of the lien securing the mortgage loan, or otherwise does not provide for, as applicable, the payment of pre-bankruptcy arrearage or the maintenance of payments due under the mortgage loan;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>A court enters an order in the bankruptcy case providing for the avoidance of the lien securing the mortgage loan, lifting the automatic stay pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 362 with regard to the dwelling securing the mortgage loan, or requiring the servicer to cease providing a periodic statement or coupon book; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The consumer files with the court overseeing the bankruptcy case a statement of intention pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 521(a) identifying an intent to surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan and a consumer has not made any partial or periodic payment on the mortgage loan after the commencement of the consumer's bankruptcy case.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title>Reaffirmation or consumer request to receive statement or coupon book.</title>
        <content>A servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to paragraph (e)(5)(i) of this section with respect to a mortgage loan if the consumer reaffirms personal liability for the loan or any consumer on the loan requests in writing that the servicer provide a periodic statement or coupon book, unless a court enters an order in the bankruptcy case requiring the servicer to cease providing a periodic statement or coupon book.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <title>Exclusive address.</title>
        <content>A servicer may establish an address that a consumer must use to submit a written request under paragraph (e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) of this section, provided that the servicer notifies the consumer of the address in a manner that is reasonably designed to inform the consumer of the address. If a servicer designates a specific address for requests under paragraph (e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) of this section, the servicer shall designate the same address for purposes of both paragraphs (e)(5)(i)(B)(1) and (e)(5)(ii) of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <title>Timing of compliance following transition</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A" marker="(A)">
          <title>Triggering events for transitioning to modified and unmodified periodic statements.</title>
          <content>A servicer transitions to providing a periodic statement or coupon book with the modifications set forth in paragraph (f) of this section or to providing a periodic statement or coupon book without such modifications when one of the following three events occurs:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>A mortgage loan becomes subject to the requirements of paragraph (f) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>A mortgage loan ceases to be subject to the requirements of paragraph (f) of this section; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>A servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to paragraph (e)(5)(i) of this section with respect to a mortgage loan.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-B" marker="(B)">
          <title>Transitional single-billing-cycle exemption.</title>
          <content>A servicer is exempt from the requirements of this section with respect to a single billing cycle when the payment due date for that billing cycle is no more than 14 days after the date on which one of the events listed in paragraph (e)(5)(iv)(A) of this section occurs.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C" marker="(C)">
          <title>Timing of first modified or unmodified statement after transition.</title>
          <content>When one of the events listed in paragraph (e)(5)(iv)(A) of this section occurs, a servicer must provide the next modified or unmodified periodic statement or coupon book that complies with the requirements of this section by delivering or placing it in the mail within a reasonably prompt time after the first payment due date, or the end of any courtesy period for the payment's corresponding billing cycle, that is more than 14 days after the date on which the applicable event listed in paragraph (e)(5)(iv)(A) of this section occurs.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-e-6" parent="1026-41-e">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6" marker="(6)">
      <title>Charged-off loans.</title>
      <content/>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>A servicer is exempt from the requirements of this section for a mortgage loan if the servicer:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Has charged off the loan in accordance with loan-loss provisions and will not charge any additional fees or interest on the account; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>Provides, within 30 days of charge-off or the most recent periodic statement, a periodic statement, clearly and conspicuously labeled “Suspension of Statements &amp; Notice of Charge Off-Retain This Copy for Your Records.” The periodic statement must clearly and conspicuously explain that, as applicable, the mortgage loan has been charged off and the servicer will not charge any additional fees or interest on the account; the servicer will no longer provide the consumer a periodic statement for each billing cycle; the lien on the property remains in place and the consumer remains liable for the mortgage loan obligation and any obligations arising from or related to the property, which may include property taxes; the consumer may be required to pay the balance on the account in the future, for example, upon sale of the property; the balance on the account is not being canceled or forgiven; and the loan may be purchased, assigned, or transferred.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title>Resuming compliance.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>If a servicer fails at any time to treat a mortgage loan that is exempt under paragraph (e)(6)(i) of this section as charged off or charges any additional fees or interest on the account, the obligation to provide a periodic statement pursuant to this section resumes.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-e-6-ii-B" marker="(B)">
          <title>Prohibition on retroactive fees.</title>
          <content>A servicer may not retroactively assess fees or interest on the account for the period of time during which the exemption in paragraph (e)(6)(i) of this section applied.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f" parent="1026-41">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-f" marker="(f)">
      <title>Modified periodic statements and coupon books for certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <content>While any consumer on a mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code, or if such consumer has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328, the requirements of this section are subject to the following modifications with regard to that mortgage loan:</content>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-f-1" marker="(1)">
        <title>Requirements not applicable.</title>
        <content>The periodic statement may omit the information set forth in paragraphs (d)(1)(ii) and (d)(8)(i), (ii), and (v) of this section. The requirement in paragraph (d)(1)(iii) of this section that the amount due must be shown more prominently than other disclosures on the page shall not apply.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-f-2" marker="(2)">
        <title>Bankruptcy notices.</title>
        <content>The periodic statement must include the following:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>A statement identifying the consumer's status as a debtor in bankruptcy or the discharged status of the mortgage loan; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>A statement that the periodic statement is for informational purposes only.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3" marker="(3)">
        <title>Chapter 12 and chapter 13 consumers.</title>
        <content>In addition to any other provisions of this paragraph (f) that may apply, with regard to a mortgage loan for which any consumer with primary liability is a debtor in a chapter 12 or chapter 13 bankruptcy case, the requirements of this section are subject to the following modifications:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-i" marker="(i)">
          <title>Requirements not applicable.</title>
          <content>In addition to omitting the information set forth in paragraph (f)(1) of this section, the periodic statement may also omit the information set forth in paragraphs (d)(8)(iii), (iv), (vi), and (vii) of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title>Amount due.</title>
          <content>The amount due information set forth in paragraph (d)(1) of this section may be limited to the date and amount of the post-petition payments due and any post-petition fees and charges imposed by the servicer.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <title>Explanation of amount due.</title>
          <content>The explanation of amount due information set forth in paragraph (d)(2) of this section may be limited to:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The monthly post-petition payment amount, including a breakdown showing how much, if any, will be applied to principal, interest, and escrow;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The total sum of any post-petition fees or charges imposed since the last statement; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>Any post-petition payment amount past due.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-iv" marker="(iv)">
          <title>Transaction activity.</title>
          <content>The transaction activity information set forth in paragraph (d)(4) of this section must include all payments the servicer has received since the last statement, including all post-petition and pre-petition payments and payments of post-petition fees and charges, and all post-petition fees and charges the servicer has imposed since the last statement. The brief description of the activity need not identify the source of any payments.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-v" marker="(v)">
          <title>Pre-petition arrearage.</title>
          <content>If applicable, a servicer must disclose, grouped in close proximity to each other and located on the first page of the statement or, alternatively, on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The total of all pre-petition payments received since the last statement;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The total of all pre-petition payments received since the beginning of the consumer's bankruptcy case; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The current balance of the consumer's pre-petition arrearage.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi" marker="(vi)">
          <title>Additional disclosures.</title>
          <content>The periodic statement must include, as applicable:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>A statement that the amount due includes only post-petition payments and does not include other payments that may be due under the terms of the consumer's bankruptcy plan;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>If the consumer's bankruptcy plan requires the consumer to make the post-petition mortgage payments directly to a bankruptcy trustee, a statement that the consumer should send the payment to the trustee and not to the servicer;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>A statement that the information disclosed on the periodic statement may not include payments the consumer has made to the trustee and may not be consistent with the trustee's records;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>A statement that encourages the consumer to contact the consumer's attorney or the trustee with questions regarding the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> of payments; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-41-f-3-vi-E" marker="(E)">
            <content>If the consumer is more than 45 days delinquent on post-petition payments, a statement that the servicer has not received all the payments that became due since the consumer filed for bankruptcy.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-f-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Multiple obligors.</title>
        <content>If this paragraph (f) applies in connection with a mortgage loan with more than one primary obligor, the servicer may provide the modified statement to any or all of the primary obligors, even if a primary obligor to whom the servicer provides the modified statement is not a debtor in bankruptcy.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-41-f-5" marker="(5)">
        <title>Coupon books.</title>
        <content>A servicer that provides a coupon book instead of a periodic statement under paragraph (e)(3) of this section must include in the coupon book the disclosures set forth in paragraphs (f)(2) and (f)(3)(vi) of this section, as applicable. The servicer may include these disclosures anywhere in the coupon book provided to the consumer or on a separate page enclosed with the coupon book. The servicer must make available upon request to the consumer by telephone, in writing, in person, or electronically, if the consumer consents, the information listed in paragraph (f)(3)(v) of this section, as applicable. The modifications set forth in paragraphs (f)(1) and (f)(3)(i) through (iv) and (vi) of this section apply to a coupon book and other information a servicer provides to the consumer under paragraph (e)(3) of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-g" parent="1026-41">
    <paragraph label="1026-41-g" marker="(g)">
      <title>Successor in interest.</title>
      <content>If, upon confirmation, a servicer provides a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the mortgage loan obligation with a written notice and acknowledgment form in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1) of this chapter, the servicer is not required to provide to the confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by this section unless and until the confirmed successor in interest either assumes the mortgage loan obligation under State law or has provided the servicer an executed acknowledgment in accordance with Regulation X, § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv) of this chapter, that the confirmed successor in interest has not revoked.</content>
    </paragraph>
  </change>
    <!-- Update TOC with H-30(E) and H-30(F) -->
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-TOC">
      <tableOfContents label="1026-H-TOC">
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-1">
          <appendixLetter>1</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-1—Credit Sale Model Form (§ 1026.18)</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-2">
          <appendixLetter>2</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-2—Loan Model Form (§ 1026.18)</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-3">
          <appendixLetter>3</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-3—Amount Financed Itemization Model Form (§ 1026.18(c))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(A)">
          <appendixLetter>4(A)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(A)—Variable-Rate Model Clauses (§ 1026.18(f)(1))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(B)">
          <appendixLetter>4(B)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(B)—Variable-Rate Model Clauses (§ 1026.18(f)(2))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(C)">
          <appendixLetter>4(C)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(C)—Variable-Rate Model Clauses (§ 1026.19(b))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(D)">
          <appendixLetter>4(D)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(D) – Variable-Rate Model Clauses (§ 1026.20(c))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(E)">
          <appendixLetter>4(E)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(E) Fixed Rate Mortgage Interest Rate and Payment Summary Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(F)">
          <appendixLetter>4(F)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(F) Adjustable-Rate Mortgage or Step-Rate Mortgage Interest Rate and Payment Summary Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(G)">
          <appendixLetter>4(G)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(G) Mortgage with Negative Amortization Interest Rate and Payment Summary Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(H)">
          <appendixLetter>4(H)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(H) Fixed Rate Mortgage with Interest Only Interest Rate and Payment Summary Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(I)">
          <appendixLetter>4(I)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(I)—Introductory Rate Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s)(2)(iii))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(J)">
          <appendixLetter>4(J)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(J)—Balloon Payment Model Clause (§ 1026.18(s)(5))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-4(K)">
          <appendixLetter>4(K)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-4(K)—“No-Guarantee-to-Refinance” Statement Model Clause (§ 1026.18(t))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-5">
          <appendixLetter>5</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-5–Demand Feature Model Clauses (§ 1026.18(i))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-6">
          <appendixLetter>6</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-6–Assumption Policy Model Clause (§ 1026.18(q))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-7">
          <appendixLetter>7</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-7–Required Deposit Model Clause (§ 1026.18(r))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-8">
          <appendixLetter>8</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-8—Rescission Model Form (General) (§ 1026.23)</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-9">
          <appendixLetter>9</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-9—Rescission Model Form (Refinancing With Original Creditor) (§ 1026.23)</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-10">
          <appendixLetter>10</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-10—Credit Sale Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-11">
          <appendixLetter>11</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-11—Installment Loan Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-12">
          <appendixLetter>12</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-12—Refinancing Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-13">
          <appendixLetter>13</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-13—Mortgage with Demand Feature Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-14">
          <appendixLetter>14</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-14—Variable-Rate Mortgage Sample (§ 1026.19(b))</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-15">
          <appendixLetter>15</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-15—Graduated Payment Mortgage Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-16">
          <appendixLetter>16</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-16—Mortgage Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-17(A)">
          <appendixLetter>17(A)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-17(A) Debt Suspension Model Clause</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-17(B)">
          <appendixLetter>17(B)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-17(B) Debt Suspension Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-18">
          <appendixLetter>18</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-18—Private Education Loan Application and Solicitation Model Form</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-19">
          <appendixLetter>19</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-19—Private Education Loan Approval Model Form</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-20">
          <appendixLetter>20</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-20—Private Education Loan Final Model Form</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-21">
          <appendixLetter>21</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-21—Private Education Loan Application and Solicitation Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-22">
          <appendixLetter>22</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-22—Private Education Loan Approval Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-23">
          <appendixLetter>23</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-23—Private Education Loan Final  Sample</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(A)">
          <appendixLetter>30(A)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(A) Sample Form of Periodic Statement</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(B)">
          <appendixLetter>30(B)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(B) Sample Form of Periodic Statement with Delinquency Box</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(C)">
          <appendixLetter>30(C)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(C) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for a Payment-Option Loan (§ 1026.41)</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(D)">
          <appendixLetter>30(D)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(D) Sample Clause for Homeownership Counselor Contact Information</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(E)">
          <appendixLetter>30(E)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(E) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 7 or Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
        <tocAppEntry target="1026-H-30(F)">
          <appendixLetter>30(F)</appendixLetter>
          <appendixSubject>H-30(F) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 12 or Chapter 13 Bankruptcy</appendixSubject>
        </tocAppEntry>
      </tableOfContents>
    </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-4(C)">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="6" label="1026-H-4(C)">
      <subject>H-4(C)—Variable-Rate Model Clauses</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p31" marker="">
        <content>This disclosure describes the features of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-i" reftype="term">adjustable-rate mortgage</ref> (ARM) program you are considering. Information on other ARM programs is available upon request.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p32" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate and Payment Are Determined.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p33" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will be based on [an index plus a margin] [a formula].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p34" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment will be based on the interest rate, loan balance, and <ref target="1026-43-b-6" reftype="term">loan term</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p35" marker="">
          <content>—[The interest rate will be based on (identification of index) plus our margin. Ask for our current interest rate and margin.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p36" marker="">
          <content>—[The interest rate will be based on (identification of formula). Ask us for our current interest rate.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p37" marker="">
          <content>—Information about the index [formula for rate adjustments] is published [can be found] ______.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-p38" marker="">
          <content>—[The initial interest rate is not based on the (index) (formula) used to make later adjustments. Ask us for the amount of current interest rate discounts.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate Can Change.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p39" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate can change (frequency).</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p40" marker="">
          <content>• [Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than __ percentage points at each adjustment.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-p41" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase [or decrease] more than __ percentage points over the term of the loan.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4" marker="">
        <title>How Your Payment Can Change.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p42" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment can change (frequency) based on changes in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p43" marker="">
          <content>• [Your payment cannot increase more than (amount or percentage) at each adjustment.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p44" marker="">
          <content>• You will be notified in writing ____ days before the due date of a payment at a new level. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount, and loan balance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p45" marker="">
          <content>• [You will be notified once each year during which interest rate adjustments, but no payment adjustments, have been made to your loan. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount, and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p46" marker="">
          <content>• [For example, on a $10,000 [term] loan with an initial interest rate of ____ [(the rate shown in the interest rate column below for the year 19 ____)] [(in effect (month) (year)], the maximum amount that the interest rate can rise under this program is ____ percentage points, to ____%, and the monthly payment can rise from a first-year payment of $____ to a maximum of $____ in the _____ year. To see what your payments would be, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 would be: $60,000 ÷ $10,000 = 6; 6 × ____ = $____ per month.)]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p47" marker="">
        <title>Example.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p48" marker="">
          <content>The example below shows how your payments would have changed under this ARM program based on actual changes in the index from 1982 to 1996. This does not necessarily indicate how your index will change in the future.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p49" marker="">
          <content>The example is based on the following assumptions:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p50" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.036)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.036.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.036.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p51" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.037)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.037.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.037.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-4(C)-h3-h4-p52" marker="">
          <content>Note: To see what your payments would have been during that period, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, in 1996 the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 taken out in 1982 would be: $60,000÷$10,000=6; 6x____=$____per month.)</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-14">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="27" label="1026-H-14">
      <subject>H-14—Variable-Rate Mortgage Sample</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-p94" marker="">
        <content>This disclosure describes the features of the <ref target="1026-18-s-7-i" reftype="term">adjustable-rate mortgage</ref> (ARM) program you are considering. Information on other ARM programs is available upon request.</content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate and Payment Are Determined.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p95" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will be based on an index rate plus a margin.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p96" marker="">
          <content>• Your payment will be based on the interest rate, loan balance, and <ref target="1026-43-b-6" reftype="term">loan term</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p97" marker="">
          <content>—The interest rate will be based on the weekly average yield on United States Treasury securities adjusted to a constant maturity of 1 year (your index), plus our margin. Ask us for our current interest rate and margin.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p98" marker="">
          <content>—Information about the index rate is published weekly in the Wall Street Journal.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h9-p99" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate will equal the index rate plus our margin unless your interest rate “caps” limit the amount of change in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10" marker="">
        <title>How Your Interest Rate Can Change.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p100" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate can change yearly.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p101" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than 2 percentage points per year.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h10-p102" marker="">
          <content>• Your interest rate cannot increase or decrease more than 5 percentage points over the term of the loan.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11" marker="">
        <title>How Your Monthly Payment Can Change.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p103" marker="">
          <content>• Your monthly payment can increase or decrease substantially based on annual changes in the interest rate.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p104" marker="">
          <content>• [For example, on a $10,000, 30-year loan with an initial interest rate of 12.41 percent in effect in July 1996, the maximum amount that the interest rate can rise under this program is 5 percentage points, to 17.41 percent, and the monthly payment can rise from a first-year payment of $106.03 to a maximum of $145.34 in the fourth year. To see what your payment is, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 would be: $60,000 ÷ $10,000 = 6; 6 × 106.03 = $636.18 per month.)</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p105" marker="">
          <content>• You will be notified in writing 25 days before the annual payment adjustment may be made. This notice will contain information about your interest rates, payment amount and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p106" marker="">
        <title>Example.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p107" marker="">
          <content>The example below shows how your payments would have changed under this ARM program based on actual changes in the index from 1982 to 1996. This does not necessarily indicate how your index will change in the future. The example is based on the following assumptions:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p108" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.046)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.046.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.046.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p109" marker="">
          <content>
            <graphic>
              <altText/>
              <text>![](ER22DE11.047)</text>
              <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.047.png</url>
              <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER22DE11.047.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
            </graphic>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p110" marker="">
          <content>
            <callout type="note">
              <line>Note:</line>
              <line>To see what your payments would have been during that period, divide your mortgage amount by $10,000; then multiply the monthly payment by that amount. (For example, in 1996 the monthly payment for a mortgage amount of $60,000 taken out in 1982 would be: $60,000÷$10,000=6; 6×$106.73=$640.38.)</line>
            </callout>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p111" marker="">
          <content>• [You will be notified at least 210, but no more than 240, days before first payment at the adjusted level is due after the initial interest rate adjustment of the loan. This notice will contain information about the adjustment, including the interest rate, payment amount, and loan balance.]
   </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-H-14-h11-p112" marker="">
          <content>[You will be notified at least 60, but no more than 120, days before first payment at the adjusted level is due after any interest rate adjustment resulting in a corresponding payment change. This notice will contain information about the adjustment, including the interest rate, payment amount, and loan balance.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-H-30(C)">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="40" label="1026-H-30(C)">
      <subject>H-30(C) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for a Payment-Option Loan (§ 1026.41)</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(C)-p7" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER14FE13.010-1)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER14FE13.010-1.png</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER14FE13.010-1.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-H-30(E)" parent="1026-H">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="42" label="1026-H-30(E)">
      <subject>H-30(E) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 7 or Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(E)-p1" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER19OC16.001)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/images.federalregister.gov/ER19OC16.001/large.png</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.001.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-H-30(F)" parent="1026-H">
    <appendixSection appendixSecNum="43" label="1026-H-30(F)">
      <subject>H-30(F) Sample Form of Periodic Statement for Consumer in Chapter 12 or Chapter 13 Bankruptcy</subject>
      <paragraph label="1026-H-30(F)-p1" marker="">
        <content>
          <graphic>
            <altText/>
            <text>![](ER19OC16.002)</text>
            <url>https://s3.amazonaws.com/images.federalregister.gov/ER19OC16.002/original.png?</url>
            <thumbUrl>https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/eregulations/ER19OC16.002.thumb.png</thumbUrl>
          </graphic>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </appendixSection>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4" parent="1026-2-a-11-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Successors in interest.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
        <title>Assumption of the mortgage loan obligation.</title>
        <content>A servicer may not require a confirmed successor in interest to assume the mortgage loan obligation to be considered a consumer for purposes of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41. If a successor in interest assumes a mortgage loan obligation under State law or is otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, the protections the successor in interest enjoys under this part are not limited to §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and 1026.41.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
        <title>Communications with confirmed successors in interest.</title>
        <content>Communications in compliance with this part to a confirmed successor in interest as defined in § 1026.2(a)(27)(ii) do not violate section 805(b) of the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) because consumer for purposes of FDCPA section 805 includes any person who meets the definition in this part of confirmed successor in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-iii" marker="iii.">
        <title>Treatment of transferor consumer.</title>
        <content>Even after a servicer's confirmation of a successor in interest, the servicer is still required to comply with all applicable requirements of §§ 1026.20(c) through (e), 1026.36(c), 1026.39, and <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref> with respect to the consumer who transferred an ownership interest to the successor in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-4-iv" marker="iv.">
        <title>Multiple notices unnecessary.</title>
        <content>Except as required by Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.36, a servicer is not required to provide to a confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 if the servicer is providing the same specific disclosure to another consumer on the account. For example, a servicer is not required to provide a periodic statement required by § 1026.41 to a confirmed successor in interest if the servicer is providing the same periodic statement to another consumer; a single statement may be sent in that billing cycle. If a servicer confirms more than one successor in interest, the servicer need not send any disclosure required by § 1026.20(c), (d), or (e), § 1026.39, or § 1026.41 to more than one of the confirmed successors in interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-2-a-27-Interp" parent="1026-2-a-Interp" after="1026-2-a-25-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-Interp">
      <title>Paragraph 2(a)(27).</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp" target="1026-2-a-27-i">
        <title>2(a)(27)(i) Successor in interest.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Joint tenants and tenants by the entirety.</title>
          <content>If a consumer who has an ownership interest as a joint tenant or tenant by the entirety in a dwelling securing a closed-end consumer credit transaction dies, a surviving joint tenant or tenant by the entirety with a right of survivorship in the property is a successor in interest as defined in § 1026.2(a)(27)(i).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-2-a-27-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Beneficiaries of inter vivos trusts.</title>
          <content>In the event of a transfer into an inter vivos trust in which the consumer is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a transfer of rights of occupancy in the property, the beneficiaries of the inter vivos trust rather than the inter vivos trust itself are considered to be the successors in interest for purposes of § 1026.2(a)(27)(i). For example, assume Consumer A transfers her home into such an inter vivos trust for the benefit of her spouse and herself. As of the transfer date, Consumer A and her spouse are considered successors in interest and, upon confirmation, are consumers for purposes of certain provisions of this part. If the creditor has not released Consumer A from the loan obligation, Consumer A also remains a consumer more generally for purposes of this part.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-20-e-4-Interp-4" parent="1026-20-e-4-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-20-e-4-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Modifications of disclosures.</title>
      <content>The requirements of § 1026.20(e)(4) to provide the § 1026.20(e) disclosures with the headings, content, order, and format substantially similar to model form H-29 in appendix H to this part do not preclude creditors and servicers from modifying the disclosures to accommodate particular consumer circumstances or transactions not addressed by the form or from adjusting the statement required by § 1026.20(e)(2)(ii)(A), concerning consequences if the consumer fails to pay property costs, to the circumstances of the particular consumer.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp-4" parent="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp-4" marker="4.">
      <title>Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
      <content>If a loan contract has not been permanently modified but the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is the amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the loan contract, regardless of the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp-5" parent="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-c-1-i-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title>Permanent loan modifications.</title>
      <content>If a loan contract has been permanently modified, a periodic payment under § 1026.36(c)(1)(i) is an amount sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow (if applicable) for a given billing cycle under the modified loan contract.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-2" parent="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-36-c-1-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
      <title>Payment requirements—Limitations.</title>
      <content>Requirements for making payments must be reasonable; it should not be difficult for most consumers and potential successors in interest to make conforming payments. For example, it would be reasonable to require a cut-off time of 5 p.m. for receipt of a mailed check at the location specified by the servicer for receipt of such check.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-a-Interp-1">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-a-Interp-1" marker="1.">
      <title>Recipient of periodic statement.</title>
      <content>When two consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling subject to § 1026.41, the periodic statement may be sent to either one of them. For example, if spouses jointly own a home, the servicer need not send statements to both spouses; a single statement may be sent.</content>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-c-Interp-5" parent="1026-41-c-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5" marker="5.">
      <title>Permissible changes.</title>
      <content>Servicers may modify the sample forms for periodic statements provided in appendix H-30 of this part to remove language that could suggest liability under the mortgage loan agreement if such language is not applicable. For example, in the case of a confirmed successor in interest who has not assumed the mortgage loan obligation under State law and is not otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, a servicer may modify the forms to:</content>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
        <content>Use “this mortgage” or “the mortgage” instead of “your mortgage.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
        <content>Use “The payments on this mortgage are late” instead of “You are late on your mortgage payments.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-c-Interp-5-iii" marker="iii.">
        <content>Use “This is the amount needed to bring the loan current” instead of “You must pay this amount to bring your loan current.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-d-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp" target="1026-41-d">
    <title>41(d) Content and layout of the periodic statement.</title>
    <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Close proximity.</title>
        <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-d" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)</ref> requires several disclosures to be provided in close proximity to one another. To meet this requirement, the items to be provided in close proximity must be grouped together, and set off from other groupings of items. This may be accomplished in a variety of ways, for example, by presenting the information in boxes, or by arranging the items on the document and including spacing between the groupings. Items in close proximity may not have any unrelated text between them. Text is unrelated if it does not explain or expand upon the required disclosures.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Not Applicable.</title>
        <content>If an item required by paragraph <ref target="1026-41-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref> or <ref target="1026-41-e" reftype="internal">(e)</ref> of this section is not applicable to the loan, it may be omitted from the periodic statement or coupon book. For example, if there is no prepayment penalty associated with a loan, the prepayment penalty disclosures need not be provided on the periodic statement.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title type="keyterm">Terminology.</title>
        <content>A servicer may use terminology other than that found on the sample periodic statements in appendix H-30, so long as the new terminology is commonly understood. For example, servicers may take into consideration regional differences in terminology and refer to the account for the collection of taxes and insurance, referred to in § <ref target="1026-41-d" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)</ref> as the “escrow account,” as an “impound account.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title type="keyterm">Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
        <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-41-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)</ref>, <ref target="1026-41-d-3" reftype="internal">(3)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-41-d-5" reftype="internal">(5)</ref> regarding how payments were and will be applied must identify how payments are applied according to the loan contract, regardless of the temporary loss mitigation program.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title type="keyterm">First statement after exemption terminates.</title>
        <content>Section <ref target="1026-41-d-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)(ii)</ref>, <ref target="1026-41-d-3-i" reftype="internal">(d)(3)(i)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-41-d-4" reftype="internal">(d)(4)</ref> requires the disclosure of the total sum of any fees or charges imposed since the last statement, the total of all payments received since the last statement, including a breakdown of how payments were applied, and a list of all transaction activity since the last statement. For purposes of the first periodic statement provided to the consumer following termination of an exemption under § <ref target="1026-41-e" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)</ref>, the disclosures required by § <ref target="1026-41-d-2-ii" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)(ii)</ref>, <ref target="1026-41-d-3-i" reftype="internal">(d)(3)(i)</ref>, and <ref target="1026-41-d-4" reftype="internal">(d)(4)</ref> may be limited to account activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. For example, if mortgage loan payments are due on the first of each month and the servicer's exemption under § <ref target="1026-41-e" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)</ref> terminated on January 15, the first statement provided to the consumer after January 15 may be limited to the total sum of any fees or charges imposed, the total of all payments received, a breakdown of how the payments were applied, and a list of all transaction activity since January 1.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp" target="1026-41-d-1">
        <title>41(d)(1) Amount due.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Acceleration.</title>
          <content>If the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the amount due under § <ref target="1026-41-d-1" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(1)</ref> must identify only the lesser amount that will be accepted to reinstate the loan. The periodic statement must be accurate when provided and should indicate, if applicable, that the amount due is accurate only for a specified period of time. For example, the statement may include language such as “as of [date]” or “good through [date]” and provide an amount due that will reinstate the loan as of that date or good through that date, respectively.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
          <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program, the amount due under § <ref target="1026-41-d-1" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(1)</ref> may identify either the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program or the amount due according to the loan contract.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Permanent loan modifications.</title>
          <content>If the loan contract has been permanently modified, the amount due under § <ref target="1026-41-d-1" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(1)</ref> must identify only the amount due under the modified loan contract.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp" target="1026-41-d-2">
        <title>41(d)(2) Explanation of amount due.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Acceleration.</title>
          <content>If the balance of a mortgage loan has been accelerated but the servicer will accept a lesser amount to reinstate the loan, the explanation of amount due under § <ref target="1026-41-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)</ref> must list both the reinstatement amount that is disclosed as the amount due and the accelerated amount but not the monthly payment amount that would otherwise be required under § <ref target="1026-41-d-2-i" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)(i)</ref>. The periodic statement must also include an explanation that the reinstatement amount will be accepted to reinstate the loan through the “as of [date]” or “good through [date],” as applicable, along with any special instructions for submitting the payment. The explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement. The explanation may include related information, such as a statement that the amount disclosed is “not a payoff amount.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Temporary loss mitigation programs.</title>
          <content>If the consumer has agreed to a temporary loss mitigation program and the amount due identifies the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program, the explanation of amount due under § <ref target="1026-41-d-2" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(2)</ref> must include both the amount due according to the loan contract and the payment due under the temporary loss mitigation program. The statement must also include an explanation that the amount due is being disclosed as a different amount because of the temporary loss mitigation program. The explanation should be on the front page of the statement or, alternatively, may be included on a separate page enclosed with the periodic statement or in a separate letter.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-3-Interp" target="1026-41-d-3">
        <title>41(d)(3) Past payment breakdown.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Partial Payments.</title>
          <content>The disclosure of any partial payments received since the previous statement that were sent to a suspense or unapplied funds account as required by § <ref target="1026-41-d-3-i" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(3)(i)</ref> should reflect any funds that were received in the time period covered by the current statement and that were placed in such account. The disclosure of any portion of payments since the beginning of the calendar year that was sent to a partial payment or suspense account as required by § <ref target="1026-41-d-3-ii" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(3)(ii)</ref> should reflect all funds that are currently held in a suspense or unapplied funds account. For example:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-3-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Suppose a payment of $1,000 is due, but the consumer sends in only $600 on January 1, which is held in a suspense account. Further assume there are no fees charged on this account. Assuming there are no other funds in the suspense account, the January statement should reflect: Unapplied funds since last statement—$600. Unapplied funds YTD—$600.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-3-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>Assume the same facts as in the preceding paragraph, except that during February the consumer sends in $300 and this too is held in the suspense account. The statement should reflect: Unapplied funds since last statement—$300. Unapplied funds YTD—$900.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-3-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>Assume the same facts as in the preceding paragraph, except that during March the consumer sends in $400. Of this payment, $100 completes a full periodic payment when added to the $900 in funds already held in the suspense account. This $1,000 is applied to the January payment, and the remaining $300 remains in the suspense account. The statement should reflect: Unapplied funds since last statement—$300. Unapplied Funds YTD—$300.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp" target="1026-41-d-4">
        <title>41(d)(4) Transaction Activity.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Meaning.</title>
          <content>Transaction activity includes any transaction that credits or debits the amount currently due. This is the same amount that is required to be disclosed under § <ref target="1026-41-d-1-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(1)(iii)</ref>. Examples of such transactions include, without limitation:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Payments received and applied;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>Payments received and held in a suspense account;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>The imposition of any fees (for example late fees); and</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
            <content>The imposition of any charges (for example, private mortgage insurance).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Description of late fees.</title>
          <content>The description of any late fee charges includes the date of the late fee, the amount of the late fee, and the fact that a late fee was imposed.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-4-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Partial Payments.</title>
          <content>If a partial payment is sent to a suspense or unapplied funds account, this fact must be in the transaction description along with the date and amount of the payment.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp" target="1026-41-d-8">
        <title>41(d)(8) Delinquency information.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Length of delinquency.</title>
          <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-41-d-8" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(8)</ref>, the length of a consumer's delinquency is measured as of the date of the periodic statement or the date of the written notice provided under § <ref target="1026-41-e-3-iv" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(3)(iv)</ref>. A consumer's delinquency begins on the date an amount sufficient to cover a periodic payment of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, becomes due and unpaid, even if the consumer is afforded a period after the due date to pay before the servicer assesses a late fee. A consumer is delinquent if one or more periodic payments of principal, interest, and escrow, if applicable, are due and unpaid.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-d-8-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Application of funds.</title>
          <content>For purposes of § <ref target="1026-41-d-8" reftype="internal">1026.41(d)(8)</ref>, if a servicer applies payments to the oldest outstanding periodic payment, a payment by a delinquent consumer advances the date the consumer's delinquency began. For example, assume a mortgage loan obligation under which a consumer's periodic payment is due on the first of each month. A consumer fails to make a payment on January 1 but makes a periodic payment on February 3. The servicer applies the payment received on February 3 to the outstanding January payment. On February 4, the consumer is three days delinquent, and the next periodic statement should disclose the length of the consumer's delinquency using February 2 as the first day of delinquency.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <!-- it's hard to insert a heading right into the middle of the flow as the notice demands -->
  <!-- so instead we'll just mod the entire paragraph from the previous reg and add the title in -->
  <change operation="modified" label="1026-41-e-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-Interp">
      <title>41(e) Exemptions.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp" target="1026-41-e-3">
        <title>41(e)(3) Coupon book exemption.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Fixed rate.</title>
          <content>For guidance on the meaning of “fixed rate” for purposes of § <ref target="1026-41-e-3" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(3)</ref>, see § <ref target="1026-18-s-7-iii" reftype="internal">1026.18(s)(7)(iii)</ref> and its commentary.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Coupon book.</title>
          <content>A coupon book is a booklet provided to the <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumer</ref> with a page for each <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref> during a set period of time (often covering one year). These pages are designed to be torn off and returned to the servicer with a payment for each <ref target="1026-2-a-4" reftype="term">billing cycle</ref>. Additional information about the loan is often included on or inside the front or back cover, or on filler pages in the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Information location.</title>
          <content>The information required by paragraph <ref target="1026-41-e-3-ii" reftype="internal">(e)(3)(ii)</ref> need not be provided on each coupon, but should be provided somewhere in the coupon book. Such information could be located, e.g., on or inside the front or back cover, or on filler pages in the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-3-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title type="keyterm">Outstanding principal balance.</title>
          <content>Paragraph <ref target="1026-41-e-3-ii-A" reftype="internal">(e)(3)(ii)(A)</ref> requires the information listed in paragraph <ref target="1026-41-d-7" reftype="internal">(d)(7)</ref> to be included in the coupon book. Paragraph <ref target="1026-41-d-7-i" reftype="internal">(d)(7)(i)</ref> requires the disclosure of the outstanding principal balance. If the servicer makes use of a coupon book and the exemption in § <ref target="1026-41-e-3" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(3)</ref>, the servicer need only disclose the principal balance at the beginning of the time period covered by the coupon book.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-Interp">
        <title>41(e)(4) Small servicers.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-4-ii">
          <title>41(e)(4)(ii) Small servicer defined.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Mortgage loans considered.</title>
            <content>Pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-a-1" reftype="internal">1026.41(a)(1)</ref>, the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> considered in determining status as a small servicer are closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a <ref target="1026-2-a-19" reftype="term">dwelling</ref>, subject to the exclusions in § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Services, together with affiliates, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>Services, together with <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans. To qualify as a small servicer, under § <ref target="CFR:12-1024-31" reftype="external">1026.41(e)(4)(</ref>ii)(A), a servicer must service, together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, for all of which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee. There are two elements to satisfying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref>. First, a servicer, together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, must service 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans. Second, a servicer must service only mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee. To be the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee of a mortgage loan, the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) must either currently own the mortgage loan or must have been the entity to which the mortgage loan obligation was initially payable (that is, the originator of the mortgage loan). A servicer is not a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> if it services any mortgage loans for which the servicer or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee (that is, for which the servicer or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> is not the owner or was not the originator). The following two examples demonstrate circumstances in which a servicer would not qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> because it did not meet both requirements under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> for determining a servicer's status as a small servicer:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>A servicer services 3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> owns or originated. An <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of the servicer services 4,000 other <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> owns or originated. Because the number of <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> serviced by a servicer is determined by counting the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> serviced by a servicer together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>, both of these servicers are considered to be servicing 7,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> and neither servicer is a small servicer.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>A service services 3,100 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>—3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it owns or originated and 100 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it neither owns nor originated, but for which it owns the mortgage servicing rights. The servicer is not a small servicer because it services <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> for which the servicer (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> or assignee, notwithstanding that the servicer services fewer than 5,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Master servicer and subservicing.</title>
              <content>A servicer that qualifies as a small servicer does not lose its small servicer status if it retains a subservicer, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.31, to service any of its <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. A subservicer can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption only if (1) the master servicer, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.31, is a small servicer and (2) the subservicer is a small servicer. A subservicer generally will not qualify as a small servicer because it does not own or did not originate the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it subservices—unless it is an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref> of a master servicer that qualifies as a small servicer. The following examples demonstrate the <ref target="1026-2-a-3-i" reftype="term">application</ref> of the small servicer exemption for different forms of servicing relationships:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
                <content>A <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union services 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it originated or owns. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union retains a <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization, that is not an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, to subservice 1,000 of the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union is a small servicer and, thus, can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption for the 3,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union services itself. The <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization is not a small servicer because it services <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it does not own or did not originate. Accordingly, the <ref target="1026-2-a-14" reftype="term">credit</ref> union service organization does not gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption and, thus, must comply with any applicable mortgage servicing requirements for the 1,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it subservices.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>A bank holding company, through a lender subsidiary, owns or originated 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>. All mortgage servicing rights for the 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> are owned by a wholly owned master servicer subsidiary. Servicing for the 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> is conducted by a wholly owned subservicer subsidiary. The bank holding company controls all of these subsidiaries and, thus, they are <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref> of the bank holding company pursuant 12 CFR <ref target="1026-32-b-2" reftype="internal">1026.32(b)(2)</ref>. Because the master servicer and subservicer service 5,000 or fewer <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, and because all the <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> are owned or originated by an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>, the master servicer and the subservicer both qualify for the small servicer exemption for all 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>.</content></interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>A nonbank servicer services 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref>, all of which it originated or owns. The servicer retains a “component servicer” to assist it with servicing functions. The component servicer is not engaged in “servicing” as defined in 12 CFR 1024.2; that is, the component servicer does not receive any scheduled periodic payments from a borrower pursuant to the terms of any <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loan</ref>, including amounts for <ref target="1026-35-b-3-iv" reftype="term">escrow accounts</ref>, and does not make the payments to the owner of the loan or other third parties of principal and interest and such other payments with respect to the amounts received from the borrower as may be required pursuant to the terms of the mortgage servicing loan documents or servicing contract. The component servicer is not a subservicer pursuant to 12 CFR 1024.31 because it is not engaged in servicing, as that term is defined in 12 CFR 1024.2. The nonbank servicer is a small servicer and, thus, can gain the benefit of the small servicer exemption with regard to all 4,000 <ref target="1026-39-a-2" reftype="term">mortgage loans</ref> it services.</content></interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
              <title type="keyterm">Nonprofit entity that services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>To qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>, a servicer must be a nonprofit entity that services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities, for all of which the servicer or an associated nonprofit entity is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. There are two elements to satisfying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>. First, a nonprofit entity must service 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities. For each associated nonprofit entity, the small servicer determination is made separately, without consideration of the number of loans serviced by another associated nonprofit entity. Second, a nonprofit entity must service only mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. To be the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) must have been the entity to which the mortgage loan obligation was initially payable (that is, the originator of the mortgage loan). A nonprofit entity is not a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> if it services any mortgage loans for which the servicer (or an associated nonprofit entity) is not the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref> (that is, for which the servicer or an associated nonprofit entity was not the originator). The first of the following two examples demonstrates circumstances in which a nonprofit entity would qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> because it meets both requirements for determining a nonprofit entity's status as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>. The second example demonstrates circumstances in which a nonprofit entity would not qualify as a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> because it does not meet both requirements under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref>.</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Nonprofit entity A services 3,000 of its own mortgage loans, and 1,500 mortgage loans on behalf of associated nonprofit entity B. All 4,500 mortgage loans were originated by A or B. Associated nonprofit entity C services 2,500 mortgage loans, all of which it originated. Because the number of mortgage loans serviced by a nonprofit entity is determined by counting the number of mortgage loans serviced by the nonprofit entity (including mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities) but not counting any mortgage loans serviced by an associated nonprofit entity, A and C are both small servicers.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-ii-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>A nonprofit entity services 4,500 mortgage loans—3,000 mortgage loans it originated, 1,000 mortgage loans originated by associated nonprofit entities, and 500 mortgage loans neither it nor an associated nonprofit entity originated. The nonprofit entity is not a small servicer because it services mortgage loans for which neither it nor an associated nonprofit entity is the <ref target="1026-2-a-17" reftype="term">creditor</ref>, notwithstanding that it services fewer than 5,000 mortgage loans.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-4-iii">
          <title>41(e)(4)(iii) Small servicer determination.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Loans obtained by merger or acquisition.</title>
            <content>Any mortgage loans obtained by a servicer or an affiliate as part of a merger or acquisition, or as part of the acquisition of all of the assets or liabilities of a branch office of a creditor, should be considered mortgage loans for which the servicer or an affiliate is the creditor to which the mortgage loan is initially payable. A branch office means either an office of a depository institution that is approved as a branch by a Federal or State supervisory agency or an office of a for-profit mortgage lending institution (other than a depository institution) that takes applications from the public for mortgage loans.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Timing for small servicer exemption.</title>
            <content>The following examples demonstrate when a servicer either is considered or is no longer considered a small servicer under § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> and (C):</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on October 1, and services more than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer would no longer be considered a small servicer on January 1 of the following year and would have to comply with any requirements from which it is no longer exempt as a small servicer on April 1 of the following year.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on February 1, and services more than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer would no longer be considered a small servicer on January 1 of the following year and would have to comply with any requirements from which it is no longer exempt as a small servicer on that same January 1.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Assume a servicer (that as of January 1 of the current year qualifies as a small servicer) begins servicing more than 5,000 mortgage loans on February 1, but services fewer than 5,000 mortgage loans as of January 1 of the following year. The servicer is considered a small servicer for the following year.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage loans not considered in determining whether a servicer is a small servicer.</title>
          <content>Mortgage loans that are not considered pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref> in applying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> are not considered either for determining whether a servicer (together with any <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliates</ref>) services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans or whether a servicer is servicing only mortgage loans that it (or an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) owns or originated. For example, assume a servicer services 5,400 mortgage loans. Of these mortgage loans, the servicer owns or originated 4,800 mortgage loans, voluntarily services 300 mortgage loans that neither it (nor an <ref target="1026-32-b-5" reftype="term">affiliate</ref>) owns or originated and for which the servicer does not receive any <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> or fees, and services 300 <ref target="1026-33-a" reftype="term">reverse mortgage transactions</ref>. The voluntarily serviced mortgage loans and reverse mortgage loans are not considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A)</ref>. Thus, because only the 4,800 mortgage loans owned or originated by the servicer are considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer, the servicer satisfies § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(A)</ref> with regard to all 5,400 mortgage loans it services.</content></interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title type="keyterm">Mortgage loans not considered in determining whether a nonprofit entity is a small servicer.</title>
          <content>Mortgage loans that are not considered pursuant to § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)</ref> in applying § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> are not considered either for determining whether a nonprofit entity services 5,000 or fewer mortgage loans, including any mortgage loans serviced on behalf of associated nonprofit entities, or whether a nonprofit entity is servicing only mortgage loans that it or an associated nonprofit entity originated. For example, assume a servicer that is a nonprofit entity services 5,400 mortgage loans. Of these mortgage loans, the nonprofit entity originated 2,800 mortgage loans and associated nonprofit entities originated 2,000 mortgage loans. The nonprofit entity receives <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> for servicing the loans originated by associated nonprofits. The nonprofit entity also voluntarily services 600 mortgage loans that were originated by an entity that is not an associated nonprofit entity, and receives no <ref target="1026-36-a-3" reftype="term">compensation</ref> or fees for servicing these loans. The voluntarily serviced mortgage loans are not considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer. Thus, because only the 4,800 mortgage loans originated by the nonprofit entity or associated nonprofit entities are considered in determining whether the servicer qualifies as a small servicer, the servicer satisfies § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-ii-C" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(ii)(C)</ref> with regard to all 5,400 mortgage loans it services.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-4-iii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
          <title type="keyterm">Limited role of voluntarily serviced mortgage loans.</title>
          <content>Reverse mortgages and mortgage loans secured by <ref target="1026-2-a-11" reftype="term">consumers</ref>' interests in timeshare plans, in addition to not being considered in determining small servicer qualification, are also exempt from the requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>. In contrast, although voluntarily serviced mortgage loans, as defined by § <ref target="1026-41-e-4-iii-A" reftype="internal">1026.41(e)(4)(iii)(A)</ref>, are likewise not considered in determining small servicer status, they are not exempt from the requirements of § <ref target="1026-41" reftype="internal">1026.41</ref>. Thus, a servicer that does not qualify as a small servicer would not have to provide periodic statements for reverse mortgages and timeshare plans because they are exempt from the rule, but would have to provide periodic statements for mortgage loans it voluntarily services.</content></interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5">
        <title>41(e)(5) Certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Consumer's representative.</title>
          <content>If an agent of the consumer, such as the consumer's bankruptcy counsel, submits a request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii), the request is deemed to be submitted by the consumer.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Multiple requests.</title>
          <content>A consumer's most recent written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) that the service cease or continue, as applicable, providing a periodic statement or coupon book determines whether the exemption in § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) applies.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Effective upon receipt.</title>
          <content>A consumer's written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1) or (e)(5)(ii) is effective as of the date of receipt by the servicer.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title>Bankruptcy case revived.</title>
          <content>If a consumer's bankruptcy case is revived, for example, if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case or reopens a case, § 1026.41(e)(5) may apply again, including the timing requirements in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i">
          <title>41(e)(5)(i) Exemption.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Multiple obligors.</title>
            <content>When two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41, § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) applies if any one of the consumers meets its criteria. For example, assume that two spouses jointly own a home and are primary obligors on the mortgage loan. One spouse files for chapter 13 bankruptcy and has a bankruptcy plan that provides for surrendering the dwelling that secures the mortgage loan. In part, § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) exempts the servicer from providing a periodic statement with regard to that mortgage loan, unless one of the spouses requests in writing that the servicer provide a periodic statement or coupon book pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(ii). If either spouse, including the one who is not a debtor in bankruptcy, submits a written request to receive a periodic statement or coupon book, the servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for that mortgage loan account.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2">
            <title>Paragraph 41(e)(5)(i)(B)(2).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Bankruptcy plan.</title>
              <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(2), bankruptcy plan refers to the consumer's most recently filed bankruptcy plan under the applicable provisions of title 11 of the United States Code, regardless of whether the court overseeing the consumer's bankruptcy case has confirmed or approved the plan.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4">
            <title>Paragraph 41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-i-B-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Statement of intention.</title>
              <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4), the statement of intention refers to the consumer's most recently filed statement of intention. For example, if a consumer files a statement of intention on June 1 identifying an intent to surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan but files an amended statement of intention on June 15 identifying an intent to retain the dwelling, the consumer's June 15 statement of intention is the relevant filing for purposes of § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-ii-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-ii">
          <title>41(e)(5)(ii) Reaffirmation or consumer request to receive statement or coupon book.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Form of periodic statement or coupon book.</title>
            <content>Section 1026.41(e)(5)(ii) generally requires a servicer, notwithstanding § 1026.41(e)(5)(i), to resume providing a periodic statement or coupon book if the consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan or any consumer on the mortgage loan requests in writing that the servicer provide a periodic statement or coupon book. Whether a servicer provides a periodic statement or coupon book as modified by § 1026.41(f) or an unmodified periodic statement or coupon book depends on whether or not § 1026.41(f) applies to that mortgage loan at that time. For example, § 1026.41(f) does not apply with respect to a mortgage loan once the consumer has reaffirmed personal liability; therefore, following a consumer's reaffirmation, a servicer generally would provide a periodic statement or coupon book that complies with § 1026.41 but without the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f). See comment 41(f)-6. Section 1026.41(f) does apply, however, with respect to a mortgage loan following a consumer's written request to receive a periodic statement or coupon book, so long as any consumer on the mortgage loan remains in bankruptcy or has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan; accordingly, following that written request, a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book that includes the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv">
          <title>41(e)(5)(iv) Timing of compliance following transition.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-A">
            <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(A) Triggering events for transitioning to modified and unmodified periodic statements.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Section 1026.41(f) becomes applicable or ceases to apply.</title>
              <content>Section 1026.41(e)(5)(iv) sets forth the time period in which a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for the first time after a mortgage loan either becomes subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) or ceases to be subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f). A mortgage loan becomes subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) when, for example, any consumer on the mortgage loan becomes a debtor in bankruptcy or discharges personal liability for the mortgage loan. A mortgage loan may cease to be subject to the requirements of § 1026.41(f) when, for example, the consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for a mortgage loan or the consumer's bankruptcy case is closed or dismissed without the consumer having discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan. See comment 41(f)-6.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>Servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption.</title>
              <content>Section 1026.41(e)(5)(iv) sets forth the time period in which a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book for the first time after a servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) with respect to a mortgage loan. A servicer ceases to qualify for an exemption pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(5)(i) with respect to a mortgage loan when, for example:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>The consumer's bankruptcy case is dismissed or closed without the consumer having discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>The consumer files an amended bankruptcy plan or statement of intention that provides, as applicable, for the maintenance of payments due under the mortgage loan and the payment of pre-petition arrearage or that the consumer will retain the dwelling securing the mortgage loan;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>A consumer makes a partial or periodic payment on the mortgage loan despite the consumer in bankruptcy having filed a statement of intention identifying an intent to surrender the dwelling securing the mortgage loan, thus making § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(4) inapplicable;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-iv" marker="iv.">
                <content>The consumer in bankruptcy reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan; or</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-A-Interp-2-v" marker="v.">
                <content>The consumer submits a written request pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(ii) that the servicer resume providing a periodic statement or coupon book.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-B-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-B">
            <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(B) Transitional single-billing-cycle exemption.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <content>An exemption under § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv) applies for only the first billing cycle that occurs after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. If a servicer is required to provide a periodic statement or coupon book, the servicer must do so beginning with the next billing cycle in accordance with the timing provisions of § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp" target="1026-41-e-5-iv-C">
            <title>41(e)(5)(iv)(C) Timing of first modified or unmodified statement or coupon book after transition.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Reasonably prompt time.</title>
              <content>Section 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C) requires that, when one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs, a servicer must provide the next periodic statement or coupon book by delivering or placing it in the mail within a reasonably prompt time after the next payment due date, or the end of any courtesy period for the payment's corresponding billing cycle, that is more than 14 days after the date on which the applicable event listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. Delivering, emailing, or placing the periodic statement or coupon book in the mail within four days after the payment due date or the end of the courtesy period generally would be considered reasonably prompt. See comment 41(b)-1.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>Subsequent periodic statements or coupon books.</title>
              <content>Section 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(C) applies to the timing of only the first periodic statement or coupon book a servicer provides after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs. For subsequent billing cycles, a servicer must provide a periodic statement or coupon book in accordance with the timing requirements of § 1026.41(a)(2) and (b), as applicable.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-5-iv-C-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Duplicate coupon books not required.</title>
              <content>With respect to coupon books, § 1026.41 requires a servicer to provide a new coupon book after one of the events listed in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv)(A) occurs only to the extent the servicer has not previously provided the consumer with a coupon book that covered the upcoming billing cycle.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp" target="1026-41-e-6">
        <title>41(e)(6) Charged-off loans.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Change in ownership.</title>
          <content>If a charged-off mortgage loan is subsequently purchased, assigned, or transferred, § 1026.39(b) requires a covered person, as defined in § 1026.39(a)(1), to provide mortgage transfer disclosures. See § 1026.39.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Change in servicing.</title>
          <content>A servicer may take advantage of the exemption in § 1026.41(e)(6)(i), subject to the requirements of that paragraph, and may rely on a prior servicer's provision to the consumer of a periodic statement pursuant to § 1026.41(e)(6)(i)(B) unless the servicer provided the consumer a periodic statement pursuant to § 1026.41(a).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B-Interp" marker="1.">
        <title>Paragraph 41(e)(6)(i)(B).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-e-6-i-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Clearly and conspicuously.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.41(e)(6)(i)(B) requires that the periodic statement be clearly and conspicuously labeled “Suspension of Statements &amp; Notice of Charge Off—Retain This Copy for Your Records” and that it clearly and conspicuously provide certain explanations to the consumer, as applicable, but no minimum type size or other technical requirements are imposed. The clear and conspicuous standard generally requires that disclosures be in a reasonably understandable form and readily noticeable to the consumer. See comment 41(c)-1.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp" target="1026-41-f">
      <title>41(f) Modified periodic statements and coupon books for certain consumers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Compliance after the bankruptcy case ends.</title>
        <content>Except as provided in § 1026.41(e)(5), § 1026.41(f) applies with regard to a mortgage loan for which any consumer with primary liability is a debtor in a case under title 11 of the United States Code. After the debtor exits bankruptcy, § 1026.41(f) continues to apply if the consumer has discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan, but § 1026.41(f) does not apply if the consumer has reaffirmed personal liability for the mortgage loan or otherwise has not discharged personal liability for the mortgage loan.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Terminology.</title>
        <content>With regard to a periodic statement provided under § 1026.41(f), a servicer may use terminology other than that found on the sample periodic statements in appendix H-30, so long as the new terminology is commonly understood. See comment 41(d)-3. For example, a servicer may take into account terminology appropriate for consumers in bankruptcy and refer to the “amount due” identified in § 1026.41(d)(1), as the “payment amount.” Similarly, a servicer may refer to an amount past due identified in § 1026.41(d)(2)(iii) as “past unpaid amount.” Additionally, a servicer may refer to the delinquency information required by § 1026.41(d)(8) as an “account history,” and to the amount needed to bring the loan current, referred to in § 1026.41(d)(8)(vi) as “the total payment amount needed to bring the account current,” as “unpaid amount.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Other periodic statement requirements continue to apply.</title>
        <content>The requirements of § 1026.41, including the content and layout requirements of § 1026.41(d), apply unless modified expressly by § 1026.41(e)(5) or (f). For example, the requirement under § 1026.41(d)(3) to disclose a past payment breakdown applies without modification with respect to a periodic statement provided to a consumer in bankruptcy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Further modifications.</title>
        <content>A periodic statement or coupon book provided under § 1026.41(f) may be modified as necessary to facilitate compliance with title 11 of the United States Code, the Federal Rules of Bankruptcy Procedure, court orders, and local rules, guidelines, and standing orders. For example, a periodic statement or coupon book may include additional disclosures or disclaimers not required under § 1026.41(f) but that are related to the consumer's status as a debtor in bankruptcy or that advise the consumer how to submit a written request under § 1026.41(e)(5)(i)(B)(1). See comment 41(f)(3)-1.ii for a discussion of the treatment of a bankruptcy plan that modifies the terms of the mortgage loan, such as by reducing the outstanding balance of the mortgage loan or altering the applicable interest rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Commencing compliance.</title>
        <content>A servicer must begin to provide a periodic statement or coupon book that complies with paragraph (f) of this section within the timeframe set forth in § 1026.41(e)(5)(iv).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-Interp-6" marker="6.">
        <title>Reaffirmation.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f), a consumer who has reaffirmed personal liability for a mortgage loan is not considered to be a debtor in bankruptcy.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3">
      <title>41(f)(3) Chapter 12 and chapter 13 consumers.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Pre-petition payments and post-petition payments.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3), pre-petition payments are payments made to cure the consumer's pre-bankruptcy defaults, and post-petition payments are payments made to satisfy the mortgage loan's periodic payments as they come due after the bankruptcy case is filed. For example, assume a consumer is $3,600 in arrears as of the bankruptcy filing date on a mortgage loan requiring monthly periodic payments of $2,000. The consumer's most recently filed bankruptcy plan requires the consumer to make payments of $100 each month for 36 months to pay the pre-bankruptcy arrearage, and $2,000 each month to satisfy the monthly periodic payments. Assuming the consumer makes the payments according to the plan, the $100 payments are the pre-petition payments and the $2,000 payments are the post-petition payments for purposes of the disclosures required under § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>If a consumer is a debtor in a case under chapter 12 or if a consumer's bankruptcy plan modifies the terms of the mortgage loan, such as by reducing the outstanding balance of the mortgage loan or altering the applicable interest rate, the disclosures under § 1026.41(d)(1) and (2) and (f)(3)(ii) and (iii) may disclose either the amount payable under the original terms of the mortgage loan, the amount payable under the remaining secured portion of the adjusted mortgage loan, or a statement that the consumer should contact the trustee or the consumer's attorney with any questions about the amount payable. In such cases, the remaining disclosures under § 1026.41(d) or (f)(3), as applicable, may be limited to how payments are applied to the remaining secured portion of the adjusted mortgage loan.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Post-petition fees and charges.</title>
        <content>For purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3), post-petition fees and charges are those fees and charges imposed after the bankruptcy case is filed. To the extent that the court overseeing the consumer's bankruptcy case requires such fees and charges to be included as an amendment to a servicer's proof of claim, a servicer may include such fees and charges in the balance of the pre-petition arrearage under § 1026.41(f)(3)(v)(C) rather than treating them as post-petition fees and charges for purposes of § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>First statement after exemption terminates.</title>
        <content>Section § 1026.41(f)(3)(iii) through (v) requires, in part, the disclosure of certain information regarding account activity that has occurred since the last statement. For purposes of the first periodic statement provided to the consumer following termination of an exemption under § 1026.41(e), those disclosures regarding account activity that has occurred since the last statement may be limited to account activity since the last payment due date that occurred while the exemption was in effect. See comment 41(d)-5.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-41-f-3-ii">
      <title>41(f)(3)(ii) Amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Amount due.</title>
        <content>The amount due under § 1026.41(d)(1) is not required to include any amounts other than post-petition payments the consumer is required to make under the terms of a bankruptcy plan, including any past due post-petition payments, and post-petition fees and charges that a servicer has imposed. The servicer is not required to include in the amount due any pre-petition payments due under a bankruptcy plan or other amounts payable pursuant to a court order. The servicer is not required to include in the amount due any post-petition fees and charges that the servicer has not imposed. A servicer that defers collecting a fee or charge until after complying with the Federal Rule of Bankruptcy Procedure 3002.1 procedures, and thus after a potential court determination on whether the fee or charge is allowed, is not required to disclose the fee or charge until complying with such procedures. However, a servicer may include in the amount due other amounts due to the servicer that are not post-petition payments or fees or charges, such as amounts due under an agreed order, provided those other amounts are also disclosed in the explanation of amount due and transaction activity.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3-iii">
      <title>41(f)(3)(iii) Explanation of amount due.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Explanation of amount due.</title>
        <content>The explanation of amount due under § 1026.41(d)(2) is not required to include any amounts other than the post-petition payments, including the amount of any past due post-petition payments and post-petition fees and charges that a servicer has imposed. Consistent with § 1026.41(d)(3)(i), the post-petition payments must be broken down by the amount, if any, that will be applied to principal, interest, and escrow. The servicer is not required to disclose, as part of the explanation of amount due, any pre-petition payments or the amount of the consumer's pre-bankruptcy arrearage. However, a servicer may identify other amounts due to the servicer provided those amounts are also disclosed in the amount due and transaction activity. See comment 41(d)-4.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp" target="1026-41-f-3-v">
      <title>41(f)(3)(v) Pre-petition arrearage.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-3-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Pre-petition arrearage.</title>
        <content>If the pre-petition arrearage is subject to dispute, or has not yet been determined by the servicer, the periodic statement may include a statement acknowledging the unresolved amount of the pre-petition arrearage. A servicer may omit the information required by § 1026.41(f)(3)(v) from the periodic statement until such time as the servicer has had a reasonable opportunity to determine the amount of the pre-petition arrearage. The servicer may not omit the information required by § 1026.41(f)(3)(v) from the periodic statement after the date that the bankruptcy court has fixed for filing proofs of claim in the consumer's bankruptcy case.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  <change operation="added" label="1026-41-f-4-Interp" parent="1026-41-Interp">
    <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp" target="1026-41-f-4">
      <title>41(f)(4) Multiple obligors.</title>
      <content/>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Modified statements.</title>
        <content>When two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41, a servicer may send the periodic statement to any one of the primary obligors. See comment 41(a)-1. Section 1026.41(f)(4) provides that a servicer may provide a modified statement under § 1026.41(f), if applicable, to any or all of the primary obligors, even if a primary obligor to whom the servicer provides the modified statement is not a debtor in bankruptcy. The servicer need not provide an unmodified statement to any of the primary obligors. For example, assume that two spouses jointly own a home and are both primarily liable on the mortgage loan. One spouse files for chapter 13 bankruptcy, and that spouse's chapter 13 bankruptcy plan provides that the same spouse will retain the home by making pre-petition and post-petition payments. The servicer complies with § 1026.41 by providing the modified periodic statement under § 1026.41(f) to either spouse.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-41-f-4-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Obligors in different chapters of bankruptcy.</title>
        <content>If two or more consumers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1026.41 and are debtors under different chapters of bankruptcy, only one of which is subject to § 1026.41(f)(3), a servicer may, but need not, include the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(3). For example, assume one joint obligor is a debtor in a case under chapter 7 and another joint obligor is a debtor in a case under chapter 13, and that the servicer is not exempt from the periodic statement requirement under § 1026.41(e)(5). The periodic statement or coupon book is subject to the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(1) and (2), but the servicer may determine whether it is appropriate to include the modifications set forth in § 1026.41(f)(3).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </interpParagraph>
  </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
