<notice xmlns="eregs" schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2017-08-11</date>
    <originalDate>2016-08-11</originalDate>
    <title>CONSUMER LEASING</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>Z</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1026</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2017-15764</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2017-10-19</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2017/08/11/2017-15764/amendments-to-federal-mortgage-disclosure-requirements-under-the-truth-in-lending-act-regulation-z</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2016-18901" leftEffectiveDate="" rightDocumentNumber="2017-15764" rightEffectiveDate="">
    <change label="1026-1-d-5" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-1-d-5" marker="(5)">
        <content>Subpart E contains special rules for mortgage transactions. Section 1026.32 requires certain disclosures and provides limitations for closed-end credit transactions and open-end credit plans that have rates or fees above specified amounts or certain prepayment penalties. Section 1026.33 requires special disclosures, including the total annual loan cost rate, for reverse mortgage transactions. Section 1026.34 prohibits specific acts and practices in connection with high-cost mortgages, as defined in § 1026.32(a). Section 1026.35 prohibits specific acts and practices in connection with closed-end higher-priced mortgage loans, as defined in § 1026.35(a). Section 1026.36 prohibits specific acts and practices in connection with an extension of credit secured by a dwelling. Sections 1026.37 and 1026.38 set forth special disclosure requirements for certain closed-end transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit, as required by § 1026.19(e) and (f).</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-3-h" operation="modified" subpath="content">
      <content>The special disclosure requirements in § 1026.19(g) and, unless the creditor chooses to provide the disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f), in § 1026.19(e) and (f) do not apply to a transaction that satisfies all of the following criteria:</content>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-3-h" operation="modified" subpath="title">
      <title>Partial exemption for certain mortgage loans.</title>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-3-h-5" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5" marker="(5)">
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The costs payable by the consumer in connection with the transaction at consummation are limited to:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Recording fees;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Transfer fees;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-i-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>A bona fide and reasonable application fee; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-i-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>A bona fide and reasonable fee for housing counseling services; and</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-3-h-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>The total of costs payable by the consumer under paragraph (h)(5)(i)(C) and (D) of this section is less than 1 percent of the amount of credit extended; and</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-3-h-6" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-3-h-6" marker="(6)">
        <content>The following disclosures are provided:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-3-h-6-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Disclosures described in § 1026.18 that comply with this part; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-3-h-6-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Alternatively, disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f) that comply with this part.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-e" operation="modified"/>
    <change label="1026-19-e-1-i" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-e-1-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>In a closed-end consumer credit transaction secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than a reverse mortgage subject to § 1026.33, the creditor shall provide the consumer with good faith estimates of the disclosures in § 1026.37.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-e-3-iii" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <content>An estimate of any of the charges specified in this paragraph (e)(3)(iii) is in good faith if it is consistent with the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time it is disclosed, regardless of whether the amount paid by the consumer exceeds the amount disclosed under paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section. For purposes of paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section, good faith is determined under this paragraph (e)(3)(iii) even if such charges are paid to the creditor or affiliates of the creditor, so long as the charges are bona fide:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>Prepaid interest;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>Property insurance premiums;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>Amounts placed into an escrow, impound, reserve, or similar account;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-D" marker="(D)">
          <content>Charges paid to third-party service providers selected by the consumer consistent with paragraph (e)(1)(vi)(A) of this section that are not on the list provided under paragraph (e)(1)(vi)(C) of this section; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-E" marker="(E)">
          <content>Property taxes and other charges paid for third-party services not required by the creditor.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-e-3-iv-E" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-E" marker="(E)">
        <content>The consumer indicates an intent to proceed with the transaction more than 10 business days, or more than any additional number of days specified by the creditor before the offer expires, after the disclosures required under paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section are provided pursuant to paragraph (e)(1)(iii) of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-e-3-iv-F" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-F" marker="(F)">
        <content>In transactions involving new construction, where the creditor reasonably expects that settlement will occur more than 60 days after the disclosures required under paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section are provided pursuant to paragraph (e)(1)(iii) of this section, the creditor may provide revised disclosures to the consumer if the original disclosures required under paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section state clearly and conspicuously that at any time prior to 60 days before consummation, the creditor may issue revised disclosures. If no such statement is provided, the creditor may not issue revised disclosures, except as otherwise provided in paragraph (e)(3)(iv) of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-f" operation="modified"/>
    <change label="1026-19-f-1-i" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-f-1-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>In a transaction subject to paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section, the creditor shall provide the consumer with the disclosures required under § 1026.38 reflecting the actual terms of the transaction.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-f-4-i" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-f-4-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>In a transaction subject to paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section that involves a seller, the settlement agent shall provide the seller with the disclosures in § 1026.38 that relate to the seller's transaction reflecting the actual terms of the seller's transaction.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-19-g-1" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>Except as provided in paragraphs (g)(1)(ii) and (iii) of this section, the creditor shall provide a copy of the special information booklet (required pursuant to section 5 of the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (12 U.S.C. 2604) to help consumers applying for federally related mortgage loans understand the nature and cost of real estate settlement services) to a consumer who applies for a consumer credit transaction secured by real property or a cooperative unit.</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The creditor shall deliver or place in the mail the special information booklet not later than three business days after the consumer's application is received. However, if the creditor denies the consumer's application before the end of the three-business-day period, the creditor need not provide the booklet. If a consumer uses a mortgage broker, the mortgage broker shall provide the special information booklet and the creditor need not do so.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>In the case of a home equity line of credit subject to § 1026.40, a creditor or mortgage broker that provides the consumer with a copy of the brochure entitled “When Your Home is On the Line: What You Should Know About Home Equity Lines of Credit,” or any successor brochure issued by the Bureau, is deemed to be in compliance with this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>The creditor or mortgage broker need not provide the booklet to the consumer for a transaction, the purpose of which is not the purchase of a one-to-four family residential property, including, but not limited to, the following:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-iii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Refinancing transactions;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-iii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Closed-end loans secured by a subordinate lien; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-19-g-1-iii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>Reverse mortgages.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-23-g-1" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1" marker="(1)">
        <title>One half of 1 percent tolerance</title>
        <content>Except as provided in paragraphs (g)(2) and (h)(2) of this section:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The finance charge and other disclosures affected by the finance charge (such as the amount financed and the annual percentage rate) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed finance charge:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than 1/2 of 1 percent of the face amount of the note or $100, whichever is greater; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>The total of payments for each transaction subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed total of payments:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than 1/2 of 1 percent of the face amount of the note or $100, whichever is greater; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-1-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-23-g-2" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2" marker="(2)">
        <title>One percent tolerance.</title>
        <content>In a refinancing of a residential mortgage transaction with a new creditor (other than a transaction covered by § 1026.32), if there is no new advance and no consolidation of existing loans:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The finance charge and other disclosures affected by the finance charge (such as the amount financed and the annual percentage rate) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed finance charge:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than 1 percent of the face amount of the note or $100, whichever is greater; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>The total of payments for each transaction subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed total of payments:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than 1 percent of the face amount of the note or $100, whichever is greater; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-g-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-23-h-2" operation="modified">
      <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2" marker="(2)">
        <title>Tolerance for disclosures.</title>
        <content>After the initiation of foreclosure on the consumer's principal dwelling that secures the credit obligation:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The finance charge and other disclosures affected by the finance charge (such as the amount financed and the annual percentage rate) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed finance charge:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than $35; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>The total of payments for each transaction subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f) shall be considered accurate for purposes of this section if the disclosed total of payments:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Is understated by no more than $35; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-23-h-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-25-c-1" operation="modified" subpath="title">
      <title>Records related to requirements for loans secured by real property or a cooperative unit—</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b" subpath="title">
      <title>Loan terms</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-b-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>The total amount the consumer will borrow, as reflected by the face amount of the note, labeled “Loan Amount.”</content>
        <title>Loan amount</title>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-c-5-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-c-5-i" marker="(i)">
        <content>The taxable assessed value of the real property or cooperative unit securing the transaction after consummation, including the value of any improvements on the property or to be constructed on the property, if known, whether or not such construction will be financed from the proceeds of the transaction, for property taxes; and</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b" subpath="content">
      <content>A separate table under the heading “Loan Terms” that contains the following information and that satisfies the following requirements:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-i" marker="(i)">
        <title>Total closing costs.</title>
        <content>The amount disclosed under paragraph (g)(6) of this section, labeled “Total Closing Costs”;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <title>Down payment and other funds from borrower.</title>
        <content>Labeled “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower”:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>In a purchase transaction as defined in paragraph (a)(9)(i) of this section, the amount determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b)(1) of this section and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) from the sale price of the property disclosed under paragraph (a)(7)(i) of this section, except as required by paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>In a purchase transaction as defined in paragraph (a)(9)(i) of this section that is a simultaneous subordinate financing transaction or that involves improvements to be made on the property, or when the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b)(1) of this section and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) exceeds the sale price of the property disclosed under paragraph (a)(7)(i) of this section, the amount of estimated funds from the consumer as determined in accordance with paragraph (h)(1)(v) of this section; or</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>In all transactions not subject to paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A) of this section, the amount of estimated funds from the consumer as determined in accordance with paragraph (h)(1)(v) of this section;</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-v">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-v" marker="(v)">
        <title>Funds for borrower.</title>
        <content>The amount of funds for the consumer, labeled “Funds for Borrower.” The amount of the down payment and other funds from the consumer disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (h)(1)(iii)(B) of this section, as applicable, and of funds for the consumer disclosed under this paragraph (h)(1)(v), are determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b)(1) of this section and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) (excluding any closing costs financed disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(ii) of this section) from the total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction;</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (h)(1)(v) yields an amount that is a positive number, such amount is disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (h)(1)(iii)(B) of this section, as applicable, and $0 is disclosed under this paragraph (h)(1)(v);</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (h)(1)(v) yields an amount that is a negative number, such amount is disclosed under this paragraph (h)(1)(v) as a negative number, and $0 is disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (h)(1)(iii)(B) of this section, as applicable;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (h)(1)(v) yields $0, then $0 is disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (h)(1)(iii)(B) of this section, as applicable, and under this paragraph (h)(1)(v);</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii" subpath="title">
      <title>Adjustments and other credits.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii" subpath="content">
      <content>The amount of all loan costs determined under paragraph (f) of this section and other costs determined under paragraph (g) of this section that are paid by persons other than the loan originator, creditor, consumer, or seller, together with any other amounts not otherwise disclosed under paragraph (f) or (g) of this section that are required to be paid by the consumer at closing in a transaction disclosed under paragraph (h)(1)(iii)(A)(1) of this section or pursuant to a purchase and sale contract, labeled “Adjustments and Other Credits”; and</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-2" subpath="title">
      <title>Optional alternative calculating cash to close table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-2">
      <content>For transactions that do not involve a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing, instead of the table described in paragraph (h)(1) above, the creditor may alternatively provide, in a separate table, under the master heading “Closing Cost Details,” under the heading “Calculating Cash to Close,” the total amount of cash or other funds that must be provided by the consumer at consummation with an itemization of that amount into the following component amounts:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-2-ii">
      <title/>
      <paragraph label="1026-37-h-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title>Total closing costs.</title>
        <content>The amount disclosed under paragraph (g)(6) of this section, disclosed as a negative number if the amount disclosed under paragraph (g)(6) of this section is a positive number and disclosed as a positive number if the amount disclosed under paragraph (g)(6) of this section is a negative number, labeled “Total Closing Costs”;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-iii">
      <title/>
      <paragraph label="1026-37-h-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <title>Payoffs and payments.</title>
        <content>The total amount of payoffs and payments to be made to third parties not otherwise disclosed under paragraphs (f) and (g) of this section, labeled “Total Payoffs and Payments”;</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-o-4">
      <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Rounding-</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4-i" marker="(i)">
          <title>Nearest dollar.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The dollar amounts required to be disclosed by paragraphs (b)(6) and (7), (c)(1)(iii), (c)(2)(ii) and (iii), (c)(4)(ii), (f), (g), (h), (i), and (l) of this section shall be rounded to the nearest whole dollar, except that the per-diem dollar amount required to be disclosed by paragraph (g)(2)(iii) of this section and the monthly dollar amounts required to be disclosed by paragraphs (g)(3)(i) through (iii) and (g)(3)(v) of this section shall not be rounded.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The dollar amount required to be disclosed by paragraph (b)(1) of this section shall not be rounded, and if the amount is a whole number then the amount disclosed shall be truncated at the decimal point.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4-i-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The dollar amounts required to be disclosed by paragraph (c)(2)(iv) of this section shall be rounded to the nearest whole dollar, if any of the component amounts are required by paragraph (o)(4)(i)(A) of this section to be rounded to the nearest whole dollar.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-37-o-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title>Percentages.</title>
          <content>The percentage amounts required to be disclosed under paragraphs (b)(2) and (6), (f)(1)(i), (g)(2)(iii), (j), and (l)(2) and (3) of this section shall be disclosed by rounding the exact amounts to three decimal places and then dropping any trailing zeros that occur to the right of the decimal place.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-a-3-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-a-3-iii" marker="iii">
        <content>The date the amount disclosed under paragraph (j)(3)(iii) (cash to close from or to borrower) or (k)(3)(iii) (cash from or to seller) of this section is expected to be paid in a purchase transaction under § 1026.37(a)(9)(i) to the consumer or seller, respectively, as applicable, except as provided in comment 38(a)(3)(iii)-1, or the date some or all of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b) of this section is expected to be paid to the consumer or a third party other than a settlement agent in a transaction that is not a purchase transaction under § 1026.37(a)(9)(i), labeled “Disbursement Date.”</content>
        <title>Disbursement date.</title>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-d-2" subpath="title">
      <title>Alternative table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-d-2" subpath="content">
      <content>For transactions that do not involve a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing, if the creditor disclosed the optional alternative table under § 1026.37(d)(2), the creditor shall disclose, with the label “Cash to Close,” instead of the sum of the dollar amounts described in paragraph (d)(1)(ii) of this section:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-e" subpath="title">
      <title>Alternative calculating cash to close table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-e">
      <content>For transactions that do not involve a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing, if the creditor disclosed the optional alternative table under § 1026.37(h)(2), the creditor shall disclose, instead of the table described in paragraph (i) of this section, in a separate table, under the heading “Calculating Cash to Close,” together with the statement “Use this table to see what has changed from your Loan Estimate”:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-e-2-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>Under the subheading “Final,” the amount disclosed under paragraph (h)(1) of this section, disclosed as a negative number if the amount disclosed under paragraph (h)(1) of this section is a positive number and disclosed as a positive number if the amount disclosed under paragraph (h)(1) of this section is a negative number; and</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-e-2-iii-A-3" subpath="content">
      <content>If the increase exceeds the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3), a statement that such increase exceeds the legal limits by the dollar amount of the excess and, if any refund is provided under § 1026.19(f)(2)(v), a statement directing the consumer to the disclosure required under paragraph (h)(3) of this section or, if applicable, a statement directing the consumer to the principal reduction disclosure under paragraph (t)(5)(vii)(B) of this section. Such dollar amount shall equal the sum total of all excesses of the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3), taking into account the different methods of calculating excesses of the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-e-4-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>Under the subheading “Final,” the total amount of payoffs and payments made to third parties disclosed under paragraph (t)(5)(vii)(B) of this section, to the extent known, disclosed as a negative number if the total amount disclosed under paragraph (t)(5)(vii)(B) of this section is a positive number and disclosed as a positive number if the total amount disclosed under paragraph (t)(5)(vii)(B) of this section is a negative number;</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-g-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-g-1" marker="1">
        <title>Taxes and other government fees.</title>
        <content>Under the subheading “Taxes and Other Government Fees,” an itemization of each amount that is expected to be paid to State and local governments for taxes and government fees and the total of all such itemized amounts that are designated borrower-paid at or before closing, as follows:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-g-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <title/>
          <content>On the first line:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-g-1-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>Before the columns described in paragraph (g) of this section, the total amount of fees for recording deeds and, separately, the total amount of fees for recording security instruments; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-g-1-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>In the applicable column as described in paragraph (g) of this section, the total amounts paid for recording fees (including, but not limited to, the amounts in paragraph (g)(1)(i)(A) of this section); and</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-g-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>On subsequent lines, in the applicable column as described in paragraph (g) of this section, an itemization of transfer taxes, with the name of the government entity assessing the transfer tax.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-h-3" subpath="content">
      <content>The amount of lender credits as a negative number, labeled “Lender Credits” and designated borrower-paid at closing, and if a refund is provided pursuant to § 1026.19(f)(2)(v), a statement that this amount includes a credit for an amount that exceeds the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3), and the amount of such credit under § 1026.19(f)(2)(v).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-i-1-iii-A-3" subpath="content">
      <content>If the increase exceeds the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3), a statement that such increase exceeds the legal limits by the dollar amount of the excess, and if any refund is provided under § 1026.19(f)(2)(v), a statement directing the consumer to the disclosure required under paragraph (h)(3) of this section or, if a principal reduction is used to provide the refund, a statement directing the consumer to the principal reduction disclosure under paragraph (j)(1)(v) of this section. Such dollar amount shall equal the sum total of all excesses of the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3), taking into account the different methods of calculating excesses of the limitations on increases in closing costs under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-i-4-ii">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-i-4-ii" marker="ii">
        <content>Under the subheading “Final”:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-4-ii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-4-ii-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>In a purchase transaction as defined in § 1026.37(a)(9)(i), the amount determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b) of this section and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that is disclosed under paragraph (j)(2)(iv) of this section from the sale price of the property disclosed under paragraph (a)(3)(vii)(A) of this section, labeled “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower,” except as required by paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A)(2) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-4-ii-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>In a purchase transaction as defined in § 1026.37(a)(9)(i) that is a simultaneous subordinate financing transaction or that involves improvements to be made on the property, or when the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b) of this section and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that is disclosed under paragraph (j)(2)(iv) of this section exceeds the sale price disclosed under paragraph (a)(3)(vii)(A) of this section, the amount of funds from the consumer as determined in accordance with paragraph (i)(6)(iv) of this section labeled “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower;” or</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-4-ii-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>In all transactions not subject to paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A) of this section, the amount of funds from the consumer as determined in accordance with paragraph (i)(6)(iv) of this section, labeled “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower.”</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-i-6-iv">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-i-6-iv" marker="iv">
        <content>The “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower” to be disclosed under paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A)(2) or (B) of this section, as applicable, and “Funds for Borrower” to be disclosed under paragraph (i)(6)(ii) of this section are determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under paragraph (b) of this section and any amount for existing loans assumed or taken subject to that is disclosed under paragraph (j)(2)(iv) of this section (excluding any closing costs financed disclosed under paragraph (i)(3)(ii) of this section) from the total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction disclosed under paragraphs (j)(1)(ii), (iii), and (v) of this section.</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-6-iv-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (i)(6)(iv) yields an amount that is a positive number, such amount shall be disclosed under paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A)(2) or (B) of this section, as applicable, and $0 shall be disclosed under paragraph (i)(6)(ii) of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-6-iv-B" marker="(B)">
          <title/>
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (i)(6)(iv) yields an amount that is a negative number, such amount shall be disclosed under paragraph (i)(6)(ii) of this section, stated as a negative number, and $0 shall be disclosed under paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A)(2) or (i)(4)(ii)(B) of this section, as applicable.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-6-iv-C" marker="(C)">
          <title/>
          <content>If the calculation under this paragraph (i)(6)(iv) yields $0, $0 shall be disclosed under paragraph (i)(4)(ii)(A)(2) or (i)(4)(ii)(B) of this section, as applicable, and under paragraph (i)(6)(ii) of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-i-7-iii">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-i-7-iii" marker="iii">
        <content>Under the subheading “Did this change?,” disclosed more prominently than the other disclosures under this paragraph (i)(7):</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-7-iii-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>If the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(7)(ii) of this section is different than the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(7)(i) of this section (unless the difference is due to rounding), a statement of that fact, along with a statement that the consumer should see the details disclosed:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-7-iii-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>Under paragraph (j)(2)(v) of this section and in the seller-paid column under paragraphs (f) and (g) of this section; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-7-iii-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>Under either paragraph (j)(2)(v) of this section or in the seller-paid column under paragraphs (f) or (g) of this section, if the details are only disclosed under paragraph (j)(2)(v) or paragraph (f) or (g); or</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-7-iii-B" marker="(B)">
          <title/>
          <content>If the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(7)(ii) of this section is equal to the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(7)(i) of this section, a statement of that fact.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-i-8">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8" marker="8">
        <title>Adjustments and other credits.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Under the subheading “Loan Estimate,” the amount disclosed on the Loan Estimate under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii), labeled “Adjustments and Other Credits.”</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title/>
          <content>Under the subheading “Final,” the amount equal to the total of the amounts disclosed under paragraphs (j)(1)(iii) and (v) of this section, to the extent amounts in paragraphs (j)(1)(iii) and (v) were not included in the calculation required by paragraph (i)(4) or (6) of this section, and paragraphs (j)(1)(vi) through (x) of this section, reduced by the total of the amounts disclosed under paragraphs (j)(2)(vi) through (xi) of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <title/>
          <content>Under the subheading “Did this change?,” disclosed more prominently than the other disclosures under this paragraph (i)(8):</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8-iii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>If the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(8)(ii) of this section is different than the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(8)(i) of this section (unless the difference is due to rounding), a statement of that fact, along with a statement that the consumer should see the details disclosed under paragraphs (j)(1)(iii) and (v) through (x) and (j)(2)(vi) through (xi) of this section, as applicable; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-i-8-iii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>If the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(8)(ii) of this section is different than the amount disclosed under paragraph (i)(8)(i) of this section (unless the difference is due to rounding), a statement of that fact, along with a statement that the consumer should see the details disclosed under paragraphs (j)(1)(iii) and (v) through (x) and (j)(2)(vi) through (xi) of this section, as applicable; or</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-j-2-vi" subpath="content">
      <content>Descriptions and amounts of other items paid by or on behalf of the consumer and not otherwise disclosed under paragraphs (f), (g), (h), and (j)(2) of this section, labeled “Other Credits,” and descriptions and the amounts of any additional amounts owed the consumer but payable to the seller before the real estate closing, under the heading “Adjustments”;</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-l-7-i">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i" marker="i">
        <content>Under the reference “For now,” a statement that an escrow account may also be called an impound or trust account, a statement of whether the creditor has established or will establish (at or before consummation) an escrow account in connection with the transaction, and the information required under paragraphs (l)(7)(i)(A) and (B) of this section:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>A statement that the creditor may be liable for penalties and interest if it fails to make a payment for any cost for which the escrow account is established, a statement that the consumer would have to pay such costs directly in the absence of the escrow account, and a table, titled “Escrow,” that contains, if an escrow account is or will be established, an itemization of the amounts listed in paragraphs (l)(7)(i)(A)(1) through (4) of this section;</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The total amount the consumer will be required to pay into an escrow account over the first year after consummation, labeled “Escrowed Property Costs over Year 1,” together with a descriptive name of each charge to be paid (in whole or in part) from the escrow account, calculated as the amount disclosed under paragraph (l)(7)(i)(A)(4) of this section multiplied by the number of periodic payments scheduled to be made to the escrow account during the first year after consummation;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The estimated amount the consumer is likely to pay during the first year after consummation for the mortgage-related obligations described in § 1026.43(b)(8) that are known to the creditor and that will not be paid using escrow account funds, labeled “Non-Escrowed Property Costs over Year 1,” together with a descriptive name of each such charge and a statement that the consumer may have to pay other costs that are not listed;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A-3" marker="(3)">
            <content>The total amount disclosed under paragraph (g)(3) of this section, a statement that the payment is a cushion for the escrow account, labeled “Initial Escrow Payment,” and a reference to the information disclosed under paragraph (g)(3) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A-4" marker="(4)">
            <content>The amount the consumer will be required to pay into the escrow account with each periodic payment during the first year after consummation, labeled “Monthly Escrow Payment.”</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-A-5" marker="(5)">
            <content>A creditor complies with the requirements of paragraphs (l)(7)(i)(A)(1) and (4) of this section if the creditor bases the numerical disclosures required by those paragraphs on amounts derived from the escrow account analysis required under Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.17.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>A statement of whether the consumer will not have an escrow account, the reason why an escrow account will not be established, a statement that the consumer must pay all property costs, such as taxes and homeowner's insurance, directly, a statement that the consumer may contact the creditor to inquire about the availability of an escrow account, and a table, titled “No Escrow,” that contains, if an escrow account will not be established, an itemization of the following:</content>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-B-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>The estimated total amount the consumer will pay directly for the mortgage-related obligations described in § 1026.43(b)(8) during the first year after consummation that are known to the creditor and a statement that, without an escrow account, the consumer must pay the identified costs, possibly in one or two large payments, labeled “Property Costs over Year 1”; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1026-38-l-7-i-B-2" marker="(2)">
            <content>The amount of any fee the creditor imposes on the consumer for not establishing an escrow account in connection with the transaction, labeled “Escrow Waiver Fee.”</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-o-1">
      <paragraph label="1026-38-o-1" marker="1">
        <title>Total of payments.</title>
        <content>The “Total of Payments,” using that term and expressed as a dollar amount, and a statement that the disclosure is the total the consumer will have paid after making all payments of principal, interest, mortgage insurance, and loan costs, as scheduled. The disclosed total of payments shall be treated as accurate if the amount disclosed as the total of payments:</content>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-o-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Is understated by no more than $100; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1026-38-o-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Is greater than the amount required to be disclosed.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-t-4-ii" subpath="title">
      <title>Percentages.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-t-4-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>The percentage amounts required to be disclosed under paragraphs (b), (f)(1), (n), and (o)(4) and (5) of this section shall be disclosed by rounding the exact amounts to three decimal places and then dropping any trailing zeros to the right of the decimal point.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-t-5-vii" subpath="title">
      <title>Transaction without a seller or simultaneous subordinate financing transaction.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-38-t-5-vii" subpath="content">
      <content>The following modifications to form H-25 of appendix H to this part may be made for a transaction that does not involve a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing, and for which the alternative tables are disclosed under paragraphs (d)(2) and (e) of this section, as illustrated by form H-25(J) of appendix H to this part:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-1-d-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-Interp">
        <title>1(d) Organization.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp" target="1026-1-d-5">
          <title>Paragraph 1(d)(5)</title>
          <content></content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Effective date.</title>
            <content></content>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
              <title>General.</title>
              <content>The Bureau's revisions to Regulation X and Regulation Z published on December 31, 2013 (the TILA-RESPA Final Rule) apply to covered loans (closed-end credit transactions that are secured by real property or a cooperative unit, whether or not treated as real property under State or other applicable law) for which the creditor or mortgage broker receives an application on or after October 3, 2015 (the effective date), except that §§ 1026.19(e)(2), the amendments to § 1026.28(a)(1), and the amendments to the commentary to § 1026.29 became effective on October 3, 2015, without respect to whether an application was received as of that date. Additionally, §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5), as amended or adopted by the TILA-RESPA Final Rule, took effect on October 3, 2015, for transactions for which the creditor or mortgage broker received an application on or after October 3, 2015, and take effect October 1, 2018, with respect to transactions for which a creditor or mortgage broker received an application prior to October 3, 2015.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
              <title>Pre-application activities.</title>
              <content>The provisions of § 1026.19(e)(2) apply prior to a consumer's receipt of the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and therefore restrict activity that may occur prior to receipt of an application by a creditor or mortgage broker. These provisions include § 1026.19(e)(2)(i), which restricts the fees that may be imposed on a consumer, § 1026.19(e)(2)(ii), which requires a statement to be included on written estimates of terms or costs specific to a consumer, and § 1026.19(e)(2)(iii), which prohibits creditors from requiring the submission of documents verifying information related to the consumer's application. Accordingly, the provisions of § 1026.19(e)(2) are effective on October 3, 2015, without respect to whether an application has been received on that date.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
              <title>Determination of preemption.</title>
              <content>The amendments to § 1026.28 and the commentary to § 1026.29 govern the preemption of State laws, and thus the amendments to those provisions and associated commentary made by the TILA-RESPA Final Rule are effective on October 3, 2015, without respect to whether an application has been received on that date.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
              <title>Post-consummation escrow cancellation disclosure and partial payment disclosure.</title>
              <content>A creditor, servicer, or covered person, as applicable, must provide the disclosures required by §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5) for transactions for which the conditions in § 1026.20(e) or § 1026.39(d)(5), as applicable, exist on or after October 1, 2018, regardless of when the corresponding applications were received. For transactions in which such conditions exist on or after October 3, 2015, through September 30, 2018, a creditor, servicer, or covered person, as applicable, complies with §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5) if it provides the mandated disclosures in all cases or if it provides them only in cases where the corresponding applications were received on or after October 3, 2015.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v" marker="v.">
              <content>For purposes of the following examples, an application received before or after the effective date is any submission for the purpose of obtaining an extension of credit that satisfies the definition in § 1026.2(a)(3), as adopted by the TILA-RESPA Final Rule, even if that definition was not yet in effect on the date in question. Cross-references in the following examples to provisions of Regulation Z refer to those provisions as adopted or amended by the TILA-RESPA Final Rule, together with any subsequent amendments, unless noted otherwise.</content>
              <title>Examples.</title>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v-A" marker="A.">
                <title>Application received on or after effective date of the TILA-RESPA Final Rule.</title>
                <content>Assume a creditor receives an application on October 3, 2015, and that consummation of the transaction occurs on October 31, 2015. The amendments of the TILA-RESPA Final Rule, including the requirement to provide the Loan Estimate and Closing Disclosure under § 1026.19(e) and (f), apply to the transaction. The creditor is also required to provide the special information booklet under § 1026.19(g).</content>
                <title/>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v-B" marker="B.">
                <content>Assume a creditor receives an application on September 30, 2015, and that consummation of the transaction occurs on October 30, 2015. The requirement to provide the Loan Estimate and Closing Disclosure under § 1026.19(e) and (f) does not apply to the transaction. Instead, the creditor and the settlement agent must provide the disclosures required by § 1026.19, as it existed prior to the effective date of the TILA-RESPA Final Rule, and by Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.8. Similarly, the creditor must provide the special information booklet required by Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.6. However, the provisions of § 1026.19(e)(2) apply to the transaction beginning on October 3, 2015, because they became effective on October 3, 2015, without respect to whether an application was received by the creditor or mortgage broker on that date.</content>
                <title>Application received before effective date of the TILA-RESPA Final Rule.</title>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v-C" marker="C.">
                <title>Predisclosure written estimates.</title>
                <content>Assume a creditor receives a request from a consumer for a written estimate of terms or costs specific to the consumer on October 3, 2015, before the consumer submits an application to the creditor and thus before the consumer has received the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). The creditor, if it provides such a written estimate to the consumer, must comply with § 1026.19(e)(2)(ii) and provide the required statement on the written estimate, even though the creditor has not received an application on that date.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v-D" marker="D.">
                <title>Request for preemption determination.</title>
                <content>Assume a creditor submits a request to the Bureau under § 1026.28(a)(1) for a determination of whether a State law is inconsistent with the disclosure requirements in Regulation Z on October 3, 2015. Because the amendments to § 1026.28(a)(1) are effective on that date and do not depend on whether the creditor has received an application, § 1026.28(a)(1) is applicable to the request on that date, and the Bureau would make a determination based on the provisions of Regulation Z in effect on that date, including the requirements of § 1026.19(e) and (f).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-1-v-E" marker="E.">
                <title>Effective dates for the post-consummation escrow cancelation disclosure and partial payment disclosure.</title>
                <content>Assume a creditor receives an application on October 10, 2010, and that the loan was consummated on November 19, 2010. Assume further that, on December 19, 2016, the escrow account established in connection with the mortgage loan was canceled or the loan is sold to another covered person. A creditor, servicer, or covered person, as applicable, may provide the disclosures required under §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5) to the consumer, but the creditor, servicer, or covered person, as applicable, is not required to provide those disclosures in this case. Assume the same circumstances, except that the escrow account established in connection with the loan is canceled or the mortgage loan is sold to another covered person on April 14, 2020. A creditor, servicer, or covered person, as applicable, must provide the disclosures in §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5), as applicable, because a condition requiring these disclosures occurred after October 1, 2018 (thus the date the application was received is irrelevant).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <content></content>
            <title>2017 TILA-RESPA Amendments.</title>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
              <title>Generally.</title>
              <content>Except as provided in comment 1(d)(5)-2.ii, compliance with the amendments to this part effective on October 10, 2017 (the 2017 TILA-RESPA Amendments) is mandatory with respect to transactions for which a creditor or mortgage broker received an application on or after October 1, 2018. Except as provided in comment 1(d)(5)-2.ii, for transactions for which a creditor or mortgage broker received an application prior to October 1, 2018, from the effective date of the 2017 TILA-RESPA Amendments:</content>
              <title/>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-2-i-A" marker="A.">
                <content>A person has the option of complying either: with 12 CFR part 1026 as it is in effect; or with 12 CFR part 1026 as it was in effect on October 9, 2017, together with any amendments to 12 CFR part 1026 that become effective after October 9, 2017, other than the 2017 TILA-RESPA Amendments; and</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-2-i-B" marker="B.">
                <content>An act or omission violates 12 CFR part 1026 only if it violates both: 12 CFR part 1026 as it is in effect; and 12 CFR part 1026 as it was in effect on October 9, 2017, together with any amendments to 12 CFR part 1026 that become effective after October 9, 2017, other than the 2017 TILA-RESPA Amendments.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1026-1-d-5-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Comment 1(d)(5)-1.iv sets forth the transactions to which the disclosures required by §§ 1026.20(e) and 1026.39(d)(5) are applicable.</content>
              <title>Post-consummation escrow cancellation disclosure and partial payment disclosure.</title>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-3" subpath="title">
      <title>Trusts.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-2-a-11-Interp-3" subpath="content">
      <content>Credit extended to trusts established for tax or estate planning purposes or to land trusts, as described in comment 3(a)-10, is considered to be extended to a natural person for purposes of the definition of consumer.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-3-h-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-3-h-Interp" target="1026-3-h">
        <title>3(h) Partial exemption for certain mortgage loans.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1026-3-h-Interp-1">
          <title>Partial exemption.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.3(h) exempts certain transactions from the disclosures described in § 1026.19(g), and, under certain circumstances, § 1026.19(e) and (f). Section 1026.3(h) exempts transactions from § 1026.19(e) and (f) if the creditor chooses to provide disclosures described in § 1026.18 that comply with this part pursuant to § 1026.3(h)(6)(i), but does not exempt transactions from § 1026.19(e) and (f) if the creditor chooses to provide disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f) that comply with this part pursuant to § 1026.3(h)(6)(ii). Creditors may provide, at their option, either the disclosures described in § 1026.18 or the disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f). In providing these disclosures, creditors must comply with all provisions of this part relating to those disclosures. Section 1026.3(h) does not exempt transactions from any of the other requirements of this part, to the extent they are applicable. For transactions that would otherwise be subject to § 1026.19(e), (f), and (g), creditors must comply with all other applicable requirements of this part, including the consumer's right to rescind the transaction under § 1026.23, to the extent that provision is applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-3-h-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Establishing compliance.</title>
          <content>The conditions that the transaction not require the payment of interest under § 1026.3(h)(3) and that repayment of the amount of credit extended be forgiven or deferred in accordance with § 1026.3(h)(4) must be reflected in the loan contract. The other requirements of § 1026.3(h) need not be reflected in the loan contract, but the creditor must retain evidence of compliance with those provisions, as required by § 1026.25(a) or (c), as applicable. In particular, because the exemption in § 1026.3(h) means the creditor is not required to provide the disclosures of closing costs under § 1026.37 or § 1026.38 (unless the creditor chooses to provide disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f) that comply with this part), the creditor must retain evidence reflecting that the costs payable by the consumer in connection with the transaction at consummation are limited to recording fees, transfer taxes, a bona fide and reasonable application fee, and a bona fide and reasonable housing counseling fee, and that the total of application and housing counseling fees is less than 1 percent of the amount of credit extended, in accordance with § 1026.3(h)(5). Unless the itemization of the amount financed provided to the consumer sufficiently details this requirement, the creditor must establish compliance with § 1026.3(h)(5) by some other written document and retain it in accordance with § 1026.25(a) or (c), as applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-3-h-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Relationship to partial exemption for certain federally related mortgage loans.</title>
          <content>Regulation X provides a partial exemption from certain Regulation X disclosure requirements in 12 CFR 1024.5(d). The partial exemption in Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.5(d)(2) provides that certain Regulation X disclosure requirements do not apply to a federally related mortgage loan, as defined in Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.2(b), that satisfies the criteria in § 1026.3(h) of this part. For a federally related mortgage loan that is not otherwise covered by Regulation Z, lenders may satisfy the criteria in § 1026.3(h)(6) by providing the disclosures described in § 1026.18 that comply with this part or the disclosures described in § 1026.19(e) and (f) that comply with this part.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-3-h-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title>Recording fees.</title>
          <content>See comment 37(g)(1)-1 for a discussion of what constitutes a recording fee.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-3-h-Interp-5" marker="5.">
          <title>Transfer taxes.</title>
          <content>See comment 37(g)(1)-3 for a discussion of what constitutes a transfer tax.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-6-Interp-5" subpath="title">
      <title>Allocation of costs.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-c-6-Interp-5" subpath="content">
      <content>When a creditor uses the special rule in § 1026.17(c)(6) to disclose credit extensions as multiple transactions, fees and charges must be allocated for purposes of calculating disclosures. In the case of a construction-permanent loan that a creditor chooses to disclose as multiple transactions, the creditor must allocate to the construction transaction finance charges under § 1026.4 and points and fees under § 1026.32(b)(1) that would not be imposed but for the construction financing. For example, inspection and handling fees for the staged disbursement of construction loan proceeds must be included in the disclosures for the construction phase and may not be included in the disclosures for the permanent phase. If a creditor charges separate amounts for finance charges under § 1026.4 and points and fees under § 1026.32(b)(1) for the construction phase and the permanent phase, such amounts must be allocated to the phase for which they are charged. If a creditor charges an origination fee for construction financing only but charges a greater origination fee for construction-permanent financing, the difference between the two fees must be allocated to the permanent phase. All other finance charges under § 1026.4 and points and fees under § 1026.32(b)(1) must be allocated to the permanent financing. Fees and charges that are not used to compute the finance charge under § 1026.4 or points and fees under § 1026.32(b)(1) may be allocated between the transactions in any manner the creditor chooses. For example, a reasonable appraisal fee paid to an independent, third-party appraiser may be allocated in any manner the creditor chooses because it would be excluded from the finance charge pursuant to § 1026.4(c)(7) and excluded from points and fees pursuant to § 1026.32(b)(1)(iii).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-17-f-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Change in rate or other terms.</title>
        <content>Redisclosure is required for changes that occur between the time disclosures are made and consummation if the annual percentage rate in the consummated transaction exceeds the limits prescribed in § 1026.17(f) even if the prior disclosures would be considered accurate under the tolerances in § 1026.18(d) or 1026.22(a). To illustrate:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <title>Transactions not secured by real property or a cooperative unit.</title>
          <content></content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-ii-A" marker="A.">
            <content>For transactions not secured by real property or a cooperative unit, if disclosures are made in a regular transaction on July 1, the transaction is consummated on July 15, and the actual annual percentage rate varies by more than 1/8 of 1 percentage point from the disclosed annual percentage rate, the creditor must either redisclose the changed terms or furnish a complete set of new disclosures before consummation. Redisclosure is required even if the disclosures made on July 1 are based on estimates and marked as such.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-ii-B" marker="B.">
            <content>In a regular transaction not secured by real property or a cooperative unit, if early disclosures are marked as estimates and the disclosed annual percentage rate is within 1/8 of 1 percentage point of the rate at consummation, the creditor need not redisclose the changed terms (including the annual percentage rate).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-ii-C" marker="C.">
            <content>If disclosures for transactions not secured by real property or a cooperative unit are made on July 1, the transaction is consummated on July 15, and the finance charge increased by $35 but the disclosed annual percentage rate is within the permitted tolerance, the creditor must at least redisclose the changed terms that were not marked as estimates. See § 1026.18(d)(2).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <title>Reverse mortgages.</title>
          <content>In a transaction subject to § 1026.19(a) and not § 1026.19(e) and (f), assume that, at the time the disclosures required by § 1026.19(a) are prepared in July, the loan closing is scheduled for July 31 and the creditor does not plan to collect per-diem interest at consummation. Assume further that consummation actually occurs on August 5, and per-diem interest for the remainder of August is collected as a prepaid finance charge. The creditor may rely on the disclosures prepared in July that were accurate when they were prepared. However, if the creditor prepares new disclosures in August that will be provided at consummation, the new disclosures must take into account the amount of the per-diem interest known to the creditor at that time.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
          <title>Transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit other than reverse mortgages.</title>
          <content>For transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit other than reverse mortgages, assume that, at the time the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e) are prepared in July, the loan closing is scheduled for July 31 and the creditor does not plan to collect per-diem interest at consummation. Assume further that consummation actually occurs on August 5, and per-diem interest for the remainder of August is collected as a prepaid finance charge. The creditor must make the disclosures required by § 1026.19(f) three days before consummation, and the disclosures required by § 1026.19(f) must take into account the amount of per-diem interest that will be collected at consummation.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-17-f-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Variable rate.</title>
        <content>The addition of a variable rate feature to the credit terms, after early disclosures are given, requires new disclosures. See § 1026.19(e) and (f) to determine when new disclosures are required for transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Scope of coverage.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Section 1026.18 applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions, other than transactions that are subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f). Section 1026.19(e) and (f) applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions that are secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages subject to § 1026.33. Accordingly, the disclosures required by § 1026.18 apply only to closed-end consumer credit transactions that are:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-i-A" marker="A.">
            <content>Unsecured;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-i-B" marker="B.">
            <content>Secured by personal property that is not a dwelling;</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-i-C" marker="C.">
            <content>Secured by personal property (other than a cooperative unit) that is a dwelling and are not also secured by real property; or</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-i-D" marker="D.">
            <content>Reverse mortgages subject to § 1026.33.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Of the foregoing transactions that are subject to § 1026.18, the creditor discloses a payment schedule under § 1026.18(g) for those described in paragraphs i.A and i.B of this comment. For transactions described in paragraphs i.C and i.D of this comment, the creditor discloses an interest rate and payment summary table under § 1026.18(s). See also comments 18(g)-6 and 18(s)-4 for additional guidance on the applicability to different transaction types of §§ 1026.18(g) or (s) and 1026.19(e) and (f).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-18-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Because § 1026.18 does not apply to transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages, references in the section and its commentary to “mortgages” refer only to transactions described in paragraphs i.C and i.D of this comment, as applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-g-Interp-6" subpath="title">
      <title>Morgage transactions.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-g-Interp-6" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.18(g) applies to closed-end transactions, other than transactions that are subject to § 1026.18(s) or § 1026.19(e) and (f). Section 1026.18(s) applies to closed-end transactions secured by real property or a dwelling, unless they are subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f). Section 1026.19(e) and (f) applies to closed-end transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages. Thus, if a closed-end consumer credit transaction is secured by real property, a cooperative unit, or a dwelling and the transaction is a reverse mortgage or the dwelling is personal property but not a cooperative unit, then the creditor discloses an interest rate and payment summary table in accordance with § 1026.18(s). See comment 18(s)-4. If a closed-end consumer credit transaction is secured by real property or a cooperative unit and is not a reverse mortgage, the creditor discloses a projected payments table in accordance with §§ 1026.37(c) and 1026.38(c), as required by § 1026.19(e) and (f). In all such cases, the creditor is not subject to the requirements of § 1026.18(g). On the other hand, if a closed-end consumer credit transaction is not secured by real property or a dwelling (for example, if it is unsecured or secured by an automobile), the creditor discloses a payment schedule in accordance with § 1026.18(g) and is not subject to the requirements of § 1026.18(s) or §§ 1026.37(c) and 1026.38(c).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-s-Interp-1" subpath="title">
      <title>In general.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-s-Interp-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.18(s) prescribes format and content for disclosure of interest rates and monthly (or other periodic) payments for reverse mortgages and certain transactions secured by dwellings that are personal property but not cooperative units. The information in § 1026.18(s)(2) through (4) is required to be in the form of a table, except as otherwise provided, with headings and format substantially similar to model clause H-4(E), H-4(F), H-4(G), or H-4(H) in appendix H to this part. A disclosure that does not include the shading shown in a model clause but otherwise follows the model clause's headings and format is substantially similar to that model clause. Where § 1026.18(s)(2) through (4) or the applicable model clause requires that a column or row of the table be labeled using the word “monthly” but the periodic payments are not due monthly, the creditor should use the appropriate term, such as “bi-weekly” or “quarterly.” In all cases, the table should have no more than five vertical columns corresponding to applicable interest rates at various times during the loan's term; corresponding payments would be shown in horizontal rows. Certain loan types and terms are defined for purposes of § 1026.18(s) in § 1026.18(s)(7).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-s-Interp-4" subpath="title">
      <title/>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-18-s-Interp-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Section 1026.18(s) applies to transactions secured by real property or a dwelling, other than transactions that are subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f). Those provisions apply to closed-end transactions secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages. Accordingly, § 1026.18(s) governs only closed-end reverse mortgages and closed-end transactions secured by a dwelling, other than a cooperative, that is personal property (such as a mobile home that is not deemed real property under State or other applicable law).</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-Interp" subpath="title">
      <title/>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-1-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-i-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-19-e-1-i">
        <title>19(e)(1)(i) Creditor.

</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirements.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(i) requires early disclosure of credit terms in closed-end credit transactions that are secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages. These disclosures must be provided in good faith. Except as otherwise provided in § 1026.19(e), a disclosure is in good faith if it is consistent with § 1026.17(c)(2)(i). Section 1026.17(c)(2)(i) provides that if any information necessary for an accurate disclosure is unknown to the creditor, the creditor shall make the disclosure based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure is provided to the consumer. The “reasonably available” standard requires that the creditor, acting in good faith, exercise due diligence in obtaining information. See comment 17(c)(2)(i)-1 for an explanation of the standard set forth in § 1026.17(c)(2)(i). See comment 17(c)(2)(i)-2 for labeling disclosures required under § 1026.19(e) that are estimates.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Cooperative units.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(i) requires early disclosure of credit terms in closed-end credit transactions, other than reverse mortgages, that are secured by real property or a cooperative unit, regardless of whether a cooperative unit is treated as real property under State or other applicable law.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5" parent="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Multiple-advance construction loans.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(iii) generally requires a creditor to deliver the Loan Estimate or place it in the mail not later than the third business day after the creditor receives the consumer's application and not later than the seventh business day before consummation. When a multiple-advance loan to finance the construction of a dwelling may be permanently financed by the same creditor, § 1026.17(c)(6)(ii) and comment 17(c)(6)-2 permit creditors to treat the construction phase and the permanent phase as either one transaction, with one combined disclosure, or more than one transaction, with a separate disclosure for each transaction. For construction—permanent transactions disclosed as one transaction, the creditor complies with § 1026.19(e)(1)(iii) by delivering or placing in the mail one combined disclosure required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) not later than the third business day after the creditor receives an application and not later than the seventh business day before consummation. For construction—permanent transactions disclosed as a separate construction phase and a separate permanent phase for which an application for both the construction and permanent financing has been received, the creditor complies with § 1026.19(e)(1)(iii) by delivering or placing in the mail the separate disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for both the construction financing and the permanent financing not later than the third business day after the creditor receives the application and not later than the seventh business day before consummation. A creditor may also provide a separate disclosure required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for the permanent phase before receiving an application for permanent financing at any time not later than the seventh business day before consummation. To illustrate:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Assume a creditor receives a consumer's application for construction financing only on Monday, June 1. The creditor must deliver or place in the mail the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for only the construction financing no later than Thursday, June 4, the third business day after the creditor received the consumer's application, and not later than the seventh business day before consummation of the transaction.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Assume the creditor receives a consumer's application for both construction and permanent financing on Monday, June 1. The creditor must deliver or place in the mail the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for both the construction and permanent financing, disclosed as either one transaction or separate transactions, no later than Thursday, June 4, the third business day after the creditor received the consumer's application, and not later than the seventh business day before consummation of the transaction.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Assume the creditor receives a consumer's application for construction financing only on Monday, June 1. Assume further that the creditor receives the consumer's application for permanent financing on Monday, June 8. The creditor must deliver or place in the mail the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for the construction financing no later than Thursday, June 4, the third business day after the creditor received the consumer's application for the construction financing only, and not later than the seventh business day before consummation of the construction transaction. The creditor must deliver or place in the mail the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for the permanent financing no later than Thursday, June 11, the third business day after the creditor received the consumer's application for the permanent financing, and not later than the seventh business day before consummation of the permanent financing transaction.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-iii-Interp-5-iv" marker="iv.">
          <content>Assume the same facts as in comment 19(e)(1)(iii)-5.ii, under which the creditor provides the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for both construction financing and permanent financing. If the creditor generally conducts separate closings for the construction financing and the permanent financing or expects that the construction financing and the permanent financing may have separate closings, providing separate Loan Estimates for the construction financing and for the permanent financing allows the creditor to deliver separate Closing Disclosures for the separate phases. For example, assume further that the consumer has requested permanent financing after receiving separate Loan Estimates for the construction financing and for the permanent financing, that consummation of the construction financing is scheduled for July 1, and that consummation of the permanent financing is scheduled on or about June 1 of the following year. The creditor may provide the construction financing Closing Disclosure at least three business days before consummation of that transaction on July 1 and delay providing the permanent financing Closing Disclosure until three business days before consummation of that transaction on or about June 1 of the following year, in accordance with § 1026.19(f)(1)(ii). The creditor may also issue a revised Loan Estimate for the permanent financing at any time prior to 60 days before consummation, following the procedures under § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(F).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <title> </title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Permission to shop.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) permits creditors to impose reasonable requirements regarding the qualifications of the provider. For example, the creditor may require that a settlement agent chosen by the consumer must be appropriately licensed in the relevant jurisdiction. In contrast, a creditor does not permit a consumer to shop for purposes of § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi) if the creditor requires the consumer to choose a provider from a list provided by the creditor. Whether the creditor permits the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) is determined based on all the relevant facts and circumstances. The requirements of § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(B) and (C) do not apply if the creditor does not permit the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Disclosure of services for which the consumer may shop.</title>
        <content>If a creditor permits a consumer to shop for a settlement service, § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(B) requires the creditor to identify settlement services required by the creditor for which the consumer is permitted to shop in the disclosures provided pursuant to § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). See § 1026.37(f)(3) regarding the content and format for disclosure of services required by the creditor for which the consumer is permitted to shop.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-3" marker="1.">
        <title>Written list of providers.</title>
        <content>If the creditor permits the consumer to shop for a settlement service it requires, § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C) requires the creditor to provide the consumer with a written list identifying at least one available provider of that service and stating that the consumer may choose a different provider for that service. The settlement service providers identified on the written list required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C) must correspond to the required settlement services for which the consumer may shop, disclosed under § 1026.37(f)(3). See form H-27 in appendix H to this part for a model list. Creditors using form H-27 in appendix H properly are deemed to be in compliance with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C). Creditors may make changes in the format or content of form H-27 in appendix H and be deemed to be in compliance with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C), so long as the changes do not affect the substance, clarity, or meaningful sequence of the form. An acceptable change to form H-27 in appendix H includes, for example, deleting the column for estimated fee amounts.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-4">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-1-vi-Interp-4" marker="1.">
        <title>Identification of available providers.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C) provides that the creditor must identify settlement service providers, that are available to the consumer, for the settlement services that are required by the creditor for which a consumer is permitted to shop. A creditor does not comply with the identification requirement in § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C) unless it provides sufficient information to allow the consumer to contact the provider, such as the name under which the provider does business and the provider's address and telephone number. Similarly, a creditor does not comply with the availability requirement in § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C) if it provides a written list consisting of only settlement service providers that are no longer in business or that do not provide services where the consumer or property is located.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Requirement.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(3)(i) provides the general rule that an estimated closing cost disclosed under § 1026.19(e) is not in good faith if the charge paid by or imposed on the consumer exceeds the amount originally disclosed under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). Although § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) and (iii) provide exceptions to the general rule, the charges that are generally subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) include, but are not limited to, the following:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Fees paid to the creditor.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Fees paid to a mortgage broker.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Fees paid to an affiliate of the creditor or a mortgage broker.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
          <content>Fees paid to an unaffiliated third party if the creditor did not permit the consumer to shop for a third party service provider for a settlement service.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-i-Interp-1-v" marker="v.">
          <content>Transfer taxes.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Requirements.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) provides that certain estimated charges are in good faith if the sum of all such charges paid by or imposed on the consumer does not exceed the sum of all such charges disclosed pursuant to § 1026.19(e) by more than 10 percent. Section 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) permits this limited increase for only the following items:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Fees paid to an unaffiliated third party if the creditor permitted the consumer to shop for the third-party service, consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Recording fees.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Aggregate increase limited to ten percent.</title>
        <content>Under § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii)(A), whether an individual estimated charge subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) is in good faith depends on whether the sum of all charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) increases by more than 10 percent, regardless of whether a particular charge increases by more than 10 percent. This is true even if an individual charge was omitted from the estimate provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and then imposed at consummation. The following examples illustrate the determination of good faith for charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii):</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Assume that, in the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), the creditor includes a $300 estimated fee for a settlement agent, the settlement agent fee is included in the category of charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii), and the sum of all charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) (including the settlement agent fee) equals $1,000. In this case, the creditor does not violate § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) if the actual settlement agent fee exceeds the estimated settlement agent fee by more than 10 percent (i.e., the fee exceeds $330), provided that the sum of all such actual charges does not exceed the sum of all such estimated charges by more than 10 percent (i.e., the sum of all such charges does not exceed $1,100).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Assume that, in the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), the sum of all estimated charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) equals $1,000. If the creditor does not include an estimated charge for a notary fee but a $10 notary fee is charged to the consumer, and the notary fee is subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii), then the creditor does not violate § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) if the sum of all amounts charged to the consumer subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) does not exceed $1,100, even though an individual notary fee was not included in the estimated disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-6" parent="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-ii-Interp-6" marker="1.">
        <title>Shopping for a third-party service.</title>
        <content>For good faith to be determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) a creditor must permit a consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A). Section 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) provides that a creditor permits a consumer to shop for a settlement service if the creditor permits the consumer to select the provider of that service, subject to reasonable requirements. If the creditor permits the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii), unless the settlement service provider is the creditor or an affiliate of the creditor, in which case good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i). As noted in comment 19(e)(1)(vi)-1, whether the creditor permits the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) is determined based on all the relevant facts and circumstances.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Good faith requirement for required services chosen by the consumer. </title>
        <content>If a service is required by the creditor, the creditor permits the consumer to shop for that service consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A), the creditor provides the list required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C), and the consumer chooses a service provider that is not on that list to perform that service, then the actual amounts of such fees need not be compared to the original estimates for such fees to perform the good faith analysis required under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) or (ii). Differences between the amounts of such charges disclosed under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and the amounts of such charges paid by or imposed on the consumer do not constitute a lack of good faith, so long as the original estimated charge, or lack of an estimated charge for a particular service, was based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure was provided. For example, if the consumer informs the creditor that the consumer will choose a settlement agent not identified by the creditor on the written list provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C), and the creditor discloses an unreasonably low estimated settlement agent fee of $20 when the average prices for settlement agent fees in that area are $150, then the under-disclosure does not comply with § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) and good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i). If the creditor permits the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) but fails to provide the written list required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(C), good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) instead of § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) unless the settlement service provider is the creditor or an affiliate of the creditor in which case good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i). As noted in comment 19(e)(1)(vi)-1 whether the creditor permits the consumer to shop consistent with § 1026.19(e)(1)(vi)(A) is determined based on all the relevant facts and circumstances.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-3" marker="1.">
        <title>Good faith requirement for property taxes or non-required services chosen by the consumer.</title>
        <content>Differences between the amounts of estimated charges for property taxes or services not required by the creditor disclosed under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and the amounts of such charges paid by or imposed on the consumer do not constitute a lack of good faith, so long as the original estimated charge, or lack of an estimated charge for a particular service, was based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure was provided. For example, if the consumer informs the creditor that the consumer will obtain a type of inspection not required by the creditor, the creditor must include the charge for that item in the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), but the actual amount of the inspection fee need not be compared to the original estimate for the inspection fee to perform the good faith analysis required by § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii). The original estimated charge, or lack of an estimated charge for a particular service, complies with § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) if it is made based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time that the estimate was provided. But, for example, if the subject property is located in a jurisdiction where consumers are customarily represented at closing by their own attorney, even though it is not a requirement, and the creditor fails to include a fee for the consumer's attorney, or includes an unreasonably low estimate for such fee, on the original estimates provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), then the creditor's failure to disclose, or unreasonably low estimation, does not comply with § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii). Similarly, the amount disclosed for property taxes must be based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure was provided. For example, if the creditor fails to include a charge for property taxes, or includes an unreasonably low estimate for that charge, on the original estimates provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), then the creditor's failure to disclose, or unreasonably low estimation, does not comply with § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) and the charge for property tax would be subject to the good faith determination under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-4" parent="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iii-Interp-4" marker="1.">
        <title>Bona fide charges.</title>
        <content>In covered transactions, § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) requires the creditor to provide the consumer with good faith estimates of the disclosures in § 1026.37. Section 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) provides that an estimate of the charges listed in § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) is in good faith if it is consistent with the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure is provided and that good faith is determined under § 1026.19(e)(3)(iii) even if such charges are paid to the creditor or affiliates of the creditor, so long as the charges are bona fide. For determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i), to be bona fide, charges must be lawful and for services that are actually performed.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Actual increase.</title>
        <content>A creditor may determine good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii) based on the increased charges reflected on revised disclosures only to the extent that the reason for revision, as identified in § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(A) through (F), actually increased the particular charge. For example, if a consumer requests a rate lock extension, then the revised disclosures on which a creditor relies for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) may reflect a new rate lock extension fee, but the fee may be no more than the rate lock extension fee charged by the creditor in its usual course of business, and the creditor may not rely on changes to other charges unrelated to the rate lock extension for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-4" parent="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-4" marker="1.">
        <title>Revised disclosures for general informational purposes.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(3)(iv) does not prohibit the creditor from issuing revised disclosures for informational purposes, e.g., to keep the consumer apprised of updated information, even if the revised disclosures may not be used for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii). See comment 19(e)(3)(iv)(A)-1.ii for an example in which the creditor issues revised disclosures even though the sum of all costs subject to the 10 percent tolerance category has not increased by more than 10 percent.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-5" parent="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-Interp-5" marker="1.">
        <title>Best information reasonably available.</title>
        <content>Regardless of whether a creditor may use particular disclosures for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii), except as otherwise provided in § 1026.19(e), any disclosures must be based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time they are provided to the consumer. See § 1026.17(c)(2)(i) and comment 17(c)(2)(i)-1. For example, if the creditor issues revised disclosures reflecting a new rate lock extension fee for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i), other charges unrelated to the rate lock extension must be reflected on the revised disclosures based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the revised disclosures are provided. Nonetheless, any increases in those other charges unrelated to the rate lock extension may not be used for the purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-e-3-iv-D-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-D-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-19-e-3-iv-D">
        <title>19(e)(3)(iv)(D) Interest rate dependent charges.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-D-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirements.</title>
          <content>If the interest rate is not locked when the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) are provided, then, no later than three business days after the date the interest rate is subsequently locked, § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(D) requires the creditor to provide a revised version of the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) reflecting the revised interest rate, the points disclosed under § 1026.37(f)(1), lender credits, and any other interest rate dependent charges and terms. The following example illustrates this requirement:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-D-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Assume a creditor sets the interest rate by executing a rate lock agreement with the consumer. If such an agreement exists when the original disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) are provided, then the actual points and lender credits are compared to the estimated points disclosed under § 1026.37(f)(1) and lender credits included in the original disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) for the purpose of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i). If the consumer enters into a rate lock agreement with the creditor after the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) were provided, then § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(D) requires the creditor to provide, no later than three business days after the date that the consumer and the creditor enter into a rate lock agreement, a revised version of the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) reflecting the revised interest rate, the points disclosed under § 1026.37(f)(1), lender credits, and any other interest rate dependent charges and terms. Provided that the revised version of the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) reflect any revised points disclosed under § 1026.37(f)(1) and lender credits, the actual points and lender credits are compared to the revised points and lender credits for the purpose of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-e-3-iv-D-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>After the Closing Disclosure is provided.</title>
        <content>Under § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(D), no later than three business days after the date the interest rate is locked, the creditor must provide to the consumer a revised version of the Loan Estimate as required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). Section 1026.19(e)(4)(ii) prohibits a creditor from providing a revised version of the Loan Estimate as required by § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) on or after the date on which the creditor provides the Closing Disclosure as required by § 1026.19(f)(1)(i). If the interest rate is locked on or after the date on which the creditor provides the Closing Disclosure and the Closing Disclosure is inaccurate as a result, then the creditor must provide the consumer a corrected Closing Disclosure, at or before consummation, reflecting any changed terms, pursuant to § 1026.19(f)(2). If the rate lock causes the Closing Disclosure to become inaccurate before consummation in a manner listed in § 1026.19(f)(2)(ii), the creditor must ensure that the consumer receives a corrected Closing Disclosure no later than three business days before consummation, as provided in that paragraph.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-e-3-iv-E-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-e-3-iv-E-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-e-3-iv-E">
        <title>Requirements.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-e-3-iv-E-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirements.</title>
          <content>If the consumer indicates an intent to proceed with the transaction more than 10 business days after the disclosures were originally provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(iii), for the purpose of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii), a creditor may use a revised estimate of a charge instead of the amount originally disclosed under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). Section 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(E) requires no justification for the change to the original estimate other than the lapse of 10 business days. For example, assume a creditor includes a $500 underwriting fee on the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and the creditor delivers those disclosures on a Monday. If the consumer indicates intent to proceed 11 business days later, the creditor may provide new disclosures with a $700 underwriting fee. In this example, § 1026.19(e) and § 1026.25 require the creditor to document that a new disclosure was provided under § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(E) but do not require the creditor to document a reason for the increase in the underwriting fee.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
      <interpParagraph marker="1." label="1026-e-3-iv-E-Interp-2">
        <title>Longer time period.</title>
        <content>For transactions in which the interest rate is locked for a specific period of time, § 1026.37(a)(13)(ii) requires the creditor to provide the date and time (including the applicable time zone) when that period ends. If the creditor establishes a period greater than 10 business days after the disclosures were originally provided (or subsequently extends it to such a longer period) before the estimated closing costs expire, notwithstanding the 10-business-day period discussed in comment 19(e)(3)(iv)(E)-1, that longer time period becomes the relevant time period for purposes of § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(E). Accordingly, in such a case, the creditor may not issue revised disclosures for purposes of determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii) under § 1026.19(e)(3)(iv)(E) until after the longer time period has expired. A creditor establishes such a period greater than 10 business days by communicating the greater time period to the consumer, including through oral communication.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-f-1-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-f-1-i-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-19-f-1-i">
        <title>19(f)(1)(i) Scope.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-f-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirements.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.19(f)(1)(i) requires disclosure of the actual terms of the credit transaction, and the actual costs associated with the settlement of that transaction, for closed-end credit transactions that are secured by real property or a cooperative unit, other than reverse mortgages subject to § 1026.33. For example, if the creditor requires the consumer to pay money into a reserve account for the future payment of taxes, the creditor must disclose to the consumer the exact amount that the consumer is required to pay into the reserve account. If the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) do not contain the actual terms of the transaction, the creditor does not violate § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) if the creditor provides corrected disclosures that contain the actual terms of the transaction and complies with the other requirements of § 1026.19(f), including the timing requirements in § 1026.19(f)(1)(ii) and (f)(2). For example, if the creditor provides the disclosures required by § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) on Monday, June 1, but the consumer adds a mobile notary service to the terms of the transaction on Tuesday, June 2, the creditor complies with § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) if it provides disclosures reflecting the revised terms of the transaction on or after Tuesday, June 2, assuming that the corrected disclosures are also provided at or before consummation, under § 1026.19(f)(2)(i).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-f-2-iii-Interp-2" parent="1026-f-2-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-f-2-iii-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Per-diem interest.</title>
        <content>Under § 1026.19(f)(2)(iii), if during the 30-day period following consummation, an event in connection with the settlement of the transaction occurs that causes the disclosures to become inaccurate, and such inaccuracy results in a change to an amount actually paid by the consumer from that amount disclosed under § 1026.19(f)(1)(i), the creditor must provide the consumer corrected disclosures, except as described in this comment. A creditor is not required to provide corrected disclosures under § 1026.19(f)(2)(iii) if the only changes that would be required to be disclosed in the corrected disclosure are changes to per-diem interest and any disclosures affected by the change in per-diem interest, even if the amount of per-diem interest actually paid by the consumer differs from the amount disclosed under § 1026.38(g)(2) and (o). Nonetheless, if a creditor is providing a corrected disclosure under § 1026.19(f)(2)(iii) for reasons other than changes in per-diem interest and the per-diem interest has changed as well, the creditor must disclose in the corrected disclosures under § 1026.19(f)(2)(iii) the correct amount of the per-diem interest and provide corrected disclosures for any disclosures that are affected by the change in per-diem interest.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-f-2-v-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-f-2-v-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-f-2-v">
        <title>19(f)(2)(v) Refunds related to the good faith analysis.

</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-f-2-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirements.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.19(f)(2)(v) provides that, if amounts paid at consummation exceed the amounts specified under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) or (ii), the creditor does not violate § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) if the creditor refunds the excess to the consumer no later than 60 days after consummation, and the creditor does not violate § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) if the creditor delivers or places in the mail disclosures corrected to reflect the refund of such excess no later than 60 days after consummation. For example, assume that at consummation the consumer must pay four itemized charges that are subject to the good faith determination under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i). If the actual amounts paid by the consumer for the four itemized charges subject to § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) exceed their respective estimates on the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) by $30, $25, $25, and $15, then the total would exceed the limitations prescribed by § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) by $95. If, further, the amounts paid by the consumer for services that are subject to the good faith determination under § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) totaled $1,190, but the respective estimates on the disclosures required under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) totaled only $1,000, then the total would exceed the limitations prescribed by § 1026.19(e)(3)(ii) by $90. The creditor does not violate § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) if the creditor refunds $185 to the consumer no later than 60 days after consummation. The creditor does not violate § 1026.19(f)(1)(i) if the creditor delivers or places in the mail corrected disclosures reflecting the $185 refund of the excess amount collected no later than 60 days after consummation. See comments 38-4 and 38(h)(3)-2 for additional guidance on disclosing refunds.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-f-3-ii-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-f-3-ii-Interp-3" marker="1.">
        <title>Uniform use.</title>
        <content>If a creditor chooses to use an average charge for a settlement service for a particular loan within a class, § 1026.19(f)(3)(ii)(C) requires the creditor to use that average charge for that service on all loans within the class. For example:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-f-3-ii-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
          <title/>
          <content>Assume a creditor elects to use an average charge for appraisal fees. The creditor defines a class of transactions as all fixed rate loans originated between January 1 and April 30 secured by real property or a cooperative unit located within a particular metropolitan statistical area. The creditor must then charge the average appraisal charge to all consumers obtaining fixed rate loans originated between May 1 and August 30 secured by real property or a cooperative unit located within the same metropolitan statistical area.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-f-3-ii-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>The example in paragraph i of this comment assumes that a consumer would not be required to pay the average appraisal charge unless an appraisal was required on that particular loan. Using the example above, if a consumer applies for a loan within the defined class, but already has an appraisal report acceptable to the creditor from a prior loan application, the creditor may not charge the consumer the average appraisal fee because an acceptable appraisal report has already been obtained for the consumer's application. Similarly, although the creditor defined the class broadly to include all fixed rate loans, the creditor may not require the consumer to pay the average appraisal charge if the particular fixed rate loan program the consumer applied for does not require an appraisal.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-19-f-4-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-19-f-4-i-Interp" marker="1.">
        <title>19(f)(4)(i) Provision to seller.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-f-4-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requirement.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.19(f)(4)(i) requires the settlement agent to provide the seller with the disclosures required under § 1026.38 that relate to the seller's transaction reflecting the actual terms of the seller's transaction. The settlement agent complies with this provision by providing a copy of the Closing Disclosure provided to the consumer, if the Closing Disclosure also contains the information under § 1026.38 relating to the seller's transaction or, alternatively, by providing the disclosures under § 1026.38(t)(5)(v) or (vi), as applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-19-f-4-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
          <content>In a purchase transaction with simultaneous subordinate financing, the settlement agent complies with § 1026.19(f)(4)(i) by providing the seller with only the first-lien transaction disclosures required under § 1026.38 that relate to the seller's transaction reflecting the actual terms of the seller's transaction in accordance with comment 19(f)(4)(i)-1 if the first-lien Closing Disclosure records the entirety of the seller's transaction. If the first-lien Closing Disclosure does not record the entirety of the seller's transaction, the settlement agent complies with § 1026.19(f)(4)(i) by providing the seller with both the first-lien and simultaneous subordinate financing transaction disclosures required under § 1026.38 that relate to the seller's transaction reflecting the actual terms of the seller's transaction in accordance with comment 19(f)(4)(i)-1.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-23-g-Interp-1" parent="1026-23-g-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-23-g-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Example.</title>
        <content>See comment 38(o)-1 for examples illustrating the interaction of the finance charge and total of payments accuracy requirements for each transaction subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-23-h-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-23-h-2-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-23-h-2">
        <title>23(h)(2) Tolerance for Disclosures.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-23-h-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>General.</title>
          <content>The tolerance for disclosure of the finance charge is based on the accuracy of the total finance charge rather than its component charges. For transactions subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f), the tolerance for disclosure of the total of payments is based on the accuracy of the total of payments, taken as a whole, rather than its component charges.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-23-h-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Example.</title>
          <content>See comment 38(o)-1 for examples illustrating the interaction of the finance charge and total of payments accuracy requirements for each transaction subject to § 1026.19(e) and (f).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-25-c-1-Interp" subpath="title">
      <title>25(c)(1) Records related to requirements for loans secured by real property or a cooperative unit.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-a-7-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-7-Interp" marker="1." target="1026-37-a-7">
        <title>37(a)(7) Sale price.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-7-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Estimated property value.</title>
          <content>In transactions where there is no seller, such as in a refinancing, § 1026.37(a)(7)(ii) requires the creditor to disclose the estimated value of the property identified in § 1026.37(a)(6) based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure is provided to the consumer, which may include, at the creditor's option, the estimated value of the improvements to be made on the property in transactions involving construction. The creditor may use the estimate provided by the consumer at application unless it has performed its own estimate of the property value by the time the disclosure is provided to the consumer, in which case the creditor must use its own estimate. If the creditor has obtained any appraisals or valuations of the property for the application at the time the disclosure is issued to the consumer, the value determined by the appraisal or valuation to be used during underwriting for the application is disclosed as the estimated property value. If the creditor has obtained multiple appraisals or valuations and has not yet determined which one will be used during underwriting, it may disclose the value from any appraisal or valuation it reasonably believes it may use in underwriting the transaction. In a transaction that involves a seller, if the sale price is not yet known, the creditor complies with § 1026.37(a)(7) if it discloses the estimated value of the property that it used as the basis for the disclosures in the Loan Estimate.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-7-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Personal property.</title>
          <content>In transactions involving personal property that is separately valued from real property, only the value of the real property or cooperative unit is disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(7). Where personal property is included in the sale price of the real property or cooperative unit (for example, if the consumer is purchasing the furniture inside the dwelling), however, § 1026.37(a)(7) permits disclosure of the aggregate price without any reduction for the appraised or estimated value of the personal property.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-37-a-8-Interp-3" parent="1026-37-a-8-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-8-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Loan term start date.</title>
        <content>See comment app. D-7.i for an explanation of how a creditor discloses the loan term of a multiple-advance loan to finance the construction of a dwelling that may be permanently financed by the same creditor.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>General.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.37(a)(9) requires disclosure of the consumer's intended use of the credit. In ascertaining the consumer's intended use, § 1026.37(a)(9) requires the creditor to consider all relevant information known to the creditor at the time of the disclosure. If the purpose is not known, the creditor may rely on the consumer's stated purpose. The following examples illustrate when each of the permissible purposes should be disclosed:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <title>Purchase.</title>
          <content>The consumer intends to use the proceeds from the transaction to purchase the property that will secure the extension of credit. In a purchase transaction with simultaneous subordinate financing, the simultaneous subordinate loan is also disclosed with the purpose “Purchase.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <title>Refinance.</title>
          <content>The consumer refinances an existing obligation already secured by the consumer's dwelling to change the rate, term, or other loan features and may or may not receive cash from the transaction. For example, in a refinance with no cash provided, the new amount financed does not exceed the unpaid principal balance, any earned unpaid finance charge on the existing debt, and amounts attributed solely to the costs of the refinancing. Conversely, in a refinance with cash provided, the consumer refinances an existing mortgage obligation and receives money from the transaction that is in addition to the funds used to pay the unpaid principal balance, any earned unpaid finance charge on the existing debt, and amounts attributed solely to the costs of the refinancing. In such a transaction, the consumer may, for example, use the newly-extended credit to pay off the balance of the existing mortgage and other consumer debt, such as a credit card balance.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
          <title>Construction.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.37(a)(9)(iii) requires the creditor to disclose that the loan is for construction in transactions where the creditor extends credit to finance only the cost of initial construction (construction-only loan), not renovations to existing dwellings, and in transactions where a multiple advance loan may be permanently financed by the same creditor (construction-permanent loan). In a construction-only loan, the borrower may be required to make interest-only payments during the loan term with the balance commonly due at the end of the construction project. For additional guidance on disclosing construction-permanent loans, see § 1026.17(c)(6)(ii), comments 17(c)(6)-2, -3, and -5, and appendix D to this part.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-9-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
          <title>Home equity loan.</title>
          <content>The creditor is required to disclose that the credit is for a “home equity loan” if the creditor intends to extend credit for any purpose other than a purchase, refinancing, or construction. This disclosure applies whether the loan is secured by a first or subordinate lien.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Additional features.</title>
        <content>When disclosing a loan product with at least one of the features described in § 1026.37(a)(10)(ii), § 1026.37(a)(10)(iii) and (iv) require the disclosure of only the first applicable feature in the order of § 1026.37(a)(10)(ii) and that it be preceded by the time period or the length of the introductory period and the frequency of the first adjustment period, as applicable, followed by a description of the loan product and its time period as provided for in § 1026.37(a)(10)(i). For example:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
          <title>Negative amortization.</title>
          <content>Some loan products, such as “payment option” loans, permit the borrower to make payments that are insufficient to cover all of the interest accrued, and the unpaid interest is added to the principal balance. Where the loan product includes a loan feature that may cause the loan balance to increase, the disclosure required by § 1026.37(a)(10)(ii)(A) is preceded by the time period that the borrower is permitted to make payments that result in negative amortization (e.g., “2 Year Negative Amortization”), followed by the loan product type. Thus, a fixed rate product with a step-payment feature for the first two years of the legal obligation that may negatively amortize is disclosed as “2 Year Negative Amortization, Fixed Rate.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
          <title>Interest only.</title>
          <content>When disclosing an “Interest Only” feature, as defined in § 1026.18(s)(7)(iv), the applicable time period must precede the label “Interest Only.” Thus, a fixed rate loan with only interest due for the first five years of the loan term is disclosed as “5 Year Interest Only, Fixed Rate.” If the interest only feature fails to cover the total interest due, then, as required by § 1026.37(a)(10)(iii), the disclosure must reference the negative amortization feature and not the interest only feature (e.g., “5 Year Negative Amortization, Fixed Rate”). See comment app. D-7.ii for an explanation of the disclosure of the time period of an interest only feature for a construction loan or a construction-permanent loan.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
          <title>Step payment.</title>
          <content>When disclosing a step payment feature (which is sometimes referred to instead as a graduated payment), the period of time at the end of which the scheduled payments will change must precede the label “Step Payment” (e.g., “5 Year Step Payment”) followed by the name of the loan product. Thus, a fixed rate mortgage subject to a 5-year step payment plan is disclosed as a “5 Year Step Payment, Fixed Rate.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2-iv" marker="iv.">
          <title>Ballon payment.</title>
          <content>If a loan product includes a “balloon payment,” as that term is defined in § 1026.37(b)(5), the disclosure of the balloon payment feature, including the year the payment is due, precedes the disclosure of the loan product. Thus, if the loan product is a step rate with an introductory rate that lasts for three years and adjusts each year thereafter until the balloon payment is due in the seventh year of the loan term, the disclosure required is “Year 7 Balloon Payment, 3/1 Step Rate.” If the loan product includes more than one balloon payment, only the earliest year that a balloon payment is due shall be disclosed.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2-v" marker="v.">
          <title>Seasonal payment.</title>
          <content>If a loan product includes a seasonal payment feature, § 1026.37(a)(10)(ii)(E) requires that the creditor disclose the feature. The feature is not, however, required to be disclosed with any preceding time period. Disclosure of the label “Seasonal Payment” without any preceding number of years satisfies this requirement.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Expiration date.</title>
        <content>The disclosure required by § 1026.37(a)(13)(ii) related to estimated closing costs is required regardless of whether the interest rate is locked for a specific period of time or whether the terms and costs are otherwise accepted or extended. If the consumer fails to indicate an intent to proceed with the transaction within 10 business days after the disclosures were originally provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(iii) (or within any longer time period established by the creditor), then, for determining good faith under § 1026.19(e)(3)(i) and (ii), a creditor may use a revised estimate of a charge instead of the amount originally disclosed under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). See comment 19(e)(3)(iv)(E)-2.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-4" parent="1026-37-a-13-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-a-13-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Revised disclosures.</title>
        <content>Once the consumer indicates an intent to proceed within the time specified by the creditor under § 1026.37(a)(13)(ii), the date and time at which estimated closing costs expire are left blank on any subsequent revised disclosures. The creditor may extend the period of availability to expire beyond the time disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(13)(ii). If the consumer indicates an intent to proceed within that longer time period, the date and time at which estimated closing costs expire are left blank on subsequent revised disclosures, if any. See comment 19(e)(3)(iv)-5.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-b-2-Interp" target="1026-37-b-2">
        <title>37(b)(2) Interest rate.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-b-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Interest rate at consummation not known.</title>
          <content>Where the interest rate that will apply at consummation is not known at the time the creditor must deliver the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e), § 1026.37(b)(2) requires disclosure of the fully-indexed rate, defined as the index plus the margin at consummation. Although § 1026.37(b)(2) refers to the index plus margin “at consummation,” if the index value that will be in effect at consummation is unknown at the time the disclosures are provided under § 1026.19(e)(1)(iii), i.e., within three business days after receipt of a consumer's application, the fully-indexed rate disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(2) may be based on the index in effect at the time the disclosure is delivered. The index in effect at consummation (or the time the disclosure is delivered under § 1026.19(e)) need not be used if the contract provides for a delay in the implementation of changes in an index value. For example, if the contract specifies that rate changes are based on the index value in effect 45 days before the change date, creditors may use any index value in effect during the 45 days before consummation (or any earlier date of disclosure) in calculating the fully-indexed rate to be disclosed. See comment app. D-7.iii for an explanation of the disclosure of the permanent financing interest rate for a construction-permanent loan.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b-3-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-b-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Initial periodic payment if not known.</title>
        <content>Under § 1026.37(b)(3), the initial periodic payment amount that will be due under the terms of the legal obligation must be disclosed. If the initial periodic payment is not known because it will be based on an interest rate at consummation that is not known at the time the disclosures required by § 1026.19(e) must be provided, for example, if it is based on an external index that may fluctuate before consummation, § 1026.37(b)(3) requires that the disclosure be based on the fully-indexed rate disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(2). See comment 37(b)(2)-1 for guidance regarding calculating the fully-indexed rate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-b-6-iii-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-b-6-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Additional information regarding increase in periodic payment.</title>
        <content>A creditor complies with the requirement under § 1026.37(b)(6)(iii) to disclose additional information indicating the scheduled frequency of adjustments to the periodic principal and interest payment by using the phrases “Adjusts every” and “starting in.” A creditor complies with the requirement under § 1026.37(b)(6)(iii) to disclose additional information indicating the maximum possible periodic principal and interest payment, and the date when the periodic principal and interest payment may first equal the maximum principal and interest payment by using the phrase “Can go as high as” and then indicating the date at the end of that phrase or, for a scheduled maximum amount, such as under a step payment loan, “Goes as high as.” A creditor complies with the requirement under § 1026.37(b)(6)(iii) to indicate that there is a period during which only interest is required to be paid and the due date of the last periodic payment of such period using the phrase “Includes only interest and no principal until.” See form H-24 of appendix H to this part for the required format of such phrases, which is required for federally related mortgage loans under § 1026.37(o)(3). See comment app. D-7.iv for an explanation of the disclosure of an increase in the periodic payment for a construction or construction-permanent loan.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-37-c-Interp-2" operation="added" parent="1026-37-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Construction loans.</title>
        <content>See comment app. D-7.v for an explanation of the projected payments disclosure for a construction or construction-permanent loan.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp" target="1026-37-c-1-iii-B">
        <title>Paragraph 37(c)(1)(iii)(B).</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Multiple events occurring in a single year.</title>
          <content>If multiple changes to periodic principal and interest payments would result in more than one separate periodic payment or range of payments in a single year, § 1026.37(c)(1)(iii)(B) requires the creditor to disclose the range of payments that would apply during the year in which the events occur. For example:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>Assume a loan with a 30-year term with a payment that adjusts every month for the first 12 months and is fixed thereafter, where mortgage insurance is not required, and where no escrow account would be established for the payment of charges described in § 1026.37(c)(4)(ii). The creditor discloses as a single range of payments the initial periodic payment and the periodic payment that would apply after each payment adjustment during the first 12 months, which single range represents the minimum payment and maximum payment, respectively. Under § 1026.37(c)(1)(i)(D), the creditor also discloses, as an additional separate periodic payment or range of payments, the periodic principal and interest payment or range of payments that would apply after the payment becomes fixed.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>Assume instead a loan with a 30-year term with a payment that adjusts upward at three months and at six months and is fixed thereafter, where mortgage insurance is not required, and where no escrow account would be established for the payment of charges described in § 1026.37(c)(4)(ii). The creditor discloses as a single range of payments the initial periodic payment, the periodic payment that would apply after the payment adjustment that occurs at three months, and the periodic payment that would apply after the payment adjustment that occurs at six months, which single range represents the minimum payment and maximum payment, respectively, which would apply during the first year of the loan. Under § 1026.37(c)(1)(i)(D), the creditor also discloses as an additional separate periodic payment or range of payments, the principal and interest payment that would apply on the first anniversary of the due date of the initial periodic payment or range of payments, because that is the anniversary that immediately follows the occurrence of the multiple payments or ranges of payments that occurred during the first year of the loan.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-1-iii-B-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
            <content>Assume that the same loan has a payment that, instead of becoming fixed after the adjustment at six months, adjusts once more at 18 months and becomes fixed thereafter. The creditor discloses the same single range of payments for year one. Under § 1026.37(c)(1)(i)(D), the creditor separately discloses the principal and interest payment that would apply on the first anniversary of the due date of the initial periodic payment in year two. Under § 1026.37(c)(1)(i)(A) and (c)(3)(ii), beginning in the next year in the sequence (i.e., in year three), the creditor separately discloses the periodic payment that would apply after the payment adjustment that occurs at 18 months. See comment 37(c)(3)(ii)-1 regarding subheadings that state the years.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change label="1026-37-c-4-iv-Interp-2" operation="modified">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-c-4-iv-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Amounts paid by the creditor using escrow account funds.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.37(c)(4)(iv) requires the creditor to disclose an indication of whether the amounts disclosed under § 1026.37(c)(4)(ii) will be paid by the creditor using escrow account funds. If only a portion of the amounts disclosed under § 1026.37(c)(4)(ii), including, without limitation, property taxes, homeowner's insurance, and assessments, will be paid by the creditor using escrow account funds, the creditor may indicate that only a portion of the amounts disclosed will be paid using escrow account funds, such as by using the word “some.”</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-d-2-Interp" subpath="title">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-d-2-Interp" marker="1.">
        <title>37(d)(2) Optional alternative table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
        <content></content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-d-2-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-d-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Optional use.</title>
        <content>The optional alternative disclosure of the estimated cash to close provided for in § 1026.37(d)(2) may be used by a creditor only in a transaction without a seller or a simultaneous subordinate financing transaction. In a purchase transaction, the optional alternative disclosure may be used for the simultaneous subordinate financing Loan Estimate only if the first-lien Closing Disclosure will record the entirety of the seller's transaction. Creditors may only use this alternative estimated cash to close disclosure in conjunction with the alternative disclosure under § 1026.37(h)(2).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-37-f-Interp-3" parent="1026-37-f-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-f-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Construction loan inspection and handling fees.</title>
        <content>Inspection and handling fees for the staged disbursement of construction loan proceeds, including draw fees, are loan costs associated with the transaction for purposes of § 1026.37(f). If inspection and handling fees are collected at or before consummation, the total of such fees is disclosed in the loan costs table. If inspection and handling fees will be collected after consummation, the total of such fees is disclosed in a separate addendum and the fees are not counted for purposes of the calculating cash to close table. See comment 37(f)(6)-3 for a description of an addendum used to disclose inspection and handling fees that will be collected after consummation. See also comments 38(f)-2 and app. D-7.vii. If the number of inspections and disbursements is not known at the time the disclosures are provided, the creditor discloses the fees that will be collected based on the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure is provided. See comment 19(e)(1)(i)-1. See § 1026.17(e) and its commentary for an explanation of the effect of subsequent events that cause inaccuracies in disclosures.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-37-f-6-Interp-3" parent="1026-37-f-6-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-f-6-Interp-3" marker="1.">
        <title>Addendum for post-consummation inspection and handling fees.</title>
        <content>A creditor makes the disclosures required by § 1026.37(f) and comment 37(f)-3 for construction loan inspection and handling fees collected after consummation by disclosing the total of such fees under the heading “Inspection and Handling Fees Collected After Closing” in an addendum, which may be the addendum pursuant to § 1026.37(f)(6) or any other addendum or additional page under § 1026.37. See comment 37(o)(1)-1. For purposes of comment 38(f)-2, the addendum may be any addendum or additional page under § 1026.38. If the actual amount of such fees is not known at the time the disclosures are provided, the disclosures in the addendum are based upon the best information reasonably available to the creditor at the time the disclosure is provided. See comment 19(e)(1)(i)-1. For example, such information could include amounts the creditor has previously charged in similar construction transactions or the amount of estimated inspection and handling fees used by the creditor for purposes of setting the construction loan's commitment amount.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-g-6-ii-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-g-6-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Lender credits.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.19(e)(1)(i) requires disclosure of lender credits as provided in § 1026.37(g)(6)(ii). Such lender credits include non-specific lender credits as well as specific lender credits. See comment 19(e)(3)(i)-5.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1026-37-h-1-Interp-2" parent="1026-37-h-1-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-Interp-2" marker="1.">
        <title>Simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
        <content>On the Loan Estimate for simultaneous subordinate financing purchase transactions, the sale price disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(7)(i) is not used under § 1026.37(h)(1) for the calculating cash to close table calculations that include the sale price as a component of the calculation. For example, sale price is generally included in the closing costs financed calculation under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii) as a component of the estimated total amount of payments to third parties. However, for simultaneous subordinate financing transactions, the estimated total amount of payments to third parties would not include the sale price. The estimated total amount of payments to third parties only includes payments occurring in the simultaneous subordinate financing transaction other than payments toward the sale price.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-ii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-ii-Interp" target="1026-37-h-1-ii">
        <title>37(h)(1)(ii) Closing costs financed.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Calculation of amount.</title>
          <content>The amount of closing costs financed disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii) is determined by subtracting the estimated total amount of payments to third parties not otherwise disclosed under § 1026.37(f) and (g) from the loan amount disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(1). The estimated total amount of payments to third parties includes the sale price disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(7)(i), if applicable, unless otherwise excluded under comment 37(h)(1)-2. Other examples of payments to third parties not otherwise disclosed under § 1026.37(f) and (g) include the amount of construction costs for transactions that involve improvements to be made on the property and payoffs of secured or unsecured debt. If the result of the calculation is zero or negative, the amount of $0 is disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii). If the result of the calculation is a positive number, that amount is disclosed as a negative number under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii), but only to the extent that the absolute value of the amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii) does not exceed the total amount of closing costs disclosed under § 1026.37(g)(6).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Loan amount.</title>
          <content>The loan amount disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(1), a component of the closing costs financed calculation, is the total amount the consumer will borrow, as reflected by the face amount of the note.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-Interp" target="1026-37-h-1-iii">
        <title>37(h)(1)(iii) Down payment and other funds from borrower.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Down payment and funds from borrower calculation.</title>
          <content>For purposes of § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(1), the down payment and funds from borrower amount is calculated as the difference between the sale price of the property disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(7)(i) and the sum of the loan amount and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv). The calculation is independent of any loan program or investor requirements.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Funds for borrower.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) requires that, in a purchase transaction as defined in paragraph (a)(9)(i) of this section that is a simultaneous subordinate financing transaction or that involves improvements to be made on the property, or when the sum of the loan amount disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(1) and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) exceeds the sale price disclosed under § 1026.37(a)(7)(i), the amount of funds from the consumer is determined in accordance with § 1026.37(h)(1)(v). Section 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(B) requires that, for all non-purchase transactions, the amount of estimated funds from the consumer is determined in accordance with § 1026.37(h)(1)(v). Pursuant to § 1026.37(h)(1)(v), the amount to be disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (B) is determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(1) and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) (excluding any closing costs financed disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii)) from the total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction. The total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction is the sum of the amounts that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure in the summaries of transactions table under § 1026.38(j)(1)(ii), (iii), and (v), as applicable. When the result of the calculation is positive, that amount is disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii) as “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower,” and $0 is disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(v) as “Funds for Borrower.” When the result of the calculation is negative, that amount is disclosed as a negative number under § 1026.37(h)(1)(v) as “Funds for Borrower,” and $0 is disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii) as “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower.” When the result is $0, $0 is disclosed as “Down Payment/Funds from Borrower” and “Funds for Borrower” under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii) and (v), respectively.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-v-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-Interp" target="1026-37-h-1-v">
        <title>37(h)(1)(v) Funds for borrower.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>No funds for borrower.</title>
          <content>When the down payment and other funds from the borrower is determined in accordance with § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(1), the amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(v) as funds for the borrower is $0.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-v-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Total amount of existing debt satisfied in the transaction,</title>
          <content>The amounts disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (B), as applicable, and (h)(1)(v) are determined by subtracting the sum of the loan amount disclosed under § 1026.37(b)(1) and any amount of existing loans assumed or taken subject to that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure under § 1026.38(j)(2)(iv) (excluding any closing costs financed disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(ii)) from the total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction. The total amount of all existing debt being satisfied in the transaction is the sum of the amounts that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure in the summaries of transactions table under § 1026.38(j)(1)(ii), (iii), and (v), as applicable.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vi-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vi-Interp" target="1026-37-h-1-vi">
        <title>37(h)(1)(vi) Seller credits.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vi-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Non-specific seller credits to be disclosed.</title>
          <content>Non-specific seller credits, i.e., general payments from the seller to the consumer that do not pay for a particular fee on the disclosures provided under § 1026.19(e)(1), known to the creditor at the time of delivery of the Loan Estimate, are disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vi). For example, a creditor may learn the amount of seller credits that will be paid in the transaction from information obtained from the consumer, from a review of the purchase and sale contract, or from information obtained from a real estate agent in the transaction.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vi-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Seller credits for specific charges.</title>
          <content>To the extent known by the creditor at the time of delivery of the Loan Estimate, specific seller credits, i.e., seller credits for specific items disclosed under § 1026.37(f) and (g), may be either disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vi) or reflected in the amounts disclosed for those specific items under § 1026.37(f) and (g). For example, if the creditor knows at the time of the delivery of the Loan Estimate that the seller has agreed to pay half of a $100 required pest inspection fee, the creditor may either disclose the required pest inspection fee as $100 under § 1026.37(f) with a $50 seller credit disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vi) or disclose the required pest inspection fee as $50 under § 1026.37(f), reflecting the specific seller credit in the amount disclosed for the pest inspection fee. If the creditor knows at the time of the delivery of the Loan Estimate that the seller has agreed to pay the entire $100 pest inspection fee, the creditor may either disclose the required pest inspection fee as $100 under § 1026.37(f) with a $100 seller credit disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vi) or disclose nothing under § 1026.37(f), reflecting that the specific seller credit will cover the entire pest inspection fee.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Other credits known at the time the Loan Estimate is issued.</title>
        <content>Amounts expected to be paid at closing by third parties not otherwise associated with the transaction, such as gifts from family members and not otherwise identified under § 1026.37(h)(1), are included in the amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii). Amounts expected to be provided in advance of closing by third parties, including family members, not otherwise associated with the transaction are not required to be disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-4">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Other credits to be disclosed.</title>
        <content>Credits other than those from the creditor or seller are disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii). Disclosure of other credits is, like other disclosures under § 1026.37, subject to the good faith requirement under § 1026.19(e)(1)(i). See § 1026.19(e)(1)(i) and comments 17(c)(2)(i)-1 and 19(e)(1)(i)-1. The creditor may obtain information regarding items to be disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii), for example, from the consumer, from a review of the purchase and sale contract, or from information obtained from a real estate agent in the transaction.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-5">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Proceeds from subordinate financing or other source.</title>
        <content>Funds that are provided to the consumer from the proceeds of subordinate financing, local or State housing assistance grants, or other similar sources are included in the amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii) on the first-lien transaction Loan Estimate.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-6">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-1-vii-Interp-6" marker="6.">
        <title>Reduction in amounts for adjustments.</title>
        <content>Adjustments that require additional funds from the consumer in a transaction disclosed using the formula under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(1) or pursuant to the real estate purchase and sale contract, such as for additional personal property that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure under § 1026.38(j)(1)(iii) or adjustments that will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure under § 1026.38(j)(1)(v), are only included in the amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii) if such amounts are not included in the calculation under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(2) or (B) or § 1026.37(h)(1)(v) as debt being satisfied in the transaction. Other examples of adjustments for additional funds from the consumer include payoffs of secured or unsecured debt in a purchase transaction disclosed using the formula under § 1026.37(h)(1)(iii)(A)(1) or prorations for property taxes and homeowner's association dues. The total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(1)(vii) is a sum of adjustments requiring additional funds from the consumer, calculated as positive amounts, and other credits, such as those provided for in comment 37(h)(1)(vii)-1, calculated as negative amounts.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-Interp" target="1026-37-h-2">
        <title>37(h)(2) Optional alternative calculating cash to close table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Optional use.</title>
          <content>The optional alternative disclosure of the calculating cash to close table in § 1026.37(h)(2) may only be provided by a creditor in a transaction without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing. In a purchase transaction, the optional alternative disclosure may be used for the simultaneous subordinate financing Loan Estimate only if the first-lien Closing Disclosure will record the entirety of the seller's transaction. The use of this alternative table for transactions without a seller or for simultaneous subordinate financing is optional, but creditors may only use this alternative estimated cash to close disclosure in conjunction with the alternative disclosure under § 1026.37(d)(2).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp" target="1026-37-h-2-iii">
        <title>37(h)(2)(iii) Payoffs and payments.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Examples.</title>
          <content>Examples of the amounts incorporated in the total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii) include, but are not limited to: Payoffs of existing liens secured by the property identified under § 1026.37(a)(6) such as existing mortgages, deeds of trust, judgments that have attached to the real property, mechanics' and materialmen's liens, and local, State and Federal tax liens; payments of unsecured outstanding debts of the consumer; construction costs associated with the transaction that the consumer will be obligated to pay in any transaction in which the creditor is otherwise permitted to use the alternative calculating cash to close table; and payments to other third parties for outstanding debts of the consumer, excluding settlement services, as required to be paid as a condition for the extension of credit. Amounts that will be paid with funds provided by the consumer, including partial payments, such as a portion of construction costs, or amounts that will be paid by third parties and will be disclosed on the Closing Disclosure under § 1026.38(t)(5)(vii)(B), are calculated as credits, using positive numbers, in the total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Disclosure of subordinate financing.</title>
          <content></content>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
            <title>First-lien Loan Estimate.</title>
            <content>On the Loan Estimate for a first-lien transaction disclosed with the optional alternative table pursuant to § 1026.37(h)(2), such as a refinance transaction that also has simultaneous subordinate financing, the proceeds of the simultaneous subordinate financing are included, as a positive number, in the total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii). The total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii) is a negative number unless the proceeds from the subordinate financing and any amounts entered as credits as discussed in comment 37(h)(2)(iii)-1 equal or exceed the total amount of other payoffs and payments that are included in the calculation under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii). If the proceeds from the subordinate financing and any amounts entered as credits as discussed in comment 37(h)(2)(iii)-1 equal or exceed the total amount of other payoffs and payments that are included in the calculation under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii), the total amount disclosed under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii) is disclosed as $0 or a positive number.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1026-37-h-2-iii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
            <title>Simultaneous subordinate financing Loan Estimate.</title>
            <content>On the simultaneous subordinate financing Loan Estimate disclosed with the optional alternative table pursuant to § 1026.37(h)(2), the proceeds of the subordinate financing that will be applied to the first-lien transaction may be included in the payoffs and payments disclosure under § 1026.37(h)(2)(iii).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-k-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-k-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Contact.</title>
        <content>Section 1026.37(k)(2) requires the disclosure of the name and NMLSR ID of the person who is the primary contact for the consumer, labeled “Loan Officer.” The loan officer is generally the natural person employed by the creditor or mortgage broker disclosed under § 1026.37(k)(1) who interacts most frequently with the consumer and who has an NMLSR ID or, if none, a license number or other unique identifier to be disclosed under § 1026.37(k)(2), as applicable.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-l-1-i-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-l-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Calculation of total payments in five years.</title>
        <content>The amount disclosed under § 1026.37(l)(1)(i) is the sum of principal, interest, mortgage insurance, and loan costs scheduled to be paid through the end of the 60th month after the due date of the first periodic payment. For guidance on how to calculate interest for mortgage loans that are Adjustable Rate products under § 1026.37(a)(10)(i)(A) for purposes of § 1026.37(l)(1)(i), see comment 17(c)(1)-10. In addition, for purposes of § 1026.37(l)(1)(i), the creditor should assume that the consumer makes payments as scheduled and on time. For purposes of § 1026.37(l)(1)(i), mortgage insurance means “mortgage insurance or any functional equivalent” as defined under comment 37(c)(1)(i)(C)-1 and includes prepaid or escrowed mortgage insurance. Loan costs are those costs disclosed under § 1026.37(f).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-l-3-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-l-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>General.</title>
        <content>When calculating the total interest percentage, the creditor assumes that the consumer will make each payment in full and on time and will not make any additional payments. The creditor includes prepaid interest that the consumer will pay when calculating the total interest percentage. Prepaid interest that is disclosed as a negative number under §§ 1026.37(g)(2) or 1026.38(g)(2) is included as a negative value when calculating the total interest percentage.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-o-4-i-A-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-o-4-i-A-Interp" target="1026-37-o-4-i-A">
        <title>Paragraph 37(o)(4)(i)(A).</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-o-4-i-A-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Rounding dollar amounts.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.37(o)(4)(i)(A) requires that certain dollar amounts be rounded to the nearest whole dollar. For example, under § 1026.37(o)(4)(i)(A), periodic mortgage insurance payments are rounded and disclosed to the nearest dollar, such that a periodic mortgage insurance payment of $164.50 is disclosed under § 1026.37(c)(2)(ii) as $165, but a periodic mortgage insurance payment of $164.49 is disclosed as $164. The per-diem amount disclosed under § 1026.37(g)(2)(iii) and the monthly amounts for the initial escrow payment at closing disclosed pursuant to § 1026.37(g)(3)(i) through (iii) and (v) do not include partial cents. Dollar amounts are rounded or truncated to the nearest whole cent. For example, under § 1026.37(g)(2)(iii), the creditor discloses per-diem interest of $68.1254 as $68.13 or $68.12. See form H-24(B) in appendix H to this part for an illustration of per-diem amounts for homeowner's insurance disclosed pursuant to § 1026.37(g)(3)(i).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1026-37-o-4-ii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1026-37-o-4-ii-Interp" target="1026-37-o-4-ii">
        <title>37(o)(4)(ii) Percentages.</title>
        <content></content>
        <interpParagraph label="1026-37-o-4-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Decimal places.</title>
          <content>Section 1026.37(o)(4)(ii) requires the percentage amounts disclosed rounding exact amounts to three decimal places, but the creditor does not disclose trailing zeros to the right of the decimal point. For example, a 2.4999 percent annual percentage rate is disclosed as “2.5%” under § 1026.37(o)(4)(ii). Similarly, a 7.005 percent annual percentage rate is disclosed as “7.005%,” and a 7.000 percent annual percentage rate is disclosed as “7%.”</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
