<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<regulation xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2011-07-22</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>ALTERNATIVE MORTGAGE TRANSACTION PARITY</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>D</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1004</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2011-18676</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2011-07-22</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2011/07/22/2011-18676/alternative-mortgage-transaction-parity-regulation-d</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <part label="1004">
    <tableOfContents>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-1">
        <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-2">
        <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-3">
        <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocSecEntry target="1004-4">
        <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
        <sectionSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</sectionSubject>
      </tocSecEntry>
      <tocAppEntry target="1004-A">
        <appendixLetter>A</appendixLetter>
        <appendixSubject>Appendix A to Part 1004—Official Commentary on Regulation D</appendixSubject>
      </tocAppEntry>
    </tableOfContents>
    <content>
      <subpart label="1004-Subpart">
        <tableOfContents label="1004-Subpart-TOC">
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-1">
            <sectionNum>1</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-2">
            <sectionNum>2</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-3">
            <sectionNum>3</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
          <tocSecEntry target="1004-4">
            <sectionNum>4</sectionNum>
            <sectionSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</sectionSubject>
          </tocSecEntry>
        </tableOfContents>
        <content>
          <section label="1004-1" sectionNum="1">
            <subject>§ 1004.1 Authority, purpose, and scope.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-a" marker="(a)">
              <title type="keyterm">Authority.</title>
              <content>Authority. This regulation, known as Regulation D, is issued by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection to implement the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act, <ref target="USC:12-3801" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3801</ref> et seq., as amended by title X, Section 1083 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (Pub. L. 111-203, <ref target="STATUTES_AT_LARGE:124-Stat.-1376" reftype="external">124 Stat. 1376</ref>). Section <ref target="1004-4" reftype="internal">1004.4</ref> is issued pursuant to the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act (as amended) and the Truth in Lending Act, <ref target="USC:15-1601" reftype="external">15 U.S.C. 1601</ref> et seq.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-b" marker="(b)">
              <title type="keyterm">Purpose.</title>
              <content>Purpose. Consistent with the Alternative Mortgage Transaction Parity Act, the Truth in Lending Act, and the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act, the purpose of this regulation is to balance access to responsible credit and enhanced parity between <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> and federal <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> regarding the making, purchase, and enforcement of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> with consumer protection and the interests of the <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">States</ref> in regulating mortgage transactions generally.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-1-c" marker="(c)">
              <title type="keyterm">Scope.</title>
              <content>Scope. This regulation applies to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> received an application for that transaction on or after July 22, 2011. This regulation does not apply to a transaction if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> received the application for that transaction before July 22, 2011.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-2" sectionNum="2">
            <subject>§ 1004.2 Definitions.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-def0" marker="">
              <content>For purposes of this part:</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-a" marker="(a)">
              <content><def term="alternative mortgage transaction">Alternative mortgage transaction</def> means a loan, credit sale, or account:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>That is secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not that structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, or trailer, if it is used as a residence;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>That is made primarily for personal, family, or household purposes; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-a-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>In which the interest rate or finance charge may be adjusted or renegotiated.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-b" marker="(b)">
              <content><def term="creditor">Creditor</def> shall have the same meaning as in <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-c" marker="(c)">
              <content><def term="housing creditor">Housing creditor</def> means:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>A depository institution, as defined in section 501(a)(2) of the Depository Institutions Deregulation and Monetary Control Act of 1980;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>A lender approved by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for participation in any mortgage insurance program under the National Housing Act;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>Any person who regularly makes loans, credit sales, or advances on an account secured by an interest in a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not the structure is attached to real property, including an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, or trailer, if it is used as a residence; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-2-c-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Any transferee of a party listed in paragraph <ref target="1004-2-c-1" reftype="internal">(c)(1)</ref>, <ref target="1004-2-c-2" reftype="internal">(2)</ref>, or <ref target="1004-2-c-3" reftype="internal">(3)</ref> of this section.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-d" marker="(d)">
              <content><def term="state">State</def> means any State of the United States of America, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands, American Samoa, Guam, and any other territory or possession of the United States.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-2-e" marker="(e)">
              <content><def term="state law">State law</def> means a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> constitution, statute, or regulation or any provision thereof.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-3" sectionNum="3">
            <subject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State law.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-3-p1" marker="">
              <content>Pursuant to 12 U.S.C. 3803, a State-chartered or -licensed housing creditor may make, purchase, and enforce alternative mortgage transactions in accordance with § 1004.4(a) through (c) of this part (as applicable), notwithstanding any provision of State law that restricts the ability of the housing creditor to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to the transaction or to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in a regular periodic payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section label="1004-4" sectionNum="4">
            <subject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for alternative mortgage transactions.</subject>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-a" marker="(a)">
              <title type="keyterm">Mortgages with adjustable rates or finance charges and home equity lines of credit.</title>
              <content>Mortgages with adjustable rates or finance charges and home equity lines of credit. A <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that makes an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> with an adjustable rate or finance charge may only increase the interest rate or finance charge as follows:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-a-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If the transaction is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b, the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b(f)(1).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>For all other transactions, the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must use either:</content>
                <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2-i" marker="(i)">
                  <content>An index to which changes in the interest rate are tied that is readily available to and verifiable by the borrower and beyond the control of the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>; or</content>
                </paragraph>
                <paragraph label="1004-4-a-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
                  <content>A formula or schedule identifying the amount that the interest rate or finance charge may increase and the times at which, or circumstances under which, a change may be made.</content>
                </paragraph>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-b" marker="(b)">
              <title type="keyterm">Renegotiable rates for renewable balloon-payment mortgages.</title>
              <content>Renegotiable rates for renewable balloon-payment mortgages. A <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> that makes an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> with payments based on an amortization period and a large final payment due after a shorter term may negotiate an increase or decrease in the interest rate when the transaction is renewed only if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes a written commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period. However, the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is not required to renew the transaction if:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>Any action or inaction by the consumer materially and adversely affects the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s security for the transaction or any right of the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> in such security;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>There is a material failure by the consumer to meet the repayment terms of the transaction;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>There is fraud or a willful or knowing material misrepresentation by the consumer in connection with the transaction; or</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-b-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Federal law dealing with credit extended by a depository institution to its executive officers specifically requires that as a condition of the extension the credit shall become due and payable on demand, provided that the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> includes such a provision in the initial agreement.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-c" marker="(c)">
              <title type="keyterm">Requirements for high-cost and higher-priced mortgage loans.</title>
              <content>Requirements for high-cost and higher-priced mortgage loans.</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-c-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>If an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>, the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref> and <ref target="CFR:12-226-34" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.34</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-4-c-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>If an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> is subject to <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>, the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-d" marker="(d)">
              <title type="keyterm">Other applicable law.</title>
              <content>Other applicable law. Notwithstanding paragraphs <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> of this section, a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> that is not making an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> pursuant to § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> of this part may make that transaction consistent with applicable <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> or Federal law other than this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-4-e" marker="(e)">
              <title type="keyterm">Reductions in interest rate or finance charge.</title>
              <content>Reductions in interest rate or finance charge. Nothing in this section prohibits a <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> from decreasing the interest rate or finance charge on an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
        </content>
      </subpart>
      <appendix appendixLetter="A" label="1004-A">
        <appendixTitle>Appendix A to Part 1004—Official Commentary on Regulation D</appendixTitle>
        <tableOfContents>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h1">
            <appendixLetter>h1</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.1 Authority, Purpose, and Scope</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h3">
            <appendixLetter>h3</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.2 Definitions</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h6">
            <appendixLetter>h6</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State Law</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
          <tocAppEntry target="1004-A-h7">
            <appendixLetter>h7</appendixLetter>
            <appendixSubject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for Alternative Mortgage Transactions</appendixSubject>
          </tocAppEntry>
        </tableOfContents>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="1" label="1004-A-h1">
          <subject>§ 1004.1 Authority, Purpose, and Scope</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2" marker="">
            <title>1(c) Scope.</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Application received before July 22, 2011.</title>
              <content>Application received before July 22, 2011. This Part does not apply to a transaction if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> received the application for that transaction before July 22, 2011, even if the transaction was consummated or completed on or after July 22, 2011. Whether <ref target="USC:12-3803" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3803</ref>(c) preempts <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> with respect to such a transaction depends on whether: (1) The transaction was an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> as defined by the version of <ref target="USC:12-3802" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3802</ref>(1) in effect at the time of application; and (2) the <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> complied with applicable federal regulations issued by the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, the National Credit Union Administration, the Office of Thrift Supervision, or the Federal Home Loan Bank Board in effect at the time of application.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Subsequent modifications and other actions.</title>
              <content>Subsequent modifications and other actions. If applicable regulations under <ref target="USC:12-3803" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 3803</ref>(c) (including this Part) preempted <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> with respect to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> at the time the application was received, the following actions with respect to that transaction are entitled to the same degree of preemption under such regulations:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>The subsequent consummation, completion, purchase, or enforcement of the transaction by a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h1-h2-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>The subsequent modification, renewal, or extension of the transaction. However, if such a transaction is satisfied and replaced by another transaction, the second transaction must independently meet the requirements for preemption in effect at the time the application for the second transaction was received.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="2" label="1004-A-h3">
          <subject>§ 1004.2 Definitions</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4" marker="">
            <title>2(a) Alternative Mortgage Transaction</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Alternative mortgage transaction.</title>
              <content><ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">Alternative mortgage transaction</ref>. For purposes of this Part, an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> that meets the definition in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> includes any consumer credit transaction that is secured by a mortgage, deed of trust, or other equivalent consensual security interest in a dwelling or in residential real property that includes a dwelling. The dwelling need not be the primary dwelling of the consumer. Home equity lines of credit and subordinate lien mortgages are <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> for purposes of this Part to the extent they meet the definition in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Examples of alternative mortgage transactions.</title>
              <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>. Examples of <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> include:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>Transactions in which the interest rate changes in accordance with fluctuations in an index.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>Transactions in which the interest rate or finance charge may be increased or decreased after a specified period of time or under specified circumstances.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>Balloon transactions in which payments are based on an amortization schedule and a large final payment is due after a shorter term, where the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> makes a commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period, but the interest rate may be renegotiated at renewal. For example, a fixed-rate mortgage loan with a 30-year amortization period but a balloon payment due five years after consummation is an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> under § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> commits to renew the mortgage at five-year intervals for the entire 30-year amortization period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-iv" marker="iv.">
                <content>Transactions in which the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and the consumer agree to share some or all of the appreciation in the value of the property (shared equity/shared appreciation).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-2-p1" marker="">
                <content>However, this Part preempts <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> only to the extent provided in § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> and only to the extent that the requirements of § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> (as applicable) are met.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Examples of transactions that are not alternative mortgage transactions.</title>
              <content>Examples of transactions that are not <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>. The following are examples of transactions that are not <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>:</content>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-i" marker="i.">
                <content>Transactions with a fixed interest rate where one or more of the regular periodic payments may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>Balloon transactions with a fixed interest rate where payments are based on an amortization schedule and a large final payment is due after a shorter term, where the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> does not make a commitment to renew the transaction at specified intervals throughout the amortization period.</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h4-3-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>Transactions with a fixed interest rate where one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature).</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h5" marker="">
            <title>2(b) Creditor</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h3-h5-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Creditor.</title>
              <content><ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">Creditor</ref>. As defined in <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>, “<ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>” includes federally and <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-chartered banks, thrifts, and credit unions, as well as non-depository institutions, such as <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-licensed lenders. The Official Staff Commentary to <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref> contains additional guidance on the definition of the term “<ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>.” See <ref target="CFR:12-226-2" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.2</ref>, Supp. I.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="3" label="1004-A-h6">
          <subject>§ 1004.3 Preemption of State Law</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Scope of State laws.</title>
            <content>Scope of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref>. Regardless of whether a <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or applies to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions, that law is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> only to the extent that it restricts the ability of a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref>-chartered or -licensed <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> to adjust or renegotiate an interest rate or finance charge with respect to an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> or to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in a regular periodic payment as a result of such an adjustment or renegotiation.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Examples of State laws that are preempted.</title>
            <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are preempted. The following are examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref>:</content>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Restrictions on the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge, including restrictions on the circumstances under which a rate or charge may be adjusted, the method by which a rate or charge may be adjusted, and the amount of the adjustment to the rate or charge. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditors</ref> from increasing an adjustable rate more than two percentage points or from increasing an adjustable rate more than once during a year, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> with respect to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> that comply with § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref>, as applicable. Similarly, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from renewing balloon transactions that meet the definition of an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref> in § <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="internal">1004.2(a)</ref> on different terms, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> only to the extent that it restricts a <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">state</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>'s ability to adjust or renegotiate the interest rate or finance charge at renewal. See also comment 1004.3-3.i.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Restrictions on the ability of a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> to change the amount of interest or finance charges included in regular periodic payments as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate or finance charge. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> prohibits <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from increasing payments or limits the amount of such increases with respect to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> to the extent that it restricts a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref>'s ability to adjust payments as a result of the adjustment or renegotiation of an interest rate on an <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>. Other restrictions on changes to payments are not preempted, including restrictions on transactions in which one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature) or may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Restrictions on the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> and the consumer sharing some or all of the appreciation in the value of the property (shared equity/shared appreciation).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-2-iv" marker="iv.">
              <content>Underwriting requirements that address the adjustment or renegotiation of interest rates or finance charges. For example, if a provision of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> requires <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> to underwrite based on the maximum contractual rate, that provision is preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> with respect to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref>, regardless of whether the provision applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3" marker="3.">
            <title type="keyterm">Examples of State laws that are not preempted.</title>
            <content>Examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are not preempted. The following are examples of <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> that are not preempted by § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> regardless of whether the provision applies solely to <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> or to both <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> and other mortgage or consumer credit transactions:</content>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Restrictions on prepayment penalties or late charges (including an increase in an interest rate or finance charge as a result of a late payment).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Restrictions on transactions in which one or more of the regular periodic payments may result in an increase in the principal balance (a negative amortization feature) or may be applied solely to accrued interest and not to loan principal (an interest-only feature).</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h6-3-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>Requirements that disclosures be provided.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
        <appendixSection appendixSecNum="4" label="1004-A-h7">
          <subject>§ 1004.4 Requirements for Alternative Mortgage Transactions</subject>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8" marker="">
            <title>4(a) Mortgages With Adjustable or Renegotiable Rates or Finance Charges and Home Equity Lines of Credit</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Index values.</title>
              <content>Index values. A <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may use any measure of index values that meets the requirements in § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>. For example, the index may be either single values as of a specific date or an average of values calculated over a specified period.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-2" marker="2.">
              <title type="keyterm">Index beyond creditor's control.</title>
              <content>Index beyond <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s control. A <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> may increase an adjustable interest rate pursuant to § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref> only if the increase is based on an index that is beyond the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s control. For purposes of § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>, an index is not beyond the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s control if the index is the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s own prime rate or cost of funds. A <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref> is permitted, however, to use a published prime rate, such as the prime rate published in the Wall Street Journal, even if the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>'s own prime rate is one of several rates used to establish the published rate.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h8-3" marker="3.">
              <title type="keyterm">Publicly available.</title>
              <content>Publicly available. For purposes of § <ref target="1004-4-a-2-i" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)(2)(i)</ref>, the index must be available to the public. A publicly available index need not be published in a newspaper, but it must be one the consumer can independently obtain (by telephone, for example) and use to verify the annual percentage rate applied to the <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transaction</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h9" marker="">
            <title>4(c) Requirements for High-Cost and Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h9-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Prepayment penalties.</title>
              <content>Prepayment penalties. If applicable, <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditors</ref> must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>, including <ref target="CFR:12-226-32" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.32</ref>(d)(6) and (d)(7) which provide limitations on prepayment penalties. Similarly, if applicable, <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditors</ref> must comply with <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>, including <ref target="CFR:12-226-35" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.35</ref>(b)(2), which also provides limitations on prepayment penalties. However, under § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref>, <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> regarding prepayment penalties are not preempted. See comment 1004.3-3.i. Accordingly, <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditors</ref> must also comply with any <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State laws</ref> regarding prepayment penalties unless an independent basis for preemption exists, such as because the <ref target="1004-2-e" reftype="term">State law</ref> is inconsistent with the requirements of Regulation Z, 12 CFR Part 226. See <ref target="CFR:12-226-28" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.28</ref>.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h10" marker="">
            <title>4(d) Other Applicable Law</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1004-A-h7-h10-1" marker="1.">
              <title type="keyterm">Other applicable law.</title>
              <content>Other applicable law. Section <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> permits <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">state</ref> <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> that do not seek preemption under § <ref target="1004-3" reftype="internal">1004.3</ref> and federal <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> to make <ref target="1004-2-a" reftype="term">alternative mortgage transactions</ref> consistent with applicable <ref target="1004-2-d" reftype="term">State</ref> or federal law other than § <ref target="1004-4-a" reftype="internal">1004.4(a)</ref> through <ref target="1004-4-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref>. However, § <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> does not exempt those <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditors</ref> from complying with the provisions of federal law that are incorporated by reference in § <ref target="1004-4" reftype="internal">1004.4</ref> and are otherwise applicable to the <ref target="1004-2-b" reftype="term">creditor</ref>. Specifically, nothing in § <ref target="1004-4-d" reftype="internal">1004.4(d)</ref> exempts a <ref target="1004-2-c" reftype="term">housing creditor</ref> from complying with <ref target="CFR:12-226-5" reftype="external">12 CFR 226.5</ref>b, 226.32, 226.34, or 226.35.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </appendixSection>
      </appendix>
    </content>
  </part>
</regulation>
