<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2016-11-22</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>ELECTRONIC FUND TRANSFERS</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>E</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1005</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-24503_20181001</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2018-10-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/11/22/2016-24503/prepaid-accounts-under-the-electronic-fund-transfer-act-regulation-e-and-the-truth-in-lending-act</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2016-24503_20171001" rightDocumentNumber="2016-24503_20181001">

    <change operation="modified" label="1005-19-b">
      <paragraph label="1005-19-b" marker="(b)">
        <title type="keyterm">Submission of agreements to the Bureau</title>
        <content>—</content>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Submissions on a rolling basis.</title>
          <content>An <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must make submissions of <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreements</ref> to the Bureau on a rolling basis, in the form and manner specified by the Bureau. Rolling submissions must be sent to the Bureau no later than 30 days after an <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> <ref target="1005-19-a-5" reftype="term">offers</ref>, <ref target="1005-19-a-2" reftype="term">amends</ref>, or ceases to offer any <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> as described in paragraphs <ref target="1005-19-b-1-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(1)(ii)</ref> through <ref target="1005-19-b-1-iv" reftype="internal">(iv)</ref> of this section. Each submission must contain:</content>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Identifying information about the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> and the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreements</ref> submitted, including the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref>'s name, address, and identifying number (such as an RSSD ID number or tax identification number), the effective date of the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref>, the name of the program manager, if any, and the names of other relevant parties, if applicable (such as the employer for a payroll card program or the agency for a government benefit program);</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>Any <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> offered by the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> that has not been previously submitted to the Bureau;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <content>Any <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> previously submitted to the Bureau that has been amended, as described in paragraph <ref target="1005-19-b-2" reftype="internal">(b)(2)</ref> of this section; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-1-iv" marker="(iv)">
            <content>Notification regarding any <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> previously submitted to the Bureau that the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is withdrawing, as described in paragraphs <ref target="1005-19-b-3" reftype="internal">(b)(3)</ref>, <ref target="1005-19-b-4-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(4)(ii)</ref>, and <ref target="1005-19-b-5-ii" reftype="internal">(b)(5)(ii)</ref> of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Amended agreements.</title>
          <content>If a <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> previously submitted to the Bureau is amended, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must submit the entire amended <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> to the Bureau, in the form and manner specified by the Bureau, no later than 30 days after the change comes effective.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-3" marker="(3)">
          <title type="keyterm">Withdrawal of agreements no longer offered.</title>
          <content>If an <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> no longer <ref target="1005-19-a-5" reftype="term">offers</ref> a <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> that was previously submitted to the Bureau, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must notify the Bureau, in the form and manner specified by the Bureau, no later than 30 days after the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> ceases to offer the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, that it is withdrawing the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-4" marker="(4)">
          <title type="keyterm">De minimis exception.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-4-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>An <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is not required to submit any <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreements</ref> to the Bureau if the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> has fewer than 3,000 <ref target="1005-19-a-7" reftype="term">open prepaid accounts</ref>. If the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> has 3,000 or more <ref target="1005-19-a-7" reftype="term">open prepaid accounts</ref> as of the last day of the calendar quarter, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must submit to the Bureau its <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreements</ref> no later than 30 days after the last day of that calendar quarter.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>If an <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> that did not previously qualify for the de minimis exception newly qualifies for the de minimis exception, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must continue to make submissions to the Bureau on a rolling basis until the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> notifies the Bureau that the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is withdrawing all <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreements</ref> it previously submitted to the Bureau.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5" marker="(5)">
          <title type="keyterm">Product testing exception.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>An <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is not required to submit a <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> to the Bureau if the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> meets the criteria set forth in paragraphs <ref target="1005-19-b-5-i-A" reftype="internal">(b)(5)(i)(A)</ref> through <ref target="1005-19-b-5-i-C" reftype="internal">(C)</ref> of this section. If the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> fails to meet the criteria set forth in paragraphs <ref target="1005-19-b-5-i-A" reftype="internal">(b)(5)(i)(A)</ref> through <ref target="1005-19-b-5-i-C" reftype="internal">(C)</ref> of this section as of the last day of the calendar quarter, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must submit to the Bureau that <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> no later than 30 days after the last day of that calendar quarter. An <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> qualifies for the product testing exception if the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>:</content>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Is offered as part of a product test offered to only a limited group of <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumers</ref> for a limited period of time;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Is used for fewer than 3,000 <ref target="1005-19-a-7" reftype="term">open prepaid accounts</ref>; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5-i-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>Is not offered other than in connection with such a product test.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-5-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>If an <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> that did not previously qualify for the product testing exception newly qualifies for the exception, the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> must continue to make submissions to the Bureau on a rolling basis with respect to that <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> until the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> notifies the Bureau that the <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> is withdrawing the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6" marker="(6)">
          <title type="keyterm">Form and content of agreements submitted to the Bureau—</title>
          <content>—</content>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i" marker="(i)">
            <title type="keyterm">Form and content generally.</title>
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Each <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> must contain the provisions of the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> and the <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref> currently in effect.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content><ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">Agreements</ref> must not include any personally identifiable information relating to any <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref>, such as name, address, telephone number, or <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">account</ref> number.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>The following are not deemed to be part of the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> for purposes of this section, and therefore are not required to be included in submissions to the Bureau:</content>
              <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-C-1" marker="(1)">
                <content>Ancillary disclosures required by <ref target="1005-2-l" reftype="term">state</ref> or Federal law, such as affiliate marketing notices, privacy policies, or disclosures under the E-Sign Act;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-C-2" marker="(2)">
                <content>Solicitation or marketing materials;</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-C-3" marker="(3)">
                <content>Periodic statements; and</content>
              </paragraph>
              <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-C-4" marker="(4)">
                <content>Documents that may be sent to the <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref> along with the <ref target="1005-19-a-8" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> or <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> such as a cover letter, a validation sticker on the card, or other information about card security.</content>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-i-D" marker="(D)">
              <content><ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">Agreements</ref> must be presented in a clear and legible font.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Fee information.</title>
            <content><ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">Fee information</ref> must be set forth either in the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">prepaid account agreement</ref> or in a single addendum to that <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>. The <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> or addendum thereto must contain all of the <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref>, as defined by paragraph <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="internal">(a)(3)</ref> of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1005-19-b-6-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <title type="keyterm">Integrated agreement.</title>
            <content>An <ref target="1005-19-a-4" reftype="term">issuer</ref> may not provide provisions of the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref> or <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref> to the Bureau in the form of change-in-terms notices or riders (other than the optional <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref> addendum). Changes in provisions or <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref> must be integrated into the text of the <ref target="1005-19-a-1" reftype="term">agreement</ref>, or the optional <ref target="1005-19-a-3" reftype="term">fee information</ref> addendum, as appropriate.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1005-19-b-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-Interp">
        <title>19(b) Submission of Agreements to the Bureau</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-1-Interp">
          <title>19(b)(1) Submissions on a Rolling Basis</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Rolling submission requirement.</title>
            <content>Section 1005.19(b)(1) requires issuers to send submissions to the Bureau no later than 30 days after offering, amending, or ceasing to offer any <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreement, as described in § 1005.19(b)(1)(ii) through (iv). For example, if on July 1 an issuer offers a <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreement that has not been previously submitted to the Bureau, it must submit that agreement to the Bureau by July 31 of the same year. Similarly, if on August 1 an issuer amends a <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreement previously submitted to the Bureau, and the change becomes effective on September 15, the issuer must submit the entire amended agreement as required by § 1005.19(b)(2) by October 15 of the same year. Furthermore, if on December 31 an issuer ceases to offer a <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreement that was previously submitted to the Bureau, it must submit notification to the Bureau that it is withdrawing that agreement as required by § 1005.19(b)(3) by January 30 of the following year.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Prepaid accounts offered in conjunction with multiple issuers.</title>
            <content>If a program manager offers <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreements in conjunction with multiple issuers, each issuer must submit its own agreement to the Bureau. Alternatively, each issuer may use the program manager to submit the agreement on its behalf, in accordance with comment <ref target="1005-19-a-4-Interp-2" reftype="internal">19(a)(4)-2</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-2-Interp">
          <title>19(b)(2) Amended Agreements</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Change-in-terms notices not permissible.</title>
            <content>Section 1005.19(b)(2) requires that if an agreement previously submitted to the Bureau is amended, the issuer must submit the entire revised agreement to the Bureau. An issuer may not fulfill this requirement by submitting a change-in-terms or similar notice covering only the terms that have changed. Amendments must be integrated into the text of the agreement (or the optional addendum described in § 1005.19(b)(6)), not provided as separate riders.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-3-Interp">
          <title>19(b)(3) Withdrawal of Agreements No Longer Offered</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">No longer offers agreement.</title>
            <content>Section 1005.19(b)(3) provides that, if an issuer no longer offers an agreement that was previously submitted to the Bureau, the issuer must notify the Bureau no later than 30 days after the issuer ceases to offer the agreement that it is withdrawing the agreement. An issuer no longer offers an agreement when it no longer allows a <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to activate or register a new <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">account</ref> in connection with that agreement.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp">
          <title>19(b)(4) De Minimis Exception</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Relationship to other exceptions.</title>
            <content>The de minimis exception in § 1005.19(b)(4) is distinct from the product testing exception under § 1005.19(b)(5). The de minimis exception provides that an issuer with fewer than 3,000 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> is not required to submit any agreements to the Bureau, regardless of whether those agreements qualify for the product testing exception. In contrast, the product testing exception provides that an issuer is not required to submit to the Bureau agreements offered solely in connection with certain types of <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> programs with fewer than 3,000 open <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">accounts</ref>, regardless of the issuer's total number of open <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">accounts</ref>.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">De minimis exception.</title>
            <content>Under § 1005.19(b)(4), an issuer is not required to submit any <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> agreements to the Bureau under § 1005.19(b)(1) if the issuer has fewer than 3,000 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref>. For example, an issuer has 2,000 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref>. The issuer is not required to submit any agreements to the Bureau because the issuer qualifies for the de minimis exception.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp-3" marker="3.">
            <title type="keyterm">Date for determining whether issuer qualifies.</title>
            <content>Whether an issuer qualifies for the de minimis exception is determined as of the last day of each calendar quarter. For example, an issuer has 2,500 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> as of December 31, the last day of the calendar quarter. As of January 30, the issuer has 3,100 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref>. As of March 31, the last day of the following calendar quarter, the issuer has 2,700 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref>. Even though the issuer had 3,100 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> at one time during the calendar quarter, the issuer qualifies for the de minimis exception because the number of open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> was less than 3,000 as of March 31. The issuer therefore is not required to submit any agreements to the Bureau under § 1005.19(b)(1).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp-4" marker="4.">
            <title type="keyterm">Date for determining whether issuer ceases to qualify.</title>
            <content>Whether an issuer ceases to qualify for the de minimis exception under § le, an issuer has 2,500 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> as of June 30, the last day of the calendar quarter. The issuer is not required to submit any agreements to the Bureau under § 1005.19(b) by July 30 (the 30th day after June 30) because the issuer qualifies for the de minimis exception. As of July 15, the issuer has 3,100 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref>. The issuer is not required to take any action at this time, because whether an issuer qualifies for the de minimis exception under § 1005.19(b)(4) is determined as of the last day of the calendar quarter. The issuer still has 3,100 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> as of September 30. Because the issuer had 3,100 open <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid accounts</ref> as of September 30, the issuer ceases to qualify for the de minimis exception and must submit its agreements to the Bureau by October 30, the 30th day after the last day of the calendar quarter.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-4-Interp-5" marker="5.">
            <title type="keyterm">Option to withdraw agreements.</title>
            <content>Section 1005.19(b)(4) provides that if an issuer that did not previously qualify for the de minimis exception newly qualifies for the de minimis exception, the issuer must continue to make rolling submissions to the Bureau as required by § 1005.19(b)(1) until the issuer notifies the Bureau that the issuer is withdrawing all agreements it previously submitted to the Bureau. For example, an issuer offers three agreements and has 3,001 open <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">accounts</ref> as of December 31. The issuer submitted each of the three agreements to the Bureau by January 30 as required under § 1005.19(b). As of March 31, the issuer has only 2,999 open <ref target="1005-2-b-1" reftype="term">accounts</ref>. The issuer has two options. First, the issuer may notify the Bureau that the issuer is withdrawing each of the three agreements it previously submitted. Once the issuer has notified the Bureau, the issuer is no longer required to make rolling submissions to the Bureau under § 1005.19(b) unless it later ceases to qualify for the de minimis exception. Alternatively, the issuer may choose not to notify the Bureau that it is withdrawing its agreements. In this case, the issuer must continue making rolling submissions to the Bureau as required by § 1005.19(b). The issuer might choose not to withdraw its agreements if, for example, the issuer believes it will likely cease to qualify for the de minimis exception again in the near future.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-6-Interp">
          <title>19(b)(6) Form and Content of Agreements Submitted to the Bureau</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-6-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Agreements currently in effect.</title>
            <content>Agreements submitted to the Bureau must contain the provisions of the agreement and fee information currently in effect. For example, on June 1, an issuer decides to decrease the out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee associated with one of the agreements it offers. The change in that fee will become effective on August 1. The issuer must submit and post the amended agreement with the decreased out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee to the Bureau by August 31 as required by § 1005.19(b)(2) and (c).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-6-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Fee information variations do not constitute separate agreements.</title>
            <content>Fee information that may vary from one <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref> to another depending on the <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref>'s <ref target="1005-2-l" reftype="term">state</ref> of residence or other factors must be disclosed by setting forth all the possible variations. For example, an issuer offers a <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref> with a monthly fee of $4.95 or $0 if the <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref> regularly receives direct deposit to the <ref target="1005-2-b-3-i" reftype="term">prepaid account</ref>. The issuer must submit to the Bureau one agreement with fee information listing the possible monthly fees of $4.95 or $0 and including the explanation that the latter fee is dependent upon the <ref target="1005-2-e" reftype="term">consumer</ref> regularly receiving direct deposit.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1005-19-b-6-Interp-3" marker="3.">
            <title type="keyterm">Integrated agreement requirement.</title>
            <content>Issuers may not submit provisions of the agreement or fee information in the form of change-in-terms notices or riders. The only addendum that may be submitted as part of an agreement is the optional fee information addendum described in § 1005.19(b)(6)(ii). Changes in provisions or fee information must be integrated into the body of the agreement or the optional fee information addendum described in § 1005.19(b)(6)(ii). For example, it would be impermissible for an issuer to submit to the Bureau an agreement in the form of a terms and conditions document on January 1 and subsequently submit a change-in-terms notice or an addendum to indicate amendments to the previously submitted agreement. Instead, the issuer must submit a document that integrates the changes made by each of the change-in-terms notices into the body of the original terms and conditions document and a single optional addendum displaying variations in fee information.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>

  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-b" notice="2016-24503_20181001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(b) Submission of Agreements to the Bureau</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b) would have required each issuer to electronically submit to the Bureau prepaid account agreements offered by the issuer on a quarterly basis for the Bureau to post on its Web site pursuant to proposed § 1005.19(b)(7).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received many comments from consumer groups and industry on this portion of the proposal. Consumer groups generally supported the proposal, arguing that it would provide important consumer benefits and impose little burden on industry. On the other hand, industry commenters, including trade associations, issuing banks, credit unions, a payment network, and a law firm writing on behalf of a coalition of prepaid issuers, cited reasons for why they believed the proposal would be burdensome and unnecessary. Several of these commenters also argued that the submission requirement in proposed § 1005.19(b) should be suspended until the Bureau develops an automated, streamlined submission process and system. A few of these commenters stated that submitting agreements to the Bureau should be manageable, assuming the process is similar to the process for submitting credit card agreements to the Bureau pursuant to Regulation Z § 1026.58. Other commenters argued, however, that the submission process should not be compared to the submission process for credit card agreements because there are many more prepaid account agreements than credit card agreements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>For the reasons set forth herein, the Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b) with several modifications. The final rule also establishes a delayed effective date of October 1, 2018 for final § 1005.19(b), as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.19(f)(2) below. The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(1) with revisions to change the time period in which issuers must submit prepaid account agreements to the Bureau from a quarterly basis to a rolling basis and to clarify the information that each submission must contain. The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(2) and (3), regarding the submission requirements for amended and withdrawn agreements, substantially as proposed. The Bureau is also finalizing § 1005.19(b)(4) and (5), regarding the de minimis and product testing exceptions, with modifications to clarify that whether an issuer or agreement qualifies for either exception is determined as of the last day of the calendar quarter. Moreover, the Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(6), regarding the form and content requirements for submissions to the Bureau, generally as proposed. Finally, the Bureau is not adopting § 1005.19(b)(7) at this time, as discussed below. The Bureau notes that due to the change requiring submissions to be made on a rolling, rather than quarterly, basis, as well as other modifications the Bureau has made for this final rule, the Bureau believes that the Regulation Z § 1026.58 guidance referenced in a number of the proposed comments would no longer be particularly useful to prepaid account issuers and thus the Bureau has modified the comments accordingly to include examples specific to prepaid directly in the commentary text.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-b" notice="2016-24503_20171001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(b) Submission of Agreements to the Bureau</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b) would have required each issuer to electronically submit to the Bureau prepaid account agreements offered by the issuer on a quarterly basis for the Bureau to post on its Web site pursuant to proposed § 1005.19(b)(7).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received many comments from consumer groups and industry on this portion of the proposal. Consumer groups generally supported the proposal, arguing that it would provide important consumer benefits and impose little burden on industry. On the other hand, industry commenters, including trade associations, issuing banks, credit unions, a payment network, and a law firm writing on behalf of a coalition of prepaid issuers, cited reasons for why they believed the proposal would be burdensome and unnecessary. Several of these commenters also argued that the submission requirement in proposed § 1005.19(b) should be suspended until the Bureau develops an automated, streamlined submission process and system. A few of these commenters stated that submitting agreements to the Bureau should be manageable, assuming the process is similar to the process for submitting credit card agreements to the Bureau pursuant to Regulation Z § 1026.58. Other commenters argued, however, that the submission process should not be compared to the submission process for credit card agreements because there are many more prepaid account agreements than credit card agreements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>For the reasons set forth herein, the Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b) with several modifications. The final rule also establishes a delayed effective date of October 1, 2018 for final § 1005.19(b), as discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.19(f)(2) below. The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(1) with revisions to change the time period in which issuers must submit prepaid account agreements to the Bureau from a quarterly basis to a rolling basis and to clarify the information that each submission must contain. The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(2) and (3), regarding the submission requirements for amended and withdrawn agreements, substantially as proposed. The Bureau is also finalizing § 1005.19(b)(4) and (5), regarding the de minimis and product testing exceptions, with modifications to clarify that whether an issuer or agreement qualifies for either exception is determined as of the last day of the calendar quarter. Moreover, the Bureau is finalizing § 1005.19(b)(6), regarding the form and content requirements for submissions to the Bureau, generally as proposed. Finally, the Bureau is not adopting § 1005.19(b)(7) at this time, as discussed below. The Bureau notes that due to the change requiring submissions to be made on a rolling, rather than quarterly, basis, as well as other modifications the Bureau has made for this final rule, the Bureau believes that the Regulation Z § 1026.58 guidance referenced in a number of the proposed comments would no longer be particularly useful to prepaid account issuers and thus the Bureau has modified the comments accordingly to include examples specific to prepaid directly in the commentary text.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-a" notice="2016-24503_20181001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(a) Definitions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed in § 1005.19(a) certain definitions specific to proposed § 1005.19. The Bureau is largely finalizing § 1005.19(a) as proposed, with several modifications as discussed below.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-a" notice="2016-24503_20171001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(a) Definitions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed in § 1005.19(a) certain definitions specific to proposed § 1005.19. The Bureau is largely finalizing § 1005.19(a) as proposed, with several modifications as discussed below.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-18-b-2-viii-A" notice="2016-24503_20181001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>Statement Regarding the Number of Additional Fee Types Charged Required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) requires a statement disclosing the number of additional fee types the financial institution may charge consumers with respect to the prepaid account, using the following clause or a substantially similar clause: “We charge [x] other types of fees.” The number of additional fee types disclosed must reflect the total number of fee types under which the financial institution may charge fees, excluding fees required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges as described in final Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11) imposed in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in new § 1026.61.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) because it continues to believe, as explained in the proposal, that it is crucial to inform consumers that there may be a cost for features not otherwise captured in the short form disclosure. Disclosure of this information will help both alert consumers that the short form is not a comprehensive fee disclosure and encourage consumers to seek out more information about the prepaid account from the long form disclosure and other sources. As noted in the proposal, the Bureau's pre-proposal consumer testing revealed that participants often did not know all the fees that might be assessed prior to their purchase of a prepaid account. In addition, the Bureau's post-proposal consumer testing revealed that, while not all participants understood the significance of the disclosure of the number of additional fee types, participants were keenly interested in this disclosure, which the Bureau believes will motivate consumers to seek more information about these additional fee types.<footnote ref="400">ICF Report II at 11-12 and 22.</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau declines to use a more general statement to alert consumers that there may be additional fees, as requested by some industry commenters. The Bureau believes that disclosure of the specific number of additional fee types, as opposed to a general statement regarding other fees charged, provides consumers with concrete information and stronger motivation to both better inform themselves and to direct their searches for additional information. Moreover, as discussed below, the Bureau believes that focusing the disclosure on tallying the <em data-original="E-03">types</em> of fees rather than counting each variation in fees toward the total directly addresses industry's concerns that disclosing a specific number of other fees would prompt consumers to assign undue negative weight to the fact that a product may have many fee variations. The change to fee types also helps reduce compliance burden across the two related disclosures of the number of additional fee types required by this provision and the disclosure of additional fee types required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau disagrees with commenters that the comprehensive disclosure of all fees in another disclosure, such as the long form or the cardholder agreement, negates the rationale for disclosing the number of additional fee types in the short form. The Bureau believes that consumers generally would rely solely on the short form disclosure in making their acquisition decisions if they do not see language that specifically emphasizes the value of consulting the long form. The Bureau thus believes that listing the total number of fee types that are not otherwise listed on the short form will complement and enhance the statement in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(xiii) directing consumers to the long form, providing a concrete incentive to consult the longer disclosure for products that are more complex.<footnote ref="401">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report II at 12 and 22.</footnote>

             Specifically, the Bureau's post-proposal consumer testing revealed that, when asked how they could learn more about “other fees” not shown on the short form, practically all participants referred to the financial institution's telephone number and Web site disclosed on the prototype short form disclosure (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> the information sources required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(xiii)).<footnote ref="402">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
             In sum, the Bureau believes that the disclosure of the number of additional fee types in the short form pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) will directly inform consumers of important information and serve to spur them to further inquiry in other more detailed disclosures.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau acknowledges commenters' concerns that some consumers may tend to assume that a prepaid account with a relatively high number of additional fees is more expensive or less desirable than other accounts, even when the opposite may be true. In part to address this concern, the Bureau is finalizing the rule requiring financial institutions to disclose the total number of <em data-original="E-03">fee types,</em> rather than the total number of all <em data-original="E-03">fees</em> (including all fee variations within a fee type) that would have been required under the proposal. Requiring disclosure of the number of fee types instead of the number of discrete fees likely will reduce the number required to be disclosed for a typical prepaid account program. The Bureau believes that this modification for the final rule should help ameliorate the risk raised by some commenters that consumers will reject prepaid accounts with a high number of additional fees out of hand without seeking more detailed fee information to determine whether the products meet their needs. Moreover, the requirements for both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix) are based on fee types (as opposed to one being based on discrete fees and the other on fee types), thereby reducing the burden of developing and maintaining two separate counts to determine and disclose the elements under their respective rules. The Bureau is also providing a list of fee types and fee variations in final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2, discussed below—which are based on fees that the Bureau is aware exist in the current prepaid marketplace—that a financial institution may use when determining both the number of additional fee types charged pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and any additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau believes that these provisions will reduce the risks and burdens raised by commenters concerning the proposed disclosure of the total number of fees not otherwise listed, while still providing the consumer with an important signal and incentive to investigate prepaid accounts that have more complex pricing structures.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In addition, the Bureau believes that this modification addresses commenters' concerns, at least in part, regarding a potential chill to innovation of new features because such fee variations within a fee type will not be required to be separately counted for purposes of this disclosure. The Bureau intends to monitor compliance with this rule, including financial institutions' disclosures of the number of additional fee types charged, as well as market innovations in the prepaid industry more generally, and will consider additional action in future rulemakings if necessary.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Modifying the final rule to require disclosure of the number of fee types also addresses concerns raised by some commenters that the proposed disclosure would have included many fees that are not commonly incurred by consumers—including fees for discretionary features that require specific consumer action before they are incurred. For example, under the final rule, a financial institution would count bill payment as an additional fee type if it offered this feature, but, unlike the rule as proposed, would not count each of the discrete fee variations within bill payment such as ACH bill payment, paper check bill payment, check cancellation, and regular or expedited delivery of a paper check. Thus, in addition to a reduction in the overall number of additional fees required to be disclosed under the final rule, a financial institution would similarly not be required to disclose many of the less common fees and fees triggered by affirmative consumer action. While some of the additional fee types required to be disclosed in the final rule may still be less common or triggered only when a consumer elects to use an optional service, the Bureau reiterates that the primary objective of this provision is to alert consumers to fee information absent from the short form and to spur consumers to take action to gain a more fulsome understanding of the terms of a prospective prepaid account; this disclosure fulfils this objective.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below, the Bureau is adopting a de minimis threshold with respect to the disclosure of specific additional fee types. The Bureau does not believe a de minimis threshold would be appropriate for the disclosure required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) regarding the total number of additional fee types. The Bureau notes, however, that with the de minimis threshold in § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix), disclosure of such fee types under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) would not be required, although such fee types would be counted in the total number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau continues to believe it is not necessary to include in the final rule specific requirements for updating the statement regarding the number of additional fee types charged required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A). As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b) above, the Bureau does not believe that financial institutions change the fee schedules for prepaid accounts often, particularly those sold at retail. If a financial institution is making available a new optional service for all prepaid accounts in a particular prepaid account program, Regulation E provides a means for financial institutions to notify consumers of terms associated with a new EFT service that is added to a consumer's account, in § 1005.7(c). A financial institution may provide new consumer disclosures in accordance with § 1005.7(c) post-acquisition, without needing to pull and replace card packaging that does not reflect that new optional feature in the disclosure of the number of additional fee types pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A). The Bureau does expect, however, that financial institutions will keep their other disclosures up to date (including those provided electronically and orally, as well as disclosures provided in writing that are not a part of pre-printed packaging materials, such as those printed by a financial institution upon a consumer's request). The Bureau intends to monitor financial institutions' practices in this area, however, and may consider additional requirements in a future rulemaking if necessary.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1 clarifies what fee types to count in the total number of additional fee types, specifically excluding fees otherwise required to be disclosed in and outside the short form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges as described in final Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11) imposed in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in final § 1026.61. Excluding the static fees and fees required to be disclosed outside the short form avoids the duplicative counting of fees already disclosed to the consumer. As discussed in more detail below, the Bureau has made a strategic decision to focus the bulk of the short form disclosure on usage of the prepaid account itself rather than any charges related to overdraft credit features. The possibility that consumers may be offered an overdraft credit feature for use in connection with the prepaid account is addressed in the short form pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(x), which requires the following statement if such a feature may be offered: “You may be offered overdraft/credit after [x] days. Fees would apply.” Consistent with this overall decision, the Bureau believes that it is appropriate to exclude any finance charges related to an overdraft credit feature that may be offered at a later date to some prepaid consumers from the disclosures regarding additional fees under both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix). If consumers are interested in such a feature, they can look to the Regulation Z disclosures in the long form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(4)(vii), discussed below, for more details.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1.i explains that the number of additional fee types includes only fee types under which the financial institution may charge fees; accordingly, third-party fees are not included unless they are imposed for services performed on behalf of the financial institution. The comment additionally clarifies that the number of additional fee types includes only fee types the financial institution may charge consumers with respect to the prepaid account; accordingly, additional fee types does not include other revenue sources such as interchange fees or fees paid by employers for payroll card programs, government agencies for government benefit programs, or other entities sponsoring prepaid account programs for financial disbursements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1.ii explains that fee types that bear a relationship to, but are separate from, the static fees disclosed in the short form must be counted as additional fee types for purposes of final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii). The comment also provides a detailed explanation regarding the treatment of international ATM fees and fees for reloading funds into a prepaid account in a form other than cash (such as electronic reload and check reload). In addition, the comment explains that additional fee types disclosed in the short form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) must be counted in the total number of additional fee types. This is because the exclusions in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix)(A)(<em data-original="E-03">1</em>) and (<em data-original="E-03">2</em>) are only for fees required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges imposed on the prepaid account as described in Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11)(ii) in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in Regulation Z § 1026.61. Further, the statement required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) explains that the additional fee types disclosed are some of the total number of additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting new comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 to provide guidance regarding the calculation of the number of additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) as well as to address concerns raised by an industry commenter regarding how to categorize fees in determining the additional fee types to disclose under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment explains that the term fee type, as used in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix), is a general category under which a financial institution charges fees to consumers. A financial institution may charge only one fee within a particular fee type, or may charge two or more variations of fees within the same fee type. (The Bureau notes that an additional fee type for which a financial institution does not charge any fee to the consumer, including for any variations of the additional fee type, is not counted in the total number of additional fee types under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) nor required to be disclosed on the short form under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).) The comment goes on to provide a list of examples of fee types a financial institution may use when determining both the number of additional fee types charged pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and any additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment also explains that a financial institution may create an appropriate name for other additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau compiled the list of examples of fee types in new comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 to provide guidance to financial institutions and to help facilitate their categorization of additional fee types for satisfying the requirements in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and (ix). The list also may encourage standardization of this portion of the short form in that, although additional fee types disclosed will vary across short forms for different prepaid account programs, the Bureau believes financial institutions will generally use consistent nomenclature for additional fee types identified on the list. The Bureau compiled this list of examples of fee types based on particular fee types referenced in comments received on the proposal and by reviewing the packaging of and disclosures for scores of prepaid account programs.<footnote ref="403">As part of the Bureau's Study of Prepaid Account Agreements, Bureau staff found fee tables or other explanations of at least some of the fees charged for 278 of the 325 agreements reviewed. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; Study of Prepaid Account Agreements at 29 and note 49.</footnote>
             The Bureau balanced multiple considerations in compiling the list in final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 for purposes of both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix), including existing industry practices with regard to fee types, the accounting burdens associated with relatively narrower or broader definitions of fee types, and the potential benefits to both industry and consumers in using narrower definitions of fee types to communicate information about specific account features and fees. The Bureau believes the resulting list strikes an appropriate balance by capturing categories and terms employed by the prepaid industry itself that will be useful to financial institutions and consumers in determining and understanding additional fee types. The Bureau is providing flexibility to financial institutions to fashion appropriate names for other fee types, including fee types for services that do not yet exist in the prepaid marketplace.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-3 clarifies that, pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(vi), a financial institution using the multiple service plan short form disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(6)(iii)(B)(<em data-original="E-03">2</em>) must disclose only the fee for calling customer service via a live agent. Thus, pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii), any charge for calling customer service via an interactive voice response system must be counted in the total number of additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-4 clarifies that a financial institution must use the same categorization of fee types in the number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and in its determination of which additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau is including this comment on consistency to make clear that a financial institution is not permitted to, for example, shorten its list of fee types into a few broad categories (in order to minimize the number of additional fee types required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)) but use a more detailed list of fee types broken out into a greater number of categories when assessing its obligations under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) (in order to maximize the number of fee types that may fall below the de minimis threshold pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix)(A)(<em data-original="E-03">2</em>)).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-18-b-2-viii-A" notice="2016-24503_20171001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>Statement Regarding the Number of Additional Fee Types Charged Required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) requires a statement disclosing the number of additional fee types the financial institution may charge consumers with respect to the prepaid account, using the following clause or a substantially similar clause: “We charge [x] other types of fees.” The number of additional fee types disclosed must reflect the total number of fee types under which the financial institution may charge fees, excluding fees required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges as described in final Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11) imposed in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in new § 1026.61.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) because it continues to believe, as explained in the proposal, that it is crucial to inform consumers that there may be a cost for features not otherwise captured in the short form disclosure. Disclosure of this information will help both alert consumers that the short form is not a comprehensive fee disclosure and encourage consumers to seek out more information about the prepaid account from the long form disclosure and other sources. As noted in the proposal, the Bureau's pre-proposal consumer testing revealed that participants often did not know all the fees that might be assessed prior to their purchase of a prepaid account. In addition, the Bureau's post-proposal consumer testing revealed that, while not all participants understood the significance of the disclosure of the number of additional fee types, participants were keenly interested in this disclosure, which the Bureau believes will motivate consumers to seek more information about these additional fee types.<footnote ref="400">ICF Report II at 11-12 and 22.</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau declines to use a more general statement to alert consumers that there may be additional fees, as requested by some industry commenters. The Bureau believes that disclosure of the specific number of additional fee types, as opposed to a general statement regarding other fees charged, provides consumers with concrete information and stronger motivation to both better inform themselves and to direct their searches for additional information. Moreover, as discussed below, the Bureau believes that focusing the disclosure on tallying the <em data-original="E-03">types</em> of fees rather than counting each variation in fees toward the total directly addresses industry's concerns that disclosing a specific number of other fees would prompt consumers to assign undue negative weight to the fact that a product may have many fee variations. The change to fee types also helps reduce compliance burden across the two related disclosures of the number of additional fee types required by this provision and the disclosure of additional fee types required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau disagrees with commenters that the comprehensive disclosure of all fees in another disclosure, such as the long form or the cardholder agreement, negates the rationale for disclosing the number of additional fee types in the short form. The Bureau believes that consumers generally would rely solely on the short form disclosure in making their acquisition decisions if they do not see language that specifically emphasizes the value of consulting the long form. The Bureau thus believes that listing the total number of fee types that are not otherwise listed on the short form will complement and enhance the statement in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(xiii) directing consumers to the long form, providing a concrete incentive to consult the longer disclosure for products that are more complex.<footnote ref="401">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report II at 12 and 22.</footnote>

             Specifically, the Bureau's post-proposal consumer testing revealed that, when asked how they could learn more about “other fees” not shown on the short form, practically all participants referred to the financial institution's telephone number and Web site disclosed on the prototype short form disclosure (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> the information sources required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(xiii)).<footnote ref="402">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;Id.&lt;/em&gt;</footnote>
             In sum, the Bureau believes that the disclosure of the number of additional fee types in the short form pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) will directly inform consumers of important information and serve to spur them to further inquiry in other more detailed disclosures.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau acknowledges commenters' concerns that some consumers may tend to assume that a prepaid account with a relatively high number of additional fees is more expensive or less desirable than other accounts, even when the opposite may be true. In part to address this concern, the Bureau is finalizing the rule requiring financial institutions to disclose the total number of <em data-original="E-03">fee types,</em> rather than the total number of all <em data-original="E-03">fees</em> (including all fee variations within a fee type) that would have been required under the proposal. Requiring disclosure of the number of fee types instead of the number of discrete fees likely will reduce the number required to be disclosed for a typical prepaid account program. The Bureau believes that this modification for the final rule should help ameliorate the risk raised by some commenters that consumers will reject prepaid accounts with a high number of additional fees out of hand without seeking more detailed fee information to determine whether the products meet their needs. Moreover, the requirements for both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix) are based on fee types (as opposed to one being based on discrete fees and the other on fee types), thereby reducing the burden of developing and maintaining two separate counts to determine and disclose the elements under their respective rules. The Bureau is also providing a list of fee types and fee variations in final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2, discussed below—which are based on fees that the Bureau is aware exist in the current prepaid marketplace—that a financial institution may use when determining both the number of additional fee types charged pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and any additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau believes that these provisions will reduce the risks and burdens raised by commenters concerning the proposed disclosure of the total number of fees not otherwise listed, while still providing the consumer with an important signal and incentive to investigate prepaid accounts that have more complex pricing structures.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In addition, the Bureau believes that this modification addresses commenters' concerns, at least in part, regarding a potential chill to innovation of new features because such fee variations within a fee type will not be required to be separately counted for purposes of this disclosure. The Bureau intends to monitor compliance with this rule, including financial institutions' disclosures of the number of additional fee types charged, as well as market innovations in the prepaid industry more generally, and will consider additional action in future rulemakings if necessary.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Modifying the final rule to require disclosure of the number of fee types also addresses concerns raised by some commenters that the proposed disclosure would have included many fees that are not commonly incurred by consumers—including fees for discretionary features that require specific consumer action before they are incurred. For example, under the final rule, a financial institution would count bill payment as an additional fee type if it offered this feature, but, unlike the rule as proposed, would not count each of the discrete fee variations within bill payment such as ACH bill payment, paper check bill payment, check cancellation, and regular or expedited delivery of a paper check. Thus, in addition to a reduction in the overall number of additional fees required to be disclosed under the final rule, a financial institution would similarly not be required to disclose many of the less common fees and fees triggered by affirmative consumer action. While some of the additional fee types required to be disclosed in the final rule may still be less common or triggered only when a consumer elects to use an optional service, the Bureau reiterates that the primary objective of this provision is to alert consumers to fee information absent from the short form and to spur consumers to take action to gain a more fulsome understanding of the terms of a prospective prepaid account; this disclosure fulfils this objective.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below, the Bureau is adopting a de minimis threshold with respect to the disclosure of specific additional fee types. The Bureau does not believe a de minimis threshold would be appropriate for the disclosure required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) regarding the total number of additional fee types. The Bureau notes, however, that with the de minimis threshold in § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix), disclosure of such fee types under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) would not be required, although such fee types would be counted in the total number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau continues to believe it is not necessary to include in the final rule specific requirements for updating the statement regarding the number of additional fee types charged required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A). As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b) above, the Bureau does not believe that financial institutions change the fee schedules for prepaid accounts often, particularly those sold at retail. If a financial institution is making available a new optional service for all prepaid accounts in a particular prepaid account program, Regulation E provides a means for financial institutions to notify consumers of terms associated with a new EFT service that is added to a consumer's account, in § 1005.7(c). A financial institution may provide new consumer disclosures in accordance with § 1005.7(c) post-acquisition, without needing to pull and replace card packaging that does not reflect that new optional feature in the disclosure of the number of additional fee types pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A). The Bureau does expect, however, that financial institutions will keep their other disclosures up to date (including those provided electronically and orally, as well as disclosures provided in writing that are not a part of pre-printed packaging materials, such as those printed by a financial institution upon a consumer's request). The Bureau intends to monitor financial institutions' practices in this area, however, and may consider additional requirements in a future rulemaking if necessary.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1 clarifies what fee types to count in the total number of additional fee types, specifically excluding fees otherwise required to be disclosed in and outside the short form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges as described in final Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11) imposed in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in final § 1026.61. Excluding the static fees and fees required to be disclosed outside the short form avoids the duplicative counting of fees already disclosed to the consumer. As discussed in more detail below, the Bureau has made a strategic decision to focus the bulk of the short form disclosure on usage of the prepaid account itself rather than any charges related to overdraft credit features. The possibility that consumers may be offered an overdraft credit feature for use in connection with the prepaid account is addressed in the short form pursuant to § 1005.18(b)(2)(x), which requires the following statement if such a feature may be offered: “You may be offered overdraft/credit after [x] days. Fees would apply.” Consistent with this overall decision, the Bureau believes that it is appropriate to exclude any finance charges related to an overdraft credit feature that may be offered at a later date to some prepaid consumers from the disclosures regarding additional fees under both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix). If consumers are interested in such a feature, they can look to the Regulation Z disclosures in the long form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(4)(vii), discussed below, for more details.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1.i explains that the number of additional fee types includes only fee types under which the financial institution may charge fees; accordingly, third-party fees are not included unless they are imposed for services performed on behalf of the financial institution. The comment additionally clarifies that the number of additional fee types includes only fee types the financial institution may charge consumers with respect to the prepaid account; accordingly, additional fee types does not include other revenue sources such as interchange fees or fees paid by employers for payroll card programs, government agencies for government benefit programs, or other entities sponsoring prepaid account programs for financial disbursements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-1.ii explains that fee types that bear a relationship to, but are separate from, the static fees disclosed in the short form must be counted as additional fee types for purposes of final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii). The comment also provides a detailed explanation regarding the treatment of international ATM fees and fees for reloading funds into a prepaid account in a form other than cash (such as electronic reload and check reload). In addition, the comment explains that additional fee types disclosed in the short form pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) must be counted in the total number of additional fee types. This is because the exclusions in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix)(A)(<em data-original="E-03">1</em>) and (<em data-original="E-03">2</em>) are only for fees required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(i) through (vii) and (5) and any finance charges imposed on the prepaid account as described in Regulation Z § 1026.4(b)(11)(ii) in connection with a covered separate credit feature accessible by a hybrid prepaid-credit card as defined in Regulation Z § 1026.61. Further, the statement required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) explains that the additional fee types disclosed are some of the total number of additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting new comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 to provide guidance regarding the calculation of the number of additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) as well as to address concerns raised by an industry commenter regarding how to categorize fees in determining the additional fee types to disclose under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment explains that the term fee type, as used in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix), is a general category under which a financial institution charges fees to consumers. A financial institution may charge only one fee within a particular fee type, or may charge two or more variations of fees within the same fee type. (The Bureau notes that an additional fee type for which a financial institution does not charge any fee to the consumer, including for any variations of the additional fee type, is not counted in the total number of additional fee types under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) nor required to be disclosed on the short form under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).) The comment goes on to provide a list of examples of fee types a financial institution may use when determining both the number of additional fee types charged pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and any additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment also explains that a financial institution may create an appropriate name for other additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau compiled the list of examples of fee types in new comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 to provide guidance to financial institutions and to help facilitate their categorization of additional fee types for satisfying the requirements in final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and (ix). The list also may encourage standardization of this portion of the short form in that, although additional fee types disclosed will vary across short forms for different prepaid account programs, the Bureau believes financial institutions will generally use consistent nomenclature for additional fee types identified on the list. The Bureau compiled this list of examples of fee types based on particular fee types referenced in comments received on the proposal and by reviewing the packaging of and disclosures for scores of prepaid account programs.<footnote ref="403">As part of the Bureau's Study of Prepaid Account Agreements, Bureau staff found fee tables or other explanations of at least some of the fees charged for 278 of the 325 agreements reviewed. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; Study of Prepaid Account Agreements at 29 and note 49.</footnote>
             The Bureau balanced multiple considerations in compiling the list in final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-2 for purposes of both final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and (ix), including existing industry practices with regard to fee types, the accounting burdens associated with relatively narrower or broader definitions of fee types, and the potential benefits to both industry and consumers in using narrower definitions of fee types to communicate information about specific account features and fees. The Bureau believes the resulting list strikes an appropriate balance by capturing categories and terms employed by the prepaid industry itself that will be useful to financial institutions and consumers in determining and understanding additional fee types. The Bureau is providing flexibility to financial institutions to fashion appropriate names for other fee types, including fee types for services that do not yet exist in the prepaid marketplace.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-3 clarifies that, pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(vi), a financial institution using the multiple service plan short form disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(6)(iii)(B)(<em data-original="E-03">2</em>) must disclose only the fee for calling customer service via a live agent. Thus, pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii), any charge for calling customer service via an interactive voice response system must be counted in the total number of additional fee types.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(A)-4 clarifies that a financial institution must use the same categorization of fee types in the number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii) and in its determination of which additional fee types to disclose pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau is including this comment on consistency to make clear that a financial institution is not permitted to, for example, shorten its list of fee types into a few broad categories (in order to minimize the number of additional fee types required to be disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)) but use a more detailed list of fee types broken out into a greater number of categories when assessing its obligations under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) (in order to maximize the number of fee types that may fall below the de minimis threshold pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix)(A)(<em data-original="E-03">2</em>)).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-33-b" notice="2012-1728" date="2012-02-07">
      <title>33(b) Notice of Error From Sender</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 205.33(b) set forth the timing and content requirements for a notice of error provided by a sender in connection with a remittance transfer. Consistent with EFTA section 919(d)(1)(A), proposed § 205.33(b)(1)(i) stated that a sender must provide a notice of error orally or in writing to the remittance transfer provider no later than 180 days after the date of availability of the remittance transfer stated in the receipt or combined disclosure. Under proposed § 205.33(b)(1)(ii), such notice of error must enable the remittance transfer provider to identify: the sender's name and telephone number or address; the recipient's name, and if known, the telephone number or address of the recipient; and the remittance transfer to which the notice of error applies. Proposed § 205.33(b)(1)(iii) stated that the notice must also indicate why the sender believes the error exists and include to the extent possible the type, date, and amount of the error, except in the case of requests for documentation, additional information, or clarification under proposed § 205.33(a)(1)(v).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Several industry commenters suggested that the time period for senders to assert an error is too long. Some industry commenters recommended that the time period be shortened to 60 days, similar to the time period that consumers have to assert errors for EFTs. <em data-original="E-03">See</em> § 1005.11(b)(3). Other industry commenters suggested 30 days. The Bureau notes that the 180-day time period for senders to assert an error is expressly stated in the statute. Given the international nature of remittance transfers, the additional time a sender may need to communicate with persons abroad, and the lack of information about problems associated with this time period, the Bureau does not believe that using its authority under EFTA sections 904(a) and (c) to change this time period is currently warranted.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Industry commenters also requested that the sender be required to assert an error in writing at a centralized address. The Bureau believes that requiring senders to assert an error in writing would have a chilling effect on the error resolution process, especially given that some senders may not feel comfortable writing in English. Although in some cases, a sender may have the ability to assert the error in a foreign language and be assured a response in that language, that ability may depend on the foreign languages used at the office of the remittance transfer provider where the error is asserted to advertise, solicit, or market remittance transfers under § 1005.31(g), as discussed above. Moreover, the current error resolution process for EFTs does not require a consumer to assert an error in writing.<footnote ref="81">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#167;&amp;#8201;1005.11(b). Although a financial institution may request that a consumer assert the error in writing, a consumer's failure to do so does not cancel the error resolution process, but gives the financial institution 45 days to investigate the error without having to provide provisional credit. &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#167;&amp;#8201;1005.11(b)(2) and (c)(2).</footnote>
             Therefore, the Bureau declines to make the requested change, and proposed § 205.33(b)(1) is adopted substantially as proposed in renumbered § 1005.33(b)(1).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 205.33(b)(2) provided that when a notice of error was based on documentation, additional information, or clarification that the sender had previously requested under § 1005.33(a)(1)(v), the sender's notice of error would be timely if it were received by the provider no later than 60 days after the provider sends the requested documentation, information, or clarification. As the Board explained in the May 2011 Proposed Rule, the proposed 60-day time frame for the sender to provide a new notice of error following the sender's receipt of documentation, information, or clarification from the remittance transfer provider is consistent with the 60-day time frame established for similar circumstances under the general error resolution provisions in Regulation E, § 1005.11(b)(3).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau agrees with the Board's reasoning that under these circumstances, 60 days, rather than the 180-day error resolution time frame generally applicable to remittance transfers, provides sufficient time for a sender to review the additional information provided by the remittance transfer provider and determine whether an error occurred in connection with a transfer. The Bureau did not receive any comments on this issue. However, the Bureau believes it is appropriate to clarify that a sender always has the original 180 days after the disclosed date of availability to assert an error. Consequently, the Bureau is amending proposed § 205.33(b)(2), renumbered as § 1005.33(b)(2), to provide that when a notice of error is based on documentation, additional information, or clarification that the sender had previously requested under § 1005.33(a)(1)(v), the sender's notice of error is timely if received by the remittance transfer provider the later of 180 days after the disclosed date of availability of the remittance transfer or 60 days after the provider sent the documentation, information, or clarification requested.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board proposed commentary to clarify proposed § 205.33(b). Proposed comment 33(b)-1 clarified that the error resolution procedures for remittance transfers apply only when a notice of error is received from the sender of the transfer. Thus, a notice of error provided by the designated recipient would not trigger the remittance transfer provider's error resolution obligations. As the Board explained in the May 2011 Proposed Rule, this interpretation is consistent with EFTA section 919(d)(1)(A), which establishes error resolution obligations for a remittance transfer provider only when a notice is received from the sender.<footnote ref="82">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See also&lt;/em&gt; EFTA section 919(g)(1) (providing that a designated recipient &amp;#8220;shall not be deemed to be a consumer for purposes of this Act&amp;#8221;).</footnote>
             Proposed comment 33(b)-1 also clarified that the error resolution provisions do not apply when the remittance transfer provider itself discovers and corrects an error. The Bureau did not receive any comments on the proposed comment, which the Bureau adopts as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board proposed comment 33(b)-2 to provide that a notice of error is effective so long as the remittance transfer provider is able to identify the remittance transfer in question. As explained in the May 2011 Proposed Rule, a sender could provide in the notice of error the confirmation number or code given to the sender for the pick-up of a remittance transfer to identify the particular transfer in their tracking systems and records, or any other identification number or code supplied by the provider in connection with the remittance transfer, if such number or code is sufficient to enable the provider to identify the transfer.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>One industry commenter requested that, for an account-based remittance transfer, the final rule require senders to include the account number in the notice of error. The Bureau notes that under comment 11(b)(1)-1 for EFTs, consumers are not required to provide their account numbers and need only provide sufficient information to enable the financial institution to identify the account. Similarly, the Bureau believes that a sender need not provide the account number, but must provide enough information such that the remittance transfer provider can identify the account and the transfer in question. The Bureau adopts comment 33(b)-2 with this clarification, and also makes other clarifying changes to comment 33(b)-2 to make the comment consistent with § 1005.33(b)(1).</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 33(b)-3 provided that a remittance transfer provider may request, or the sender may provide, an email address of the sender or the designated recipient, as applicable, instead of a physical address if the email address would be sufficient to enable the provider to identify the remittance transfer to which the notice applies. Proposed comment 33(b)-4 provided that if the sender fails to provide a timely notice of error within 180 days from the stated date of delivery, the remittance transfer provider would not be required to comply with the error resolution requirements set forth in the rule. As the Board noted in the May 2011 Proposed Rule, proposed comment 33(b)-4 is similar to comment 11(b)(1)-7 for EFTs. The Bureau did not receive any comments on these proposed comments. Therefore, the Bureau adopts comment 33(b)-3 substantially as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>However, given that a sender may provide a second notice of error based on documentation, additional information, or clarification that the sender requested pursuant to § 1005.33(b)(2), as discussed above, the Bureau is revising comment 33(b)-4 to include the time periods relevant to § 1005.33(b)(2). Consequently, comment 33(b)-4 provides that, if applicable, a remittance transfer provider is not required to comply with the error resolution requirements for any notice of error from a sender that is received by the provider more than 60 days after a provider sent documentation, additional information, or clarification requested by the sender, provided such date is later than 180 days after the disclosed date of availability.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Board proposed comment 33(b)-5 to provide that a notice of error from a sender received by a remittance transfer provider's agent is deemed to be received by the provider for purposes of the 180-day time frame for reporting errors under § 1005.33(b)(1)(i). Some industry commenters suggested that senders should only be permitted to assert an error at a centralized address or telephone number. These commenters noted that because remittance transfers are not the primary business for most or all of the agents of a remittance transfer provider, relying on an agent to properly forward disputes and relevant supporting documents to the remittance transfer provider would impose unnecessary costs on agents. Commenters also argued that introducing agents into the error resolution process would increase the likelihood that disputes would not be handled and resolved in a timely way.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As the Board noted in the May 2011 Proposed Rule, a sender that has a problem or issue with a particular remittance transfer may contact the agent location that the sender used to send the transfer to resolve the problem or issue, rather than notifying the provider directly. The Bureau agrees with the Board that because in many cases, for transfers sent through money transmitters, it will be the agent with whom the sender has a direct relationship, and not the provider, it is appropriate to treat a notice of error given to the agent as notice to the provider. This approach also ensures that a sender does not lose his or her error resolution rights merely because the sender was unaware of a need to directly notify the provider. This is consistent with the approach the Bureau is taking with respect to a sender asserting his or her right to cancel, as discussed in further detail below in comment 34(a)-4. Moreover, the Bureau notes that the comment does not require the agent to perform the error resolution procedures. Remittance transfer providers may require their agents to pass on any error notice they receive to the remittance transfer providers, who can then fulfill the requirements of § 1005.33. Therefore, the Bureau adopts proposed comment 33(b)-5 substantially as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Finally, proposed comment 33(b)-6 cross-referenced the disclosure requirements in § 205.31 to reiterate that a remittance transfer provider must include an abbreviated notice of the consumer's error resolution rights on the receipt under § 205.31(b)(2) or combined disclosure under § 205.31(b)(3), as applicable. In addition, the proposed comment provided that the remittance transfer provider must make available to a sender upon request, a notice providing a full description of error resolution rights that is substantially similar to the model error resolution and cancellation notice set forth in Appendix A of this regulation (Model Form A-36). The Bureau did not receive any comments on the proposed comment. The Bureau adopts comment 33(b)-6 substantially as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-b-6-i" notice="2016-24503_20181001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(b)(6)(i) Form and Content Generally</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) to provide that each prepaid account agreement must contain the provisions of the agreement and the fee information in effect as of the last business day of the preceding calendar quarter. Proposed comment 19(b)(6)-1 would have provided the following example to aid in determining the “as of” date of an agreement: On June 1, an issuer decides to decrease the out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee associated with one of the agreements it offers to the public. The change in that fee will become effective on August 1. If the issuer submits the agreement to the Bureau on July 31 (for example, because the agreement has been otherwise amended), the agreement submitted should not include the new lower out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee because that lower fee was not in effect on June 30, the last business day of the preceding calendar quarter. Proposed comment 19(b)(6)-1 was similar to Regulation Z comment 58(c)(8)-1.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have also stated that agreements must not include any personally identifiable information relating to any consumer, such as name, address, telephone number, or account number. Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have also stated that the following would not be deemed to be part of the agreement for purposes of proposed § 1005.19, and therefore are not required to be included in submissions to the Bureau: (1) ancillary disclosures required by State or Federal law, such as affiliate marketing notices, privacy policies, or disclosures under the E-Sign Act; (2) solicitation or marketing materials; (3) periodic statements; and (4) documents that may be sent to the consumer along with the prepaid account or prepaid account agreement such as a cover letter, a validation sticker on the card, or other information about card security. Finally, proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have required that agreements must be presented in a clear and legible font.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) generally mirrored the provisions in Regulation Z § 1026.58(c)(8)(i) regarding the form and content of agreements that would be submitted to the Bureau. This provision would have excluded, however, two additional items listed in Regulation Z § 1026.58(c)(8)(i)(C) that are not deemed to be part of a credit card agreement—ancillary agreements between the issuer and the consumer, such as debt cancellation contracts or debt suspension agreements, and offers for credit insurance or other optional products and other similar advertisements—because the Bureau did not believe these items were relevant in the prepaid account context.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received no comments specifically addressing § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) and is therefore finalizing it as proposed, with modifications for consistency with the revisions to proposed § 1005.19(b)(1) to change the time period in which issuers must submit agreements to the Bureau from a quarterly basis to a rolling basis. The Bureau notes that final § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) is not intended to provide an exhaustive list of the ancillary State and Federal law disclosures that are not deemed to be part of an agreement under final § 1005.19. As indicated by the use of the term “such as,” the listed disclosures are merely examples of “ancillary disclosures required by Federal or State law.” The Bureau does not believe it is feasible to include in this paragraph a comprehensive list of all such disclosures, as such a list would be extensive and would change as State and Federal laws and regulations are amended. The Bureau notes that an issuer would not be prohibited by this or any other provision of § 1005.19 from choosing to include these items in submitted agreements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from several consumer groups and one credit union trade association regarding the Bureau's request for comment about whether issuers should be required to post agreements on their Web sites in an electronic format that is readily usable by the general public, or whether issuers should be required to provide agreements using, for example, a machine-readable text format, such as JSON or XML, that could be used by the Bureau or third parties to more easily create comparison shopping tools.<footnote ref="544">The Bureau solicited comment on this issue in the section-by-section analysis of proposed § 1005.19(b)(2); however, the Bureau believes it is more appropriate to discuss this issue here in the section-by-section analysis § 1005.19(b)(6)(i), regarding the requirements for the form and content of the agreements submitted to the Bureau.</footnote>
             The consumer groups argued that agreements should be submitted in a machine-readable text format because this format would allow researchers and other third parties to analyze information more easily and create comparison shopping tools. The credit union trade association disagreed, however, arguing that requiring agreements to be submitted in a format other than PDF would impose substantial software engineering fees on issuers. The Bureau appreciates the comments it received and continues to believe that it is important for issuers to submit agreements in a machine-readable format for these agreements to be useful to both the Bureau in its market monitoring efforts and to the consumers and other parties reviewing agreements on the Bureau's Web site in the future. The Bureau will provide technical specifications that will include details regarding appropriate file formats that the Bureau expects issuers will use when submitting new agreements and amended agreements following a substantive change.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also received comments from several consumer groups and a labor organization requesting that in addition to including with each submission the names of the bank issuer, program manager, and branding entity (such as an employer, organization, institution of higher education), and other names that might be associated with a prepaid account (such as the entity that provides customer support), agreements should be searchable by such information. One of these commenters explained that many issuers use marketing or other affinity related names that make it difficult for a consumer to know which entity issued the prepaid account. The Bureau has considered these comments will consider incorporating such search functionality into its Web site.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing comment 19(b)(6)-1 substantially as proposed, with several modifications for clarity and consistency with the revisions to § 1005.19(b)(1). In addition, the Bureau has removed from final comment 19(b)(6)-1 the reference to “offers to the public” and leaving only the term “offers” to reflect the changes to § 1005.19(a)(5) as discussed. Specifically, final comment 19(b)(6)-1 explains that agreements submitted to the Bureau must contain the provisions of the agreement and fee information currently in effect. For example, on June 1, an issuer decides to decrease the out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee associated with one of the agreements it offers. The change in that fee will become effective on August 1. The issuer must submit and post the amended agreement with the decreased out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee to the Bureau by August 31 as required by final § 1005.19(b)(2) and (c).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-19-b-6-i" notice="2016-24503_20171001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>19(b)(6)(i) Form and Content Generally</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) to provide that each prepaid account agreement must contain the provisions of the agreement and the fee information in effect as of the last business day of the preceding calendar quarter. Proposed comment 19(b)(6)-1 would have provided the following example to aid in determining the “as of” date of an agreement: On June 1, an issuer decides to decrease the out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee associated with one of the agreements it offers to the public. The change in that fee will become effective on August 1. If the issuer submits the agreement to the Bureau on July 31 (for example, because the agreement has been otherwise amended), the agreement submitted should not include the new lower out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee because that lower fee was not in effect on June 30, the last business day of the preceding calendar quarter. Proposed comment 19(b)(6)-1 was similar to Regulation Z comment 58(c)(8)-1.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have also stated that agreements must not include any personally identifiable information relating to any consumer, such as name, address, telephone number, or account number. Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have also stated that the following would not be deemed to be part of the agreement for purposes of proposed § 1005.19, and therefore are not required to be included in submissions to the Bureau: (1) ancillary disclosures required by State or Federal law, such as affiliate marketing notices, privacy policies, or disclosures under the E-Sign Act; (2) solicitation or marketing materials; (3) periodic statements; and (4) documents that may be sent to the consumer along with the prepaid account or prepaid account agreement such as a cover letter, a validation sticker on the card, or other information about card security. Finally, proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) would have required that agreements must be presented in a clear and legible font.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Proposed § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) generally mirrored the provisions in Regulation Z § 1026.58(c)(8)(i) regarding the form and content of agreements that would be submitted to the Bureau. This provision would have excluded, however, two additional items listed in Regulation Z § 1026.58(c)(8)(i)(C) that are not deemed to be part of a credit card agreement—ancillary agreements between the issuer and the consumer, such as debt cancellation contracts or debt suspension agreements, and offers for credit insurance or other optional products and other similar advertisements—because the Bureau did not believe these items were relevant in the prepaid account context.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received no comments specifically addressing § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) and is therefore finalizing it as proposed, with modifications for consistency with the revisions to proposed § 1005.19(b)(1) to change the time period in which issuers must submit agreements to the Bureau from a quarterly basis to a rolling basis. The Bureau notes that final § 1005.19(b)(6)(i) is not intended to provide an exhaustive list of the ancillary State and Federal law disclosures that are not deemed to be part of an agreement under final § 1005.19. As indicated by the use of the term “such as,” the listed disclosures are merely examples of “ancillary disclosures required by Federal or State law.” The Bureau does not believe it is feasible to include in this paragraph a comprehensive list of all such disclosures, as such a list would be extensive and would change as State and Federal laws and regulations are amended. The Bureau notes that an issuer would not be prohibited by this or any other provision of § 1005.19 from choosing to include these items in submitted agreements.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from several consumer groups and one credit union trade association regarding the Bureau's request for comment about whether issuers should be required to post agreements on their Web sites in an electronic format that is readily usable by the general public, or whether issuers should be required to provide agreements using, for example, a machine-readable text format, such as JSON or XML, that could be used by the Bureau or third parties to more easily create comparison shopping tools.<footnote ref="544">The Bureau solicited comment on this issue in the section-by-section analysis of proposed § 1005.19(b)(2); however, the Bureau believes it is more appropriate to discuss this issue here in the section-by-section analysis § 1005.19(b)(6)(i), regarding the requirements for the form and content of the agreements submitted to the Bureau.</footnote>
             The consumer groups argued that agreements should be submitted in a machine-readable text format because this format would allow researchers and other third parties to analyze information more easily and create comparison shopping tools. The credit union trade association disagreed, however, arguing that requiring agreements to be submitted in a format other than PDF would impose substantial software engineering fees on issuers. The Bureau appreciates the comments it received and continues to believe that it is important for issuers to submit agreements in a machine-readable format for these agreements to be useful to both the Bureau in its market monitoring efforts and to the consumers and other parties reviewing agreements on the Bureau's Web site in the future. The Bureau will provide technical specifications that will include details regarding appropriate file formats that the Bureau expects issuers will use when submitting new agreements and amended agreements following a substantive change.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also received comments from several consumer groups and a labor organization requesting that in addition to including with each submission the names of the bank issuer, program manager, and branding entity (such as an employer, organization, institution of higher education), and other names that might be associated with a prepaid account (such as the entity that provides customer support), agreements should be searchable by such information. One of these commenters explained that many issuers use marketing or other affinity related names that make it difficult for a consumer to know which entity issued the prepaid account. The Bureau has considered these comments will consider incorporating such search functionality into its Web site.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing comment 19(b)(6)-1 substantially as proposed, with several modifications for clarity and consistency with the revisions to § 1005.19(b)(1). In addition, the Bureau has removed from final comment 19(b)(6)-1 the reference to “offers to the public” and leaving only the term “offers” to reflect the changes to § 1005.19(a)(5) as discussed. Specifically, final comment 19(b)(6)-1 explains that agreements submitted to the Bureau must contain the provisions of the agreement and fee information currently in effect. For example, on June 1, an issuer decides to decrease the out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee associated with one of the agreements it offers. The change in that fee will become effective on August 1. The issuer must submit and post the amended agreement with the decreased out-of-network ATM withdrawal fee to the Bureau by August 31 as required by final § 1005.19(b)(2) and (c).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-18-b-2-viii-B" notice="2016-24503_20181001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>Statement Directing Consumers To Disclosure of Additional Fee Types Required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) requires that, if a financial institution makes a disclosure of specific additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix), the financial institution must include a statement directing consumers to that disclosure, located after but on the same line of text as the statement regarding the number of additional fee types required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A), using the following clause or a substantially similar clause: “Here are some of them:”.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The disclosure required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) indicating the number of additional fee types will generally be followed by the specific disclosure of two additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau believes that a brief transition statement linking these two disclosures will enhance consumer understanding of both disclosures and dispel potential consumer misunderstanding that features are not offered if they are not disclosed on the short form.<footnote ref="404">See the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below discussing industry commenters' concern that disclosure of the proposed incidence-based fees would mislead consumers into thinking that features are not offered if they are not disclosed as incidence-based fees.</footnote>
             Thus, the line in the short form disclosure following the static fees would disclose the following or substantially similar clauses: “We charge X other types of fees. Here are some of them:”.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below, the Bureau believes that the brevity and clarity of the short form disclosure necessary for optimal consumer comprehension and engagement cannot support a detailed explanation of what additional fee types are or the criteria the financial institution used in determining which additional fee types to disclose. The Bureau's pre-proposal consumer testing of such explanations support this conclusion.<footnote ref="405">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report I at 35 and ICF Report II at 22-23.</footnote>
             Pre-proposal testing of a statement intended to inform consumers that the fees listed were those that generated significant revenue for the financial institution resulted in minimal participant comprehension or notice.<footnote ref="406">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report I at 35. (Certain prototype short form disclosures tested included the statement: &amp;#8220;The fees below generate significant revenue for this company.&amp;#8221;)</footnote>

             Post-proposal testing of a similar disclosure that, in addition to including an explanation of the criteria for disclosing such fees (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> that the two fees listed were the most commonly charged), also directed consumers where to find detail about all fees, similarly did not increase participant comprehension.<footnote ref="407">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report II at 22-23. (Certain prototype short form disclosures tested included the statement: &amp;#8220;We charge [x] additional fees. Details on fees inside the package, at 800-234-5678 or at &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;bit.ly/XYZprepaids&lt;/em&gt;. These are our most common:&amp;#8221;.)</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Thus, to make the connection for consumers that the additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) are a subset of the number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A), and that absence of any feature on the short form does not necessarily mean the prepaid account program does not offer that feature, the Bureau is including in the final rule the transition statement set forth above.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(B)-1 provides guidance regarding the statement required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) directing consumers to the disclosure of additional fee types pursuant final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment explains that a financial institution that makes no disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) may not include a disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B). The comment also provides examples regarding substantially similar clauses a financial institution may use in certain circumstances to make its disclosures under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and (B), such as when a financial institution has several additional fee types but is only required to disclose one of them pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1005-18-b-2-viii-B" notice="2016-24503_20171001" date="2016-11-22">
      <title>Statement Directing Consumers To Disclosure of Additional Fee Types Required by § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>Final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) requires that, if a financial institution makes a disclosure of specific additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix), the financial institution must include a statement directing consumers to that disclosure, located after but on the same line of text as the statement regarding the number of additional fee types required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A), using the following clause or a substantially similar clause: “Here are some of them:”.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The disclosure required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) indicating the number of additional fee types will generally be followed by the specific disclosure of two additional fee types pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The Bureau believes that a brief transition statement linking these two disclosures will enhance consumer understanding of both disclosures and dispel potential consumer misunderstanding that features are not offered if they are not disclosed on the short form.<footnote ref="404">See the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below discussing industry commenters' concern that disclosure of the proposed incidence-based fees would mislead consumers into thinking that features are not offered if they are not disclosed as incidence-based fees.</footnote>
             Thus, the line in the short form disclosure following the static fees would disclose the following or substantially similar clauses: “We charge X other types of fees. Here are some of them:”.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis of § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) below, the Bureau believes that the brevity and clarity of the short form disclosure necessary for optimal consumer comprehension and engagement cannot support a detailed explanation of what additional fee types are or the criteria the financial institution used in determining which additional fee types to disclose. The Bureau's pre-proposal consumer testing of such explanations support this conclusion.<footnote ref="405">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report I at 35 and ICF Report II at 22-23.</footnote>
             Pre-proposal testing of a statement intended to inform consumers that the fees listed were those that generated significant revenue for the financial institution resulted in minimal participant comprehension or notice.<footnote ref="406">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report I at 35. (Certain prototype short form disclosures tested included the statement: &amp;#8220;The fees below generate significant revenue for this company.&amp;#8221;)</footnote>

             Post-proposal testing of a similar disclosure that, in addition to including an explanation of the criteria for disclosing such fees (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> that the two fees listed were the most commonly charged), also directed consumers where to find detail about all fees, similarly did not increase participant comprehension.<footnote ref="407">&lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;See&lt;/em&gt; ICF Report II at 22-23. (Certain prototype short form disclosures tested included the statement: &amp;#8220;We charge [x] additional fees. Details on fees inside the package, at 800-234-5678 or at &lt;em data-original="E-03"&gt;bit.ly/XYZprepaids&lt;/em&gt;. These are our most common:&amp;#8221;.)</footnote>
            
          </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Thus, to make the connection for consumers that the additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) are a subset of the number of additional fee types disclosed pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A), and that absence of any feature on the short form does not necessarily mean the prepaid account program does not offer that feature, the Bureau is including in the final rule the transition statement set forth above.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Final comment 18(b)(2)(viii)(B)-1 provides guidance regarding the statement required by final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B) directing consumers to the disclosure of additional fee types pursuant final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix). The comment explains that a financial institution that makes no disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix) may not include a disclosure pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(B). The comment also provides examples regarding substantially similar clauses a financial institution may use in certain circumstances to make its disclosures under final § 1005.18(b)(2)(viii)(A) and (B), such as when a financial institution has several additional fee types but is only required to disclose one of them pursuant to final § 1005.18(b)(2)(ix).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>

  </analysis>
</notice>
