<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs http://cfpb.github.io/regulations-schema/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2014-01-01</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>REAL ESTATE SETTLEMENT PROCEDURES ACT</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1024</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-22752_20140101</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2014-01-01</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/articles/2013/10/01/2013-22752/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-equal-credit-opportunity-act-regulation-b-real</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-5">
      <section label="1024-5" sectionNum="5">
        <subject>§ 1024.5 Coverage of RESPA.</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-5-a" marker="(a)">
          <title type="keyterm">Applicability.</title>
          <content><ref target="1024-2-b-RESPA" reftype="term">RESPA</ref> and this part apply to all <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">federally related mortgage loans</ref>, except for the exemptions provided in paragraph <ref target="1024-5-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> of this section.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-5-b" marker="(b)">
          <title type="keyterm">Exemptions.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-1" marker="(1)">
            <content>A loan on property of 25 acres or more.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-2" marker="(2)">
            <title type="keyterm">Business purpose loans.</title>
            <content>An extension of credit primarily for a business, commercial, or agricultural purpose, as defined by <ref target="CFR:12-1026-3" reftype="external">12 CFR 1026.3</ref>(a)(1) of <ref target="1024-2-b-RegulationZ" reftype="term">Regulation Z</ref>. Persons may rely on <ref target="1024-2-b-RegulationZ" reftype="term">Regulation Z</ref> in determining whether the exemption applies.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-3" marker="(3)">
            <title type="keyterm">Temporary financing.</title>
            <content>Temporary financing, such as a construction loan. The exemption for temporary financing does not apply to a loan made to finance construction of 1- to 4-family residential property if the loan is used as, or may be converted to, permanent financing by the same <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> or is used to finance transfer of title to the first user. If a <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> issues a commitment for permanent financing, with or without conditions, the loan is covered by this part. Any construction loan for new or rehabilitated 1- to 4-family residential property, other than a loan to a bona fide builder (a person who regularly constructs 1- to 4-family residential structures for sale or lease), is subject to this part if its term is for two years or more. A “bridge loan” or “swing loan” in which a <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> takes a security interest in otherwise covered 1- to 4-family residential property is not covered by <ref target="1024-2-b-RESPA" reftype="term">RESPA</ref> and this part.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-4" marker="(4)">
            <title type="keyterm">Vacant land.</title>
            <content>Any loan secured by vacant or unimproved property, unless within two years from the date of the <ref target="1024-2-b-Settlement" reftype="term">settlement</ref> of the loan, a structure or a manufactured home will be constructed or placed on the real property using the loan proceeds. If a loan for a structure or manufactured home to be placed on vacant or unimproved property will be secured by a lien on that property, the transaction is covered by this part.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-5" marker="(5)">
            <title type="keyterm">Assumption without lender approval.</title>
            <content><ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> approval. Any assumption in which the <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> does not have the right expressly to approve a subsequent person as the borrower on an existing <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">federally related mortgage loan</ref>. Any assumption in which the <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref>'s permission is both required and obtained is covered by <ref target="1024-2-b-RESPA" reftype="term">RESPA</ref> and this part, whether or not the <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> charges a fee for the assumption.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-6" marker="(6)">
            <title type="keyterm">Loan conversions.</title>
            <content>Any conversion of a <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">federally related mortgage loan</ref> to different terms that are consistent with provisions of the original mortgage instrument, as long as a new note is not required, even if the <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref> charges an additional fee for the conversion.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-5-b-7" marker="(7)">
            <title type="keyterm">Secondary market transactions.</title>
            <content>A bona fide transfer of a loan obligation in the secondary market is not covered by <ref target="1024-2-b-RESPA" reftype="term">RESPA</ref> and this part, except as set forth in section 6 of <ref target="1024-2-b-RESPA" reftype="term">RESPA</ref> (<ref target="USC:12-2605" reftype="external">12 U.S.C. 2605</ref>) and § <ref target="1024-21" reftype="internal">1024.21</ref>. In determining what constitutes a bona fide transfer, the <ref target="1024-2-b-Bureau" reftype="term">Bureau</ref> will consider the real source of funding and the real interest of the funding <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref>. <ref target="1024-2-b-MortgageBroker" reftype="term">Mortgage broker</ref> transactions that are table-funded are not secondary market transactions. Neither the creation of a <ref target="1024-2-b-DealerLoanOrDealerConsumerCreditContract" reftype="term">dealer loan or dealer consumer credit contract</ref>, nor the first assignment of such loan or contract to a <ref target="1024-2-b-Lender" reftype="term">lender</ref>, is a secondary market transaction (see § <ref target="1024-2" reftype="internal">1024.2</ref>).</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
