<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-10-01</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>REAL ESTATE SETTLEMENT PROCEDURES ACT</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>X</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1024</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-22752</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2014-01-10</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2013/10/01/2013-22752/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-equal-credit-opportunity-act-regulation-b-real</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-16962" rightDocumentNumber="2013-22752">
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-30-a">
      <paragraph label="1024-30-a" marker="(a)">
        <title type="keyterm">In general.</title>
        <content>Except as provided in paragraphs <ref target="1024-30-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> and <ref target="1024-30-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> of this section, this subpart applies to any mortgage loan, as that term is defined in § <ref target="1024-31" reftype="internal">1024.31</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-35-g-1-iii-B">
      <paragraph label="1024-35-g-1-iii-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>The mortgage loan is discharged.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-36-f-1-v-B">
      <paragraph label="1024-36-f-1-v-B" marker="(B)">
        <content>The mortgage loan balance was paid in full.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-b-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Notice required.</title>
        <content>Except as otherwise provided in this section, a servicer shall provide to a delinquent borrower a written notice with the information set forth in paragraph (b)(2) of this section not later than the 45th day of the borrower's delinquency. A servicer is not required to provide the written notice more than once during any 180-day period.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-3">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-b-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Model clauses.</title>
        <content>Model clauses <ref target="1024-MS-4(A)" reftype="internal">MS-4(A)</ref>, <ref target="1024-MS-4(B)" reftype="internal">MS-4(B)</ref>, and <ref target="1024-MS-4(C)" reftype="internal">MS-4(C)</ref>, in appendix <ref target="1024-MS-4" reftype="internal">MS-4</ref> to this part may be used to comply with the requirements of this paragraph <ref target="1024-39-b" reftype="internal">(b)</ref> of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-b-2-ii">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <title type="keyterm">Time period disclosure.</title>
        <content>The notice required pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1024-41-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref> of this section must include a reasonable date by which the borrower should submit the documents and information necessary to make the loss mitigation application complete.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-b-3">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-b-3" marker="(3)">
        <title type="keyterm">Determining Protections.</title>
        <content>To the extent a determination of whether protections under this section apply to a borrower is made on the basis of the number of days between when a complete loss mitigation application is received and when a foreclosure sale occurs, such determination shall be made as of the date a complete loss mitigation application is received.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-1-ii">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
        <content>Provide the borrower with a notice in writing stating the servicer's determination of which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower on behalf of the owner or assignee of the mortgage loan. The servicer shall include in this notice the amount of time the borrower has to accept or reject an offer of a loss mitigation program as provided for in paragraph <ref target="1024-41-e" reftype="internal">(e)</ref> of this section, if applicable, and a notification, if applicable, that the borrower has the right to appeal the denial of any loan modification option as well as the amount of time the borrower has to file such an appeal and any requirements for making an appeal, as provided for in paragraph <ref target="1024-41-h" reftype="internal">(h)</ref> of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-i">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-2-i" marker="(i)">
        <title type="keyterm">In general.</title>
        <content>Except as set forth in paragraphs <ref target="1024-41-c-2-ii" reftype="internal">(c)(2)(ii)</ref> and <ref target="1024-41-c-2-iii" reftype="internal">(iii)</ref> of this section, a servicer shall not evade the requirement to evaluate a complete loss mitigation application for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower by offering a loss mitigation option based upon an evaluation of any information provided by a borrower in connection with an incomplete loss mitigation application.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-2-iii">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
        <title type="keyterm">Payment forbearance.</title>
        <content>Notwithstanding paragraph <ref target="1024-41-c-2-i" reftype="internal">(c)(2)(i)</ref> of this section, a servicer may offer a shortterm payment forbearance program to a borrower based upon an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. A servicer shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or nonjudicial foreclosure process, and shall not move for foreclosure judgment or order of sale, or conduct a foreclosure sale, if a borrower is performing pursuant to the terms of a payment forbearance program offered pursuant to this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-2-iv">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <title type="keyterm">Facially complete application.</title>
        <content>If a borrower submits all the missing documents and information as stated in the notice required pursuant to § <ref target="CFR:12-1026-41" reftype="external">1026.41(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref>, or no additional information is requested in such notice, the application shall be considered facially complete. If the servicer later discovers additional information or corrections to a previously submitted document are required to complete the application, the servicer must promptly request the missing information or corrected documents and treat the application as complete for the purposes of paragraphs <ref target="1024-41-f-2" reftype="internal">(f)(2)</ref> and <ref target="1024-41-g" reftype="internal">(g)</ref> of this section until the borrower is given a reasonable opportunity to complete the application. If the borrower completes the application within this period, the application shall be considered complete as of the date it was facially complete, for the purposes of paragraphs <ref target="1024-41-d" reftype="internal">(d)</ref>, <ref target="1024-41-e" reftype="internal">(e)</ref>, <ref target="1024-41-f-2" reftype="internal">(f)(2)</ref>, <ref target="1024-41-g" reftype="internal">(g)</ref>, and <ref target="1024-41-h" reftype="internal">(h)</ref> of this section, and as of the date the application was actually complete for the purposes of paragraph <ref target="1024-41-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref>. A servicer that complies with this paragraph will be deemed to have fulfilled its obligation to provide an accurate notice under paragraph <ref target="1024-41-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref>.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-d">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-d" marker="(d)">
        <title type="keyterm">Denial of loan modification options.</title>
        <content>If a borrower’s complete loss mitigation application is denied for any trial or permanent loan modification option available to the borrower pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1024-41-c" reftype="internal">(c)</ref> of this section, a servicer shall state in the notice sent to the borrower pursuant to paragraph <ref target="1024-41-c-1-ii" reftype="internal">(c)(1)(ii)</ref> of this section the specific reason or reasons for the servicer’s determination for each such trial or permanent loan modification option and, if applicable, that the borrower was not evaluated on other criteria.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-f-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-f-1" marker="(1)">
        <title type="keyterm">Pre-foreclosure review period.</title>
        <content>A servicer shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process unless:</content>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-f-1-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>A borrower’s mortgage loan obligation is more than 120 days delinquent;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-f-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>The foreclosure is based on a borrower’s violation of a due-on-sale clause; or</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-f-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>The servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a subordinate lienholder.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>      
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-h-4">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-h-4" marker="(4)">
        <title type="keyterm">Appeal determination.</title>
        <content>Within 30 days of a borrower making an appeal, the servicer shall provide a notice to the borrower stating the servicer's determination of whether the servicer will offer the borrower a loss mitigation option based upon the appeal and, if applicable, how long the borrower has to accept or reject such an offer or a prior offer of a loss mitigation option. A servicer may require that a borrower accept or reject an offer of a loss mitigation option after an appeal no earlier than 14 days after the servicer provides the notice to a borrower. A servicer's determination under this paragraph is not subject to any further appeal.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-j">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-j" marker="(j)">
        <title type="keyterm">Small servicer requirements.</title>
        <content>A small servicer shall be subject to the prohibition on foreclosure referral in paragraph <ref target="1024-41-f-1" reftype="internal">(f)(1)</ref> of this section. A small servicer shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process and shall not move for foreclosure judgment or order of sale, or conduct a foreclosure sale, if a borrower is performing pursuant to the terms of an agreement on a loss mitigation option.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(D)" subpath="subject">
      <subject>MS-3(D)—Model Form for Renewal or Replacement of Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(e)(2)</subject>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-17-k-5-ii-Interp" subpath="title">
      <title>17(k)(5)(ii) Inability to disburse funds.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-33-a-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-33-a-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Terminology.</title>
        <content>Although the servicing disclosure statement must be clear and conspicuous pursuant to § <ref target="1024-32-a" reftype="internal">1024.32(a)</ref>, § <ref target="1024-33-a" reftype="internal">1024.33(a)</ref> does not set forth any specific rules for the format of the statement, and the specific language of the servicing disclosure statement in appendix <ref target="1024-MS-1" reftype="internal">MS-1</ref> is not required to be used. The model format may be supplemented with additional information that clarifies or enhances the model language.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-33-c-1-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-33-c-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Compliance with § 1024.39.</title>
        <content>A transferee servicer's compliance with § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> during the 60-day period beginning on the effective date of a servicing transfer does not constitute treating a payment as late for purposes of § <ref target="1024-33-c-1" reftype="internal">1024.33(c)(1)</ref>.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-35-c-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-35-c-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Notice of an exclusive address.</title>
        <content>A notice establishing an address that a borrower must use to assert an error may be included with a different disclosure, such as a notice of transfer. The notice is subject to the clear and conspicuous requirement in § <ref target="1024-32-a-1" reftype="internal">1024.32(a)(1)</ref>. If a servicer establishes an address that a borrower must use to assert an error, a servicer must provide that address to the borrower in the following contexts:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-35-c-Interp-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The written notice designating the specific address, required pursuant to § <ref target="1024-35-c" reftype="internal">1024.35(c)</ref> and § <ref target="1024-36-b" reftype="internal">1024.36(b)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-35-c-Interp-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Any periodic statement or coupon book required pursuant to <ref target="CFR:12-1026-41" reftype="external">12 CFR 1026.41</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-35-c-Interp-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>Any Web site the servicer maintains in connection with the servicing of the loan. </content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-35-c-Interp-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
          <content>Any notice required pursuant to §§ <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> or <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">.41</ref> that includes contact information for assistance.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-36-b-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-36-b-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title type="keyterm">Notice of an exclusive address.</title>
        <content>A notice establishing an address that a borrower must use to request information may be included with a different disclosure, such as a notice of transfer. The notice is subject to the clear and conspicuous requirement in § <ref target="1024-32-a-1" reftype="internal">1024.32(a)(1)</ref>. If a servicer establishes an address that a borrower must use to request information, a servicer must provide that address to the borrower in the following contexts:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-b-Interp-2-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>The written notice designating the specific address, required pursuant to § <ref target="1024-35-c" reftype="internal">1024.35(c)</ref> and § <ref target="1024-36-b" reftype="internal">1024.36(b)</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-b-Interp-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>Any periodic statement or coupon book required pursuant to <ref target="CFR:12-1026-41" reftype="external">12 CFR 1026.41</ref>.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-b-Interp-2-iii" marker="(iii)">
          <content>Any Web site the servicer maintains in connection with the servicing of the loan. </content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-b-Interp-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
          <content>Any notice required pursuant to §§ <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> or <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">.41</ref> that includes contact information for assistance.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-38-b-5-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-5-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title type="keyterm">Notices of error incorrectly sent to addresses associated with submission of loss mitigation applications or the continuity of contact.</title>
        <content>A servicer’s policies and procedures must be reasonably designed to ensure that if a borrower incorrectly submits an assertion of an error to any address given to the borrower in connection with submission of a loss mitigation application or the continuity of contact pursuant to § <ref target="1024-40" reftype="internal">1024.40</ref>, the servicer will inform the borrower of the procedures for submitting written notices of error set forth in § <ref target="1024-35" reftype="internal">1024.35</ref>, including the correct address. Alternatively, the servicer could redirect such notices to the correct address.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-Interp" subpath="title">
      <title>§ 1024.41—Loss Mitigation Procedures.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-b-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-Interp" target="1024-41-b-2">
        <title>41(b)(2) Review of loss mitigation application submission.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-i-Interp">
          <title>41(b)(2)(i) Requirements.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-i-B-Interp" target="1024-41-b-2-i-B">
            <title>Paragraph 41(b)(2)(i)(B).</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-i-B-Interp-1" marker="(1)">
              <title>Later discovery of additional information required to evaluate application.</title>
              <content>Even if a servicer has informed a borrower that an application is complete (or notified the borrower of specific information necessary to complete an incomplete application), if the servicer determines, in the course of evaluating the loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower, that additional information or a corrected version of a previously submitted document is required, the servicer must promptly request the additional information or corrected document from the borrower pursuant to the reasonable diligence obligation in § <ref target="1024-41-b-1" reftype="internal">1024.41(b)(1)</ref>. See § <ref target="1024-41-c-2-iv" reftype="internal">1024.41(c)(2)(iv)</ref> addressing facially complete applications.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp" target="1024-41-b-2-ii">
          <title>41(b)(2)(ii) Time period disclosure.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Reasonable date.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) requires that a notice informing a borrower that a loss mitigation application is incomplete must include a reasonable date by which the borrower should submit the documents and information necessary to make the loss mitigation application complete. In determining a reasonable date, a servicer should select the deadline that preserves the maximum borrower rights under § <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">1024.41</ref> based on the milestones listed below, except when doing so would be impracticable to permit the borrower sufficient time to obtain and submit the type of documentation needed. Generally, it would be impracticable for a borrower to obtain and submit documents in less than seven days. In setting a date, the following milestones should be considered (if the date of a foreclosure sale is not known, a servicer may use a reasonable estimate of the date for which a foreclosure sale may be scheduled):</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
              <content>The date by which any document or information submitted by a borrower will be considered stale or invalid pursuant to any requirements applicable to any loss mitigation option available to the borrower;</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>The date that is the 120th day of the borrower’s delinquency;</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>The date that is 90 days before a foreclosure sale;</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
              <content>The date that is 38 days before a foreclosure sale.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-b-3-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-3-Interp" target="1024-41-b-3">
        <title>41(b)(3) Determining Protections.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Foreclosure sale not scheduled.</title>
          <content>If no foreclosure sale has been scheduled as of the date that a complete loss mitigation application is received, the application is considered to have been received more than 90 days before any foreclosure sale.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Foreclosure sale re-scheduled.</title>
          <content>The protections under § <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">1024.41</ref> that have been determined to apply to a borrower pursuant to § <ref target="1024-41-b-3" reftype="internal">1024.41(b)(3)</ref> remain in effect thereafter, even if a foreclosure sale is later scheduled or rescheduled.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp" target="1024-41-c-2-iii">
        <title>41(c)(2)(iii) Payment forbearance.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Short-term payment forbearance program.</title>
          <content>The exemption in § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) applies to short-term payment forbearance programs. A payment forbearance program is a loss mitigation option for which a servicer allows a borrower to forgo making certain payments or portions of payments for a period of time. A short-term payment forbearance program allows the forbearance of payments due over periods of no more than six months. Such a program would be short-term regardless of the amount of time a servicer allows the borrower to make up the missing payments.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Payment forbearance and incomplete applications.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) allows a servicer to offer a borrower a short-term payment forbearance program based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. Such an incomplete loss mitigation application is still subject to the other obligations in § <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">1024.41</ref>, including the obligation in § <ref target="1024-41-b-2" reftype="internal">1024.41(b)(2)</ref> to review the application to determine if it is complete, the obligation in § <ref target="1024-41-b-1" reftype="internal">1024.41(b)(1)</ref> to exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining documents and information to complete a loss mitigation application (see comment <ref target="1024-41-b-1-Interp-4-iii" reftype="internal">41(b)(1)–4.iii</ref>), and the obligation to provide the borrower with the § <ref target="1024-41-b-2-i-B" reftype="internal">1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B)</ref> notice that the servicer acknowledges the receipt of the application and has determined the application is incomplete.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Payment forbearance and complete applications.</title>
          <content>Even if a servicer offers a borrower a payment forbearance program based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, the servicer must still comply with all the requirements in § <ref target="1024-41" reftype="internal">1024.41</ref> if the borrower completes his or her loss mitigation application.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-2-iv-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iv-Interp" target="1024-41-c-2-iv" marker="(iv)">
        <title type="keyterm">41(c)(2)(iv) Facially complete application.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iv-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Reasonable opportunity.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) requires a servicer to treat a facially complete application as complete for the purposes of paragraphs (f)(2) and (g) until the borrower has been given a reasonable opportunity to complete the application. A reasonable opportunity requires the servicer to notify the borrower of what additional information or corrected documents are required, and to afford the borrower sufficient time to gather the information and documentation necessary to complete the application and submit it to the servicer. The amount of time that is sufficient for this purpose will depend on the facts and circumstances.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iv-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Borrower fails to complete the application.</title>
          <content>If the borrower fails to complete the application within the timeframe provided under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv), the application shall be considered incomplete.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-Interp" subpath="title">
      <title>41(c) Evaluation of loss mitigation applications.</title>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-d-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-Interp" target="1024-41-d">
        <title>41(d) Denial of loan modification options.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title type="keyterm">Investor requirements.</title>
          <content>If a trial or permanent loan modification option is denied because of a requirement of an owner or assignee of a mortgage loan, the specific reasons in the notice provided to the borrower must identify the owner or assignee of the mortgage loan and the requirement that is the basis of the denial. A statement that the denial of a loan modification option is based on an investor requirement, without additional information specifically identifying the relevant investor or guarantor and the specific applicable requirement, is insufficient. However, where an owner or assignee has established an evaluation criteria that sets an order ranking for evaluation of loan modification options (commonly known as a waterfall) and a borrower has qualified for a particular loan modification option in the ranking established by the owner or assignee, it is sufficient for the servicer to inform the borrower, with respect to other loan modification options ranked below any such option offered to a borrower, that the investor's requirements include the use of such a ranking and that an offer of a loan modification option necessarily results in a denial for any other loan modification options below the option for which the borrower is eligible in the ranking.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title type="keyterm">Net present value calculation.</title>
          <content>If a trial or permanent loan modification is denied because of a net present value calculation, the specific reasons in the notice provided to the borrower must include the inputs used in the net present value calculation.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-1-Interp-2-p1" marker="">
            <title type="keyterm">(c)(1)(4) Other notices.</title>
            <content>A servicer may combine other notices required by applicable law, including, without limitation, a notice with respect to an adverse action required by Regulation B (12 CFR 1002 et seq.) or a notice required pursuant to the Fair Credit Reporting Act, with the notice required pursuant to § <ref target="1024-41-d" reftype="internal">1024.41(d)</ref>, unless otherwise prohibited by applicable law.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title type="keyterm">Determination not to offer a loan modification option constitutes a denial.</title>
          <content>A servicer's determination not to offer a borrower a loan modification available to the borrower constitutes a denial of the borrower for that loan modification option, notwithstanding whether a servicer offers a borrower a different loan modification option or other loss mitigation option.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-d-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title type="keyterm">Reasons listed.</title>
          <content>A servicer is required to disclose the actual reason or reasons for the denial. If a servicer’s systems establish a hierarchy of eligibility criteria and reach the first criterion that causes a denial but do not evaluate the borrower based on additional criteria, a servicer complies with the rule by providing only the reason or reasons with respect to which the borrower was actually evaluated and rejected as well as notification that the borrower was not evaluated on other criteria. A servicer is not required to determine or disclose whether a borrower would have been denied on the basis of additional criteria if such criteria were not actually considered.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="deleted" label="1024-41-f-1-Interp"/>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-f-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-f-Interp-1" target="1024-41-f-1" marker="1.">
        <title type="keyterm">Prohibited activities.</title>
        <content>Section 1024.41(f) prohibits a servicer from making the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process under certain circumstances. Whether a document is considered the first notice or filing is determined on the basis of foreclosure procedure under the applicable State law.</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-f-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Where foreclosure procedure requires a court action or proceeding, a document is considered the first notice or filing if it is the earliest document required to be filed with a court or other judicial body to commence the action or proceeding (e.g., a complaint, petition, order to docket, or notice of hearing).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-f-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>Where foreclosure procedure does not require an action or court proceeding, such as under a power of sale, a document is considered the first notice or filing if it is the earliest document required to be recorded or published to initiate the foreclosure process.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-f-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
          <content>Where foreclosure procedure does not require any court filing or proceeding, and also does not require any document to be recorded or published, a document is considered the first notice or filing if it is the earliest document that establishes, sets, or schedules a date for the foreclosure sale.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-f-Interp-1-iv" marker="iv.">
          <content>A document provided to the borrower but not initially required to be filed, recorded, or published is not considered the first notice or filing on the sole basis that the document must later be included as an attachment accompanying another document that is required to be filed, recorded, or published to carry out a foreclosure.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1024-35" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>Sections 1024.35 and .36 Error Resolution Procedures and Requests for Information</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed minor amendments to the error resolution and request for information provisions of Regulation X, adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules. In the areas in which amendments were proposed, the error resolution procedures largely parallel the information request procedures; thus the two sections are discussed together below. Section 1024.35 implements section 6(k)(1)(C) of RESPA, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act, and § 1024.36 implements section 6(k)(1)(D) of RESPA, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act. To the extent the requirements under §§ 1024.35 and 1024.36 are applicable to qualified written requests, these provisions also implement sections 6(e) and 6(k)(1)(B) of RESPA. As discussed in part III (Legal Authority), the Bureau is finalizing these amendments pursuant to its authority under RESPA sections 6(j), 6(k)(1)(E) and 19(a). As explained in more detail below, the Bureau believes these provisions are necessary and appropriate to achieve the consumer protection purposes of RESPA, including ensuring responsiveness to consumer requests and complaints and the provision and maintenance of accurate and relevant information.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-36" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>Sections 1024.35 and .36 Error Resolution Procedures and Requests for Information</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed minor amendments to the error resolution and request for information provisions of Regulation X, adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules. In the areas in which amendments were proposed, the error resolution procedures largely parallel the information request procedures; thus the two sections are discussed together below. Section 1024.35 implements section 6(k)(1)(C) of RESPA, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act, and § 1024.36 implements section 6(k)(1)(D) of RESPA, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act. To the extent the requirements under §§ 1024.35 and 1024.36 are applicable to qualified written requests, these provisions also implement sections 6(e) and 6(k)(1)(B) of RESPA. As discussed in part III (Legal Authority), the Bureau is finalizing these amendments pursuant to its authority under RESPA sections 6(j), 6(k)(1)(E) and 19(a). As explained in more detail below, the Bureau believes these provisions are necessary and appropriate to achieve the consumer protection purposes of RESPA, including ensuring responsiveness to consumer requests and complaints and the provision and maintenance of accurate and relevant information.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-35-c" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>35(c) and 36(b) Contact Information for Borrowers To Assert Errors and Information Requests</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend the commentary to § 1024.35(c) and § 1024.36(b) with respect to disclosure of the exclusive address (a servicer may designate an exclusive address for the receipt of notifications of errors and requests for information) when a servicer discloses contact information to the borrower for the purpose of assistance from the servicer. Section 1024.35(c), as adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, state that a servicer may, by written notice provided to a borrower, establish an address that a borrower must use to submit a notice of error to a servicer in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.35. Comment 35(c)-2 clarifies that, if a servicer establishes any such exclusive address, the servicer must provide that address to the borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with contact information for assistance from the servicer. Similarly, § 1024.36(b) states that a servicer may, by written notice provided to a borrower, establish an address that a borrower must use to submit information requests to a servicer in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.36. Comment 36(b)-2 clarifies that, if a servicer establishes any such exclusive address, the servicer must provide that address to the borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with contact information for assistance from the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In the proposal, the Bureau expressed concern that comments 35(c)-2 and 36(b)-2 could be interpreted more broadly than the Bureau had intended. Section 1024.35(c) and comment 35(c)-2, as well as § 1024.36(b) and comment 36(b)-2, are intended to ensure that servicers inform borrowers of the correct address for the borrower to use for purposes of submitting notices of error or information requests, so that borrowers do not inadvertently send these communications to other non-designated servicer addresses (which would not provide the protections afforded by §§ 1024.35 and 1024.36, respectively). If interpreted literally, the existing comments would require the servicer to include the designated address for notices of error and requests for information when <em data-original="E-03">any</em> contact information, even just a phone number or web address, for the servicer is given to the borrower. The Bureau did not intend that the servicer be required to inform the borrower of the designated address in all communications with borrowers where any contact information whatsoever for the servicer is provided.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the Bureau proposed to amend comment 35(c)-2 to provide that, if a servicer establishes a designated error resolution address, the servicer must provide that address to a borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with an <em data-original="E-03">address</em> for assistance from the servicer. Similarly, the Bureau proposed to amend comment 36(b)-2 to provide that, if a servicer establishes a designated information request address, the servicer must provide that address to a borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with an <em data-original="E-03">address</em> for assistance from the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing these proposed clarifications. Industry commenters supported limiting the locations where the designated address is required, but asserted that the requirement was still overbroad and unclear as to when the designated address must be provided. These commenters expressed concern that they would have to provide the designated address on every letter that included a return address or an address in the letterhead. The commenters also stated this would be unduly burdensome as it would require significant programming costs. Commenters further stated this would create problems for borrowers by causing cluttered, confusing documents leading borrowers to incorrectly send other things to the designated address (<em data-original="E-03">e.g.,</em> a borrower may send a payment to the designated address, leading to a delay in payment processing). Finally, commenters stated the proposed clarification could create conflicts with other regulations, such as the force-placed insurance letters, which include an address but do not allow additional information to be included. Industry commenters generally suggested the designated address be required only in a specific subset of contexts: the initial designation letter, the periodic statements and coupon book, the servicer's Web site, and loss mitigation documents.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Consumer group commenters expressed concern that borrowers will not be informed of their rights. Such commenters objected to a decision the Bureau made, in the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, to eliminate the requirement that a servicer receiving a transferred loan include information on the error resolution procedures in its notice to the borrower about the transfer. Such commenters suggested that information on the error resolution and information request rights should be included on each periodic statement.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting revised versions of proposed comments 35(c)-2 and 36(b)-2. The Bureau notes that the proposal only addressed when the designated address must be provided, and that comments about providing borrowers information about the general procedures to submit error notifications or information requests are beyond the scope of the proposed changes to the rule.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is persuaded that the proposed language of “an address for assistance” might not have fully addressed the concerns of the provision being overbroad, as the proposed language could have been interpreted to require the designated address on every document from the servicer that contains a return address. The Bureau is further persuaded by the concern that borrowers could have been confused and incorrectly sent items that did not concern error resolution to the designated address. To require the designated address on every piece of written communication that includes a return address would be unduly burdensome and not in the best interests of the borrower. Thus, under the final rule, the designated address need be included in only a specific subset of contexts, specifically (1) the written notice, required by § 1024.35(c) and § 1024.36(b) if a servicer designates an exclusive address; (2) any periodic statement or coupon book required pursuant to 12 CFR 1026.41; (3) any Web site maintained by the servicer in connection with the servicing of the loan; and (4) any notice required pursuant to §§ 1024.39 or 1026.41 that includes contact information for assistance.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>While servicers will not specifically be required to provide the designated address in contexts other than those described in the amended comments, the Bureau notes that a servicer remains subject to the requirement in § 1026.38(b)(5) to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure that the servicer informs the borrower of the procedures for submitting written notices of error and information requests. Further, as discussed below in the section-by-section analysis of section 38(b)(5), the Bureau is adopting new comment 38(b)(5)-3 clarifying a servicer's obligation to ensure borrowers are informed of the designated address. The Bureau believes this the final rule will best balance practical considerations with the need to notify borrowers of the designated address.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-38-b-5" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>38(b)(5) Informing Borrowers of the Written Error Resolution and Information Request</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed above in the section-by-section discussion of §§ 1024.35(c) and 1024.36(b), the Bureau is amending comments 35(c)-2 and 36(b)-2 to clarify in what contexts the designated address for notices of error or requests for information must be provided. The finalized comments clarify that, if a servicer designates such an address, that address must be provided in any notice required pursuant to §§ 1024.39 or 1024.41 that includes contact information for assistance. The Bureau notes that servicers may provide borrowers in delinquency with different addresses for different purposes. For example, a servicer may provide a borrower with the designated address for asserting errors, and a separate address for submission of loss mitigation applications. To mitigate the risk of a borrower sending a notification of error to the wrong address (and thus not triggering the associated protections), the Bureau is adopting new comment 38(b)(5)-3.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Section 1024.35 sets out certain procedures a servicer must follow when a borrower submits a written notice of error. These procedures provide important protections to borrowers who in are in delinquency (as well as at other times). Specifically, the procedures in § 1024.35(e)(3)(i)(B) require a servicer to take certain actions before a scheduled foreclosure sale if a borrower asserts certain errors.<footnote ref="22">Section 1024.35(e)(3)(i)(B) requires that, if a borrower asserts an error related to a servicer making the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process in violation of § 1024.41(f) or (j), or related to a servicer moving for foreclosure judgment or order of sale or conducting a foreclosure sale in violation of § 1024.41(g) or (j), the servicer must comply with the requirements of the error resolution procedures prior to the date of a foreclosure sale, or within 30 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) after the servicer receives the notice of error, whichever is earlier.</footnote> These protections are only triggered if a borrower submits a written notice of error to the designated address (assuming the servicer has designated such an address). Thus, the Bureau believes it is important that borrowers asserting errors send the notice of error to the proper address.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau notes that existing provisions do address ensuring the borrower is aware of the procedures required to trigger the error resolution protections. Section 1024.38(b)(5) requires a servicer to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to achieve the objective of informing borrowers of the written error resolution and information request procedures. The Bureau acknowledges that a borrower in delinquency who is working with a continuity of contact representative and submitting documents related to loss mitigation may be confused about where to submit notices asserting errors. If such a borrower were to orally report the assertion of the error to the continuity of contact representative, comment 38(b)(5)-2 explains that § 1024.38(b)(s) would require servicers to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to notify a borrower who is not satisfied with the resolution of the complaint of the procedures for submitting a written notice of error. However, the Bureau is concerned that, if borrowers were to submit written assertions of an error to the addresses where they were submitting loss mitigation documents, such borrowers may believe they have properly followed the procedures, but in fact would not have triggered the protections under § 1024.35.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>To address this concern, in connection with the clarification above on the contexts in which the designated address must be provided, the Bureau is adopting new comment 38(b)(5)-3. The new comment clarifies a servicer's obligation pursuant to § 1024.38(b)(5) by stating that a servicer's policies and procedures must be reasonably designed to ensure that if a borrower submits a notice of error to an incorrect address that was given to the borrower in connection with submission of a loss mitigation application or the continuity of contact pursuant to § 1024.40, the servicer will ensure the borrower is informed of the procedures for submitting written notices of error set forth in § 1024.35, including the correct address. Alternatively, the servicer could redirect notices of error that were sent to an incorrect address to the designated address established pursuant to § 1024.35(c).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-36-b" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>35(c) and 36(b) Contact Information for Borrowers To Assert Errors and Information Requests</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend the commentary to § 1024.35(c) and § 1024.36(b) with respect to disclosure of the exclusive address (a servicer may designate an exclusive address for the receipt of notifications of errors and requests for information) when a servicer discloses contact information to the borrower for the purpose of assistance from the servicer. Section 1024.35(c), as adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, state that a servicer may, by written notice provided to a borrower, establish an address that a borrower must use to submit a notice of error to a servicer in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.35. Comment 35(c)-2 clarifies that, if a servicer establishes any such exclusive address, the servicer must provide that address to the borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with contact information for assistance from the servicer. Similarly, § 1024.36(b) states that a servicer may, by written notice provided to a borrower, establish an address that a borrower must use to submit information requests to a servicer in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.36. Comment 36(b)-2 clarifies that, if a servicer establishes any such exclusive address, the servicer must provide that address to the borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with contact information for assistance from the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In the proposal, the Bureau expressed concern that comments 35(c)-2 and 36(b)-2 could be interpreted more broadly than the Bureau had intended. Section 1024.35(c) and comment 35(c)-2, as well as § 1024.36(b) and comment 36(b)-2, are intended to ensure that servicers inform borrowers of the correct address for the borrower to use for purposes of submitting notices of error or information requests, so that borrowers do not inadvertently send these communications to other non-designated servicer addresses (which would not provide the protections afforded by §§ 1024.35 and 1024.36, respectively). If interpreted literally, the existing comments would require the servicer to include the designated address for notices of error and requests for information when <em data-original="E-03">any</em> contact information, even just a phone number or web address, for the servicer is given to the borrower. The Bureau did not intend that the servicer be required to inform the borrower of the designated address in all communications with borrowers where any contact information whatsoever for the servicer is provided.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Accordingly, the Bureau proposed to amend comment 35(c)-2 to provide that, if a servicer establishes a designated error resolution address, the servicer must provide that address to a borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with an <em data-original="E-03">address</em> for assistance from the servicer. Similarly, the Bureau proposed to amend comment 36(b)-2 to provide that, if a servicer establishes a designated information request address, the servicer must provide that address to a borrower in any communication in which the servicer provides the borrower with an <em data-original="E-03">address</em> for assistance from the servicer.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing these proposed clarifications. Industry commenters supported limiting the locations where the designated address is required, but asserted that the requirement was still overbroad and unclear as to when the designated address must be provided. These commenters expressed concern that they would have to provide the designated address on every letter that included a return address or an address in the letterhead. The commenters also stated this would be unduly burdensome as it would require significant programming costs. Commenters further stated this would create problems for borrowers by causing cluttered, confusing documents leading borrowers to incorrectly send other things to the designated address (<em data-original="E-03">e.g.,</em> a borrower may send a payment to the designated address, leading to a delay in payment processing). Finally, commenters stated the proposed clarification could create conflicts with other regulations, such as the force-placed insurance letters, which include an address but do not allow additional information to be included. Industry commenters generally suggested the designated address be required only in a specific subset of contexts: the initial designation letter, the periodic statements and coupon book, the servicer's Web site, and loss mitigation documents.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Consumer group commenters expressed concern that borrowers will not be informed of their rights. Such commenters objected to a decision the Bureau made, in the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, to eliminate the requirement that a servicer receiving a transferred loan include information on the error resolution procedures in its notice to the borrower about the transfer. Such commenters suggested that information on the error resolution and information request rights should be included on each periodic statement.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting revised versions of proposed comments 35(c)-2 and 36(b)-2. The Bureau notes that the proposal only addressed when the designated address must be provided, and that comments about providing borrowers information about the general procedures to submit error notifications or information requests are beyond the scope of the proposed changes to the rule.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is persuaded that the proposed language of “an address for assistance” might not have fully addressed the concerns of the provision being overbroad, as the proposed language could have been interpreted to require the designated address on every document from the servicer that contains a return address. The Bureau is further persuaded by the concern that borrowers could have been confused and incorrectly sent items that did not concern error resolution to the designated address. To require the designated address on every piece of written communication that includes a return address would be unduly burdensome and not in the best interests of the borrower. Thus, under the final rule, the designated address need be included in only a specific subset of contexts, specifically (1) the written notice, required by § 1024.35(c) and § 1024.36(b) if a servicer designates an exclusive address; (2) any periodic statement or coupon book required pursuant to 12 CFR 1026.41; (3) any Web site maintained by the servicer in connection with the servicing of the loan; and (4) any notice required pursuant to §§ 1024.39 or 1026.41 that includes contact information for assistance.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>While servicers will not specifically be required to provide the designated address in contexts other than those described in the amended comments, the Bureau notes that a servicer remains subject to the requirement in § 1026.38(b)(5) to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure that the servicer informs the borrower of the procedures for submitting written notices of error and information requests. Further, as discussed below in the section-by-section analysis of section 38(b)(5), the Bureau is adopting new comment 38(b)(5)-3 clarifying a servicer's obligation to ensure borrowers are informed of the designated address. The Bureau believes this the final rule will best balance practical considerations with the need to notify borrowers of the designated address.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-36-f-1-v-B" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>35(g)(1)(iii)(B) and 36(f)(1)(v)(B)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed amendments to § 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) (untimely notices of error) and § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) (untimely requests for information). Section 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) provides that a notice of error is untimely if it is delivered to the servicer more than one year after a mortgage loan balance was paid in full. Similarly, current § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) provides that an information request is untimely if it is delivered to the servicer more than one year after a mortgage loan balance was paid in full.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to replace the references to “the date a mortgage loan balance is paid in full” with “the date the mortgage loan is discharged.” The proposal noted that this change would address circumstances in which a loan is terminated without being paid in full, such as a loan that was discharged through foreclosure or deed in lieu of foreclosure without full satisfaction of the underlying contractual obligation. Further, the proposal stated that this change also would align more closely with § 1024.38(c)(1), which requires a servicer to retain records that document actions taken with respect to a borrower's mortgage loan account only until one year after the date a mortgage loan is “discharged.”</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing the proposed modifications. Commenters were generally supportive of changing the rule to address situations when the loan is not paid in full, but expressed concerns about the use of the word “discharged,” stating that this word has a specific meaning in bankruptcy and that there may be some ambiguity as to when a loan is discharged in certain situations. In particular, commenters discussed the foreclosure process, as well as situations in which there is a deficiency balance after a foreclosure sale, and situations in which bankruptcy proceedings may eliminate the debt but leave a lien on the property.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting § 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) and § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) as proposed. The Bureau believes the requirement to resolve errors and respond to information requests should last over the same timeframe as the obligation to retain records. The Bureau believes it would be impractical to require a servicer to resolve errors and provide information at a time when Regulation X no longer requires the servicer to retain the relevant records. Conversely, the Bureau believes the servicer should be responsible to correct those records during the period when Regulation X does require a servicer to retain records, if necessary, and provide borrowers information from the records. Further, the Bureau believes the use of the term “discharged” is appropriate, especially given that the term is already used in the timing of the record-retention requirement. For purposes of the Bureau's mortgage servicing rules, as opposed to bankruptcy purposes, a mortgage loan is discharged when both the debt and all corresponding liens have been extinguished or released, as applicable. The Bureau believes a borrower should have the benefit of the error resolution, information request, and record retention provisions so long as a debt <em data-original="E-03">or</em> lien remains because only after both have been eliminated will there be no further possibility of a borrower needing to seek servicing information or to assert a servicing error. Thus, the Bureau is finalizing this provision as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-35-g-1-iii-B" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>35(g)(1)(iii)(B) and 36(f)(1)(v)(B)</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed amendments to § 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) (untimely notices of error) and § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) (untimely requests for information). Section 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) provides that a notice of error is untimely if it is delivered to the servicer more than one year after a mortgage loan balance was paid in full. Similarly, current § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) provides that an information request is untimely if it is delivered to the servicer more than one year after a mortgage loan balance was paid in full.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to replace the references to “the date a mortgage loan balance is paid in full” with “the date the mortgage loan is discharged.” The proposal noted that this change would address circumstances in which a loan is terminated without being paid in full, such as a loan that was discharged through foreclosure or deed in lieu of foreclosure without full satisfaction of the underlying contractual obligation. Further, the proposal stated that this change also would align more closely with § 1024.38(c)(1), which requires a servicer to retain records that document actions taken with respect to a borrower's mortgage loan account only until one year after the date a mortgage loan is “discharged.”</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing the proposed modifications. Commenters were generally supportive of changing the rule to address situations when the loan is not paid in full, but expressed concerns about the use of the word “discharged,” stating that this word has a specific meaning in bankruptcy and that there may be some ambiguity as to when a loan is discharged in certain situations. In particular, commenters discussed the foreclosure process, as well as situations in which there is a deficiency balance after a foreclosure sale, and situations in which bankruptcy proceedings may eliminate the debt but leave a lien on the property.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting § 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) and § 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) as proposed. The Bureau believes the requirement to resolve errors and respond to information requests should last over the same timeframe as the obligation to retain records. The Bureau believes it would be impractical to require a servicer to resolve errors and provide information at a time when Regulation X no longer requires the servicer to retain the relevant records. Conversely, the Bureau believes the servicer should be responsible to correct those records during the period when Regulation X does require a servicer to retain records, if necessary, and provide borrowers information from the records. Further, the Bureau believes the use of the term “discharged” is appropriate, especially given that the term is already used in the timing of the record-retention requirement. For purposes of the Bureau's mortgage servicing rules, as opposed to bankruptcy purposes, a mortgage loan is discharged when both the debt and all corresponding liens have been extinguished or released, as applicable. The Bureau believes a borrower should have the benefit of the error resolution, information request, and record retention provisions so long as a debt <em data-original="E-03">or</em> lien remains because only after both have been eliminated will there be no further possibility of a borrower needing to seek servicing information or to assert a servicing error. Thus, the Bureau is finalizing this provision as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-b-1" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(b)(1) Complete Loss Mitigation Application</title>
      <analysisParagraph>In connection with the provisions addressing payment forbearance discussed below in the section-by-section analysis of 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), the Bureau is amending comment 41(b)(1)-4 to clarify the obligation of a servicer to use reasonable diligence to complete a loss mitigation application. See the discussion below.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-b-2-i" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(b)(2)(i) Requirements</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend the commentary to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i) to clarify servicers' obligations with respect to providing notices to borrowers regarding the review of loss mitigation applications. Section 1024.41(b)(2)(i) requires a servicer that receives a loss mitigation application 45 days or more before a foreclosure sale to review and evaluate the application promptly and determine, based on that review, whether the application is complete or incomplete.<footnote ref="23">A “complete loss mitigation application” is defined in § 1024.41(b)(1) as “an application in connection with which a servicer has received all the information the servicer requires from a borrower in evaluating applications for the loss mitigation options available to the borrower.”</footnote> The servicer then must notify the borrower within five days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays and Sundays) that the servicer acknowledges receipt of the application, and that the servicer has determined that the loss mitigation application is either complete or incomplete. If an application is incomplete, the notice must state the additional documents and information that the borrower must submit to make the loss mitigation application complete. In addition, servicers are obligated under § 1024.41(b)(1) to exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining documents and information necessary to complete an incomplete application, which may require, when appropriate, the servicer to contact the borrower and request such information as illustrated in comment 41(b)(1)-4.i.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Following publication of the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, the Bureau received numerous inquiries from industry stakeholders requesting guidance or clarification regarding how this provision may apply in instances where a servicer determines that additional information from the borrower is needed to complete an evaluation of a loss mitigation application after either (1) the servicer has provided notice to the borrower informing the borrower that the loss mitigation application is complete, or (2) the servicer has provided notice to the borrower identifying other specific information or documentation necessary to complete the application and the borrower has furnished that documentation or information. As these stakeholders noted, servicers sometimes must collect additional information from borrowers, the need for which may not have been apparent at the point of initial application, in order to process the application and satisfy the applicable investor requirements. In these situations, a borrower may have submitted the documents and information identified in the initial notice, resulting in an application that is facially complete based on the servicer's initial review, but the servicer, upon further evaluation, determines that additional information is required to evaluate the borrower for a loss mitigation option pursuant to requirements imposed by an investor or guarantor of a mortgage.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed additional commentary to address these concerns. As the Bureau explained in the June 2013 Proposal, the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) is intended to provide the borrower with timely notification that a loss mitigation application was received and either is considered complete by the servicer or is considered incomplete and that the borrower is required to take further action for the servicer to evaluate the loss mitigation application. The Bureau was conscious of concerns that servicers have unnecessarily prolonged loss mitigation processes by incomplete and inadequate document reviews that lead to repeated requests for supplemental information that reasonably could have been requested initially, and so the Bureau designed the rule to ensure an adequate up-front review. At the same time, the Bureau did not believe it would be in the best interest of borrowers or servicers to create a system that leads to borrower applications being denied solely because they contain inadequate information and the servicer believes it may not request the additional information needed.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau therefore proposed three provisions to address these concerns. First, the Bureau proposed new comment 41(b)(2)(i)(B)-1, which would have clarified that, notwithstanding that a servicer has informed a borrower that an application is complete (or notified the borrower of specific information necessary to complete an incomplete application), a servicer must request additional information from a borrower if the servicer determines, in the course of evaluating the loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower, that additional information is required.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Second, the Bureau proposed new comment 41(b)(2)(i)(B)-2, which would have clarified that, except as provided in § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) (the Bureau's third proposed new provision, discussed below), the protections triggered by a complete loss mitigation application in § 1024.41 would not be triggered by an incomplete application. An application would have been considered complete only when a servicer has received all the information the servicer requires from a borrower in evaluating applications for the loss mitigation options available to the borrower, even if an inaccurate § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice had been sent to the borrower. The Bureau noted that the proposed clarifications would not have allowed servicers deliberately to inform borrowers that incomplete applications are complete or to describe the information necessary to complete an application as something less than all of the necessary information. Servicers are required under § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(A) to review a loss mitigation application to determine whether it is complete or incomplete. In addition, servicers are subject to the § 1024.38(b)(2)(iv) requirement to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to achieve the objectives of identifying documents and information that a borrower is required to submit to complete an otherwise incomplete loss mitigation application, and servicers are obligated under § 1024.41(b)(1) to exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining documents and information necessary to complete an incomplete application. Thus, the proposed clarifications were intended to address situations where servicers make bona fide mistakes in initially evaluating loss mitigation applications.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Third, as described more fully below, the Bureau proposed new § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) to require that, if a servicer creates a reasonable expectation that a loss mitigation application is complete, but later discovers information is missing, the servicer must treat the application as complete for certain purposes until the borrower has been given a reasonable opportunity to complete the loss mitigation application. The Bureau believed the proposed rule would mitigate potential risks to consumers that could arise through a loss mitigation process prolonged by incomplete and inadequate document reviews and repeated requests for supplemental information. The Bureau believed these new provisions would provide a mechanism for servicers to correct bona fide mistakes in conducting up-front reviews of loss mitigation applications for completeness, while ensuring that borrowers do not lose the protections under the rule due to such mistakes and that servicers have incentives to conduct rigorous up-front review of loss mitigation applications.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing the proposed provisions addressing a facially complete application. Commenters were generally supportive of the Bureau addressing situations where a servicer later discovers additional information is required to evaluate an application that is complete according to the terms of the notice the servicer sent the borrower. Commenters generally agreed that a strict rule that prevents servicers from seeking additional information when needed would result in unnecessary denials of loss mitigation to the borrower and that encouraging communication from the servicer to the borrower will improve loss mitigation procedures for the borrower. However, some commenters expressed the view that the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules were sufficient in this regard and that revisions at a date so close to implementation are counterproductive to institutions trying to implement the rule.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed further below in connection with § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv), the Bureau is adopting amendments that achieve largely the same effect as the proposal in addressing situations where a servicer requires additional information to review a facially complete loss mitigation application. The Bureau believes, as it suggested in the proposal, that there is little value in requiring a servicer to evaluate a loss mitigation application when the servicer has determined certain items of information are missing. The Bureau is therefore adopting comment 41(b)(2)(i)(B)-1, which clarifies that if, a servicer determines, in the course of evaluating the loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower, that additional information is required, the servicer must promptly request the additional information from the borrower. The comment also references § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv), a new provision that sets forth requirements and procedures for a servicer to follow in the event that a facially complete application is later found by the servicer to require additional information or documentation to be evaluated. See the discussion of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) in the section-by-section analysis below.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is not adopting proposed comment 41(b)(2)(i)(B)-2, which would have provided that protections triggered by a “complete” loss mitigation application would not be triggered by a facially complete application— <em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> where the servicer informs the borrower that the application is complete, or the borrower provides all the documents and information specified by the servicer in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice as needed to render the application complete. The Bureau continues to believe that certain protections must be provided to borrowers who have submitted all the missing documents and information requested in the 1026.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice, even if a servicer later determines additional information is necessary. However, the Bureau has been persuaded by commenters that argued a borrower who submits all the documents requested in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice (if any) should receive the protection the rule affords to borrowers at the time the borrower submits those documents. In accordance with this approach, proposed comment 41(b)(2)(i)(B)-2 has not been finalized.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-b-2-ii" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(b)(2)(ii) Time Period Disclosure</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend the § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) time period disclosure requirement, which requires a servicer to provide a date by which a borrower should submit any missing documents and information necessary to make a loss mitigation application complete. Section 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) requires a servicer to provide in the notice required pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) the earliest remaining of four specific dates set forth in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii). The four dates set forth in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) are: (1) The date by which any document or information submitted by a borrower will be considered stale or invalid pursuant to any requirements applicable to any loss mitigation option available to the borrower; (2) the date that is the 120th day of the borrower's delinquency; (3) the date that is 90 days before a foreclosure sale; and (4) the date that is 38 days before a foreclosure sale.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In general, many of the protections afforded to a borrower by § 1024.41 are dependent on a borrower submitting a complete loss mitigation application a certain amount of time before a foreclosure sale. The later a borrower submits a complete application, and the closer in time to a foreclosure sale, the fewer protections the borrower receives under § 1024.41. It is therefore in the interest of borrowers to complete loss mitigation applications as early in the delinquency and foreclosure process as possible. However, even if a borrower does not complete a loss mitigation application sufficiently early in the process to secure <em data-original="E-03">all</em> the protections possibly available under § 1024.41, that borrower may still benefit from some of the protections afforded. Borrowers should not be discouraged from completing loss mitigation applications merely because they cannot complete a loss mitigation application by the date that would be most advantageous in terms of securing the protections available under § 1024.41. Accordingly, the goal of § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) is to inform borrowers of the time by which they should complete their loss mitigation applications to receive the greatest set of protections available, without discouraging later efforts if the borrower does not complete the loss mitigation application by the suggested date. The Bureau notes § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) requires servicers to inform borrowers of the date by which the borrower <em data-original="E-03">should</em> make the loss mitigation application complete, as opposed to the date by which the borrower <em data-original="E-03">must</em> make the loss mitigation application complete.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believed, based on communications with consumer advocates, servicers, and trade associations, that the requirement in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) may be overly prescriptive and may prevent a servicer from having the flexibility to suggest an appropriate date by which a borrower should complete a loss mitigation application. For example, if a borrower submits a loss mitigation application on the 114th day of delinquency, the servicer would have to inform him or her by the 119th day that the borrower should complete the loss mitigation application by the 120th day under the current provision. A borrower is unlikely to be able to assemble the missing information within one day, and would be better served by being advised to complete the loss mitigation application by a reasonable later date that would afford the borrower most of the benefits of the rule as well as enough time to gather the information.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In response to these concerns, and in accordance with the goals of the provision, the Bureau proposed to amend the requirement in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii). Specifically, the Bureau proposed to replace the requirement that a servicer disclose the earliest remaining date of the four specific dates set forth in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) with a more flexible requirement that a servicer determine and disclose a reasonable date by which the borrower should submit the documents and information necessary to make the loss mitigation application complete. The Bureau proposed to clarify this amendment in proposed comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-1, which would have explained that, in determining a reasonable date, a servicer should select the deadline that preserves the maximum borrower rights under § 1024.41, except when doing so would be impracticable. Proposed comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-1 would have clarified further that a servicer should consider the four deadlines previously set forth in § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) as factors in selecting a reasonable date. Proposed comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-1 also would have clarified that if a foreclosure sale is not scheduled, for the purposes of determining a reasonable date, a servicer may make a reasonable estimate of when a foreclosure sale may be scheduled. This proposal was intended to provide appropriate flexibility while also requiring that servicers consider the impact of the various times, and the associated protections, set forth in § 1024.41.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing these proposed provisions. Industry commenters appreciated the extra flexibility offered by the proposal, but expressed concern about the complexity of selecting a date. Such commenters noted that different servicers might have different estimates of what should be a reasonable time for otherwise similarly situated borrowers, and differences in state law might also cause two apparently similar borrowers to receive different notices. Additionally, these commenters expressed concern that ambiguity in what is “practical” increases the risk of litigation. These commenters suggested either a simpler rule, under which the application should be complete by the earlier of 30 days after the borrower submitted the incomplete application or the 38th day before a scheduled foreclosure sale (an approach taken by HAMP), or that the Bureau provide additional guidance for determining what is impractical. Finally, commenters expressed concern about borrower confusion, stating that borrowers will not understand the significance of the various dates.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Consumer groups expressed concern that if servicers have discretion about how to inform borrowers when they should complete their applications, servicers will misguide borrowers and cause them to complete applications too late to receive all the protections that could have been available under the rule. Additionally, some consumer groups expressed the view that this whole issue would be avoided if the loss mitigation protections were triggered by an initial application package, defined as a specific subset of documents required for loss mitigation, rather than a complete loss mitigation application.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is amending the text of § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) to require that the related notice must include a reasonable date by which the borrower should submit the missing information. Additionally, the Bureau is adopting an revised version of proposed comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-1 to clarify what is a reasonable date to include in a notice sent pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B). Similar to the proposal, final comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-1 states that, in determining a reasonable date, a servicer should select the date that preserves the maximum borrower rights possible under § 1024.41 (and provides the four milestones originally in the regulation text), except when doing so would be impracticable to permit the borrower sufficient time to obtain and submit the type of documentation needed. The final comment has been amended to state further that, generally, it would be impracticable for a borrower to obtain and submit documents in less than seven days.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the proposed rule, the Bureau has structured this provision so that borrowers receive information that encourages them to submit a complete application in time to receive the most protections possible under the rule, while not discouraging borrowers who miss this time from later submitting an application to receive a subset of the protections. Because some of the protections are triggered by the submission of a complete loss mitigation application when a certain amount of time remains before a scheduled foreclosure sale, the protections decrease the later a borrower submits an application. Thus, the Bureau declines to adopt a rule that simply suggests the borrower complete the application within 30 days because such a rule will not meet the intended purposes of the provision.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also understands that a borrower may not understand the significance of certain milestones, and may be confused if presented by a list of different dates. This is the very reason the rule requires the servicer to provide a single date by which the borrower should complete the application—it removes the burden from the borrower of calculating the different timelines and attempting to determine by when they should complete their application.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau does appreciate the challenges of determining what would be impracticable, thus the Bureau has added language to the commentary explaining that generally it would be impracticable for a borrower to obtain and submit documents in less than seven days. The Bureau notes this is a minimum number of days, and that a servicer may extend this timeline if it believes the borrower would need more time to gather the information. The Bureau believes this approach gives servicers guidance as to what is impracticable, while allowing some flexibility for servicers to address situations where additional time would be required for the borrower to submit particular types of missing information.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, while the final rule does not permit servicers to estimate foreclosure sale dates in other contexts, such as for purposes of determining whether a borrower will be granted an appeal right when no foreclosure sale has actually been scheduled, the Bureau believes it appropriate to allow servicers to estimate a foreclosure sale date for the narrow purpose of this provision. The Bureau notes that servicers may have information about when a foreclosure sale is likely to be scheduled and that allowing a servicer to use this information in determining the time by which a borrower should complete the application would provide the most useful date for borrowers. Thus, the Bureau includes this provision in the comment adopted by this final rule.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau notes that some consumer groups suggested loss mitigation protections should be triggered by an initial application package, defined as a specific subset of documents required for loss mitigation, rather than a complete loss mitigation application. The Bureau notes that while such an approach has been used in other loss mitigation programs, such a modification to the loss mitigation provisions of § 1024.41 is beyond the scope of the proposed changes to the rule.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-c-1-ii" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(c)(1)(ii)</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend § 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) to state explicitly that the notice this provision requires must state the deadline for accepting or rejecting a servicer's offer of a loss mitigation option, in addition to the requirements currently in § 1024.41(d)(2) to specify, where applicable, that the borrower may appeal the servicer's denial of a loan modification option, the deadline for doing so, and any requirements for making an appeal. As described in the proposal, the Bureau intended that the § 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) notice would specify the time and procedures for the borrower to accept or to reject the servicer's offer, in accordance with requirements specified in § 1024.41(e). Indeed, § 1024.41(e)(2)(i) provides that the servicer may deem the borrower to have rejected the offer if the borrower does not respond within the timelines specified under § 1024.41(e)(1). Further, under § 1024.41(e)(2)(ii) and that the servicer must give the borrower a reasonable opportunity to complete documentation necessary to accept an offer of a trial loan modification plan if the borrower does not follow the specified procedures but begins making payments in accordance with the offer by the deadline specified in § 1024.41(e)(1). Commenters did not have any objections to the proposed provision, and the Bureau is adopting this provision as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-d" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(d) Denial of Loan Modification Options</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to move the substance of § 1024.41(d)(2), a provision addressing disclosure of information on the borrower's right to appeal, to § 1024.41(c)(1)(ii). As a conforming amendment, the Bureau proposed to re-codify § 1024.41(d)(1) as § 1024.41(d) and to re-designate the corresponding commentary accordingly. The Bureau is finalizing these provisions as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also proposed to clarify the requirement in § 1024.41(d)(1), re-codified as § 1024.41(d), that a servicer must disclose the reasons for the denial of any trial or permanent loan modification option available to the borrower. The Bureau believed it was appropriate to clarify that the requirement to disclose the reasons for denial focuses on only those determinations actually made by the servicer and does not require a servicer to continue evaluating additional factors after the servicer has already decided to deny a borrower for a particular loss mitigation option. Thus, when a servicer's automated system uses a program that considers a borrower for a loan modification by proceeding through a series of questions and ends the process if the consumer is denied, the servicer need not modify the system to continue evaluating the borrower under additional criteria. For example, suppose a borrower must meet qualifications A, B, and C to receive a loan modification, but the borrower does not meet any of these qualifications. A servicer's system may start by asking if the borrower meets qualification A, and on the failure of that qualification end the analysis for that specific loan modification option. If a servicer were required to disclose all potential reasons why the borrower may have been denied for that loan modification option (<em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> A, B, and C), it would need to consider a lengthy series of hypothetical scenarios: for example, if the borrower had met qualification A, would the borrower also have met qualification B? The Bureau did not intend such a requirement, which it believes would be unnecessarily burdensome.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau instead intended to require only the disclosure of the actual reason or reasons on which the borrower was evaluated and denied. Accordingly, the Bureau proposed to amend § 1024.41(d) to require that a denial notice provided by the servicer must state the “specific reason or reasons” for the denial and also, where applicable, disclose that the borrower was not evaluated based on other criteria. The notice would not be required to list such criteria. The Bureau believed that this additional information will help borrowers understand the status of their application and the fact that they were not fully evaluated under all factors (where applicable). The Bureau also proposed new comment 41(d)-4 stating that, if a servicer's system reaches the first issue that causes a denial but does not evaluate borrowers for additional factors, a servicer need only provide the reason or reasons actually considered. The Bureau believed this proposed amendment would appropriately balance potential concerns about compliance challenges with concerns about informing borrowers about the status of their applications and about information that is relevant to potential appeals.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from both industry and consumer groups addressing the proposed modifications. Commenters were generally in favor of this revision to the rule, and agreed it would be unduly burdensome for servicers to construct systems to consider hypothetical scenarios solely for the purpose of compiling a complete list of all potential denial reasons. One industry commenter suggested that the denial reasons disclosed be limited to “primary” or “initial” reasons. One consumer group expressed concern that the proposed revision would allow servicers to avoid disclosing the factors used in the net present value analysis.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>For the reasons discussed in the proposal, the Bureau is finalizing the rule as proposed. The Bureau declines to modify the rule to require only the “initial” or “primary” reasons as suggested by some commenters because the Bureau believes these terms are unclear. The Bureau also disagrees with commenters that suggested that the modification to the rule allows a servicer to evade disclosure of a factor used in an NPV analysis. The rule requires servicers to disclose the basis for the denial, so if a servicer denies a borrower for a loan modification option based on an NPV analysis, that servicer must disclose the factors used in the analysis. However, if a servicer denies a borrower a loan modification option on other grounds, it would be unduly burdensome for the servicer to disclose factors that would have been used, had the servicer done a NPV analysis.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-f" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(f) Prohibition on Foreclosure Referral</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>First Notice or Filing</title>
        <analysisParagraph/>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>Section 1024.41(f) prohibits a servicer from making the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process unless a borrower's mortgage loan is more than 120 days delinquent. A servicer also is prohibited from making such a notice or filing while a borrower's complete loss mitigation application is being evaluated. In response to numerous questions received by the Bureau about the meaning of the phrase “first notice or filing,” the Bureau proposed to redesignate comment 41(f)(1)-1 as comment 41(f)-1, and then revise it to clarify what actions § 1024.41(f) would prohibit.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Specifically, the proposed comment would have stated that whether a document is considered the first notice or filing is determined under applicable State law. Under the proposal, a document that would be used as evidence of compliance with foreclosure practices required pursuant to State law would have been considered the first notice or filing. Thus, a servicer would have been prohibited from sending such a notice or filing such a document during the pre-foreclosure review period or during the review period for a complete loss mitigation application. Documents that would not be used in this fashion would not have been considered the first notice or filing. The proposed comment would have stated expressly that this prohibition does not extend to activity such as attempting to collect the debt, sending periodic statements, sending breach letters, or any other activity during the pre-foreclosure review period, so long as such documents would not be used as evidence of complying with requirements applicable pursuant to State law in connection with a foreclosure process.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau acknowledged that, under the proposed interpretation, if a State law mandates a notice to a borrower of the availability of mediation as a prerequisite to commence foreclosure, such notices would be considered the “first notice or filing” for purposes of § 1024.41. The Bureau also recognized that existing State foreclosure processes often can be lengthy. The proposed comment sought to balance protecting consumers and encouraging communication between borrowers and servicers by providing borrowers sufficient time to submit a complete loss mitigation application without the stress and costs of foreclosure, but also permitting servicers to communicate with borrowers to respond promptly to requests. However, recognizing potential practical difficulties for servicers as well as borrower protection concerns that could arise from chilling early communications provided for borrowers under State law, the Bureau sought comment on the best way to establish a workable rule that clearly identifies what is prohibited, while balancing these goals.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received substantial comments from trade associations, individual servicers including credit unions, the GSEs, some State governments, and two consumer advocacy groups, which generally disagreed with the proposed “evidence of compliance with State law” standard and asked the Bureau to reconsider the scope of the prohibition. Numerous commenters, including trade organizations, the GSEs, individual servicers and credit unions, asserted that the proposed comment would cause significant delays in the foreclosure process, especially where the first notice or filing would be followed by lengthy periods mandated by State law before actual initiation of court proceedings or establishing a foreclosure sale date. These commenters asserted that the proposal would have prohibited often lengthy processes from starting until after 120 days of delinquency have passed. For example, commenters noted that Massachusetts requires its own notice and opportunity to cure process that may take up to 150 additional days before foreclosure is filed. Thus, if the notice beginning that cure process is deemed the “first notice” for purposes of the prohibition on foreclosure referral (as it would have been under the proposal), foreclosure proceedings may be delayed until the 270th day of delinquency. One industry commenter raised concerns that such delays would impact compliance with regulatory capital requirements.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Industry commenters expressed substantial concerns with the proposal's use of the phrase “evidence of compliance with State law.” These commenters asserted that the phrase is vague, and that State law may often require proof of compliance with the mortgage contract's terms, which may include the sending of general default notices not expressly required by statute. The commenters indicated servicers would have difficulty understanding what documents were prohibited and likely would be discouraged from sending any early communications to borrowers if they later must use such document to show compliance with applicable State law.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Industry commenters, State governments, and some consumer advocates indicated that the proposal likely would delay notices required under State-mandated pre-foreclosure programs. As these commenters noted, under the proposal such notices likely would constitute “evidence of compliance with State law” and thus would be prohibited until after the 120th day of delinquency. These commenters also asserted that such programs complement the Bureau's early intervention rule and that there is substantial benefit to borrowers in receiving these notices early in their delinquencies. For example, many statutory notices require that counseling, legal aid, or other resources be identified to borrowers, and consumer groups agreed that borrowers are more likely to respond and seek loss mitigation when they receive notices clearly informing them that foreclosure is imminent if they do not act. Several commenters pointed to data or experience that indicated many borrowers do not reach out to servicers for loss mitigation assistance until foreclosure notices or notices of default are sent. These commenters believed that borrowers would receive little benefit if these notices were delayed until after the 120th day of delinquency because the likelihood of a successful resolution would be reduced. On the whole, these commenters indicated that delaying State-mandated notices relating to loss mitigation programs or statutory rights to cure delinquencies would frustrate State efforts at avoiding foreclosure by making resolutions more difficult or cure more costly to consumers.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As an alternative to the proposed interpretation of “first notice or filing,” many industry commenters recommended that the Bureau adopt an interpretation based on the Federal Housing Administration's (FHA) definition of “first legal,” citing familiarity with this concept. In the alternative, some industry commenters suggested a more uniform and objective definition or a State-by-State determination. These commenters generally stated that a prohibition that extends to documents defined in a manner that closely tracks “first legal” would better facilitate compliance for industry, while at the same time would permit and encourage the early notices to borrowers, including those that provide counseling, legal aid, or other resources. A number of commenters suggested that specific notices be expressly permitted, including State-mandated outreach to delinquent borrowers and breach letters required by the GSEs.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting a revised version of proposed comment 41(f)-1 that states a document is considered the “first notice or filing” on the basis of foreclosure procedure under applicable State law, but adjusts the Bureau's interpretation of what constitutes a “first notice or filing.” Rather than relying on the general notion that any evidence of compliance with State foreclosure law constitutes a first notice or filing, the Bureau is revising comment 41(f)-1 and adopting four new subparts that are more specifically addressed to different types of foreclosure procedures. New comment 41(f)-1.i explains that, when the foreclosure procedure under applicable State law requires commencement of a court action or proceeding, a document is considered the first notice or filing if it is the earliest document required to be filed with a court or other judicial body to commence the action or proceeding (<em data-original="E-03">e.g.,</em> a complaint, petition, order to docket, notice of hearing). The Bureau also is adopting new comment 41(f)-1.ii, which explains that, when the foreclosure procedure under applicable State law does not require a court action or proceeding, a document is considered the first notice or filing if it is the earliest document required to be recorded or published to initiate the foreclosure process. To address situations not already covered by comments (i) and (ii), new comment 41(f)-1.iii provides that, where a foreclosure procedure does not require initiating a court action or proceeding or recording or publishing of any document, a document is considered a “first notice or filing” if it is the first document which establishes, sets or schedules the foreclosure sale date.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As noted above, the proposal sought to balance protecting consumers and encouraging communication between servicers and borrowers. The Bureau believed that, under the proposed interpretation of “first notice or filing,” borrowers would be ensured sufficient time to submit a complete loss mitigation application, but servicers would still be able to send many of the typical early-default communications, so long as they were not being used as evidence of compliance with State law. The Bureau requested comment on whether the proposal established a workable rule that was clear, in light of varied foreclosure procedures in different states, and the multiple purposes for notices. As noted above, many commenters, including consumer advocate groups and State governments, indicated concerns with the proposed interpretation's impact on communication and its impact on State-mandated loss mitigation programs. Many commenters asserted that the proposal would result in either less or ineffective early default communication and <em data-original="E-03">lessen</em> the likelihood that borrowers would successfully access loss mitigation resolutions or otherwise avoid foreclosure.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is persuaded by these comments that revising the interpretation is necessary to provide greater clarity and also provide for more effective pre-foreclosure outreach. As commenters noted, the proposed interpretation would have prohibited the use of many State-mandated notices that do not initiate foreclosure proceedings and are intended to provide borrowers with information about counseling and other loss mitigation resources as a means of avoiding foreclosure. In addition, the Bureau is persuaded by comments that the proposed interpretation would have chilled other servicer communications, such as cure notices or breach letters, based on confusion over whether such communications were “evidence of compliance” and thus prohibited by § 1024.41.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes the interpretation of first notice or filing adopted by this final rule provides an objective basis for determining compliance with the prohibition on foreclosure referral. In addition, it addresses the concerns raised in comments that the proposal would restrict communications informing borrowers of assistance and statutory rights to cure. The Bureau agrees with commenters that permitting communication about cure rights or pre-foreclosure loss mitigation assistance or procedures available under State law, even within the first 120 days of a borrower's delinquency, furthers the objective of § 1024.41's loss mitigation procedures. The Bureau believes early communication to borrowers about resources such as housing counseling, emergency loan programs, and pre-foreclosure mediation will increase the likelihood that borrowers will submit complete applications in time to benefit from the full loss mitigation procedures under § 1024.41. The Bureau appreciates that, under this modified interpretation, some borrowers who have not yet submitted loss mitigation applications may face shorter foreclosure timeframes after the 120th day of delinquency than under the proposed interpretation. However, the Bureau believes the adopted interpretation provides sufficient opportunity for borrowers to seek loss mitigation assistance without the pressure of pending litigation or foreclosure proceedings. The Bureau also believes a borrower's ability to exercise a statutory or contractual right to cure a default likely will be greater where notice of the cure rights is provided before several months of arrearages have accumulated. While the proposed interpretation was not intended to prohibit sending any such notice, only one that would be used as evidence of compliance with applicable law, the modified interpretation provides greater clarity.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau acknowledges that its interpretation of “first notice or filing” may prohibit, during the 120-day period, initiation of State-mandated loss mitigation efforts or opportunities to cure in those jurisdictions where the applicable foreclosure procedure requires such information to appear first in a court filing, or a document that is recorded or published. However, were the Bureau to adopt an interpretation that excluded such notices from the definition of first filing, based on their inclusion of information related to cure rights or loss mitigation assistance, this likely would create significant confusion and frustrate the purposes of the rule, by permitting certain foreclosure actions within the 120-day period.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau is adding new comment 41(f)-1.iv to clarify that a document provided to a borrower that initially is not required to be filed, recorded or published is not considered the first notice or filing solely on the basis that the foreclosure procedure requires a copy of the document to be included as an attachment to a subsequent document required to be filed or recorded to carry out the foreclosure process. The Bureau is aware through comments that, in many states, letters or notices (including breach letters, notices of rights to cure) that are required to be sent to the borrower, <em data-original="E-03">but do not initiate formal foreclosure proceedings,</em> nonetheless are required to be included in later filings, <em data-original="E-03">i.e.,</em> as part of a complaint or subsequent pleading. Such letters or notices may be sent during the pre-foreclosure review period without violating the foreclosure referral ban.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The interpretation of “first notice or filing” adopted by this final rule closely tracks, but may not be identical in all jurisdictions, to the FHA's “first legal action necessary to initiate foreclosure” or “first legal” or “first public” action, as some commenters requested.<footnote ref="24">See Department of Housing and Urban Development, Mortgagee Letter 2005-30, July 12, 2005.</footnote> However, the Bureau believes to the extent there are jurisdictions where “first notice or filing” of § 1024.41(f) is inconsistent with the FHA standard, it will not hinder servicers' compliance with obligations under the FHA or investor requirements based upon the FHA's standard. The Bureau notes that the “first legal” standard primarily serves to inform mortgagees of their contractual obligations as servicers of FHA-insured mortgages. In light of the fact that § 1024.41(f) is enforceable by private right of action, the Bureau is adopting this interpretation of “first notice or filing” in order to provide sufficient clarity to borrowers, servicers, and courts. The Bureau also believes this interpretation provides States with clarity of the application of § 1024.41(f), not just as to present State foreclosure procedure but with respect to future modifications of State law.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Exceptions to the Prohibition of Early Foreclosure Referrals</title>
        <analysisParagraph/>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau also proposed to amend § 1024.41(f)(1) so that the prohibition on referral to foreclosure until after the 120th day of delinquency would not apply in two situations: (1) When the foreclosure is based on a borrower's violation of a due-on-sale clause, and (2) when the servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a subordinate lienholder. As discussed in the proposal, the Bureau is aware that there may be some circumstances when a foreclosure is not based upon a borrower's delinquency, and thus protections designed to provide delinquent borrowers time to bring their mortgages current or apply for loss mitigation (such as the 120-day ban on foreclosure referral) may not be appropriate or necessary. The Bureau proposed amending § 1024.41(f)(1) to provide the two exemptions for foreclosures based upon due-on-sale clauses and for joining a subordinate lienholder's foreclosure, but also recognized that other situations may exist that also warrant exclusion. Thus, in addition to the two situations described above, the Bureau sought comment on what other situations may be appropriate to exempt, or whether the proposed exemptions were appropriate in situations in which a borrower has submitted a complete loss mitigation application.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received substantial comments from trade associations, individual servicers including credit unions, and the GSEs, which generally supported the added exemptions to § 1024.41(f)(1). Industry commenters generally supported the proposed exemptions, citing a need to provide relief from the foreclosure referral ban where default is based upon a non-monetary provision of a mortgage. With respect to the Bureau's request for comment on other situations that may warrant exclusion, numerous commenters suggested the Bureau provide guidance or add exemptions for foreclosure based upon a determination that the property was abandoned or vacant. Some commenters advocated an exemption for abandoned properties and suggested the Bureau provide a list of factors to be considered in determining whether the property was abandoned. Consumer groups, however, expressed concerns that, because abandonment or vacancy status is necessarily a fact-specific determination, an exemption may facilitate evasion.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In addition, some commenters suggested the Bureau exempt situations where the borrower is deceased without heirs or in other cases. Some industry commenters requested that the rule permit foreclosure within the 120-day period where borrowers have failed to maintain insurance or property tax payments or where the borrower had failed to pay late fees. Finally, some commenters requested an exemption for other situations including where borrowers commit waste, are non-responsive to the servicer's attempts to maintain live contact, or state a desire to surrender the property.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Consumer groups acknowledged that situations may exist that warrant exclusion from the 120-day prohibition, such as the proposed exemptions, but raised concerns about their breadth. Specifically, these commenters expressed concerns that an exemption for all foreclosures based on violation of a due-on-sale clause may be overly broad, and could be construed to allow foreclosure where the transfer is to a deceased borrowers' family member or where a transfer occurs as a result of State divorce decree or probate order, or other transfer to a borrower's family member. Many of these commenters suggested that the exemption expressly exclude such transfers to the extent they were protected under the Garn-St. Germain Act.<footnote ref="25">Garn-St. Germain Depository Institutions Act, Public Law 97-320 (1982) (codified in various sections). The Act generally prohibits the exercise of due-on-sale clauses with respect to certain protected transfers. See 12 U.S.C. 1701j-3.</footnote> Consumer advocate commenters also suggested that the exemption for joining a foreclosure action of a subordinate lienholder should be limited to situations where all of the servicers and lienholders with respect to the property are separate entities.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting the amendments to § 1024.41(f)(1) as proposed, without adopting additional exemptions. The Bureau appreciates comments that suggested the 120-day prohibition was designed to protect delinquent borrowers, but should not extend to non-monetary defaults or breaches of the underlying mortgage agreement. However, the Bureau remains mindful of consumer protection concerns that could arise from a broader set of exemptions. For example, industry commenters suggested that foreclosure based on a borrower's failure to maintain insurance or pay property taxes should be excluded, but, as some of these commenters acknowledged, those and other examples provided are likely to coincide with borrower delinquency. The Bureau does not believe that servicers should be allowed to sidestep the borrower protections set forth in § 1024.41 for delinquent borrowers simply because borrowers may have breached other components of the underlying mortgage, such as requirements to pay property taxes, maintain insurance, or pay late fees. The Bureau believes that additional exemptions would create uncertainty and could potentially be construed in a manner that permits evasion of the requirements of § 1024.41(f). Moreover, the Bureau does not believe exemption from the pre-foreclosure review period is appropriate merely because foreclosure is based upon an obligation other than the borrower's monthly payment. In many instances, these borrowers are likely experiencing financial distress and thus may benefit from time to seek loss mitigation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>For similar reasons, the Bureau does not believe it is appropriate to adopt an exemption from the 120-day prohibition for situations where a borrower may be deemed to commit “waste” in violation of an underlying mortgage agreement. As noted above, the Bureau is concerned that such an exemption could be used to circumvent the 120-day prohibition for borrowers who are also delinquent. However, the Bureau also notes that what constitutes waste is very fact-specific and the few commenters who suggested an exemption provided no precise definition of the term. Furthermore, while mortgages typically permit foreclosure in the event of waste, they also frequently provide other non-foreclosure remedies. In light of the absence of evidence suggesting waste that would necessitate rapid foreclosure is a significant problem, the Bureau is convinced that no such exemption is necessary.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In addition, the Bureau does not believe any further narrowing or clarifying revisions to the due-on-sale clause exemption in § 1024.41(f)(1)(i), to protect transfers to family members or transfers ordered by divorce decree or probate proceedings, are necessary. The Bureau notes that, to the extent the Garn-St. Germain Act prohibits the exercise of due-on-sale clauses, the exemption from the 120-day period would not apply. The exemption does not alter limitations or obligations imposed on a servicer by another Federal or State law with respect to whether a due-on-sale clause validly may be exercised. Rather it merely provides an exception to the 120-day pre-foreclosure review period where the basis for foreclosure is a due-on-sale clause. The Bureau notes that servicers may not avail themselves of the due-on-sale clause exemption and make the first notice or filing before the 120th day of delinquency unless such a clause is validly enforceable.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is also not adopting any limitation on the exemption for joining a foreclosure initiated by a subordinate lienholder. The Bureau does not believe it is appropriate to limit the exemption application to only those situations where the senior and junior liens are held or serviced by separate entities, as was requested. In the case where an entity services both a first and a second lien, the servicer will be required to complete the pre-foreclosure review for the second lien, and will be required to respond to a borrower's loss mitigation application with respect to the first mortgage as well. Furthermore, the comments did not provide an adequate explanation to persuade the Bureau that servicers are more likely to pursue foreclosure in a manner that evades the 120-day pre-foreclosure review period when the senior and junior lien are held and serviced by the same entity.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau notes that several commenters requested that the Bureau exempt vacant or abandoned properties from the 120-day prohibition. However, while many commenters asserted that there is a limited benefit to prohibiting foreclosure referral where a property is “vacant” or “abandoned”, they also generally agreed that such a determination depends on the individual facts and circumstances, and may vary according applicable State law. While some commenters suggested the Bureau adopt a multiple-factor test to determine whether a property was “abandoned,” the Bureau believes any such test would inherently rely on a holistic determination based on individual facts and circumstances, and would not provide the clear guideline that the Bureau believes is appropriate with respect to the prohibition on foreclosure referral. Moreover, as noted by consumer groups, a number of borrower protection concerns could arise from affording servicers too much discretion in determining whether a property is abandoned or vacant. In addition, some industry commenters conceded that it would be rare for a property to be determined abandoned or vacant earlier than the 120th day of delinquency.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>For these reasons, the Bureau is not adopting an exclusion from the 120-day prohibition for vacant or abandoned properties. However, the Bureau notes that the provisions of §§ 1024.39 through 1024.41 apply only to a mortgage loan secured by property that is a borrower's principal residence. <em data-original="E-03">See</em> 12 CFR 1024.30(c)(2). Thus, depending on the facts and circumstances, it is possible that some foreclosures against vacant or abandoned properties will not be subject to § 1024.41(f).</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-h-4" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(h)(4) Appeal Determination</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to amend § 1024.41(h)(4) to provide expressly that the notice informing a borrower of the determination of his or her appeal must also state the amount of time the borrower has to accept or reject an offer of a loss mitigation option after the notice is provided to the borrower. The Bureau did not receive any comments on this provision and is finalizing it as proposed.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-j" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(j) Prohibition on Foreclosure Referral</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, the Bureau is adopting, as proposed, amendments to § 1024.41(f)(1) that exempt two situations from the prohibition on referral to foreclosure until after the 120th day of delinquency: When the foreclosure is based on a borrower's violation of a due-on-sale clause and when the servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a subordinate lienholder. The Bureau also proposed corresponding amendments to the provision in § 1024.41(j), which provides the same prohibition with respect to small servicers. While the Bureau received a number of comments regarding the proposed amendments to § 1024.41(f)(1) as discussed above, the Bureau received no comments addressing the corresponding amendments to § 1024.41(j). Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting, as proposed, the amendments to § 1024.41(j) to allow foreclosure before the 120th day of delinquency when the foreclosure is based on a borrower's violation of a due-on-sale clause and when the servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a subordinate lienholder, by incorporating a cross-reference to § 10124.41(f)(1).</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>Section 1024.41—Loss mitigation procedures</title>
      <analysisParagraph>As discussed above in part III (Legal Authority), the Bureau is finalizing amendments to § 1024.41 pursuant to its authority under sections 6(j)(3), 6(k)(1)(E), and 19(a) of RESPA. The Bureau believes that these amendments are necessary and appropriate to achieve the consumer protection purposes of RESPA and in particular of section 6 of RESPA, including to facilitate the evaluation of borrowers for foreclosure avoidance options. Further, the amendments implement, in part, section 6(k)(1)(C) of RESPA, which obligates a servicer to take timely action to correct errors relating to avoiding foreclosure, by establishing servicer duties and procedures that must be followed where appropriate to avoid such errors. In addition, the Bureau relies on its authority pursuant to section 1022(b) of the Dodd-Frank Act to prescribe regulations necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes and objectives of Federal consumer financial law, including the purpose and objectives under sections 1021(a) and (b) of the Dodd-Frank Act. The Bureau additionally relies on its authority under section 1032(a) of the Dodd-Frank Act, which authorizes the Bureau to prescribe rules to ensure that the features of any consumer financial product or service, both initially and over the terms of the product or service, are fully, accurately, and effectively disclosed to consumers in a manner that permits consumers to understand the costs, benefits, and risks associated with the product or service, in light of the facts and circumstances.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-b-3" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(b)(3) Determining Protections</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to add new § 1024.41(b)(3) addressing the borrowers' rights in situations in which no foreclosure sale has been scheduled as of the date a complete loss mitigation application is received, or a previously scheduled foreclosure sale is rescheduled after receipt of a complete application. As discussed in the proposal, § 1024.41 is structured to provide different procedural rights to borrowers and impose different requirements on servicers depending on the number of days remaining until a foreclosure sale is scheduled to occur, as of the time that a complete loss mitigation application is received. However, the provisions of § 1024.41 do not expressly address situations in which a foreclosure sale has not yet been scheduled at the time a complete loss mitigation application is received, or is rescheduled after the application is received. Since issuance of the final rule, the Bureau has received questions about the applicability of the timing provisions in such situations. Specifically, industry stakeholders have asked whether it is appropriate to use estimated dates of foreclosure where a foreclosure sale has not been scheduled at the time a complete loss mitigation application is received. Further, industry stakeholders have requested guidance on how to apply the timelines if no foreclosure is scheduled as of the date a complete loss mitigation application is received, but a foreclosure sale is subsequently scheduled less than 90 days after receipt of such application, or if a foreclosure sale has been scheduled for less than 90 days after a complete application is received, but is then postponed to a date that is 90 days or more after the receipt date.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed new § 1024.41(b)(3), which stated that, for purposes of § 1024.41, timelines based on the proximity of a foreclosure sale to the receipt of a complete loss mitigation application will be determined as of the date a complete loss mitigation application is received. Proposed comment 41(b)(3)-1 would have clarified that if a foreclosure sale has not yet been scheduled as of the date that a complete loss mitigation application is received, the application shall be treated as if it were received at least 90 days before a foreclosure sale. Proposed comment 41(b)(3)-2 would have clarified that such timelines would remain in effect even if at a later date a foreclosure sale was rescheduled.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believed this approach would provide certainty to both servicers and borrowers as well as ensure that borrowers receive the broadest protections available under the rule in situations in which a foreclosure sale has not been scheduled at the time a borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application. In the proposal, the Bureau also discussed alternative modifications to the rule, which the Bureau declined to propose, including having the applicable timelines vary depending on the newly scheduled (or re-scheduled) sale date, or allowing servicers to estimate when a foreclosure sale might be scheduled. On balance, the Bureau believed that a straightforward rule under which the protections that attach are determined as of the date of receipt of a complete loss mitigation application, and a complete loss mitigation application is treated as having been received 90 days or more before a foreclosure sale if no sale is scheduled as of the date the application is received, is preferable because it would provide industry and borrowers with clarity regarding its application, without the unnecessary complexity that other approaches might produce. The Bureau recognized that the proposed rule might in some cases require a servicer to delay a foreclosure sale to allow the specified time for the borrower to respond to a loss mitigation offer and to appeal the servicer's denial of a loan modification option, where applicable, and sought comment and supporting data regarding circumstances in which this may occur.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from industry as well as consumer groups addressing these proposed provisions. Overall, commenters appreciated the clarity and simplicity of the proposed rule. They supported the idea that borrower protection should be clear and certain. One consumer advocate expressed concern that the rule limits, but does not eliminate, dual tracking. This commenter was concerned that a sale may be scheduled with less than 37 days' notice. Another consumer advocate suggested the rule should always adopt the most consumer-friendly timeline. That is, if a sale is postponed, a borrower should receive the benefit of any extra protections that might arise given a longer time between the sale and the submission of a complete application; but if a sale is scheduled to occur on a short timeline, the borrower should not lose the original protections that had attached on the basis of the longer timeline.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Industry commenters expressed concern about the feasibility of the proposed rule. Such commenters were concerned this may inappropriately extend the timeline of a foreclosure sale. These commenters urged the Bureau to limit the appeal right to when a complete application is submitted within 30 days of the first notice or filing required for a foreclosure sale. Alternatively, some commenters urged the Bureau to allow servicers to estimate when a foreclosure sale may occur. For example, one commenter suggested such estimates could be based on estimates provided by nationally recognized sources. Finally, industry commenters expressed concern the proposed provision may not be feasible because a servicer may be unable to move a scheduled foreclosure sale. One commenter recommended the Bureau offer an exemption from liability when an investor or court requires a servicer to continue with a foreclosure sale in violation of the applicable timelines.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is finalizing § 1024.41(b)(3) and its related commentary substantially as proposed, but with minor wording changes. For the reasons discussed in the proposal, the Bureau believes the final rule appropriately balances consumer protection and servicer needs. This approach provides certainty to both servicers and borrowers, as well as ensures that borrowers receive the broadest protections available under the rule in situations where a foreclosure sale has not been scheduled at the time a complete loss mitigation application is received.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau declines to adopt other approaches suggested in comments. The Bureau notes that structuring the rule such that a borrower's rights may be added or removed because a foreclosure sale was moved or rescheduled would not provide the certainty or simplicity created by the proposed rule. Further, the Bureau is concerned that if moving a foreclosure sale to a later date could trigger new protections, such a policy may provide a disincentive for a servicer to reschedule a foreclosure sale for a later date. Finally, the Bureau does not believe it is appropriate to limit the appeal rights to when a complete application is submitted within 30 days of the first notice or filing, because, regardless of when a first notice or filing is made, a servicer should be able to provide a borrower an appeal when there is sufficient time before the scheduled foreclosure sale.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau does not believe that the rule being finalized, which grants the borrower certain rights if a borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application before a sale has been scheduled, will cause inappropriate delays in the foreclosure process. First, while some States may schedule foreclosure sales to occur in less than 90 days of the scheduling of the sale, completing the process of reviewing a loss mitigation application may not necessitate a delay in the scheduled sale. For example, if the scheduling of a sale occurs 30 days after a complete loss mitigation application is submitted, and the sale is scheduled for 60 days after the scheduling occurs, the servicer will have sufficient time to follow the complete loss mitigation procedures without having to move the foreclosure sale. Second, servicers control many of the timelines in the process, including the 30-day evaluation window, and the time to process an appeal. If a foreclosure sale is rescheduled to occur in less than 90 days after a borrower submitted a complete application, a servicer does have the option to review the application quickly and, in doing so, the servicer may avoid the need to postpone the foreclosure sale.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In situations where there is a conflict (a later scheduled foreclosure sale that does not allow a servicer or borrower sufficient time to complete the procedures required by the loss mitigation rules), the Bureau expects a servicer to take the necessary steps to avoid having the foreclosure sale occur before the loss mitigation review procedures run their course, including asking a court to move a scheduled foreclosure sale, if necessary. An important objective of the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules is to ensure that loss mitigation applications receive careful review, so that a servicer does not foreclose on a borrower who would have qualified for a loss mitigation option and who timely submitted a complete application for loss mitigation. Consistent with that objective, once a borrower has submitted an application, a servicer should carry out the procedures prescribed by the rule in light of the timing and content of the application. To permit a later scheduled (or rescheduled) foreclosure sale to cut short those procedures would be inconsistent with the objective just described. For these reasons, the Bureau finalizes the rule substantially as proposed, with minor wording changes.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-c-2-iii" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(c)(2)(iii) Payment Forbearance</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau proposed to modify § 1024.41(c)(2) to allow servicers to offer short-term forbearance to borrowers based on a review of an incomplete loss mitigation application, notwithstanding that provision's restriction on servicers offering a loss mitigation option to a borrower based on the review of an incomplete loss mitigation application. In adopting the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, the Bureau crafted broad definitions of “loss mitigation option” and “loss mitigation application” for purposes of § 1024.41, to provide a streamlined process in which a borrower will be evaluated for all available loss mitigation options at the same time, rather than having to apply multiple times to be evaluated for different options one at a time. Since publication of the final rule, however, both industry and consumer advocates have raised questions and concerns about how the rule applies in situations in which a borrower needs and requests only short-term forbearance. For instance, a number of servicers have inquired about whether the rule would prevent them from granting a borrower's request for waiver of late fees or other short-term relief after a natural disaster until the borrower submits all information necessary for evaluation of the borrower for long-term loss mitigation options. Additionally, both consumer advocates and servicers have raised questions about whether a borrower's request for short-term relief would later preclude a borrower from invoking the protections afforded by the rule if the borrower encounters a significant change in circumstances that warrants long-term loss mitigation alternatives.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau was conscious of the difficulties involved in distinguishing short-term forbearance programs from other types of loss mitigation and of the concern that some servicers may have significantly exacerbated borrowers' financial difficulties by using short-term forbearance programs inappropriately instead of reviewing the borrowers for long-term options. Nevertheless, the Bureau believed that it was possible to revise the rule to facilitate appropriate use of short-term payment forbearance programs without creating undue risk for borrowers who need to be evaluated for a full range of loss mitigation alternatives.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>At the outset, the Bureau noted that it does not construe the existing rule to require that servicers obtain a complete loss mitigation application prior to exercising their discretion to waive late fees. Additionally the Bureau noted that, under the rule as adopted, a servicer may offer any borrower any loss mitigation option if the borrower has not submitted a loss mitigation application or if the offer is not based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, as clarified in existing comment 41(c)(2)(i)-1.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>With regard to short-term forbearance programs that involve more than simply waiving late fees, such as where a servicer allows a borrower to forgo making a certain number of payments and then to catch up by spreading the unpaid amounts over some subsequent period of time, the Bureau believed that the issues raised by various stakeholders could most appropriately be addressed by providing more flexibility to servicers to provide such relief even if it is based on review of an incomplete loss mitigation application. Thus, the Bureau did not propose to change the current definition of loss mitigation option, which includes all forbearance programs. Rather, the Bureau proposed to relax the anti-evasion restriction in § 1024.41(c)(2)(i), which prohibits a servicer from offering a loss mitigation option based upon an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau thus proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), which would have allowed short-term payment forbearance programs to be offered based on a review of an incomplete loss mitigation application. The proposed exemption would have applied only to short-term payment forbearance programs. Proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iii)-1 stated that a payment forbearance program is a loss mitigation option for which a servicer allows a borrower to forgo making certain payments for a period of time. Short-term payment forbearance programs may be offered when a borrower is having a short-term difficulty brought on, for example, by a natural disaster. In such cases, the servicer offers a short-term payment forbearance arrangement to assist the borrower in managing the hardship. The Bureau explained that, in its view, it is appropriate for servicers to have the flexibility to offer short-term payment forbearance programs prior to receiving a complete loss mitigation application for all available loss mitigation options. Proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iii)-1 also would have explained that a short-term program is one that allows the forbearance of payments due over periods of up to two months.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau noted that, under the proposed approach, servicers that receive a request for short-term payment forbearance and grant such requests would remain subject to the requirements triggered by the receipt of a loss mitigation application in § 1024.41. Thus, as explained in proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iii)-2, if a servicer offers a payment forbearance program based on an incomplete loss mitigation application, the servicer still would be required to review the application for completeness, to send the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice to inform the borrower whether the application is complete or incomplete, and if incomplete what documents or additional information are required, and to use reasonable diligence to complete the loss mitigation application. If a borrower in this situation submits a complete application, the servicer must evaluate it for all available loss mitigation options. The Bureau believed that maintaining these requirements is important to ensure that borrowers are not inappropriately diverted into short-term forbearance programs without access to the full protections of the regulation. At the same time, if a borrower in fact does not want an evaluation for long-term options, the borrower may simply refrain from providing the additional information necessary to submit a complete application and the servicer will therefore not be required to conduct a full assessment for all options.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>To ensure that a borrower who is receiving an offer of short-term payment forbearance understands the options available, proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) would have required a servicer offering a short-term payment forbearance program to a borrower based on an incomplete loss mitigation application to include in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice additional information, specifically that: (1) The servicer has received an incomplete loss mitigation application and on the basis of that application the servicer is offering a short-term payment forbearance program; (2) absent further action by the borrower, the servicer will not be reviewing the incomplete application for other loss mitigation options; and (3) if the borrower would like to be considered for other loss mitigation options, he or she must submit the missing documents and information required to complete the loss mitigation application. The Bureau believed that providing borrowers this more specific information is important to ensure that borrowers do not face unwarranted delays and paperwork and that servicers do not misuse short-term forbearance to avoid addressing long-term problems.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iii)-3 to clarify servicers' obligations on receipt of a complete loss mitigation application. The proposed comment would have stated that, notwithstanding that a servicer may have offered a borrower a payment forbearance program after an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, and even if the borrower accepted the payment forbearance offer, a servicer must still comply with all requirements in § 1024.41 on receipt of a borrower's submission of a complete loss mitigation application. This proposed comment was intended to clarify that, even though payment forbearance may be offered as short-term assistance to a borrower, a borrower is still entitled to submit a complete loss mitigation application and receive an evaluation of such application for all available loss mitigation options. Although payment forbearance may assist a borrower with a short-term hardship, a borrower should not be precluded from demonstrating a long-term inability to afford the original mortgage, and being considered for long-term solutions, such as a loan modification, when that may be appropriate.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments from both industry and consumer group commenters on this provision. Commenters were generally very supportive of allowing an exclusion from the full loss mitigation procedures for short-term problems, that is, problems that can be quickly resolved (e.g., a borrower needed new tires for his or her car and thus falls a month behind on mortgage payments). They asserted that short-term problems are better resolved quickly and that the full loss mitigation procedures should apply only to consumers with long-term problems. One industry commenter stated that the paperwork of the full procedures would be seen as burdensome when a borrower had a short-term problem, and this would be perceived as poor customer service. Additionally, commenters pointed out that, under § 1024.41(i), a borrower is entitled to the full procedures for only a single complete loss mitigation application, and it would not be in the borrower's best interest to “waste” that single evaluation under the full procedures on a simple, short-term problem. Consumer advocate commenters suggested that borrowers should be warned before they use their single evaluation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Both consumer advocate and industry commenters expressed concern that the two-month forbearance contemplated by the proposed rule was too brief. Such commenters urged the Bureau to permit payment forbearances of as long as six months or a year, to allow borrowers the opportunity to resolve their problems (for example, attempting to find a new job) before using up their opportunities to be evaluated for long-term options, such as a loan modification. Further, commenters expressed that the industry standard for payment forbearance programs was longer than two months—often six months or even a year. Finally, commenters expressed that short-term forbearances were particularly important for addressing two situations, unemployment and natural disasters.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) generally as proposed. However, in light of comments received, the Bureau has made some adjustments to the proposed provisions. As discussed below, the Bureau is clarifying the servicer's reasonable diligence obligation when a borrower has been offered a payment forbearance based on evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, and the Bureau has adjusted the limit on the length of payment forbearances that would be allowed under this provision.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Payment forbearance based on an incomplete application. The Bureau is adopting, with some adjustments, the general exclusion for short-term forbearance from the prohibition on offering loss mitigation based on an incomplete application. The Bureau continues to believe this exclusion is appropriate, because it should provide servicers greater flexibility to address short-term problems quickly and efficiently. Further, because the exclusion applies to decisions based on review of incomplete loss mitigation applications, it will allow the borrower's short-term problems to be addressed while preserving a borrower's single use of the full § 1024.41 loss mitigation procedures.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau declines to exclude payment forbearance from the definition of loss mitigation. The final rule provides the same benefits in flexibility that would be achieved by revising the definition of loss mitigation while preserving important consumer protections. If a borrower requests payment forbearance, he or she should be regarded as having requested loss mitigation under the terms of § 1024.41, and the procedures generally required by the rule should take place. Further, the Bureau notes that a borrower always has the option of completing his or her loss mitigation application and receiving a full evaluation for all options. This is reflected in comment 41(c)(2)(iii)-3, which states that even if a servicer offers a borrower a payment forbearance program after an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, the servicer must still comply with all other requirements in § 1024.41 if the borrower completes his or her loss mitigation application.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau notes that the new provision addresses only payment forbearance that is offered based on an evaluation of an incomplete application. The Bureau is aware, as some commenters noted, that situations may arise where a borrower completes a loss mitigation application and goes through a full loss mitigation evaluation, and the end result is the borrower being offered a payment forbearance—which would exhaust his or her single use of the § 1024.41 loss mitigation procedures. The Bureau notes that some consumer advocates asked the Bureau to exempt any such loss mitigation evaluation from the successive request provision in § 1024.41(i), or require that such borrowers be warned so they know not to complete their application if they are seeking only payment forbearance.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>While the Bureau acknowledges these concerns, the Bureau notes that the proposal was limited to discussing payment forbearance based on incomplete applications, and comments addressing payment forbearance based on complete applications are beyond the scope of the proposed rule. Further, the Bureau notes that the loss mitigation rules are intended to address only procedures, and leave the substantive decisions on different loss mitigation programs to the discretion of the owner or assignee. Finally, the Bureau notes that any issues related to the second or successive request provision in § 1024.41(i) would more appropriately be addressed in a rulemaking focusing on that provision.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Payment forbearance and reasonable diligence. The proposed provision on payment forbearance included a modification to the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice, which would have required the notice to include additional information when a servicer was offering a borrower payment forbearance based on an incomplete application. While the Bureau believes it is important for borrowers to be informed that they are being offered payment forbearance based on an incomplete loss mitigation application and they may receive a full review for all other options by completing their applications, the Bureau believes that servicers should have flexibility to provide this message at the appropriate time. A servicer may, in some circumstances, need to communicate additional information regarding payment forbearance. For example, a servicer may require additional information—short of a complete loss mitigation application—to offer a borrower a payment forbearance program. Further, the Bureau acknowledges that a servicer may decide to offer a borrower payment forbearance at various stages of the loss mitigation process, and the message should be provided at the appropriate time. For example, if a servicer needs additional information before offering payment forbearance, the servicer might not decide to offer a borrower payment forbearance until after the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice has been sent out. In light of these considerations, the Bureau declines to finalize the provision regarding modification of the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice in the context of payment forbearance. Instead, the Bureau has amended comment 41(b)(1)-4, added paragraph 4.iii, which addresses a servicer's reasonable diligence obligations. The comment explains that, when a servicer offers a borrower payment forbearance based on an incomplete application, the servicer should notify the borrower that the borrower may complete the application to receive a full evaluation of all loss mitigation options available to the borrower.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes a servicer's diligence obligations may vary depending on the facts and circumstances. In some instances, it may be appropriate for servicers to include this additional information in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice. For example, if a servicer decides to offer a borrower payment forbearance based on the initial submission that establishes the loss mitigation application (e.g., the borrower calls the servicer and, on the basis of that call, the servicer decides to offer the borrower payment forbearance), the servicer might include the message (that the borrower is being offered payment forbearance but may complete the application to receive a full evaluation) in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice, along with the full list of information and documents necessary to complete the loss mitigation application. Alternatively, if the servicer wanted to offer the borrower a payment forbearance program, but needed a few additional documents to do so, the servicer might send a § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice explaining that the borrower has the option of submitting a few items and receiving payment forbearance, or submitting all the missing information and receiving a full evaluation. If the borrower submitted only the items for the payment forbearance and the servicer offered the borrower a payment forbearance program, at that time the servicer could to notify the borrower that he or she has the option of completing the application.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Conversely, if the servicer does not decide to offer a payment forbearance program based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application until after the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice has been sent, the servicer would still have the option of offering the borrower payment forbearance at that later time. The servicer would notify the borrower that he or she has the option of completing the application at the time the servicer offered the payment forbearance program.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>In addition, the Bureau is adding a new subpart to comment 41(b)(1)-4 to further elaborate on the servicer's reasonable diligence obligation when a borrower is considered for short-term forbearance under this provision. Once a borrower has begun a payment forbearance program, the Bureau believes the servicer need not continue to request missing items from the borrower during the course of the payment forbearance program, unless the borrower fails to comply with the payment forbearance program or the borrower indicates he or she would like to continue completing the application. Thus, comment 41(b)(1)-4.iii states that, once a servicer provides this notification, the servicer could suspend reasonable diligence efforts until near the end of the payment forbearance program, so long as the borrower remains in compliance with the payment forbearance program and does not request any further assistance.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, the Bureau believes that, unless the borrower has brought his or her loan current, it may be necessary for the servicer to contact the borrower prior to the end of the forbearance period to determine if the borrower wishes to complete the application and proceed with a full loss mitigation evaluation. Thus, comment 41(b)(1)-4.iii states that near the end of the program, and prior to the end of the forbearance period, it may be necessary for the servicer to contact the borrower to determine if the borrower wishes to complete the application and proceed with a full loss mitigation evaluation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Length of payment forbearance. The Bureau is amending the proposed interpretation of “short-term” forbearance, in light of public comments that supported the general exception, but suggested that an exception permitting only two-month forbearances would be of limited benefit to borrowers and servicers. The Bureau is persuaded that a two-month payment forbearance window may not allow the borrower sufficient time to remedy even some short-term problems. As adopted, comment 41(b)(2)(iii)-1 explains that “short-term” forbearance means a program that allows the forbearance of payments due over periods of no more than six months, as opposed to two months. The Bureau notes that this six-month period may cover time both before and after the payment forbearance was granted (for example, if a borrower is one month delinquent when a servicer offers a payment forbearance program, the program may only extend 5 months into the future). The Bureau believes the extended timeline allows the servicer sufficient flexibility to address most short-term situations.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed in the proposal, the Bureau was concerned that, if a servicer offered a borrower a payment forbearance of more than two months, the borrower may lose the benefit of the 120-day foreclosure referral prohibition in § 1024.41(f)(1), because the 120 days may run out during the course of the forbearance plan. The Bureau believes that, as part of a payment forbearance program as contemplated by this rule, a servicer should not foreclose on a borrower who is complying with the payment forbearance program. To make explicit that this restriction is an aspect of the payment forbearance programs permissible under the new provision, the Bureau has added a foreclosure protection clause to the payment forbearance provision in § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii).</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau received comments requesting longer payment forbearance programs and noting that existing programs that may be offered through HUD or HAMP, or by the Federal National Mortgage Association and Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation (collectively “GSEs”), may offer payment forbearance for periods extending beyond six months to a year, particularly in situations such as natural disaster or unemployment. The Bureau remains convinced that, if a borrower has a long-term problem, such a borrower should, if the borrower chooses, receive a full evaluation for all loss mitigation options. Because forbearance programs under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) should only be used for temporary problems, the Bureau believes it is important to reassess a borrower's situation after no more than six months.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>However, the new rule does not preclude a servicer from offering multiple successive short-term payment forbearance programs. As discussed below in the Section 1022(b)(2) of the Dodd-Frank Act analysis, the Bureau has sought to ensure that borrowers would receive significant benefits from the additional option without losing protections provided by § 1024.41. Commenters strongly felt that a short forbearance period would not provide much additional benefit to borrowers, and further explained that a payment forbearance of less than a year may interfere with existing programs under HUD, HAMP, and the GSEs. The Bureau acknowledges that a borrower will generate a significant unpaid debt over the course of a long forbearance period. However, the Bureau notes that a borrower who believes the circumstances warrant cutting a long forbearance short can receive a full review for all loss available mitigation options by submitting a complete loss mitigation application. In addition, the Bureau believes that the risk servicers would attempt to evade the full loss mitigation procedures by offering sequential six-month forbearances to delinquent borrowers is low. Thus, the Bureau believes that borrowers benefit more from renewable forbearance agreements than they would benefit from any limit the Bureau might impose at this time on the maximum number of forbearances. The Bureau notes, however, that while the final rule does not prohibit a servicer from offering multiple short-term forbearances under this provision, the Bureau intends to monitor how temporary forbearances are used after this final rule becomes effective and, if it determines servicers are inappropriately offering sequential payment forbearances, may address the issue in a later rulemaking or by other means at a later date.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-41-c-2-iv" notice="2013-22752_20140110" date="2013-10-01">
      <title>41(c)(2)(iv) Facially Complete Application</title>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>The Proposal</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed above, the Bureau proposed new § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv), which stated that if a servicer creates a reasonable expectation that a loss mitigation application is complete but later discovers additional documents or information is needed to evaluate the application, the servicer shall treat the application as complete as of the date the borrower had reason to believe the application was complete, for purposes of applying § 1024.41(f)(2) and (g), until the borrower has been given a reasonable opportunity to complete the loss mitigation application. This provision was designed to work together with proposed new comments 41(b)(2)(i)-1 and -2, as discussed above, to address situations when a servicer determines that an application the servicer previously determined to be complete (or to be missing particular information) is in fact is lacking additional information needed for evaluation.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau has received questions about the impact of an error in the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B), particularly in light of the short time the servicer has to review the information submitted by the borrower. As discussed above, the Bureau recognizes that, in certain circumstances, an application may appear to be complete (or to be missing only specific information), but the servicer, upon further evaluation, may determine that additional information is needed before the servicer can evaluate the borrower for all available loss mitigation options. The proposed commentary to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i) was intended to clarify that servicers are required to obtain the missing information in such situations. Proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) was intended to protect borrowers while a servicer requests the missing information.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iv)-1 would have clarified that a reasonable expectation is created when the borrower submits all the missing items (if any) identified in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice. When a reasonable expectation that a loss mitigation application is complete is created but the servicer later discovers that the application is incomplete, proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) would have provided that the servicer shall treat the application as complete for certain purposes until the borrower has been given a reasonable opportunity to supply the missing information necessary to complete the loss mitigation application. Specifically, under this provision, the servicer would need to treat the application as complete for purposes of the foreclosure referral prohibition in § 1024.41(f)(2) and the foreclosure sale limitations in § 1024.41(g). Proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) would have ensured that servicers that made bona fide mistakes in making initial determinations of completeness need not be considered in violation of the rule, and that borrowers do not lose protections under the rule due to such mistakes. The Bureau believed that, once a borrower is given reason to believe he or she has the benefit of certain protections (which are triggered by submission of a complete loss mitigation application), if the servicer discovers that an application is incomplete, the borrower should have a reasonable opportunity to complete the application before losing the benefit of such protections.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Proposed comment 41(c)(2)(iv)-2 would have provided guidance on what would be a reasonable opportunity for the borrower to complete a loss mitigation application. The comment states that a reasonable opportunity requires that the borrower be notified of what information is missing and be given sufficient time to gather the information and submit it to the servicer. The amount of time that is sufficient for this purpose would depend on the facts and circumstances.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believed that proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) would preserve servicers' obligation to conduct rigorous up-front reviews, while providing servicers the ability to correct a good-faith mistake or clerical error. Further, servicers seeking relief under the provision need only give borrowers a reasonable opportunity to provide the missing information, thus allowing a servicer to continue the foreclosure process if a borrower does not provide such information.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Comments</title>
        <analysisParagraph>As discussed above in the section-by-section analysis of § 1024.41(b)(2)(i), the Bureau received comments from industry as well a consumer groups addressing these proposed provisions. Commenters were generally supportive of the Bureau addressing situations where a servicer later discovers additional documents or information are required to complete a loss mitigation application. However, commenters sought additional clarification on several aspects of the proposed amendment. First, commenters sought clarification on when a borrower's rights or protections are triggered. Commenters also expressed concern that it was unclear when a reasonable expectation had been created. For example, one commenter stated that a servicer may argue a homeowner had no reasonable expectation even if a complete application was submitted. Second, commenters sought clarification as to what would be considered a reasonable amount of time for a borrower to complete an application. Commenters suggested a set number of days should be given. Finally, commenters asked what happens after the missing information is provided or a reasonable time passes and the borrower fails to provide the information. Some commenters stated that the application should be considered complete only as of the date the missing information was provided and the application was actually completed. Other commenters stated the application should be treated as if it were complete when the reasonable expectation was created. One commenter pointed out that the expectation should be created based on the borrower's action (submitting the items requested in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice), rather than on an action (or inaction) of the servicer. As this commenter noted, if a borrower initially submits a complete application, the related protections of the rule should be triggered when the borrower submits the application, not when the servicer sends the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice. Therefore, this commenter asserted, if a borrower is asked to provide certain items, the protections should be triggered when those items are provided, not when the servicer deems the application to be complete. Finally, some commenters suggested the proposed revisions should go further and require a confirmation notice, as well as provide additional guidance on the timing and content of that notice. For example, one commenter suggested that servicers should be required to explain the reason a particular document does not meet underwriting guidelines, rather than simply requesting the document again.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
      <analysisSection>
        <title>Final Rule</title>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is adopting a final version of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) that is similar to the proposed version, but with some modifications. First, the Bureau is not including the “reasonable expectation” standard set forth in the proposal. Instead, the provision as adopted states that, if a borrower submits all the missing information listed in the notice required pursuant to § 1026.41(b)(2)(i)(B), or if no additional information is requested in such notice, the application shall be considered “facially complete” and will trigger certain borrower protections. Upon further consideration, the Bureau believes the subjective nature of the term “reasonable expectation” could have resulted in unnecessary compliance challenges and confusion as to when a reasonable expectation had been established. The Bureau believes the concept of facial completeness, on the other hand, provides greater clarity to servicers and borrowers.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Second, the Bureau is modifying proposed § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) to enhance borrower protections by providing that servicers are required to treat a “facially complete” application as complete for purposes of the § 1026.41(h) appeal right and the borrower response timelines in § 1024.41(e). As discussed above, proposed § 1026.41(c)(2)(iv) would have required servicers to treat the application as complete for purposes of the foreclosure referral ban in § 1024.41(f)(2) and the foreclosure sale limitations in § 1024.41(g) until the borrower had been given a reasonable opportunity to supply the missing information necessary to complete the loss mitigation application. However, for purposes of the appeal right under § 1024.41(h) and the borrower response timelines under § 1024.41(e), the proposal would have treated the application as complete only once the borrower submitted the additional information or documents needed to evaluate the application. Thus, under the proposal, if a servicer gave a borrower a reasonable expectation that he or she had submitted a complete application more than 90 days before a scheduled foreclosure sale but later requested more information pursuant to new § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv), the borrower might not have received the right to an appeal or to a 14-day response time depending on the timing of the supplemental information request and the borrower's response. The Bureau has been persuaded that such a borrower should enjoy the benefit of the appeal right and the 14-day response timeline. Furthermore, the Bureau is persuaded by the comment that suggested that the protections of § 1024.41 should be triggered based on the date when a borrower submits all the documents and information as stated in the § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice, rather than when the servicer deems the application to be complete.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Thus, under § 1026.41(c)(2)(iv) as adopted by the final rule, if a borrower submits a facially complete application that is later found by the servicer to require additional information or corrected documents to be evaluated, and the borrower subsequently provides the corrected documents or information necessary to complete the application, the application is treated as complete, for the purposes of § 1024.41(d), (e), (f)(2), (g), and (h), as of the date it was facially complete. However, the 30-day window during which the servicer must evaluate the borrower for all available loss mitigation options (as required pursuant to § 1026.41(c)) will begin only when the servicer receives the missing information. The Bureau continues to believe there is little value in requiring a servicer to evaluate a loss mitigation application when a servicer has determined certain items of information are missing.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>Finally, Bureau has adopted new comment 41(c)(2)(iv)-2 to address situations in which a borrower fails to provide the missing information within a reasonable timeframe as prescribed by the servicer. This comment states that, if the borrower fails to complete the application within the reasonable timeframe, the servicer may treat the application as incomplete.</analysisParagraph>
        <analysisParagraph>The Bureau is not addressing in this final rule comments that suggested further protections for borrowers are needed, including additional notice requirements. The Bureau believes these concerns are adequately addressed. Several protections already established by the rule, including the requirement to have polices and procedures reasonable designed to achieve the objective of facilitating compliance with the requirement to send an accurate § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice (in § 1024.38(b)(2)(iv); the continuity of contact requirements in § 1024.40, and the obligation on the servicer to use reasonable diligence in completing an application already require that servicers work with borrowers to complete a loss mitigation application. For example, the reasonable diligence obligation requires servicers to promptly seek documents or information necessary to complete a loss mitigation application, which the Bureau believes includes an obligation to work proactively with borrowers when they discover any additional documents or information are needed to complete the application, as well as notify a borrower when a submitted document is insufficient to complete an application—for example, because a signature is missing. Servicers cannot be dilatory in seeking such materials or corrected documents. Given these and other protections and obligations, the Bureau believes borrowers will be adequately protected, because the rules should ensure they receive the benefits of foreclosure protections at the time their applications are facially complete, and will continue to receive those protections once they have submitted the additional materials. The Bureau notes that a servicer that complies with § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) will be deemed to have satisfied the requirement to provide an accurate § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice. The Bureau believes this approach appropriately balances the servicer's need to collect additional pieces of information while still providing protection for the borrower.</analysisParagraph>
      </analysisSection>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
