<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2013-10-23</date>
    <originalDate>2012-01-01</originalDate>
    <title>REAL ESTATE SETTLEMENT PROCEDURES ACT</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>X</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1024</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2013-24521</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2014-01-10</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2013/10/23/2013-24521/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation-x</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2013-22752" rightDocumentNumber="2013-24521">

    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-d">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-d" marker="(d)">
        <title type="keyterm">Exemptions</title>
        <content> </content>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-1" marker="(1)">
          <title type="keyterm">Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
          <content>A servicer is exempt from the requirements of this section for a mortgage loan while the borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy under Title 11 of the United States Code.</content>
          </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-2" marker="(2)">
          <title type="keyterm">Fair Debt Collections Practices Act.</title>
          <content>A servicer subject to the Fair Debt Collections Practices Act (FDCPA) (<ref target="USC:15-1692" reftype="external">15 U.S.C. 1692</ref> et seq.) with respect to a borrower is exempt from the requirements of this section with regard to a mortgage loan for which the borrower has sent a notification pursuant to FDCPA section 805(c) (<ref target="USC:15-1692" reftype="external">15 U.S.C. 1692</ref>c(c)).</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1024-39-c-Interp"/>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-d-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-Interp">
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp" target="1024-39-d-1" marker="(1)">
          <title>39(d)(1) Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title type="keyterm">Commencing a case.</title>
            <content>The requirements of § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> do not apply once a petition is filed under Title 11 of the United States Code, commencing a case in which the borrower is a debtor.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title type="keyterm">Obligation to resume early intervention requirements.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
              <content>With respect to any portion of the mortgage debt that is not discharged, a servicer must resume compliance with § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> after the first delinquency that follows the earliest of any of three potential outcomes in the borrower's bankruptcy case: the case is dismissed, the case is closed, or the borrower receives a discharge under <ref target="USC:11-727" reftype="external">11 U.S.C. 727</ref>, <ref target="USC:11-1141" reftype="external">1141</ref>, <ref target="USC:11-1228" reftype="external">1228</ref>, or <ref target="USC:11-1328" reftype="external">1328</ref>. However, this requirement to resume compliance with § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> does not require a servicer to communicate with a borrower in a manner that would be inconsistent with applicable bankruptcy law or a court order in a bankruptcy case. To the extent permitted by such law or court order, a servicer may adapt the requirements of § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> in any manner believed necessary.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Compliance with § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> is not required for any portion of the mortgage debt that is discharged under applicable provisions of the U.S. Bankruptcy Code. If the borrower's bankruptcy case is revived for example if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case, reopens the case, or revokes a discharge the servicer is again exempt from the requirement in § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref>.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
            <title type="keyterm">Joint obligors.</title>
            <content>When two or more borrowers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref>, the exemption in § <ref target="1024-39-d-1" reftype="internal">1024.39(d)(1)</ref> applies if any of the borrowers is in bankruptcy. For example, if a husband and wife jointly own a home, and the husband files for bankruptcy, the servicer is exempt from complying with § <ref target="1024-39" reftype="internal">1024.39</ref> as to both the husband and the wife.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
  <analysis>
    <analysisSection target="1024-39-d" notice="2013-24521" date="2013-10-23">
      <title>Section 1024.39Early intervention requirements for certain borrowers 1024.39(d) Exemptions</title>
      <analysisParagraph>The early intervention requirements in § 1024.39 are intended to provide delinquent borrowers with opportunities to pursue available loss mitigation options at the early stages of a delinquency by requiring that the servicer attempt to make live contact with the borrower and to issue a written notice. The requirements apply to each payment for which the borrower is delinquent, although the written notice must be provided only once every 180 days.<footnote ref="15">


          The Bureau has issued guidance to clarify how a servicer may comply with the requirements in § 1024.39 to make good faith efforts to establish live contact with a borrower in CFPB Bulletin 2013-12,available at https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/f/201310_cfpb_mortgage-servicing_bulletin.pdf.

        </footnote>
        In this interim final rule, the Bureau is adding new § 1024.39(d)(1), exempting a servicer from the early intervention requirements while a borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy, and new § 1024.39(d)(2), exempting a servicer from the early intervention requirements when a borrower has invoked the cease communication provisions under the Fair Debt Collections Practices Act (FDCPA).<footnote ref="16">

          15 U.S.C. 1692et seq.

        </footnote>

      </analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau first proposed the early intervention requirements in § 1024.39 on August 10, 2012. In the preamble to the proposed rule, the Bureau noted that servicers may be subject to State and Federal laws related to debt collection practices, such as the FDCPA. In addition, the preamble acknowledged that the Bankruptcy Code's automatic stay provisions generally prohibit, among other things, actions to collect, assess, or recover a claim against a debtor that arose before the debtor filed for bankruptcy.<footnote ref="17">


          See11 U.S.C. 362 (automatic stay);see also11 U.S.C. 524 (effect of discharge).
        </footnote>
        The Bureau invited comment on whether servicers may reasonably question how they could comply with the Bureau's proposal in light of those laws.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Several industry commenters expressed concern that the Bureau's rules overlap with and could conflict with existing State and Federal law. Several commenters requested guidance on whether servicers would be required to comply with the early intervention requirements if the borrower instructed the servicer to cease collection efforts, not to contact the borrower by telephone, or if the borrower refused to pay the debt. Several of these commenters requested that the Bureau include an exemption from the early intervention requirements in cases involving debt collection or bankruptcy law. One industry commenter requested that the Bureau clarify whether servicers would have immunity from claims of harassment or improper conduct under the FDCPA.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>With respect to addressing potential conflicts between the Bureau's rules and existing State and Federal law as well as existing industry practice, commenters identified a variety of ways the Bureau could provide relief, including by not adopting rules that exceed or otherwise conflict with existing requirements, providing safe harbors (such as by clarifying that compliance with existing laws and agreements satisfies § 1024.39), adopting more flexible standards, providing exemptions, including a mechanism in the rule to resolve compliance conflicts, or broadly preempting State laws.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>On January 17, 2013, the Bureau issued the 2013 RESPA Servicing Final Rule with early intervention requirements in § 1024.39 that included a conflicts of law provision specifying that servicers are not required to make contact with borrowers in a manner that may be prohibited by Federal laws, such as the FDCPA or the Bankruptcy Code's automatic stay provisions. The Bureau also added comment 39(c)-1, addressing borrowers in bankruptcy. The comment specified, “Section 1024.39 does not require a servicer to communicate with a borrower in a manner that would be inconsistent with applicable bankruptcylaw or a court order in a bankruptcy case. To the extent permitted by such law or court order, servicers may adapt the requirements of § 1024.39 in any manner that would permit them to notify borrowers of loss mitigation options.” In the preamble to the final rule, the Bureau stated that it did not seek to interpret the Bankruptcy Code through this comment, but instead intended to indicate that servicers could take a flexible approach to complying with § 1024.39 for borrowers in bankruptcy.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>

    <analysisSection target="1024-39-d-1" notice="2013-24521" date="2013-10-23">
      <title>1024.39(d)(1) Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
      <analysisParagraph>After publication of the 2013 RESPA Servicing Final Rule, industry stakeholders expressed continued concerns to the Bureau about complying with certain servicing requirements for borrowers under the protection of bankruptcy law. In general, and as discussed further below with regard to periodic statement requirements, servicers asserted that simply providing flexibility in accommodating bankruptcy law restrictions on communications with borrowers was not sufficient because they faced a substantial legal burden in determining when and how bankruptcy law provisions applied in the first instance. Servicers also expressed concern about how to fulfill the servicing rules' requirements in a way that did not confuse borrowers with regard to their status in bankruptcy and the fact that servicers were not attempting to collect on accounts. Bankruptcy trustees raised similar concerns about the likelihood of servicers providing information that will be confusing to borrowers/debtors, debtor attorneys, and even courts and trustees. Specifically, with regard to early intervention, industry sought additional guidance on whether the Bureau would require some attempt at compliance even if there was an automatic stay and whether servicers would be subject to claims by private litigants asserting that bankruptcy was not an excuse for a servicer's lack of performance under § 1024.39.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Based on these inquiries, the Bureau believes that the potential interactions between the § 1024.39 early intervention requirements and bankruptcy law requirements can be highly varied and complex. The Bankruptcy Code itself provides a robust set of consumer protections for debtors, including oversight of debt repayment plans, where applicable. However, whether certain communications with the borrower may violate an automatic stay or discharge injunction are fact-specific inquiries and can vary depending on the Chapter of the Bankruptcy Code at issue, the intention of the debtor to retain the property, and the frequency and detailed contents of the communications.<footnote ref="18">See infra note 35; see also In re Duke, 79 F.3d 43 (7th Cir. 1996) (holding creditor does not violate automatic stay when sending “nonthreatening and non-coercive” offer to reaffirm Chapter 7 debtor's pre-petition debt); In re Silva, No. 09-02504, 2010 WL 605578 (Bankr. D. Haw. Feb. 19, 2010) (“Nothing in the Bankruptcy Code prevents or prohibits a chapter 7 or chapter 13 debtor or its secured creditors from entering into communications or negotiations about the possibility of a loan modification.”)</footnote>
        Uncertainty with respect to loss mitigation-related communications has led federal regulators<footnote ref="19">See, e.g., HUD, Mortgagee Letter 2008-32 (Oct. 17, 2008) (“[M]ortgagees must, upon receipt of notice of a bankruptcy filing, send information to debtor's counsel indicating that loss mitigation may be available, and provide instruction sufficient to facilitate workout discussions including documentation requirements, timeframes and servicer contact information . . . . Nothing in this mortgagee letter requires that mortgagees make direct contact with any borrower under bankruptcy protection.”) (emphasis added) available at  http://www.hud.gov/offices/adm/hudclips/letters/mortgagee/2008ml.cfm; U.S. Dep't of Treasury, Making Home Affordable Program Handbook for Servicers of Non-GSE Loans, v.4.3 at 77, 80 (Sept. 16, 2013) (“Borrowers in active Chapter 7 or Chapter 13 bankruptcy cases are eligible for HAMP at the servicer's discretion in accordance with investor guidelines, but servicers are not required to solicit these borrowers proactively for HAMP . . . . Borrowers who have received a Chapter 7 bankruptcy discharge in a case involving the first lien mortgage who did not reaffirm the mortgage debt under applicable law are eligible for HAMP . . . . [A] servicer is deemed to have made a Reasonable Effort to solicit [those] borrower[s] after sending two written notices to the last address of record in addition to the two required written notices. . . .”) (emphasis added) available at  http://www.makinghomeaffordable.gov/for-partners/understanding-guidelines/Documents/mhahandbook_43.pdf.</footnote>
        and several bankruptcy courts<footnote ref="20">See, e.g., Amended General Order Regarding Negotiations Between Debtor(s) and Mortgage Servicer(s) to Consider Loan Modifications (Bankr. D.N.J. July 24, 2009) (“[C]ommunications and/or negotiations between debtors and mortgagees/mortgage servicers about loan modification shall not be deemed as a violation of the automatic stay . . . . [A]ny such communication or negotiation shall not be used by either party against the other in any subsequent litigation . . . .”) available at http://www.njb.uscourts.gov/sites/default/files/general-ordes/2009_07_27_generalOrderLoanModify2.pdf; Bankr. W.D. Wash. R. 4001-2(b) (“A mortgage creditor's contact with the debtor and/or the debtor's counsel for the purposes of negotiating a loan modification shall not be considered a violation of the automatic stay imposed by 11 U.S.C. 362.”). While these two courts' rules might permit some communications regarding loan modifications, their approach is not necessarily generally accepted.</footnote>
        to issue guidelines or rules for servicers on the interaction between those communications and bankruptcy law. While some sources identified by the Bureau suggest that it is permissible for servicers to engage in loss mitigation negotiations with borrowers who have invoked bankruptcy protections, they do not address affirmative outreach directly to the borrower to solicit discussions about loss mitigation options.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>In addition, when a borrower is under bankruptcy protections, the benefits of continuing early intervention contacts may depend on the context. Borrowers who became delinquent on their mortgage loans prior to filing bankruptcy will likely already have received early intervention contacts from the servicer and thus will already be on notice about the availability of potential loss mitigation options. In such cases, continuing contacts may have limited if any utility. And while the small group of borrowers who file bankruptcy without first becoming delinquent on their mortgage loans might benefit from information regarding the availability of loss mitigation information, the Bureau is concerned that additional guidance is needed to ensure that any early intervention contacts communicate effectively regarding the borrower's status in bankruptcy and do not instead create borrower confusion.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The Bureau believes that further study of these issues is warranted but cannot be concluded quickly enough to provide further calibration of the requirements before January 2014. Therefore, the interim final rule adds § 1024.39(d)(1), which exempts servicers from the requirements of § 1024.39 for a mortgage loan while the borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy. However, the Bureau is not taking any position on whether early intervention efforts generally may violate an automatic stay or discharge injunction and encourages servicers who communicate with borrowers in bankruptcy about loss mitigation options to continue such tailored communications so far as bankruptcy law permits. The Bureau believes that some borrowers facing the complexities of bankruptcy could benefit from receiving loss mitigation information in some tailored form that is appropriate to their circumstances.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Because of the new exemption addressing bankruptcy in § 1024.39(d)(1), the interim final rule removes comment 39(c)-1 and incorporates it into new commentary in § 1024.39(d)(1)-2, as discussed below. Comment 39(d)(1)-1 clarifies that the exemption begins once a petition has been filed commencing a case under Title 11 of the United States Code in which the borrower is a debtor. Comment 39(d)(1)-2 clarifies that with respect to any portion of the mortgage debt that is not discharged, a servicer must resume compliance with § 1024.39 after the first delinquency that follows the earliest of any of three potential outcomes in the borrower's bankruptcy case: (i) the case is dismissed, (ii) the case is closed, or (iii) the borrower receives a discharge under 11 U.S.C. §§ 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328. However, this requirement to resume compliance does not require a servicer to communicate with a borrower in a manner that would be inconsistent with applicable bankruptcy law or a court order in a bankruptcy case. To the extent permitted by such law or court order, a servicer may adapt the requirements of § 1024.39 in any manner believed necessary. Compliance with § 1024.39 is not required for any portion of the mortgage debt that is discharged under applicable provisions of the U.S. Bankruptcy Code. If the borrower's bankruptcy case is revived for example if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case, reopens the case, or revokes a discharge the servicer is again exempt from the requirement in § 1024.39. Comment 39(d)(1)-3 clarifies that the exemption applies when any of the borrowers who are joint obligors with primary liability on the mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>For the reasons discussed, the Bureau is providing this exemption at this time, particularly because of the complex compliance concerns and the impending effective date of the 2013 RESPA Servicing Final Rule. The Bureau will continue to examine this issue and may reinstate an early intervention requirement with respect to borrowers in bankruptcy, but it will not reinstate any such requirement without notice and comment rulemaking and an appropriate implementation period. The Bureau solicits comment on the scope of the exemption, the triggers for meeting the exemption and having to resume early intervention, and how the early intervention communications might be tailored to meet the particular needs of borrowers in bankruptcy. The Bureau also seeks comment on other factors the Bureau should take into consideration in determining whether to reinstate any type of early intervention requirement with respect to borrowers in bankruptcy.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph><em data-original="E-03">Legal Authority.</em> The Bureau uses its authority under RESPA sections 6(j)(3) and 19(a) to exempt servicers from the early intervention requirements in § 1024.39 for a mortgage loan while the borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy and to adopt related official Bureau interpretations in Supplement I to Part 1024. For the reasons discussed above, the Bureau does not believe at this time that the consumer protection purposes of RESPA would be furthered by requiring servicers to comply with § 1024.39 for a mortgage loan while the borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
    <analysisSection target="1024-39-d-2" notice="2013-24521" date="2013-10-23">
      <title>1024.39(d)(2) Fair Debt Collection Practices Act</title>
      <analysisParagraph>A servicer of defaulted mortgage loans may also be a debt collector under the FDCPA. The FDCPA grants debtors the right generally to bar debt collectors from communicating with them regarding the debt by sending a written “cease communication” request.<footnote ref="21">15 U.S.C. 1692c(c).</footnote>
        As discussed above, the Bureau is separately issuing a bulletin that concludes that the FDCPA “cease communication” provision does not override servicers' obligations to have various communications with borrowers that are specifically mandated by the Dodd-Frank Act or to respond to certain borrower-initiated communications in accordance with the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules.<footnote ref="22">The new mortgage servicing rules that do not exempt servicers based on their status as debt collectors under the FDCPA are, in Regulation X, 12 CFR 1024.35 (error resolution), 1024.36 (requests for information), 1024.37 (force-place insurance), and 1024.41 (loss mitigation) and, in Regulation Z, 12 CFR 1026.20(d) (ARM initial interest rate adjustment) and 1026.41 (periodic statement). See CFPB Bulletin 2013-12, available at https://s3.amazonaws.com/files.consumerfinance.gov/f/201310_cfpb_mortgage-servicing_bulletin.pdf. Note that, elsewhere in this interim final rule, the Bureau is issuing an exemption for § 1026.20(c) similar to the one for § 1024.39.</footnote>
        However, because the early intervention requirements are neither statutorily mandated nor borrower-initiated, the interplay between the early intervention requirements and the “cease communication” provision of the FDCPA is less clear than it is with the servicing provisions discussed in the bulletin.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>Therefore, new § 1024.39(d)(2) exempts a servicer that is a debt collector under the FDCPA with respect to a borrower from the requirements of § 1024.39 after the borrower has exercised this “cease communication” right. The exemption provides a servicer that is a debt collector under the FDCPA with certainty that it has no obligations under § 1024.39 with regard to a borrower who has followed FDCPA procedure and instructed the servicer/debt collector to stop communicating with the borrower about the debt. The Bureau is not, however, making a determination as to the legal status of intervention efforts following receipt of proper cease communication requests, and servicers are encouraged to pursue loss mitigation options to the extent that the FDCPA permits.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph>The CFPB will be exploring the legal issues and practical benefits of requiring some type of early intervention to notify borrowers of the potential availability of loss mitigation options, in an upcoming rulemaking on debt collection. Balancing the rights of debtors to protect themselves against certain debt collector practices with the consumer protections afforded by servicer-borrower contact that may lead to the resolution of borrower default is more appropriately addressed in the broader context of a notice-and-comment rulemaking. For this reason, the interim final rule revises § 1024.39 to add the exemption discussed above and provide clarity to stakeholders, but the Bureau notes that the future rulemaking on debt collection may alter or eliminate this exemption.</analysisParagraph>
      <analysisParagraph><em data-original="E-03">Legal Authority.</em> The Bureau uses its authority under RESPA sections 6(j)(3) and 19(a) to exempt a servicer that is a debt collector pursuant to the FDCPA with regard to a mortgage loan from the early intervention requirements in § 1024.39 when a borrower has exercised the “cease communication” right under the FDCPA prohibiting the servicer/debt collector from communicating with the borrower regarding the debt. For the reasons discussed above, the Bureau believes at this time that the consumer protection purposes of RESPA would not be furthered by requiring compliance with § 1024.39 at a time when a borrower has specifically requested the servicer/debt collector to stop communicating with the borrower about the debt.</analysisParagraph>
    </analysisSection>
  </analysis>
</notice>
