<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2016-10-19</date>
    <originalDate>2016-10-19</originalDate>
    <title>REAL ESTATE SETTLEMENT PROCEDURES ACT</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>X</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1024</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-18901</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2017-10-19</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/10/19/2016-18901/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation-x</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2015-18239" rightDocumentNumber="2016-18901">
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-6-d-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-6-d-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>No changes to, deletions from, or additions to the special information booklet currently prescribed by the Bureau shall be made other than the permissible changes specified in paragraphs (d)(2) and (3) of this section or changes as otherwise approved in writing by the Bureau in accordance with the procedures described in this paragraph (d). A request to the Bureau for approval of any changes other than the permissible changes specified in paragraphs (d)(2) and (3) of this section shall be submitted in writing to the address indicated in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2, stating the reasons why the applicant believes such changes, deletions, or additions are necessary.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-6-d-2">
      <paragraph label="1024-6-d-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>The cover of the booklet may be in any form and may contain any drawings, pictures, or artwork, provided that the words “settlement costs” are used in the title. Names, addresses and telephone numbers of the lender or others and similar information may appear on the cover, but no discussion of the matters covered in the booklet shall appear on the cover.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-9-a-5">
      <paragraph label="1024-9-a-5" marker="(5)">
        <content>The following variations in layout and format are within the discretion of persons reproducing the HUD-1 and do not require prior Bureau approval: Size of pages; tint or color of pages; size and style of type or print; vertical spacing between lines or provision for additional horizontal space on lines (for example, to provide sufficient space for recording time periods used in prorations); printing of the HUD-1 contents on separate pages, on the front and back of a single page, or on one continuous page; use of multicopy tear-out sets; printing on rolls for computer purposes; reorganization of sections B through I, when necessary to accommodate computer printing; and manner of placement of the HUD number, but not the OMB approval number, neither of which may be deleted. The expiration date associated with the OMB number listed on the form may be deleted. Any changes in the HUD number or OMB approval number may be announced by notice in the Federal Register, rather than by amendment of this part.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-9-c">
      <paragraph label="1024-9-c" marker="(c)">
        <title>Written approval.</title>
        <content>Any other deviation in the HUD-1 or HUD-1A forms is permissible only upon receipt of written approval of the Bureau; provided, however, that notwithstanding contrary instructions in this section or appendix A of this part, reproducing the HUD-1 or HUD-1A forms with the Bureau's OMB approval number displayed in place of HUD's OMB approval number does not require the written approval of the Bureau. A request to the Bureau for approval shall be submitted in writing to the address indicated in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2 and shall state the reasons why the applicant believes such deviation is needed. The prescribed form(s) must be used until approval is received.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-17-h-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-17-h-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>The format and a completed example for an initial escrow account statement are set out in Public Guidance Documents entitled “Initial Escrow Account Disclosure Statement—Format” and “Initial Escrow Account Disclosure Statement—Example,” available in accordance with the direction in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-31-Delinquency" parent="1024-31" after="1024-31-Day">
      <paragraph label="1024-31-Delinquency" marker="">
        <content><def term="delinquency">Delinquency</def> means a period of time during which a borrower and a borrower's mortgage loan obligation are delinquent. A borrower and a borrower's mortgage loan obligation are delinquent beginning on the date a periodic payment sufficient to cover principal, interest, and, if applicable, escrow becomes due and unpaid, until such time as no periodic payment is due and unpaid.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-c-2-v">
      <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>A statement that:</content>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>The borrower's hazard insurance is expiring, has expired, or provides insufficient coverage, as applicable;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>The servicer does not have evidence that the borrower has hazard insurance coverage past the expiration date or evidence that the borrower has hazard insurance that provides sufficient coverage, as applicable; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>If applicable, identifies the type of hazard insurance for which the servicer lacks evidence of coverage;</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-c-4">
      <paragraph label="1024-37-c-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Additional information.</title>
        <content>Except for the mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (c)(2) of this section in the written notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(i) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii" subpath="title">
      <title>Servicer lacking evidence of continuous coverage.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer that has received hazard insurance information after delivering to a borrower or placing in the mail the notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(i) of this section, but has not received, from the borrower or otherwise, evidence demonstrating that the borrower has had sufficient hazard insurance coverage in place continuously, must set forth in the notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section the following information:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii-B" subpath="content">
      <content>The information required by paragraphs (c)(2)(ii) through (iv) and (ix) through (xi) and (d)(2)(i)(B) and (D) of this section;</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-3" subpath="title">
      <title>Format.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-3" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer must set the information required by paragraphs (d)(2)(i)(B) and (D) of this section in bold text. The requirements of paragraph (c)(3) of this section apply to the information required by paragraph (d)(2)(i)(C) of this section. A servicer may use form MS-3B in appendix MS-3 of this part to comply with the requirements of paragraphs (d)(1) and (d)(2)(i) of this section. A servicer may use form MS-3C in appendix MS-3 of this part to comply with the requirements of paragraphs (d)(1) and (d)(2)(ii) of this section.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-4" subpath="title">
      <title>Additional information.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Except for the borrower's mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (d)(2)(i) or (ii) of this section, as applicable, in the written notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-e-4" subpath="title">
      <title>Additional information.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-e-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Except for the borrower's mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (e)(2) of this section in the written notice required by paragraph (e)(1) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-38-b-2-vi">
      <paragraph label="1024-38-b-2-vi" marker="(vi)">
        <content>Promptly identify and obtain documents or information not in the borrower's control that the servicer requires to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, to offer the borrower in accordance with the requirements of § 1024.41(c)(4).</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-a" marker="(a)">
        <title>Live contact.</title>
        <content>Except as otherwise provided in this section, a servicer shall establish or make good faith efforts to establish live contact with a delinquent borrower no later than the 36th day of a borrower's delinquency and again no later than 36 days after each payment due date so long as the borrower remains delinquent. Promptly after establishing live contact with a borrower, the servicer shall inform the borrower about the availability of loss mitigation options, if appropriate.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1" subpath="title">
      <title>Notice required.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Except as otherwise provided in this section, a servicer shall provide to a delinquent borrower a written notice with the information set forth in paragraph (b)(2) of this section no later than the 45th day of the borrower's delinquency and again no later than 45 days after each payment due date so long as the borrower remains delinquent. A servicer is not required to provide the written notice, however, more than once during any 180-day period. If a borrower is 45 days or more delinquent at the end of any 180-day period after the servicer has provided the written notice, a servicer must provide the written notice again no later than 180 days after the provision of the prior written notice. If a borrower is less than 45 days delinquent at the end of any 180-day period after the servicer has provided the written notice, a servicer must provide the written notice again no later than 45 days after the payment due date for which the borrower remains delinquent.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-c">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-c" marker="(c)">
        <title>Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1" marker="(1)">
          <title>Partial exemption.</title>
          <content>While any borrower on a mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code, a servicer, with regard to that mortgage loan:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (a) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section if no loss mitigation option is available, or if any borrower on the mortgage loan has provided a notification pursuant to the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) section 805(c) (15 U.S.C. 1692c(c)) with respect to that mortgage loan as referenced in paragraph (d) of this section; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <content>If the conditions of paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section are not met, must comply with the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section, as modified by this paragraph (c)(1)(iii):</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>If a borrower is delinquent when the borrower becomes a debtor in bankruptcy, a servicer must provide the written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section not later than the 45th day after the borrower files a bankruptcy petition under title 11 of the United States Code. If the borrower is not delinquent when the borrower files a bankruptcy petition, but subsequently becomes delinquent while a debtor in bankruptcy, the servicer must provide the written notice not later than the 45th day of the borrower's delinquency. A servicer must comply with these timing requirements regardless of whether the servicer provided the written notice in the preceding 180-day period.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section may not contain a request for payment.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>A servicer is not required to provide the written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section more than once during a single bankruptcy case.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2" marker="(2)">
          <title>Resuming compliance.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(2)(ii) of this section, a servicer that was exempt from paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section pursuant to paragraph (c)(1) of this section must resume compliance with paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section after the next payment due date that follows the earliest of the following events:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>The bankruptcy case is dismissed;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The bankruptcy case is closed; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>The borrower reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>With respect to a mortgage loan for which the borrower has discharged personal liability pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328, a servicer:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Is not required to resume compliance with paragraph (a) of this section; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Must resume compliance with paragraph (b) of this section if the borrower has made any partial or periodic payment on the mortgage loan after the commencement of the borrower's bankruptcy case.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-d">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-d" marker="(d)">
        <title>Fair Debt Collection Practices Act—partial exemption.</title>
        <content>With regard to a mortgage loan for which any borrower has provided a notification pursuant to the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) section 805(c) (15 U.S.C. 1692c(c)), a servicer subject to the FDCPA with respect to that borrower's loan:</content>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-1" marker="(1)">
          <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (a) of this section;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-2" marker="(2)">
          <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section if no loss mitigation option is available, or while any borrower on that mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code as referenced in paragraph (c) of this section; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3" marker="(3)">
          <content>If the conditions of paragraph (d)(2) of this section are not met, must comply with the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section, as modified by this paragraph (d)(3):</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>In addition to the information required pursuant to paragraph (b)(2) of this section, the written notice must include a statement that the servicer may or intends to invoke its specified remedy of foreclosure. Model clause MS-4(D) in appendix MS-4 to this part may be used to comply with this requirement.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>The written notice may not contain a request for payment.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <content>A servicer is prohibited from providing the written notice more than once during any 180-day period.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-1" subpath="title">
      <title>Complete loss mitigation application.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii) of this section, if a servicer receives a complete loss mitigation application more than 37 days before a foreclosure sale, then, within 30 days of receiving the complete loss mitigation application, a servicer shall:</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iii">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii" marker="iii.">
        <title>Short-term loss mitigation options.</title>
        <content>Notwithstanding paragraph (c)(2)(i) of this section, a servicer may offer a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan to a borrower based upon an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. Promptly after offering a payment forbearance program or a repayment plan under this paragraph (c)(2)(iii), unless the borrower has rejected the offer, the servicer must provide the borrower a written notice stating the specific payment terms and duration of the program or plan, that the servicer offered the program or plan based on an evaluation of an incomplete application, that other loss mitigation options may be available, and that the borrower has the option to submit a complete loss mitigation application to receive an evaluation for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower regardless of whether the borrower accepts the program or plan. A servicer shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, and shall not move for foreclosure judgment or order of sale or conduct a foreclosure sale, if a borrower is performing pursuant to the terms of a payment forbearance program or repayment plan offered pursuant to this paragraph (c)(2)(iii). A servicer may offer a short-term payment forbearance program in conjunction with a short-term repayment plan pursuant to this paragraph (c)(2)(iii).</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iv">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-2-iv" marker="iv.">
        <title>Facially complete application.</title>
        <content>A loss mitigation application shall be considered facially complete when a borrower submits all the missing documents and information as stated in the notice required under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section, when no additional information is requested in such notice, or once the servicer is required to provide the borrower a written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(3)(i) of this section. If the servicer later discovers that additional information or corrections to a previously submitted document are required to complete the application, the servicer must promptly request the missing information or corrected documents and treat the application as complete for the purposes of paragraphs (f)(2) and (g) of this section until the borrower is given a reasonable opportunity to complete the application. If the borrower completes the application within this period, the application shall be considered complete as of the date it first became facially complete, for the purposes of paragraphs (d), (e), (f)(2), (g), and (h) of this section, and as of the date the application was actually complete for the purposes of this paragraph (c). A servicer that complies with this paragraph (c)(2)(iv) will be deemed to have fulfilled its obligation to provide an accurate notice under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-3">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3" marker="(3)">
        <title>Notice of complete application.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(3)(ii) of this section, within 5 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) after receiving a borrower's complete loss mitigation application, a servicer shall provide the borrower a written notice that sets forth the following information:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>That the loss mitigation application is complete;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The date the servicer received the complete application;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>That the servicer expects to complete its evaluation within 30 days of the date it received the complete application;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>That the borrower is entitled to certain foreclosure protections because the servicer has received the complete application, and, as applicable, either:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>If the servicer has not made the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, that the servicer cannot make the first notice or filing required to commence or initiate the foreclosure process under applicable law before evaluating the borrower's complete application; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>If the servicer has made the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, that the servicer has begun the foreclosure process, and that the servicer cannot conduct a foreclosure sale before evaluating the borrower's complete application;</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-E" marker="(E)">
            <content>That the servicer may need additional information at a later date to evaluate the application, in which case the servicer will request that information from the borrower and give the borrower a reasonable opportunity to submit it, the evaluation process may take longer, and the foreclosure protections could end if the servicer does not receive the information as requested; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-F" marker="(F)">
            <content>That the borrower may be entitled to additional protections under State or Federal law.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>A servicer is not required to provide a notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(3)(i) of this section if:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The servicer has already provided the borrower a notice under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section informing the borrower that the application is complete and the servicer has not subsequently requested additional information or a corrected version of a previously submitted document from the borrower pursuant to paragraph (c)(2)(iv) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The application was not complete or facially complete more than 37 days before a foreclosure sale; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The servicer has already provided the borrower a notice regarding the application under paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-4">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Information not in the borrower's control</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-i" marker="(i)">
          <title>Reasonable diligence.</title>
          <content>If a servicer requires documents or information not in the borrower's control to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower, the servicer must exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining such documents or information.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title>Effect in case of delay.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A" marker="">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) of this section, a servicer must not deny a complete loss mitigation application solely because the servicer lacks required documents or information not in the borrower's control.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>If a servicer has exercised reasonable diligence to obtain required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, but the servicer has been unable to obtain such documents or information for a significant period of time following the 30-day period identified in paragraph (c)(1) of this section, and the servicer, in accordance with applicable requirements established by the owner or assignee of the borrower's mortgage loan, is unable to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer the borrower without such documents or information, the servicer may deny the application and provide the borrower with a written notice in accordance with paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section. When providing the written notice in accordance with paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section, the servicer must also provide the borrower with a copy of the written notice required by paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>If a servicer is unable to make a determination within the 30-day period identified in paragraph (c)(1) of this section as to which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower because the servicer lacks required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, the servicer must, within such 30-day period or promptly thereafter, provide the borrower a written notice, informing the borrower:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>That the servicer has not received documents or information not in the borrower's control that the servicer requires to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower on behalf of the owner or assignee of the mortgage;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>Of the specific documents or information that the servicer lacks;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-3" marker="(3)">
              <content>That the servicer has requested such documents or information; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-4" marker="(4)">
              <content>That the servicer will complete its evaluation of the borrower for all available loss mitigation options promptly upon receiving the documents or information.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>If a servicer must provide a notice required by paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B) of this section, the servicer must not provide the borrower a written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section until the servicer receives the required documents or information referenced in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B)(2) of this section, except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) of this section. Upon receiving such required documents or information, the servicer must promptly provide the borrower with the written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-f-1-iii" subpath="content">
      <content>The servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a superior or subordinate lienholder.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i" subpath="title">
      <title>Duplicative requests.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer must comply with the requirements of this section for a borrower's loss mitigation application, unless the servicer has previously complied with the requirements of this section for a complete loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower and the borrower has been delinquent at all times since submitting the prior complete application.</content>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-k">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-k" marker="(k)">
        <title>Servicing transfers—</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1" marker="(1)">
          <title>In general—</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Timing of compliance.</title>
            <content>Except as provided in paragraphs (k)(2) through (4) of this section, if a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which a loss mitigation application is pending as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must comply with the requirements of this section for that loss mitigation application within the timeframes that were applicable to the transferor servicer based on the date the transferor servicer received the loss mitigation application. All rights and protections under paragraphs (c) through (h) of this section to which a borrower was entitled before a transfer continue to apply notwithstanding the transfer.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Transfer date defined.</title>
            <content>For purposes of this paragraph (k), the transfer date is the date on which the transferee servicer will begin accepting payments relating to the mortgage loan, as disclosed on the notice of transfer of loan servicing pursuant to § 1024.33(b)(4)(iv).</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2" marker="(2)">
          <title>Acknowledgment notices—</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Transferee servicer timeframes.</title>
            <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which the period to provide the notice required by paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section has not expired as of the transfer date and the transferor servicer has not provided such notice, the transferee servicer must provide the notice within 10 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) of the transfer date.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Prohibitions.</title>
            <content>A transferee servicer that must provide the notice required by paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section under this paragraph (k)(2):</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process until a date that is after the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section, notwithstanding paragraph (f)(1) of this section. For purposes of paragraph (f)(2) of this section, a borrower who submits a complete loss mitigation application on or before the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section shall be treated as having done so during the pre-foreclosure review period set forth in paragraph (f)(1) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Shall comply with paragraphs (c), (d), and (g) of this section if the borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application to the transferee or transferor servicer 37 or fewer days before the foreclosure sale but on or before the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-3" marker="(3)">
          <title>Complete loss mitigation applications pending at transfer.</title>
          <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which a complete loss mitigation application is pending as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must comply with the applicable requirements of paragraphs (c)(1) and (4) of this section within 30 days of the transfer date.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4" marker="(4)">
          <title>Applications subject to appeal process.</title>
          <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which an appeal of a transferor servicer's determination pursuant to paragraph (h) of this section has not been resolved by the transferor servicer as of the transfer date or is timely filed after the transfer date, the transferee servicer must make a determination on the appeal if it is able to do so or, if it is unable to do so, must treat the appeal as a pending complete loss mitigation application.</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Determining appeal.</title>
            <content>If a transferee servicer is required under this paragraph (k)(4) to make a determination on an appeal, the transferee servicer must complete the determination and provide the notice required by paragraph (h)(4) of this section within 30 days of the transfer date or 30 days of the date the borrower made the appeal, whichever is later.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Servicer unable to determine appeal.</title>
            <content>A transferee servicer that is required to treat a borrower's appeal as a pending complete loss mitigation application under this paragraph (k)(4) must comply with the requirements of this section for such application, including evaluating the borrower for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower from the transferee servicer. For purposes of paragraph (c) or (k)(3) of this section, as applicable, such a pending complete loss mitigation application shall be considered complete as of the date the appeal was received by the transferor servicer or the transferee servicer, whichever occurs first. For purposes of paragraphs (e) through (h) of this section, the transferee servicer must treat such a pending complete loss mitigation application as facially complete under paragraph (c)(2)(iv) as of the date it was first facially complete or complete, as applicable, with respect to the transferor servicer.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-5" marker="(5)">
          <title>Pending loss mitigation offers.</title>
          <content>A transfer does not affect a borrower's ability to accept or reject a loss mitigation option offered under paragraph (c) or (h) of this section. If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which the borrower's time period under paragraph (e) or (h) of this section for accepting or rejecting a loss mitigation option offered by the transferor servicer has not expired as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must allow the borrower to accept or reject the offer during the unexpired balance of the applicable time period.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(A)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="4" label="1024-MS-3(A)">
        <subject>MS-3(A)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(c)(2)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p30" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p31" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p32" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p33" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p34" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p35" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p36" marker="">
          <content>Our records show that your [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance [is expiring] [expired] [provides insufficient coverage], and we do not have evidence that you have obtained new coverage. Because [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance is required on your property, [we bought insurance for your property] [we plan to buy insurance for your property]. You must pay us for any period during which the insurance we buy is in effect but you do not have insurance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p37" marker="">
          <content>You should immediately provide us with your insurance information. [Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p38" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p39" marker="">
          <content>May be significantly more expensive than the insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p40" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p41" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p42" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(B)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="5" label="1024-MS-3(B)">
        <subject>MS-3(B)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(d)(2)(i)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p43" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p44" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p45" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p46" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p47" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Second and final notice—please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p48" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p49" marker="">
          <content>This is your second and final notice that our records show that your [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance [is expiring] [expired] [provides insufficient coverage], and we do not have evidence that you have obtained new coverage. Because [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance is required on your property, [we bought insurance for your property] [we plan to buy insurance for your property]. You must pay us for any period during which the insurance we buy is in effect but you do not have insurance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p50" marker="">
          <content>You should immediately provide us with your insurance information. [Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p51" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p52" marker="">
          <content>[Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p53" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p54" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p55" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(C)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="6" label="1024-MS-3(C)">
        <subject>MS-3(C)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(d)(2)(ii)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p56" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p57" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p58" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p59" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p60" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Second and final notice—please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p61" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p62" marker="">
          <content>We received the insurance information you provided, but we are unable to verify coverage from [Date Range].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p63" marker="">
          <content>Please provide us with insurance information for [Date Range] immediately.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p64" marker="">
          <content>We will charge you for insurance we [bought] [plan to buy] for [Date Range] unless we can verify that you have insurance coverage for [Date Range].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p65" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p66" marker="">
          <content>Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p67" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p68" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p69" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(D)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="7" label="1024-MS-3(D)">
        <subject>MS-3(D)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(e)(2)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p70" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p71" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p72" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p73" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p74" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Please update insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p75" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p76" marker="">
          <content>Because we did not have evidence that you had [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance on the property listed above, we bought insurance on your property and added the cost to your mortgage loan account.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p77" marker="">
          <content>The policy that we bought [expired] [is scheduled to expire]. Because [hazard][Insurance Type] insurance] is required on your property, we intend to maintain insurance on your property by renewing or replacing the insurance we bought.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p78" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we buy:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p79" marker="">
          <content>[Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p80" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p81" marker="">
          <content>If you buy [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance, you should immediately provide us with your insurance information.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p82" marker="">
          <content>[Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p83" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p84" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-MS-4(D)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="12" label="1024-MS-4(D)">
        <subject>MS-4(D)—Written Early Intervention Notice for Servicers Subject to FDCPA (§ 1024.39(d)(2)(iii))</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-4(D)-p1" marker="">
          <content>This is a legally required notice. We are sending this notice to you because you are behind on your mortgage payment. We want to notify you of possible ways to avoid losing your home. We have a right to invoke foreclosure based on the terms of your mortgage contact. Please read this letter carefully.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-30-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-30-c-2-Interp" target="1024-30-c-2">
        <title>Paragraph 30(c)(2).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-30-c-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Principal residence.</title>
          <content>If a property ceases to be a borrower's principal residence, the procedures set forth in §§ 1024.39 through 1024.41 do not apply to a mortgage loan secured by that property. Determination of principal residence status will depend on the specific facts and circumstances regarding the property and applicable State law. For example, a vacant property may still be a borrower's principal residence.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-30-d-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-30-d-Interp" target="1024-30-d">
        <title>30(d) Successors in interest.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-30-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Treatment of confirmed successors in interest.</title>
          <content>Under § 1024.30(d), a confirmed successor in interest must be considered a borrower for purposes of this subpart and § 1024.17, regardless of whether the successor in interest assumes the mortgage loan obligation under State law. For example, if a servicer receives a loss mitigation application from a confirmed successor in interest, the servicer must review and evaluate the application and notify the confirmed successor in interest in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.41 if the property is the confirmed successor in interest's principal residence and the procedures set forth in § 1024.41 are otherwise applicable. Treatment of a confirmed successor in interest as a borrower for purposes of this subpart and § 1024.17 does not affect whether the confirmed successor in interest is subject to the contractual obligations of the mortgage loan agreement, which is determined by applicable State law. Communications in compliance with this part to a confirmed successor in interest as defined in § 1024.31 do not violate section 805(b) of the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) because consumer for purposes of FDCPA section 805 includes any person who meets the definition in this part of confirmed successor in interest.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-30-d-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Assumption of the mortgage loan obligation.</title>
          <content>A servicer may not require a confirmed successor in interest to assume the mortgage loan obligation under State law to be considered a borrower for purposes of § 1024.17 and this subpart. If a successor in interest assumes a mortgage loan obligation under State law or is otherwise liable on the mortgage loan obligation, the protections that the successor in interest enjoys under this part are not limited to the protections that apply under § 1024.30(d) to a confirmed successor in interest.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-30-d-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Treatment of transferor borrowers.</title>
          <content>Even after a servicer's confirmation of a successor in interest, the servicer is still required to comply with all applicable requirements of this subpart with respect to the transferor borrower.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency" before="1024-31-Interp-LossMitigationApplication">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency" target="1024-31-Delinquency">
        <title>Delinquency.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Length of delinquency.</title>
          <content>A borrower's delinquency begins on the date an amount sufficient to cover a periodic payment of principal, interest, and, if applicable, escrow becomes due and unpaid, and lasts until such time as no periodic payment is due and unpaid, even if the borrower is afforded a period after the due date to pay before the servicer assesses a late fee.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Application of funds.</title>
          <content>If a servicer applies payments to the oldest outstanding periodic payment, a payment by a delinquent borrower advances the date the borrower's delinquency began. For example, assume a borrower's mortgage loan obligation provides that a periodic payment sufficient to cover principal, interest, and escrow is due on the first of each month. The borrower fails to make a payment on January 1 or on any day in January, and on January 31 the borrower is 30 days delinquent. On February 3, the borrower makes a periodic payment. The servicer applies the payment it received on February 3 to the outstanding January payment. On February 4, the borrower is three days delinquent.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Payment tolerance.</title>
          <content>For any given billing cycle for which a borrower's payment is less than the periodic payment due, if a servicer chooses not to treat a borrower as delinquent for purposes of any section of this subpart, that borrower is not delinquent as defined in § 1024.31.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-Delinquency-4" marker="4.">
          <title>Creditor's contract rights.</title>
          <content>This subpart does not prevent a creditor from exercising a right provided by a mortgage loan contract to accelerate payment for a breach of that contract. Failure to pay the amount due after the creditor accelerates the mortgage loan obligation in accordance with the mortgage loan contract would begin or continue delinquency.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-31-Interp-SuccessorInInterest" after="1024-31-Interp-ServiceProvider">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-SuccessorInInterest" target="1024-31-SuccessorInInterest">
        <title>Successor in interest.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-SuccessorInInterest-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Joint tenants and tenants by the entirety.</title>
          <content>If a borrower who has an ownership interest as a joint tenant or tenant by the entirety in a property securing a mortgage loan subject to this subpart dies, a surviving joint tenant or tenant by the entirety with a right of survivorship in the property is a successor in interest as defined in § 1024.31.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-31-Interp-SuccessorInInterest-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Beneficiaries of inter vivos trusts.</title>
          <content>In the event of a transfer into an inter vivos trust in which the borrower is and remains a beneficiary and which does not relate to a transfer of rights of occupancy in the property, the beneficiaries of the inter vivos trust rather than the inter vivos trust itself are considered to be the successors in interest for purposes of § 1024.31. For example, assume Borrower A transfers her home into such an inter vivos trust for the benefit of her spouse and herself. As of the transfer date, Borrower A and her spouse would be considered successors in interest and, upon confirmation, would be borrowers for purposes of certain provisions of Regulation X. If the lender has not released Borrower A from the loan obligation, Borrower A would also remain a borrower more generally for purposes of Regulation X.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-32-Interp" before="1024-33-Interp">
      <interpSection label="1024-32-Interp" sectionNum="32">
        <title>§ 1024.32—General Disclosure Requirements.</title>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-Interp" target="1024-32-c">
          <title>32(c) Confirmed successors in interest.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-1-Interp-1" target="1024-32-c-1">
            <title>32(c)(1) Optional notice with acknowledgment form.</title>
            <content>1. A servicer may identify in the acknowledgment form examples of the types of notices and communications identified in § 1024.32(c)(1)(iii), such as periodic statements and mortgage servicing transfer notices. Any examples provided should be the types of notices or communications that would be available to a confirmed successor in interest if the confirmed successor in interest executed the acknowledgment and returned it to the servicer.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-2-Interp" target="1024-32-c-2">
            <title>32(c)(2) Effect of failure to execute acknowledgment.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>No time limit to return acknowledgment.</title>
              <content>A confirmed successor in interest may provide an executed acknowledgment that complies with § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv) to the servicer at any time after confirmation.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-2-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>Effect of revocation of acknowledgment.</title>
              <content>If a confirmed successor in interest who is not liable on the mortgage loan obligation executes and then later revokes an acknowledgment pursuant to § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv), the servicer is not required to provide to the confirmed successor in interest any written disclosure required by § 1024.17, § 1024.33, § 1024.34, § 1024.37, or § 1024.39 or to comply with the live contact requirements in § 1024.39(a) with respect to the confirmed successor in interest from the date the revocation is received until the confirmed successor in interest either assumes the mortgage loan obligation under State law or executes a new acknowledgment that complies with § 1024.32(c)(1)(iv) and provides it to the servicer.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-4-Interp" target="1024-32-c-4">
            <title>32(c)(4) Multiple notices unnecessary.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-32-c-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Specific written disclosure.</title>
              <content>A servicer may rely on § 1024.32(c)(4) if the servicer provides a specific written disclosure required by § 1024.17, § 1024.33, § 1024.34, § 1024.37, or § 1024.39(b) to another borrower. For example, a servicer is not required to provide a force-placed insurance notice required under § 1024.37 to a confirmed successor in interest if the servicer is providing the same force-placed insurance notice to a transferor borrower or to another confirmed successor in interest.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-36-a-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Owner or assignee of a mortgage loan.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
          <content>When a loan is not held in a trust for which an appointed trustee receives payments on behalf of the trust, a servicer complies with § 1024.36(d) by responding to a request for information regarding the owner or assignee of a mortgage loan by identifying the person on whose behalf the servicer receives payments from the borrower. A servicer is not the owner or assignee for purposes of § 1024.36(d) if the servicer holds title to the loan, or title is assigned to the servicer, solely for the administrative convenience of the servicer in servicing the mortgage loan obligation. The Government National Mortgage Association is not the owner or assignee for purposes of such requests for information solely as a result of its role as the guarantor of the security in which the loan serves as the collateral.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>When the loan is held in a trust for which an appointed trustee receives payments on behalf of the trust, a servicer complies with § 1024.36(d) by responding to a borrower's request for information regarding the owner, assignee, or trust of the mortgage loan with the following information, as applicable:</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2-ii-A" marker="A.">
            <content>For any request for information where the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation is not the owner of the loan or the trustee of the securitization trust in which the loan is held: The name of the trust, and the name, address, and appropriate contact information for the trustee. Assume, for example, a mortgage loan is owned by Mortgage Loan Trust, Series ABC-1, for which XYZ Trust Company is the trustee. The servicer complies with § 1024.36(d) by identifying the owner as Mortgage Loan Trust, Series ABC-1, and providing the name, address, and appropriate contact information for XYZ Trust Company as the trustee.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2-ii-B" marker="B.">
            <content>If the request for information did not expressly request the name or number of the trust or pool and the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation is the owner of the loan or the trustee of the securitization trust in which the loan is held: The name and contact information for the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation, as applicable, without also providing the name of the trust.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-36-a-Interp-2-ii-C" marker="C.">
            <content>If the request for information did expressly request the name or number of the trust or pool and the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation is the owner of the loan or the trustee of the securitization trust in which the loan is held: The name of the trust, and the name, address, and appropriate contact information for the trustee, as in comment 36(a)-2.ii.A above.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-36-i-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-36-i-Interp" target="1024-36-i">
        <title>36(i) Potential successors in interest.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Requests that indicate that the person may be a successor in interest.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.36(i) requires a servicer to respond to certain written requests received from a person that indicate the person may be a successor in interest. Examples of written requests that indicate that the person may be a successor in interest include, without limitation, a written statement from a person other than a borrower indicating that there has been a transfer of ownership or of an ownership interest in the property to the person or that a borrower has been divorced, legally separated, or died, or a written loss mitigation application received from a person other than a borrower.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Time limits.</title>
          <content>A servicer must respond to a request under § 1024.36(i) not later than the time limits set forth in § 1024.36(d)(2). Servicers subject to § 1024.38(b)(1)(vi)(B) must also maintain policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure that, upon receiving notice of the existence of a potential successor in interest, the servicer can promptly determine the documents the servicer reasonably requires to confirm that person's identity and ownership interest in the property and promptly provide to the potential successor in interest a description of those documents and how the person may submit a written request under § 1024.36(i) (including the appropriate address). Depending on the facts and circumstances of the request, responding promptly may require a servicer to respond more quickly than the time limits established in § 1024.36(d)(2).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-36-i-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Potential successor in interest's representative.</title>
          <content>An information request pursuant to § 1024.36(i) is submitted by a potential successor in interest if the information request is submitted by an agent of the potential successor in interest. A servicer may undertake reasonable procedures to determine if a person that claims to be an agent of a potential successor in interest has authority from the potential successor in interest to act on the potential successor in interest's behalf, for example, by requiring that a person that claims to be an agent of the potential successor in interest provide documentation from the potential successor in interest stating that the purported agent is acting on the potential successor in interest's behalf. Upon receipt of such documentation, the servicer shall treat the request for information as having been submitted by the potential successor in interest.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-37-d-5-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-37-d-5-Interp" target="1024-37-d-5">
        <title>37(d)(5) Updating notice with borrower information.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-37-d-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Reasonable time.</title>
          <content>If the written notice required by § 1024.37(c)(1)(ii) was put into production a reasonable time prior to the servicer delivering or placing the notice in the mail, the servicer is not required to update the notice with new insurance information received. For purposes of § 1024.37(d)(5), a reasonable time is no more than five days (excluding legal holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp" target="1024-38-b-1-vi">
        <title>Paragraph 38(b)(1)(vi).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Identification of potential successors in interest.</title>
          <content>A servicer may be notified of the existence of a potential successor in interest in a variety of ways. For example, a person could indicate that there has been a transfer of ownership or of an ownership interest in the property or that a borrower has been divorced, legally separated, or died, or a person other than a borrower could submit a loss mitigation application. A servicer must maintain policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure that the servicer can retain this information and promptly facilitate communication with potential successors in interest when a servicer is notified of their existence. A servicer is not required to conduct a search for potential successors in interest if the servicer has not received actual notice of their existence.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Documents reasonably required.</title>
          <content>The documents a servicer requires to confirm a potential successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the property must be reasonable in light of the laws of the relevant jurisdiction, the specific situation of the potential successor in interest, and the documents already in the servicer's possession. The required documents may, where appropriate, include, for example, a death certificate, an executed will, or a court order. The required documents may also include documents that the servicer reasonably believes are necessary to prevent fraud or other criminal activity (for example, if a servicer has reason to believe that documents presented are forged).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Examples of reasonable requirements.</title>
          <content>Because the relevant law governing each situation may vary from State to State, the following examples are illustrative only. The examples illustrate what documents it would generally be reasonable for a servicer to require to confirm a potential successor in interest's identity and ownership interest in the property under the specific circumstances described.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
            <title>Tenancy by the entirety or joint tenancy.</title>
            <content>Assume that a servicer knows that the potential successor in interest and the transferor borrower owned the property as tenants by the entirety or joint tenants and that the transferor borrower has died. Assume further that, upon the death of the transferor borrower, the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction does not require a probate proceeding to establish that the potential successor in interest has sole interest in the property but requires only that there be a prior recorded deed listing both the potential successor in interest and the transferor borrower as tenants by the entirety (e.g., married grantees) or joint tenants. Under these circumstances, it would be reasonable for the servicer to require the potential successor in interest to provide documentation of the recorded instrument, if the servicer does not already have it, and the death certificate of the transferor borrower. Because in this situation a probate proceeding is not required under the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction, it generally would not be reasonable for the servicer to require documentation of a probate proceeding.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
            <title>Affidavits of heirship.</title>
            <content>Assume that a potential successor in interest indicates that an ownership interest in the property transferred to the potential successor in interest upon the death of the transferor borrower through intestate succession and offers an affidavit of heirship as confirmation. Assume further that, upon the death of the transferor borrower, the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction does not require a probate proceeding to establish that the potential successor in interest has an interest in the property but requires only an appropriate affidavit of heirship. Under these circumstances, it would be reasonable for the servicer to require the potential successor in interest to provide the affidavit of heirship and the death certificate of the transferor borrower. Because a probate proceeding is not required under the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction to recognize the transfer of title, it generally would not be reasonable for the servicer to require documentation of a probate proceeding.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-3-iii" marker="iii.">
            <title>Divorce or legal separation.</title>
            <content>Assume that a potential successor in interest indicates that an ownership interest in the property transferred to the potential successor in interest from a spouse who is a borrower as a result of a property agreement incident to a divorce proceeding. Assume further that the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction does not require a deed conveying the interest in the property but accepts a final divorce decree and accompanying separation agreement executed by both spouses to evidence transfer of title. Under these circumstances, it would be reasonable for the servicer to require the potential successor in interest to provide documentation of the final divorce decree and an executed separation agreement. Because the applicable law of the relevant jurisdiction does not require a deed, it generally would not be reasonable for the servicer to require a deed.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-3-iv" marker="iv.">
            <title>Living spouses or parents.</title>
            <content>Assume that a potential successor in interest indicates that an ownership interest in the property transferred to the potential successor in interest from a living spouse or parent who is a borrower by quitclaim deed or act of donation. Under these circumstances, it would be reasonable for the servicer to require the potential successor in interest to provide the quitclaim deed or act of donation. It generally would not be reasonable, however, for the servicer to require additional documents.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title>Additional documentation required for confirmation determination.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.38(b)(1)(vi)(C) requires a servicer to maintain policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure that, upon receipt of the documents identified by the servicer, the servicer promptly notifies a potential successor in interest that, as applicable, the servicer has confirmed the potential successor in interest's status, has determined that additional documents are required, or has determined that the potential successor in interest is not a successor in interest. If a servicer reasonably determines that it cannot make a determination of the potential successor in interest's status based on the documentation provided, it must specify what additional documentation is required. For example, if there is pending litigation involving the potential successor in interest and other claimants regarding who has title to the property at issue, a servicer may specify that documentation of a court determination or other resolution of the litigation is required.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-1-vi-Interp-5" marker="5.">
          <title>Prompt confirmation and loss mitigation.</title>
          <content>A servicer's policies and procedures must be reasonably designed to ensure that the servicer can promptly notify the potential successor in interest that the servicer has confirmed the potential successor in interest's status. Notification is not prompt for purposes of this requirement if it unreasonably interferes with a successor in interest's ability to apply for loss mitigation options according to the procedures provided in § 1024.41.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-38-b-3-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-3-iii-Interp" target="1024-38-b-3-iii">
        <title>Paragraph 38(b)(3)(iii).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-38-b-3-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Sharing information with service provider personnel handling foreclosure proceedings.</title>
          <content>A servicer's policies and procedures must be reasonably designed to ensure that servicer personnel promptly inform service provider personnel handling foreclosure proceedings that the servicer has received a complete loss mitigation application and promptly instruct foreclosure counsel to take any step required by § 1024.41(g) sufficiently timely to avoid violating the prohibition against moving for judgment or order of sale, or conducting a foreclosure sale.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Delinquency.</title>
        <content>Section 1024.39 requires a servicer to establish or attempt to establish live contact no later than the 36th day of a borrower's delinquency. This provision is illustrated as follows:</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
          <content>Assume a mortgage loan obligation with a monthly billing cycle and monthly payments of $2,000 representing principal, interest, and escrow due on the first of each month.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-1-i-A" marker="A.">
            <content>The borrower fails to make a payment of $2,000 on, and makes no payment during the 36-day period after, January 1. The servicer must establish or make good faith efforts to establish live contact not later than 36 days after January 1—i.e., on or before February 6.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-1-i-B" marker="B.">
            <content>The borrower makes no payments during the period January 1 through April 1, although payments of $2,000 each on January 1, February 1, and March 1 are due. Assuming it is not a leap year, the borrower is 90 days delinquent as of April 1. The servicer may time its attempts to establish live contact such that a single attempt will meet the requirements of § 1024.39(a) for two missed payments. To illustrate, the servicer complies with § 1024.39(a) if the servicer makes a good faith effort to establish live contact with the borrower, for example, on February 5 and again on March 25. The February 5 attempt meets the requirements of § 1024.39(a) for both the January 1 and February 1 missed payments. The March 25 attempt meets the requirements of § 1024.39(a) for the March 1 missed payment.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Establishing live contact.</title>
        <content>Live contact provides servicers an opportunity to discuss the circumstances of a borrower's delinquency. Live contact with a borrower includes speaking on the telephone or conducting an in-person meeting with the borrower but not leaving a recorded phone message. A servicer may rely on live contact established at the borrower's initiative to satisfy the live contact requirement in § 1024.39(a). Servicers may also combine contacts made pursuant to § 1024.39(a) with contacts made with borrowers for other reasons, for instance, by telling borrowers on collection calls that loss mitigation options may be available.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Good faith efforts.</title>
        <content>Good faith efforts to establish live contact consist of reasonable steps, under the circumstances, to reach a borrower and may include telephoning the borrower on more than one occasion or sending written or electronic communication encouraging the borrower to establish live contact with the servicer. The length of a borrower's delinquency, as well as a borrower's failure to respond to a servicer's repeated attempts at communication pursuant to § 1024.39(a), are relevant circumstances to consider. For example, whereas “good faith efforts” to establish live contact with regard to a borrower with two consecutive missed payments might require a telephone call, “good faith efforts” to establish live contact with regard to an unresponsive borrower with six or more consecutive missed payments might require no more than including a sentence requesting that the borrower contact the servicer with regard to the delinquencies in the periodic statement or in an electronic communication. Comment 39(a)-6 discusses the relationship between live contact and the loss mitigation procedures set forth in § 1024.41.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a-Interp-4">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Promptly inform if appropriate.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
          <title>Servicer's determination.</title>
          <content>It is within a servicer's reasonable discretion to determine whether informing a borrower about the availability of loss mitigation options is appropriate under the circumstances. The following examples demonstrate when a servicer has made a reasonable determination regarding the appropriateness of providing information about loss mitigation options.</content>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-4-i-A" marker="A.">
            <content>A servicer provides information about the availability of loss mitigation options to a borrower who notifies a servicer during live contact of a material adverse change in the borrower's financial circumstances that is likely to cause the borrower to experience a long-term delinquency for which loss mitigation options may be available.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-4-i-B" marker="B.">
            <content>A servicer does not provide information about the availability of loss mitigation options to a borrower who has missed a January 1 payment and notified the servicer that full late payment will be transmitted to the servicer by February 15.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
          <title>Promptly inform.</title>
          <content>If appropriate, a servicer may inform borrowers about the availability of loss mitigation options orally, in writing, or through electronic communication, but the servicer must provide such information promptly after the servicer establishes live contact. A servicer need not notify a borrower about any particular loss mitigation options at this time; if appropriate, a servicer need only inform borrowers generally that loss mitigation options may be available. If appropriate, a servicer may satisfy the requirement in § 1024.39(a) to inform a borrower about loss mitigation options by providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b)(1), but the servicer must provide such notice promptly after the servicer establishes live contact.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-a-Interp-5">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Borrower's representative.</title>
        <content>Section 1024.39 does not prohibit a servicer from satisfying its requirements by establishing live contact with and, if applicable, providing information about loss mitigation options to a person authorized by the borrower to communicate with the servicer on the borrower's behalf. A servicer may undertake reasonable procedures to determine if a person that claims to be an agent of a borrower has authority from the borrower to act on the borrower's behalf, for example, by requiring a person that claims to be an agent of the borrower to provide documentation from the borrower stating that the purported agent is acting on the borrower's behalf.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-a-Interp-6">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-a-Interp-6" marker="6.">
        <title>Relationship between live contact and loss mitigation procedures.</title>
        <content>If the servicer has established and is maintaining ongoing contact with the borrower under the loss mitigation procedures under § 1024.41, including during the borrower's completion of a loss mitigation application or the servicer's evaluation of the borrower's complete loss mitigation application, or if the servicer has sent the borrower a notice pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) that the borrower is not eligible for any loss mitigation options, the servicer complies with § 1024.39(a) and need not otherwise establish or make good faith efforts to establish live contact. A servicer must resume compliance with the requirements of § 1024.39(a) for a borrower who becomes delinquent again after curing a prior delinquency.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Frequency of the written notice.</title>
        <content>A servicer need not provide the written notice under § 1024.39(b) more than once during a 180-day period beginning on the date on which the written notice is provided. A servicer must provide the written notice under § 1024.39(b) at least once every 180 days to a borrower who is 45 days or more delinquent. This provision is illustrated as follows: Assume a borrower becomes delinquent on March 1, the amount due is not fully paid during the 45 days after March 1, and the servicer provides the written notice on the 45th day after March 1, which is April 15. Assume the borrower also fails to make the payment due on April 1 and the amount due is not fully paid during the 45 days after April 1. The servicer need not provide the written notice again until after the 180-day period beginning on April 15—i.e., no sooner than on October 12—and then only if the borrower is at that time 45 days or more delinquent.</content>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
          <content>If the borrower is 45 days or more delinquent on October 12, the date that is 180 days after the prior provision of the written notice, the servicer is required to provide the written notice again on October 12.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
          <content>If the borrower is less than 45 days delinquent on October 12, the servicer must again provide the written notice 45 days after the payment due date for which the borrower remains delinquent. For example, if the borrower becomes delinquent on October 1, and the amount due is not fully paid during the 45 days after October 1, the servicer will need to provide the written notice again no later than 45 days after October 1—i.e., by November 15.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Borrower's representative.</title>
        <content>Comment 39(a)-5 explains how a servicer may satisfy the requirements under § 1024.39 with a person authorized by the borrower to communicate with the servicer on the borrower's behalf.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-5">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-b-1-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Servicing transfers.</title>
        <content>A transferee servicer is required to comply with the requirements of § 1024.39(b) regardless of whether the transferor servicer provided a written notice to the borrower in the preceding 180-day period. However, a transferee servicer is not required to provide a written notice under § 1024.39(b) if the transferor servicer provided the written notice under § 1024.39(b) within 45 days of the transfer date. For example, assume a borrower has monthly payments, with a payment due on March 1. The transferor servicer provides the notice required by § 1024.39(b) on April 10. The loan is transferred on April 12. Assuming the borrower remains delinquent, the transferee servicer is not required to provide another written notice until 45 days after May 1, the first post-transfer payment due date—i.e., by June 15.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-c-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-Interp" target="1024-39-c">
        <title>39(c) Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Borrower's representative.</title>
          <content>If the borrower is represented by a person authorized by the borrower to communicate with the servicer on the borrower's behalf, the servicer may provide the written notice required by § 1024.39(b), as modified by § 1024.39(c)(1)(iii), to the borrower's representative. See comment 39(a)-5. In general, bankruptcy counsel is the borrower's representative. A servicer's procedures for determining whether counsel is the borrower's representative are generally considered reasonable if they are limited to, for example, confirming that the attorney's name is listed on the borrower's bankruptcy petition or other court filing.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Adapting requirements in bankruptcy.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.39(c) does not require a servicer to communicate with a borrower in a manner that would be inconsistent with applicable bankruptcy law or a court order in a bankruptcy case. If necessary to comply with such law or court order, a servicer may adapt the requirements of § 1024.39 as appropriate.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-Interp" target="1024-39-c-1">
          <title>39(c)(1) Borrowers in bankruptcy—Partial exemption.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Commencing a case.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.39(c)(1) applies once a petition is filed under title 11 of the United States Code, commencing a case in which the borrower is a debtor in bankruptcy.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii-Interp" target="1024-39-c-1-ii">
          <title>Paragraph 39(c)(1)(ii)</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Availability of loss mitigation options.</title>
            <content>In part, § 1024.39(c)(1)(ii) exempts a servicer from the requirements of § 1024.39(b) if no loss mitigation option is available. A loss mitigation option is available if the owner or assignee of a mortgage loan offers an alternative to foreclosure that is made available through the servicer and for which a borrower may apply, even if the borrower ultimately does not qualify for such option.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>Fair Debt Collections Practices Act.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
              <title>Exemption.</title>
              <content>To the extent the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) (15 U.S.C. 1692 et seq.) applies to a servicer's communications with a borrower in bankruptcy and any borrower on the mortgage loan has provided a notification pursuant to FDCPA section 805(c) notifying the servicer that the borrower refuses to pay a debt or that the borrower wishes the servicer to cease further communications, with regard to that mortgage loan, § 1024.39(c)(1)(ii) exempts a servicer from providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
              <title>Example.</title>
              <content>For example, assume that two spouses jointly own a home and are both primarily liable on the mortgage loan. Further assume that the servicer is subject to the FDCPA with respect to that mortgage loan. One spouse is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code subject to § 1024.39(c). The other spouse provided the servicer a notification pursuant to FDCPA section 805(c). Section 1024.39(c)(1)(ii) exempts the servicer from providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b) with respect to that mortgage loan.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Joint obligors.</title>
            <content>When two or more borrowers are joint obligors with primary liability on a mortgage loan subject to § 1024.39, if any of the borrowers is a debtor in bankruptcy, a servicer may provide the written notice required by § 1024.39(b), as modified by § 1024.39(c)(1)(iii), to any borrower.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-2-Interp" target="1024-39-c-2">
          <title>39(c)(2) Resuming compliance.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-39-c-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Bankruptcy case revived.</title>
            <content>If the borrower's bankruptcy case is revived, for example if the court reinstates a previously dismissed case or reopens the case, § 1024.39(c)(1) once again applies. However, § 1024.39(c)(1)(iii)(C) provides that a servicer is not required to provide the written notice more than once during a single bankruptcy case. For example, assume a borrower's bankruptcy case commences on June 1, the servicer provides the written notice on July 10 in compliance with § 1024.39(b) as modified by § 1024.39(c)(1)(iii), and the bankruptcy case is dismissed on August 1. If the court subsequently reopens or reinstates the borrower's bankruptcy case and the servicer does not provide a second written notice for that bankruptcy case, the servicer has complied with § 1024.39(b) and (c)(1)(iii).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-d-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-Interp" target="1024-39-d">
        <title>39(d) Fair Debt Collection Practices Act—partial exemption.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Availability of loss mitigation options.</title>
          <content>In part, § 1024.39(d)(2) exempts a servicer from providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b) if no loss mitigation option is available. A loss mitigation option is available if the owner or assignee of a mortgage loan offers an alternative to foreclosure that is made available through the servicer and for which a borrower may apply, even if the borrower ultimately does not qualify for such option.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Early intervention communications under the FDCPA.</title>
          <content>To the extent the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) (15 U.S.C. 1692 et seq.) applies to a servicer's communications with a borrower, a servicer does not violate FDCPA section 805(c) by providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b) as modified by § 1024.39(d)(3) after a borrower has provided a notification pursuant to FDCPA section 805(c) with respect to that borrower's loan. Nor does a servicer violate FDCPA section 805(c) by providing loss mitigation information or assistance in response to a borrower-initiated communication after the borrower has invoked the cease communication right under FDCPA section 805(c). A servicer subject to the FDCPA must continue to comply with all other applicable provisions of the FDCPA, including restrictions on communications and prohibitions on harassment or abuse, false or misleading representations, and unfair practices as contained in FDCPA sections 805 through 808 (15 U.S.C. 1692c through 1692f).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-39-d-2-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-2-Interp" target="1024-39-d-2">
        <title>Paragraph 39(d)(2).</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-39-d-2-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Borrowers in bankruptcy.</title>
          <content>To the extent the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) (15 U.S.C. 1692 et seq.) applies to a servicer's communications with a borrower and the borrower has provided a notification pursuant to FDCPA section 805(c) notifying the servicer that the borrower refuses to pay a debt or that the borrower wishes the servicer to cease further communications, with regard to that mortgage loan, § 1024.39(d)(2) exempts a servicer from providing the written notice required by § 1024.39(b) while any borrower on the mortgage loan is also a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code. For an example, see comment 39(c)(1)(ii)-1.ii.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-40-a-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-40-a-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Delinquency.</title>
        <content>See § 1024.31 for the definition of delinquency applicable to subpart C of Regulation X.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-b-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-Interp" target="1024-41-b">
        <title>41(b) Receipt of a loss mitigation application.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Successors in interest.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
            <content>If a servicer receives a loss mitigation application from a potential successor in interest before confirming that person's identity and ownership interest in the property, the servicer may, but need not, review and evaluate the loss mitigation application in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.41. If a servicer complies with the requirements of § 1024.41 for a complete loss mitigation application submitted by a potential successor in interest before confirming that person's identity and ownership interest in the property, § 1024.41(i)'s limitation on duplicative requests applies to that person, provided the servicer's evaluation of loss mitigation options available to the person would not have resulted in a different determination due to the person's confirmation as a successor in interest if it had been conducted after the servicer confirmed the person's status as a successor in interest.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
            <content>If a servicer receives a loss mitigation application from a potential successor in interest and elects not to review and evaluate the loss mitigation application before confirming that person's identity and ownership interest in the property, the servicer must preserve the loss mitigation application and all documents submitted in connection with the application, and, upon such confirmation, the servicer must review and evaluate the loss mitigation application in accordance with the procedures set forth in § 1024.41 if the property is the confirmed successor in interest's principal residence and the procedures set forth in § 1024.41 are otherwise applicable. For purposes of § 1024.41, the servicer must treat the loss mitigation application as if it had been received on the date that the servicer confirmed the successor in interest's status. If the loss mitigation application is incomplete at the time of confirmation because documents submitted by the successor in interest became stale or invalid after they were submitted and confirmation is 45 days or more before a foreclosure sale, the servicer must identify the stale or invalid documents that need to be updated in a notice pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2).</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp" target="1024-41-b-1">
          <title>41(b)(1) Complete loss mitigation application.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>In general.</title>
            <content>A servicer has flexibility to establish its own application requirements and to decide the type and amount of information it will require from borrowers applying for loss mitigation options. In the course of gathering documents and information from a borrower to complete a loss mitigation application, a servicer may stop collecting documents and information for a particular loss mitigation option after receiving information confirming that, pursuant to any requirements established by the owner or assignee of the borrower's mortgage loan, the borrower is ineligible for that option. A servicer may not stop collecting documents and information for any loss mitigation option based solely upon the borrower's stated preference but may stop collecting documents and information for any loss mitigation option based on the borrower's stated preference in conjunction with other information, as prescribed by any requirements established by the owner or assignee. A servicer must continue to exercise reasonable diligence to obtain documents and information from the borrower that the servicer requires to evaluate the borrower as to all other loss mitigation options available to the borrower. For example:</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Assume a particular loss mitigation option is only available for borrowers whose mortgage loans were originated before a specific date. Once a servicer receives documents or information confirming that a mortgage loan was originated after that date, the servicer may stop collecting documents or information from the borrower that the servicer would use to evaluate the borrower for that loss mitigation option, but the servicer must continue its efforts to obtain documents and information from the borrower that the servicer requires to evaluate the borrower for all other available loss mitigation options.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Assume applicable requirements established by the owner or assignee of the mortgage loan provide that a borrower is ineligible for home retention loss mitigation options if the borrower states a preference for a short sale and provides evidence of another applicable hardship, such as military Permanent Change of Station orders or an employment transfer more than 50 miles away. If the borrower indicates a preference for a short sale or, more generally, not to retain the property, the servicer may not stop collecting documents and information from the borrower pertaining to available home retention options solely because the borrower has indicated such a preference, but the servicer may stop collecting such documents and information once the servicer receives information confirming that the borrower has an applicable hardship under requirements established by the owner or assignee, such as military Permanent Change of Station orders or employment transfer.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>When an inquiry or prequalification request becomes an application.</title>
            <content>A servicer is encouraged to provide borrowers with information about loss mitigation programs. If in giving information to the borrower, the borrower expresses an interest in applying for a loss mitigation option and provides information the servicer would evaluate in connection with a loss mitigation application, the borrower's inquiry or prequalification request has become a loss mitigation application. A loss mitigation application is considered expansively and includes any “prequalification” for a loss mitigation option. For example, if a borrower requests that a servicer determine if the borrower is “prequalified” for a loss mitigation program by evaluating the borrower against preliminary criteria to determine eligibility for a loss mitigation option, the request constitutes a loss mitigation application.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-3" marker="3.">
            <title>Examples of inquiries that are not applications.</title>
            <content>The following examples illustrate situations in which only an inquiry has taken place and no loss mitigation application has been submitted:</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-3-i" marker="i.">
              <content>A borrower calls to ask about loss mitigation options and servicer personnel explain the loss mitigation options available to the borrower and the criteria for determining the borrower's eligibility for any such loss mitigation option. The borrower does not, however, provide any information that a servicer would consider for evaluating a loss mitigation application.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-3-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>A borrower calls to ask about the process for applying for a loss mitigation option but the borrower does not provide any information that a servicer would consider for evaluating a loss mitigation application.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-4" marker="4.">
            <title></title>
            <content>Although a servicer has flexibility to establish its own requirements regarding the documents and information necessary for a loss mitigation application, the servicer must act with reasonable diligence to collect information needed to complete the application. A servicer must request information necessary to make a loss mitigation application complete promptly after receiving the loss mitigation application. Reasonable diligence for purposes of § 1024.41(b)(1) includes, without limitation, the following actions:</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-4-i" marker="i.">
              <content>A servicer requires additional information from the applicant, such as an address or a telephone number to verify employment; the servicer contacts the applicant promptly to obtain such information after receiving a loss mitigation application;</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-4-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>Servicing for a mortgage loan is transferred to a servicer and the borrower makes an incomplete loss mitigation application to the transferee servicer after the transfer; the transferee servicer reviews documents provided by the transferor servicer to determine if information required to make the loss mitigation application complete is contained within documents transferred by the transferor servicer to the servicer; and</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-1-Interp-4-iii" marker="iii.">
              <content>A servicer offers a borrower a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application and provides the borrower the written notice pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii). If the borrower remains in compliance with the short-term payment forbearance program or short-term repayment plan, and the borrower does not request further assistance, the servicer may suspend reasonable diligence efforts until near the end of the payment forbearance program or repayment plan. However, if the borrower fails to comply with the program or plan or requests further assistance, the servicer must immediately resume reasonable diligence efforts. Near the end of a short-term payment forbearance program offered based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), and prior to the end of the forbearance period, if the borrower remains delinquent, a servicer must contact the borrower to determine if the borrower wishes to complete the loss mitigation application and proceed with a full loss mitigation evaluation.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-Interp" target="1024-41-b-2">
          <title>41(b)(2) Review of loss mitigation application submission.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-i-Interp">
            <title>41(b)(2)(i) Requirements.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Foreclosure sale not scheduled.</title>
              <content>For purposes of § 1024.41(b)(2)(i), if no foreclosure sale has been scheduled as of the date a servicer receives a loss mitigation application, the servicer must treat the application as having been received 45 days or more before any foreclosure sale.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp" target="1024-41-b-2-ii">
            <title>41(b)(2)(ii) Time period disclosure.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Thirty days is generally reasonable.</title>
              <content>In general and subject to the restrictions described in comments 41(b)(2)(ii)-2 and -3, a servicer complies with the requirement to include a reasonable date in the written notice required under § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) by including a date that is 30 days after the date the servicer provides the written notice.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>No later than the next milestone.</title>
              <content>For purposes of § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii), subject to the restriction described in comment 41(b)(2)(ii)-3, the reasonable date must be no later than the earliest of:</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-2-i" marker="i.">
                <content>The date by which any document or information submitted by a borrower will be considered stale or invalid pursuant to any requirements applicable to any loss mitigation option available to the borrower;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-2-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>The date that is the 120th day of the borrower's delinquency;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-2-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>The date that is 90 days before a foreclosure sale;</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-2-iv" marker="iv.">
                <content>The date that is 38 days before a foreclosure sale.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-b-2-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Seven-day minimum.</title>
              <content>A reasonable date for purposes of § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) must never be less than seven days from the date on which the servicer provides the written notice pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-1-Interp-4">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-1-Interp-4" marker="4.">
        <title>Other notices.</title>
        <content>A servicer may combine other notices required by applicable law, including, without limitation, a notice with respect to an adverse action required by Regulation B, 12 CFR part 1002, or a notice required pursuant to the Fair Credit Reporting Act, with the notice required pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(1), unless otherwise prohibited by applicable law.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp" target="1024-41-c-2-iii">
        <title>41(c)(2)(iii) Short-term loss mitigation options.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Short-term payment forbearance program.</title>
          <content>The exemption in § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) applies to, among other things, short-term payment forbearance programs. For purposes of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), a payment forbearance program is a loss mitigation option pursuant to which a servicer allows a borrower to forgo making certain payments or portions of payments for a period of time. A short-term payment forbearance program for purposes of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) allows the forbearance of payments due over periods of no more than six months. Such a program would be short-term regardless of the amount of time a servicer allows the borrower to make up the missing payments.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
          <title>Short-term loss mitigation options and incomplete applications.</title>
          <content>Section 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) allows a servicer to offer a borrower a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. The servicer must still comply with the other requirements of § 1024.41 with respect to the incomplete loss mitigation application, including the requirement in § 1024.41(b)(2) to review the application to determine if it is complete, the requirement in § 1024.41(b)(1) to exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining documents and information to complete a loss mitigation application (see comment 41(b)(1)-4.iii), and the requirement in § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) to provide the borrower with written notice that the servicer acknowledges the receipt of the application and has determined that the application is incomplete.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
          <title>Short-term loss mitigation options and complete applications.</title>
          <content>Even if a servicer offers a borrower a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application, the servicer must still comply with all applicable requirements in § 1024.41 if the borrower completes a loss mitigation application.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-4" marker="4.">
          <title>Short-term repayment plan.</title>
          <content>The exemption in § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) applies to, among other things, short-term repayment plans. For purposes of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), a repayment plan is a loss mitigation option with terms under which a borrower would repay all past due payments over a specified period of time to bring the mortgage loan account current. A short-term repayment plan for purposes of § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) allows for the repayment of no more than three months of past due payments and allows a borrower to repay the arrearage over a period lasting no more than six months.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-5" marker="5.">
          <title>Specific payment terms and duration.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-5-i" marker="i.">
            <title>General requirement.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) requires a servicer to provide the borrower a written notice stating, among other things, the specific payment terms and duration of a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan offered based on an evaluation of an incomplete application. Generally, a servicer complies with these requirements if the written notice states the amount of each payment due during the program or plan, the date by which the borrower must make each payment, and whether the mortgage loan will be current at the end of the program or plan if the borrower complies with the program or plan.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-5-ii" marker="ii.">
            <title>Disclosure of payment amounts that may change.</title>
            <content>At the time a servicer provides the written notice pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii), if the servicer lacks information necessary to determine the amount of a specific payment due during the program or plan (for example, because the borrower's interest rate will change to an unknown rate based on an index or because an escrow account computation year as defined in § 1024.17(b) will end and the borrower's escrow payment might change), the servicer complies with the requirement to disclose the specific payment terms and duration of a short-term payment forbearance program or short-term repayment plan if the disclosures are based on the best information reasonably available to the servicer at the time the notice is provided and the written notice identifies which payment amounts may change, states that such payment amounts are estimates, and states the general reason that such payment amounts might change. For example, if an escrow account computation year as defined in § 1024.17(b) will end during a borrower's short-term repayment plan, the written notice complies with § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) if it identifies the payment amounts that may change, states that those payment amounts are estimates, and states that the affected payments might change because the borrower's escrow payment might change.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-2-iii-Interp-6" marker="6.">
          <title>Timing of notice.</title>
          <content>Generally, a servicer acts promptly to provide the written notice required by § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii) if the servicer provides such written notice no later than five days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) after offering the borrower a short-term payment forbearance program or short-term repayment plan. A servicer may provide the written notice at the same time the servicer offers the borrower the program or plan. A written offer that contains all the required elements of the written notice also satisfies § 1024.41(c)(2)(iii).</content>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-3-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-3-Interp" target="1024-41-c-3">
        <title>41(c)(3) Notice of complete application.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-Interp" target="1024-41-c-3-i">
          <title>Paragraph 41(c)(3)(i).</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Completion date.</title>
            <content>A servicer complies with § 1024.41(c)(3)(i)(B) by disclosing on the notice the most recent date the servicer received the complete loss mitigation application. For example, assume that a borrower first submits a complete loss mitigation application on March 1. The servicer must disclose March 1 as the date the servicer received the application under § 1024.41(c)(3)(i)(B). Assume the servicer discovers on March 10 that it requires additional information or corrected documents to complete the application and promptly requests such additional information or documents from the borrower pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv). If the borrower subsequently completes the application on March 21, the servicer must provide another notice in accordance with § 1024.41(c)(3)(i) and disclose March 21 as the date the servicer received the complete application. See comment 41(c)(3)(i)-3.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>First notice or filing.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(c)(3)(i)(D)(1) and (2) sets forth different requirements depending on whether the servicer has made the first notice or filing under applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process at the time the borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application. See comment 41(f)-1 for a description of whether a document is considered the first notice or filing under applicable law.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-Interp-3" marker="3.">
            <title>Additional notices.</title>
            <content>Except as provided in § 1024.41(c)(3)(ii), § 1024.41(c)(3)(i) requires a servicer to provide a written notice every time a loss mitigation application becomes complete. For example, assume that a borrower first submits a complete loss mitigation application on March 1, and the servicer provides the notice under § 1024.41(c)(3)(i). Assume the servicer discovers on March 10 that it requires additional information or corrected documents regarding a source of income that the borrower previously identified. The servicer must promptly request such additional information or documents from the borrower pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv). If the borrower subsequently completes the application on March 21, the servicer must provide another notice in accordance with § 1024.41(c)(3)(i), unless an exception applies under § 1024.41(c)(3)(ii). See comment 41(c)(3)(i)-1.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-4-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-Interp" target="1024-41-c">
        <title>41(c)(4) Information not in the borrower's control.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-i-Interp" target="1024-41-c-4-i">
          <title>41(c)(4)(i) Diligence requirements.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>During the first 30 days following receipt of a complete loss mitigation application.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(c)(4)(i) requires a servicer to act with reasonable diligence to obtain documents or information not in the borrower's control, which includes information in the servicer's control, that the servicer requires to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower. At a minimum and without limitation, a servicer must request such documents or information from the appropriate party:</content>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-i-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
              <content>Promptly upon determining that the servicer requires the documents or information to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, the servicer will offer the borrower; and</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-i-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
              <content>By a date that will enable the servicer to complete the evaluation within 30 days of receiving the complete loss mitigation application, as set forth in § 1024.41(c)(1), to the extent practicable.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>More than 30 days following receipt of a complete loss mitigation application.</title>
            <content>If a servicer has not, within 30 days of receiving a complete loss mitigation application, received the required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, the servicer acts with reasonable diligence pursuant to § 1024.41(c)(4)(i) by heightening efforts to obtain the documents or information promptly, to minimize delay in making a determination of which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower. Such heightened efforts include, for example, promptly verifying that it has contacted the appropriate party and determining whether it should obtain the required documents or information from a different party.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Third-party delay.</title>
            <content>Notwithstanding delay in receiving required documents or information from any party other than the borrower or the servicer, § 1024.41(c)(1)(i) requires a servicer to complete all possible steps in the process of evaluating a complete loss mitigation application within 30 days of receiving the complete loss mitigation application. Such steps may include requirements imposed on the servicer by third parties, such as mortgage insurance companies, guarantors, owners, or assignees. For example, if a servicer can determine a borrower's eligibility for all available loss mitigation options based on an evaluation of the borrower's complete loss mitigation application subject only to approval from the mortgage insurance company, § 1024.41(c)(1)(i) requires the servicer to do so within 30 days of receiving the complete loss mitigation application notwithstanding the need to obtain such approval before offering the borrower any loss mitigation options.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>Offers not prohibited.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) permits a servicer to deny a complete loss mitigation application (in accordance with applicable investor requirements) if, after exercising reasonable diligence to obtain the required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, the servicer has been unable to obtain such documents or information for a significant period of time and the servicer cannot complete its determination without the required documents or information. Section 1024.41(c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) does not require a servicer to deny a complete loss mitigation application and permits a servicer to offer a borrower a loss mitigation option, even if the servicer does not obtain the requested documents or information.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="deleted" label="1024-41-d-1-Interp-2-p1"/>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-g-Interp-3">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-g-Interp-3" marker="3.">
        <title>Interaction with foreclosure counsel.</title>
        <content>The prohibitions in § 1024.41(g) against moving for judgment or order of sale or conducting a sale may require a servicer to act through foreclosure counsel retained by the servicer in a foreclosure proceeding. If a servicer has received a complete loss mitigation application, the servicer must instruct counsel promptly not to make a dispositive motion for foreclosure judgment or order of sale; where such a dispositive motion is pending, to avoid a ruling on the motion or issuance of an order of sale; and, where a sale is scheduled, to prevent conduct of a foreclosure sale, unless one of the conditions in § 1024.41(g)(1) through (3) is met. A servicer is not relieved of its obligations because foreclosure counsel's actions or inaction caused a violation.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-g-Interp-5">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-g-Interp-5" marker="5.">
        <title>Conducting a sale prohibited.</title>
        <content>Section 1024.41(g) prohibits a servicer from conducting a foreclosure sale, even if a person other than the servicer administers or conducts the foreclosure sale proceedings. Where a foreclosure sale is scheduled, and none of the conditions under § 1024.41(g)(1) through (3) are applicable, conduct of the sale violates § 1024.41(g).</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i-Interp-1">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
        <title>Applicability of loss mitigation protections.</title>
        <content>Under § 1024.41(i), a servicer must comply with § 1024.41 with respect to a loss mitigation application unless the servicer has previously done so for a complete loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower and the borrower has been delinquent at all times since submitting the prior complete application. Thus, for example, if the borrower has previously submitted a complete loss mitigation application and the servicer complied fully with § 1024.41 for that application, but the borrower then ceased to be delinquent and later became delinquent again, the servicer again must comply with § 1024.41 for any subsequent loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower. When a servicer is required to comply with the requirements of § 1024.41 for such a subsequent loss mitigation application, the servicer must comply with all applicable requirements of § 1024.41. For example, in such a case, the servicer's provision of the notice of determination of which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower under § 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) regarding the borrower's prior complete loss mitigation application does not affect the servicer's obligations to provide a new notice of complete application under § 1024.41(c)(3)(i) regarding the borrower's subsequent complete loss mitigation application.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i-Interp-2">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
        <title>Servicing transfers.</title>
        <content>Section 1024.41(i) provides that a servicer need not comply with § 1024.41 for a subsequent loss mitigation application from a borrower where certain conditions are met. A transferee servicer and a transferor servicer, however, are not the same servicer. Accordingly, a transferee servicer is required to comply with the applicable requirements of § 1024.41 upon receipt of a loss mitigation application from a borrower whose servicing the transferee servicer has obtained through a servicing transfer, even if the borrower previously received an evaluation of a complete loss mitigation application from the transferor servicer.</content>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-k-Interp">
      <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-Interp" target="1024-41-k">
        <title>41(k) Servicing transfers.</title>
        <content/>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-Interp-1" marker="1.">
          <title>Pending loss mitigation application.</title>
          <content>For purposes of § 1024.41(k), a loss mitigation application is pending if it was subject to § 1024.41 and had not been fully resolved before the transfer date. For example, a loss mitigation application would not be considered pending if a transferor servicer had denied a borrower for all options and the borrower's time for making an appeal, if any, had expired prior to the transfer date, such that the transferor servicer had no continuing obligations under § 1024.41 with respect to the application. A pending application is considered a pending complete application if it was complete as of the transfer date under the transferor servicer's criteria for evaluating loss mitigation applications.</content>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-Interp" target="1024-41-k-1">
          <title>41(k)(1) In general.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp" target="1024-41-k-1-i">
            <title>41(k)(1)(i) Timing of compliance.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Obtaining loss mitigation documents and information.</title>
              <content/>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
                <content>In connection with a transfer, a transferor servicer must timely transfer, and a transferee servicer must obtain from the transferor servicer, documents and information submitted by a borrower in connection with a loss mitigation application, consistent with policies and procedures adopted pursuant to § 1024.38(b)(4). A transferee servicer must comply with the applicable requirements of § 1024.41 with respect to a loss mitigation application received as a result of a transfer, even if the transferor servicer was not required to comply with § 1024.41 with respect to that application (for example, because § 1024.41(i) precluded applicability of § 1024.41 with respect to the transferor servicer). If an application was not subject to § 1024.41 prior to a transfer, then for purposes of § 1024.41(b) and (c), a transferee servicer is considered to have received the loss mitigation application on the transfer date. Any such application is subject to the timeframes for compliance set forth in § 1024.41(k).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>A transferee servicer must, in accordance with § 1024.41(b)(1), exercise reasonable diligence to complete a loss mitigation application, including a facially complete application, received as a result of a transfer. In the transfer context, reasonable diligence includes ensuring that a borrower is informed of any changes to the application process, such as a change in the address to which the borrower should submit documents and information to complete the application, as well as ensuring that the borrower is informed about which documents and information are necessary to complete the application.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-1-iii" marker="iii.">
                <content>A borrower may provide documents and information necessary to complete an application to a transferor servicer after the transfer date. Consistent with policies and procedures maintained pursuant to § 1024.38(b)(4), the transferor servicer must timely transfer, and the transferee servicer must obtain, such documents and information.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>Determination of rights and protections.</title>
              <content>For purposes of § 1024.41(c) through (h), a transferee servicer must consider documents and information that constitute a complete loss mitigation application for the transferee servicer to have been received as of the date such documents and information were received by the transferor servicer, even if such documents and information were received by the transferor servicer after the transfer date. See comment 41(k)(1)(i)-1.iii. An application that was facially complete under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) with respect to the transferor servicer remains facially complete under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) with respect to the transferee servicer as of the date it was facially complete with respect to the transferor servicer. If an application was complete with respect to the transferor servicer, but is not complete with respect to the transferee servicer, the transferee servicer must treat the application as facially complete under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) as of the date the application was complete with respect to the transferor servicer.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-i-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Duplicative notices not required.</title>
              <content>A transferee servicer is not required to provide notices under § 1024.41 with respect to a particular loss mitigation application that the transferor servicer provided prior to the transfer. For example, if the transferor servicer provided the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) prior to the transfer, the transferee servicer is not required to provide the notice again for that application.</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-ii-Interp" target="1024-41-k-1-ii">
          <title>41(k)(1)(ii) Transfer date defined.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-1-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Transfer date.</title>
            <content>Section 1024.41(k)(1)(ii) provides that the transfer date is the date on which the transferee servicer will begin accepting payments relating to the mortgage loan, as disclosed on the notice of transfer of loan servicing pursuant to § 1024.33(b)(4)(iv). The transfer date is the same date as that on which the transfer of the servicing responsibilities from the transferor servicer to the transferee servicer occurs. The transfer date is not necessarily the same date as either the effective date of the transfer of servicing as disclosed on the notice of transfer of loan servicing pursuant to § 1024.33(b)(4)(i) or the sale date identified in a servicing transfer agreement.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-Interp" target="1024-41-k-2">
          <title>41(k)(2) Acknowledgment notices.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp" target="1024-41-k-2-ii">
            <title>41(k)(2)(ii) Prohibitions.</title>
            <content/>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp-1" marker="1.">
              <title>Examples of prohibitions.</title>
              <content>Section 1024.41(k)(2)(ii)(A) and (B) adjusts the timeframes for certain borrower rights and foreclosure protections where § 1024.41(k)(2)(i) applies. These provisions are illustrated as follows: Assume a transferor servicer receives a borrower's initial loss mitigation application on October 1, and the loan is transferred five days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, or Sundays) later, on October 8. Assume that Columbus Day, a legal public holiday, occurs on October 14, and the transferee servicer provides the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) 10 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, or Sundays) after the transfer date, on October 23. Assume the transferee servicer discloses a 30-day reasonable date, November 22, under § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii).</content>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp-1-i" marker="i.">
                <content>If the transferor servicer receives the borrower's initial loss mitigation application when the borrower's mortgage loan is 101 days delinquent, the borrower's mortgage loan would be 123 days delinquent on October 23, the date the transferee servicer provides the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B). Pursuant to § 1024.41(k)(2)(ii)(A), the transferee servicer cannot make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process until after November 22, the reasonable date disclosed under § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii), and then only if the borrower has not submitted a complete application by that date.</content>
              </interpParagraph>
              <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp-1-ii" marker="ii.">
                <content>If the transferor servicer receives the borrower's initial loss mitigation application 55 days before the foreclosure sale, the date that the transferee servicer provides the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B), October 23, is 33 days before the foreclosure sale. Pursuant to § 1024.41(k)(2)(ii)(B), the transferee servicer must comply with § 1024.41(c), (d), and (g) if the borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application on or before November 22, the reasonable date disclosed under § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii).</content>
              </interpParagraph>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp-2" marker="2.">
              <title>Applicability of loss mitigation provisions.</title>
              <content>Section 1024.41(k)(2)(ii)(A) prohibits a servicer from making the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process until a date that is after the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii), notwithstanding § 1024.41(f)(1). Section 1024.41(k)(2)(ii)(B) requires a servicer to comply with § 1024.41(c), (d), and (g) if a borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application on or before the reasonable date disclosed in the notice required by § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B), even if the servicer would otherwise not be required to comply with § 1024.41(c), (d), and (g) because the application is submitted 37 days or fewer before a foreclosure sale. Section 1024.41(k)(2)(ii) provides additional protections for borrowers but does not remove any protections. Servicers remain subject to the requirements of § 1024.41 as applicable and so, for example, must comply with § 1024.41(h) if the servicer receives a complete loss mitigation application 90 days or more before a foreclosure sale. Similarly, a servicer is prohibited from making the first notice or filing before the borrower's mortgage loan obligation is more than 120 days delinquent, even if that is after the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
            <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-Interp-3" marker="3.">
              <title>Reasonable date when no milestones remain.</title>
              <content>Generally, a servicer does not provide the notice required under § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) after the date that is 38 days before a foreclosure sale, so at least one milestone specified in comment 41(b)(ii)-1 always remains applicable. When § 1024.41(k)(2)(i) applies, however, the transferee servicer may sometimes provide the notice after the date that is 38 days before a foreclosure sale. When this occurs, the transferee servicer must determine the reasonable date when none of the four specified milestones remain. The other requirements of § 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) continue to apply. In this circumstance, a reasonable date may occur less than 30 days, but not less than seven days, after the date the transferee servicer provides the written notice pursuant to § 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B).</content>
            </interpParagraph>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-3-Interp" target="1024-41-k-3">
          <title>41(k)(3) Complete loss mitigation applications pending at transfer.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-3-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Additional information or corrections to a previously submitted document.</title>
            <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which a complete loss mitigation application is pending as of the transfer date and the transferee servicer determines that additional information or a correction to a previously submitted document is required based upon its criteria for evaluating loss mitigation applications, the application is considered facially complete under § 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) as of the date it was first facially complete or complete, as applicable, with respect to the transferor servicer. Once the transferee servicer receives the information or corrections necessary to complete the application, § 1024.41(c)(3) requires the transferee servicer to provide a notice of complete application.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-3-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>Applications first complete upon transfer.</title>
            <content>If the borrower's loss mitigation application was incomplete based on the transferor servicer's criteria prior to transfer but is complete based upon the transferee servicer's criteria, the application is considered a pending loss mitigation application complete as of the transfer date for purposes of § 1024.41(k)(3). Consequently, the transferee servicer must comply with the applicable requirements of § 1024.41(c)(1) and (4) within 30 days of the transfer date. For purposes of § 1024.41(c) through (h), the application is complete as of the date the transferor servicer received the documents and information constituting the complete application. See comment 41(k)(1)(i)-2. In such circumstances, § 1024.41(c)(3) requires the transferee servicer to provide a notice of complete application that discloses the date the transferor servicer received the documents and information constituting the complete application.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-4-Interp" target="1024-41-k-4">
          <title>41(k)(4) Applications subject to appeal process.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-4-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Obtaining appeal.</title>
            <content>A borrower may submit an appeal of a transferor servicer's determination pursuant to § 1024.41(h) to the transferor servicer after the transfer date. Consistent with policies and procedures maintained pursuant to § 1024.38(b)(4), the transferor servicer must timely transfer, and the transferee servicer must obtain, documents and information regarding such appeals.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-4-Interp-2" marker="2.">
            <title>Servicer unable to determine appeal.</title>
            <content>A transferee servicer may be unable to make a determination on an appeal when, for example, the transferor servicer denied a borrower for a loan modification option that the transferee servicer does not offer or when the transferee servicer receives the mortgage loan through an involuntary transfer and the transferor servicer failed to maintain proper records such that the transferee servicer lacks sufficient information to review the appeal. In that circumstance, the transferee servicer is required to treat the appeal as a pending complete application, and it must permit the borrower to accept or reject any loss mitigation options offered by the transferor servicer, even if it does not offer the loss mitigation options offered by the transferor servicer, in addition to the loss mitigation options, if any, that the transferee servicer determines to offer the borrower based on its own evaluation of the borrower's complete loss mitigation application. For example, assume a transferor servicer denied a borrower for all loan modification options but offered the borrower a short sale option, and assume that the borrower's appeal of the loan modification denial was pending as of the transfer date. If the transferee servicer is unable to determine the borrower's appeal, the transferee servicer must evaluate the borrower for all available loss mitigation options in accordance with § 1024.41(c) and (k)(3). At the conclusion of such evaluation, the transferee servicer must permit the borrower to accept the short sale option offered by the transferor servicer, even if the transferee servicer does not offer the short sale option, in addition to any loss mitigation options the transferee servicer determines to offer the borrower based upon its own evaluation.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
        <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-5-Interp" target="1024-41-k-5">
          <title>41(k)(5) Pending loss mitigation offers.</title>
          <content/>
          <interpParagraph label="1024-41-k-5-Interp-1" marker="1.">
            <title>Obtaining evidence of borrower acceptance.</title>
            <content>A borrower may provide an acceptance or rejection of a pending loss mitigation offer to a transferor servicer after the transfer date. Consistent with policies and procedures maintained pursuant to § 1024.38(b)(4), the transferor servicer must timely transfer, and the transferee servicer must obtain, documents and information regarding such acceptances and rejections, and the transferee servicer must provide the borrower with any timely accepted loss mitigation option, even if the borrower submitted the acceptance to the transferor servicer.</content>
          </interpParagraph>
        </interpParagraph>
      </interpParagraph>
    </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
