<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<notice xmlns="eregs" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eregs https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cfpb/regulations-schema/master/src/eregs.xsd">
  <fdsys>
    <cfrTitleNum>12</cfrTitleNum>
    <cfrTitleText>Banks and Banking</cfrTitleText>
    <volume>8</volume>
    <date>2016-10-19</date>
    <originalDate>2016-10-19</originalDate>
    <title>REAL ESTATE SETTLEMENT PROCEDURES ACT</title>
  </fdsys>
  <preamble>
    <agency>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</agency>
    <regLetter>X</regLetter>
    <cfr>
      <title>12</title>
      <section>1024</section>
    </cfr>
    <documentNumber>2016-18901</documentNumber>
    <effectiveDate>2017-10-19</effectiveDate>
    <federalRegisterURL>https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2016/10/19/2016-18901/amendments-to-the-2013-mortgage-rules-under-the-real-estate-settlement-procedures-act-regulation-x</federalRegisterURL>
  </preamble>
  <changeset leftDocumentNumber="2015-18239" rightDocumentNumber="2016-18901">

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-6-d-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-6-d-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>No changes to, deletions from, or additions to the special information booklet currently prescribed by the Bureau shall be made other than the permissible changes specified in paragraphs (d)(2) and (3) of this section or changes as otherwise approved in writing by the Bureau in accordance with the procedures described in this paragraph (d). A request to the Bureau for approval of any changes other than the permissible changes specified in paragraphs (d)(2) and (3) of this section shall be submitted in writing to the address indicated in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2, stating the reasons why the applicant believes such changes, deletions, or additions are necessary.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-6-d-2">
      <paragraph label="1024-6-d-2" marker="(2)">
        <content>The cover of the booklet may be in any form and may contain any drawings, pictures, or artwork, provided that the words “settlement costs” are used in the title. Names, addresses and telephone numbers of the lender or others and similar information may appear on the cover, but no discussion of the matters covered in the booklet shall appear on the cover.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-9-a-5">
      <paragraph label="1024-9-a-5" marker="(5)">
        <content>The following variations in layout and format are within the discretion of persons reproducing the HUD-1 and do not require prior Bureau approval: Size of pages; tint or color of pages; size and style of type or print; vertical spacing between lines or provision for additional horizontal space on lines (for example, to provide sufficient space for recording time periods used in prorations); printing of the HUD-1 contents on separate pages, on the front and back of a single page, or on one continuous page; use of multicopy tear-out sets; printing on rolls for computer purposes; reorganization of sections B through I, when necessary to accommodate computer printing; and manner of placement of the HUD number, but not the OMB approval number, neither of which may be deleted. The expiration date associated with the OMB number listed on the form may be deleted. Any changes in the HUD number or OMB approval number may be announced by notice in the Federal Register, rather than by amendment of this part.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-9-c">
      <paragraph label="1024-9-c" marker="(c)">
        <title>Written approval.</title>
        <content>Any other deviation in the HUD-1 or HUD-1A forms is permissible only upon receipt of written approval of the Bureau; provided, however, that notwithstanding contrary instructions in this section or appendix A of this part, reproducing the HUD-1 or HUD-1A forms with the Bureau's OMB approval number displayed in place of HUD's OMB approval number does not require the written approval of the Bureau. A request to the Bureau for approval shall be submitted in writing to the address indicated in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2 and shall state the reasons why the applicant believes such deviation is needed. The prescribed form(s) must be used until approval is received.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-17-h-1">
      <paragraph label="1024-17-h-1" marker="(1)">
        <content>The format and a completed example for an initial escrow account statement are set out in Public Guidance Documents entitled “Initial Escrow Account Disclosure Statement—Format” and “Initial Escrow Account Disclosure Statement—Example,” available in accordance with the direction in the definition of Public Guidance Documents in § 1024.2.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1024-31-Delinquency" parent="1024-31" after="1024-31-p1">
      <paragraph label="1024-31-Delinquency" marker="">
        <content><def term="delinquency">Delinquency</def> means a period of time during which a borrower and a borrower's mortgage loan obligation are delinquent. A borrower and a borrower's mortgage loan obligation are delinquent beginning on the date a periodic payment sufficient to cover principal, interest, and, if applicable, escrow becomes due and unpaid, until such time as no periodic payment is due and unpaid.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-c-2-v">
      <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v" marker="(v)">
        <content>A statement that:</content>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-A" marker="(A)">
          <content>The borrower's hazard insurance is expiring, has expired, or provides insufficient coverage, as applicable;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-B" marker="(B)">
          <content>The servicer does not have evidence that the borrower has hazard insurance coverage past the expiration date or evidence that the borrower has hazard insurance that provides sufficient coverage, as applicable; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-37-c-2-v-C" marker="(C)">
          <content>If applicable, identifies the type of hazard insurance for which the servicer lacks evidence of coverage;</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-c-4">
      <paragraph label="1024-37-c-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Additional information.</title>
        <content>Except for the mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (c)(2) of this section in the written notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(i) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii" subpath="title">
      <title>Servicer lacking evidence of continuous coverage.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer that has received hazard insurance information after delivering to a borrower or placing in the mail the notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(i) of this section, but has not received, from the borrower or otherwise, evidence demonstrating that the borrower has had sufficient hazard insurance coverage in place continuously, must set forth in the notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section the following information:</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-2-ii-B" subpath="content">
      <content>The information required by paragraphs (c)(2)(ii) through (iv) and (ix) through (xi) and (d)(2)(i)(B) and (D) of this section;</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-3" subpath="title">
      <title>Format.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-3" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer must set the information required by paragraphs (d)(2)(i)(B) and (D) of this section in bold text. The requirements of paragraph (c)(3) of this section apply to the information required by paragraph (d)(2)(i)(C) of this section. A servicer may use form MS-3B in appendix MS-3 of this part to comply with the requirements of paragraphs (d)(1) and (d)(2)(i) of this section. A servicer may use form MS-3C in appendix MS-3 of this part to comply with the requirements of paragraphs (d)(1) and (d)(2)(ii) of this section.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-4" subpath="title">
      <title>Additional information.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-d-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Except for the borrower's mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (d)(2)(i) or (ii) of this section, as applicable, in the written notice required by paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-e-4" subpath="title">
      <title>Additional information.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-37-e-4" subpath="content">
      <content>Except for the borrower's mortgage loan account number, a servicer may not include any information other than information required by paragraph (e)(2) of this section in the written notice required by paragraph (e)(1) of this section. However, a servicer may provide such additional information to a borrower on separate pieces of paper in the same transmittal.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1024-38-b-2-vi">
      <paragraph label="1024-38-b-2-vi" marker="(vi)">
        <content>Promptly identify and obtain documents or information not in the borrower's control that the servicer requires to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, to offer the borrower in accordance with the requirements of § 1024.41(c)(4).</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-a">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-a" marker="(a)">
        <title>Live contact.</title>
        <content>Except as otherwise provided in this section, a servicer shall establish or make good faith efforts to establish live contact with a delinquent borrower no later than the 36th day of a borrower's delinquency and again no later than 36 days after each payment due date so long as the borrower remains delinquent. Promptly after establishing live contact with a borrower, the servicer shall inform the borrower about the availability of loss mitigation options, if appropriate.</content>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1" subpath="title">
      <title>Notice required.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-b-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Except as otherwise provided in this section, a servicer shall provide to a delinquent borrower a written notice with the information set forth in paragraph (b)(2) of this section no later than the 45th day of the borrower's delinquency and again no later than 45 days after each payment due date so long as the borrower remains delinquent. A servicer is not required to provide the written notice, however, more than once during any 180-day period. If a borrower is 45 days or more delinquent at the end of any 180-day period after the servicer has provided the written notice, a servicer must provide the written notice again no later than 180 days after the provision of the prior written notice. If a borrower is less than 45 days delinquent at the end of any 180-day period after the servicer has provided the written notice, a servicer must provide the written notice again no later than 45 days after the payment due date for which the borrower remains delinquent.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-c">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-c" marker="(c)">
        <title>Borrowers in bankruptcy</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1" marker="(1)">
          <title>Partial exemption.</title>
          <content>While any borrower on a mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code, a servicer, with regard to that mortgage loan:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (a) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section if no loss mitigation option is available, or if any borrower on the mortgage loan has provided a notification pursuant to the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) section 805(c) (15 U.S.C. 1692c(c)) with respect to that mortgage loan as referenced in paragraph (d) of this section; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <content>If the conditions of paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section are not met, must comply with the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section, as modified by this paragraph (c)(1)(iii):</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>If a borrower is delinquent when the borrower becomes a debtor in bankruptcy, a servicer must provide the written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section not later than the 45th day after the borrower files a bankruptcy petition under title 11 of the United States Code. If the borrower is not delinquent when the borrower files a bankruptcy petition, but subsequently becomes delinquent while a debtor in bankruptcy, the servicer must provide the written notice not later than the 45th day of the borrower's delinquency. A servicer must comply with these timing requirements regardless of whether the servicer provided the written notice in the preceding 180-day period.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section may not contain a request for payment.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-1-iii-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>A servicer is not required to provide the written notice required by paragraph (b) of this section more than once during a single bankruptcy case.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2" marker="(2)">
          <title>Resuming compliance.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(2)(ii) of this section, a servicer that was exempt from paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section pursuant to paragraph (c)(1) of this section must resume compliance with paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section after the next payment due date that follows the earliest of the following events:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>The bankruptcy case is dismissed;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>The bankruptcy case is closed; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-i-C" marker="(C)">
              <content>The borrower reaffirms personal liability for the mortgage loan.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>With respect to a mortgage loan for which the borrower has discharged personal liability pursuant to 11 U.S.C. 727, 1141, 1228, or 1328, a servicer:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Is not required to resume compliance with paragraph (a) of this section; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-39-c-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Must resume compliance with paragraph (b) of this section if the borrower has made any partial or periodic payment on the mortgage loan after the commencement of the borrower's bankruptcy case.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-39-d">
      <paragraph label="1024-39-d" marker="(d)">
        <title>Fair Debt Collection Practices Act—partial exemption.</title>
        <content>With regard to a mortgage loan for which any borrower has provided a notification pursuant to the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act (FDCPA) section 805(c) (15 U.S.C. 1692c(c)), a servicer subject to the FDCPA with respect to that borrower's loan:</content>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-1" marker="(1)">
          <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (a) of this section;</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-2" marker="(2)">
          <content>Is exempt from the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section if no loss mitigation option is available, or while any borrower on that mortgage loan is a debtor in bankruptcy under title 11 of the United States Code as referenced in paragraph (c) of this section; and</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3" marker="(3)">
          <content>If the conditions of paragraph (d)(2) of this section are not met, must comply with the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section, as modified by this paragraph (d)(3):</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-i" marker="(i)">
            <content>In addition to the information required pursuant to paragraph (b)(2) of this section, the written notice must include a statement that the servicer may or intends to invoke its specified remedy of foreclosure. Model clause MS-4(D) in appendix MS-4 to this part may be used to comply with this requirement.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <content>The written notice may not contain a request for payment.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-39-d-3-iii" marker="(iii)">
            <content>A servicer is prohibited from providing the written notice more than once during any 180-day period.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-1" subpath="title">
      <title>Complete loss mitigation application.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-1" subpath="content">
      <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii) of this section, if a servicer receives a complete loss mitigation application more than 37 days before a foreclosure sale, then, within 30 days of receiving the complete loss mitigation application, a servicer shall:</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iii" subpath="title">
      <title>Short-term loss mitigation options.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iii" subpath="content">
      <content>Notwithstanding paragraph (c)(2)(i) of this section, a servicer may offer a short-term payment forbearance program or a short-term repayment plan to a borrower based upon an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. Promptly after offering a payment forbearance program or a repayment plan under this paragraph (c)(2)(iii), unless the borrower has rejected the offer, the servicer must provide the borrower a written notice stating the specific payment terms and duration of the program or plan, that the servicer offered the program or plan based on an evaluation of an incomplete application, that other loss mitigation options may be available, and that the borrower has the option to submit a complete loss mitigation application to receive an evaluation for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower regardless of whether the borrower accepts the program or plan. A servicer shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, and shall not move for foreclosure judgment or order of sale or conduct a foreclosure sale, if a borrower is performing pursuant to the terms of a payment forbearance program or repayment plan offered pursuant to this paragraph (c)(2)(iii). A servicer may offer a short-term payment forbearance program in conjunction with a short-term repayment plan pursuant to this paragraph (c)(2)(iii).</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iv" subpath="title">
      <title>Facially complete application.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-c-2-iv" subpath="content">
      <content>A loss mitigation application shall be considered facially complete when a borrower submits all the missing documents and information as stated in the notice required under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section, when no additional information is requested in such notice, or once the servicer is required to provide the borrower a written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(3)(i) of this section. If the servicer later discovers that additional information or corrections to a previously submitted document are required to complete the application, the servicer must promptly request the missing information or corrected documents and treat the application as complete for the purposes of paragraphs (f)(2) and (g) of this section until the borrower is given a reasonable opportunity to complete the application. If the borrower completes the application within this period, the application shall be considered complete as of the date it first became facially complete, for the purposes of paragraphs (d), (e), (f)(2), (g), and (h) of this section, and as of the date the application was actually complete for the purposes of this paragraph (c). A servicer that complies with this paragraph (c)(2)(iv) will be deemed to have fulfilled its obligation to provide an accurate notice under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-3">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3" marker="(3)">
        <title>Notice of complete application.</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i" marker="(i)">
          <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(3)(ii) of this section, within 5 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) after receiving a borrower's complete loss mitigation application, a servicer shall provide the borrower a written notice that sets forth the following information:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>That the loss mitigation application is complete;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The date the servicer received the complete application;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>That the servicer expects to complete its evaluation within 30 days of the date it received the complete application;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D" marker="(D)">
            <content>That the borrower is entitled to certain foreclosure protections because the servicer has received the complete application, and, as applicable, either:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>If the servicer has not made the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, that the servicer cannot make the first notice or filing required to commence or initiate the foreclosure process under applicable law before evaluating the borrower's complete application; or</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-D-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>If the servicer has made the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process, that the servicer has begun the foreclosure process, and that the servicer cannot conduct a foreclosure sale before evaluating the borrower's complete application;</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-E" marker="(E)">
            <content>That the servicer may need additional information at a later date to evaluate the application, in which case the servicer will request that information from the borrower and give the borrower a reasonable opportunity to submit it, the evaluation process may take longer, and the foreclosure protections could end if the servicer does not receive the information as requested; and</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-i-F" marker="(F)">
            <content>That the borrower may be entitled to additional protections under State or Federal law.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <content>A servicer is not required to provide a notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(3)(i) of this section if:</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-A" marker="(A)">
            <content>The servicer has already provided the borrower a notice under paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section informing the borrower that the application is complete and the servicer has not subsequently requested additional information or a corrected version of a previously submitted document from the borrower pursuant to paragraph (c)(2)(iv) of this section;</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>The application was not complete or facially complete more than 37 days before a foreclosure sale; or</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-3-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>The servicer has already provided the borrower a notice regarding the application under paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-c-4">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4" marker="(4)">
        <title>Information not in the borrower's control</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-i" marker="(i)">
          <title>Reasonable diligence.</title>
          <content>If a servicer requires documents or information not in the borrower's control to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower, the servicer must exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining such documents or information.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
          <title>Effect in case of delay.</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A" marker="">
            <content/>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>Except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) of this section, a servicer must not deny a complete loss mitigation application solely because the servicer lacks required documents or information not in the borrower's control.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-A-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>If a servicer has exercised reasonable diligence to obtain required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, but the servicer has been unable to obtain such documents or information for a significant period of time following the 30-day period identified in paragraph (c)(1) of this section, and the servicer, in accordance with applicable requirements established by the owner or assignee of the borrower's mortgage loan, is unable to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer the borrower without such documents or information, the servicer may deny the application and provide the borrower with a written notice in accordance with paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section. When providing the written notice in accordance with paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section, the servicer must also provide the borrower with a copy of the written notice required by paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B" marker="(B)">
            <content>If a servicer is unable to make a determination within the 30-day period identified in paragraph (c)(1) of this section as to which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower because the servicer lacks required documents or information from a party other than the borrower or the servicer, the servicer must, within such 30-day period or promptly thereafter, provide the borrower a written notice, informing the borrower:</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-1" marker="(1)">
              <content>That the servicer has not received documents or information not in the borrower's control that the servicer requires to determine which loss mitigation options, if any, it will offer to the borrower on behalf of the owner or assignee of the mortgage;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-2" marker="(2)">
              <content>Of the specific documents or information that the servicer lacks;</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-3" marker="(3)">
              <content>That the servicer has requested such documents or information; and</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-B-4" marker="(4)">
              <content>That the servicer will complete its evaluation of the borrower for all available loss mitigation options promptly upon receiving the documents or information.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-c-4-ii-C" marker="(C)">
            <content>If a servicer must provide a notice required by paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B) of this section, the servicer must not provide the borrower a written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section until the servicer receives the required documents or information referenced in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(B)(2) of this section, except as provided in paragraph (c)(4)(ii)(A)(2) of this section. Upon receiving such required documents or information, the servicer must promptly provide the borrower with the written notice pursuant to paragraph (c)(1)(ii) of this section.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-f-1-iii" subpath="content">
      <content>The servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a superior or subordinate lienholder.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i" subpath="title">
      <title>Duplicative requests.</title>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-41-i" subpath="content">
      <content>A servicer must comply with the requirements of this section for a borrower's loss mitigation application, unless the servicer has previously complied with the requirements of this section for a complete loss mitigation application submitted by the borrower and the borrower has been delinquent at all times since submitting the prior complete application.</content>
    </change>

    <change operation="added" label="1024-41-k">
      <paragraph label="1024-41-k" marker="(k)">
        <title>Servicing transfers—</title>
        <content/>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1" marker="(1)">
          <title>In general—</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Timing of compliance.</title>
            <content>Except as provided in paragraphs (k)(2) through (4) of this section, if a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which a loss mitigation application is pending as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must comply with the requirements of this section for that loss mitigation application within the timeframes that were applicable to the transferor servicer based on the date the transferor servicer received the loss mitigation application. All rights and protections under paragraphs (c) through (h) of this section to which a borrower was entitled before a transfer continue to apply notwithstanding the transfer.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-1-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Transfer date defined.</title>
            <content>For purposes of this paragraph (k), the transfer date is the date on which the transferee servicer will begin accepting payments relating to the mortgage loan, as disclosed on the notice of transfer of loan servicing pursuant to § 1024.33(b)(4)(iv).</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2" marker="(2)">
          <title>Acknowledgment notices—</title>
          <content/>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Transferee servicer timeframes.</title>
            <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which the period to provide the notice required by paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section has not expired as of the transfer date and the transferor servicer has not provided such notice, the transferee servicer must provide the notice within 10 days (excluding legal public holidays, Saturdays, and Sundays) of the transfer date.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Prohibitions.</title>
            <content>A transferee servicer that must provide the notice required by paragraph (b)(2)(i)(B) of this section under this paragraph (k)(2):</content>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-A" marker="(A)">
              <content>Shall not make the first notice or filing required by applicable law for any judicial or non-judicial foreclosure process until a date that is after the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section, notwithstanding paragraph (f)(1) of this section. For purposes of paragraph (f)(2) of this section, a borrower who submits a complete loss mitigation application on or before the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section shall be treated as having done so during the pre-foreclosure review period set forth in paragraph (f)(1) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph label="1024-41-k-2-ii-B" marker="(B)">
              <content>Shall comply with paragraphs (c), (d), and (g) of this section if the borrower submits a complete loss mitigation application to the transferee or transferor servicer 37 or fewer days before the foreclosure sale but on or before the reasonable date disclosed to the borrower pursuant to paragraph (b)(2)(ii) of this section.</content>
            </paragraph>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-3" marker="(3)">
          <title>Complete loss mitigation applications pending at transfer.</title>
          <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which a complete loss mitigation application is pending as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must comply with the applicable requirements of paragraphs (c)(1) and (4) of this section within 30 days of the transfer date.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4" marker="(4)">
          <title>Applications subject to appeal process.</title>
          <content>If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which an appeal of a transferor servicer's determination pursuant to paragraph (h) of this section has not been resolved by the transferor servicer as of the transfer date or is timely filed after the transfer date, the transferee servicer must make a determination on the appeal if it is able to do so or, if it is unable to do so, must treat the appeal as a pending complete loss mitigation application.</content>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4-i" marker="(i)">
            <title>Determining appeal.</title>
            <content>If a transferee servicer is required under this paragraph (k)(4) to make a determination on an appeal, the transferee servicer must complete the determination and provide the notice required by paragraph (h)(4) of this section within 30 days of the transfer date or 30 days of the date the borrower made the appeal, whichever is later.</content>
          </paragraph>
          <paragraph label="1024-41-k-4-ii" marker="(ii)">
            <title>Servicer unable to determine appeal.</title>
            <content>A transferee servicer that is required to treat a borrower's appeal as a pending complete loss mitigation application under this paragraph (k)(4) must comply with the requirements of this section for such application, including evaluating the borrower for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower from the transferee servicer. For purposes of paragraph (c) or (k)(3) of this section, as applicable, such a pending complete loss mitigation application shall be considered complete as of the date the appeal was received by the transferor servicer or the transferee servicer, whichever occurs first. For purposes of paragraphs (e) through (h) of this section, the transferee servicer must treat such a pending complete loss mitigation application as facially complete under paragraph (c)(2)(iv) as of the date it was first facially complete or complete, as applicable, with respect to the transferor servicer.</content>
          </paragraph>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-41-k-5" marker="(5)">
          <title>Pending loss mitigation offers.</title>
          <content>A transfer does not affect a borrower's ability to accept or reject a loss mitigation option offered under paragraph (c) or (h) of this section. If a transferee servicer acquires the servicing of a mortgage loan for which the borrower's time period under paragraph (e) or (h) of this section for accepting or rejecting a loss mitigation option offered by the transferor servicer has not expired as of the transfer date, the transferee servicer must allow the borrower to accept or reject the offer during the unexpired balance of the applicable time period.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(A)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="4" label="1024-MS-3(A)">
        <subject>MS-3(A)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(c)(2)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p30" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p31" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p32" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p33" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p34" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p35" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p36" marker="">
          <content>Our records show that your [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance [is expiring] [expired] [provides insufficient coverage], and we do not have evidence that you have obtained new coverage. Because [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance is required on your property, [we bought insurance for your property] [we plan to buy insurance for your property]. You must pay us for any period during which the insurance we buy is in effect but you do not have insurance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p37" marker="">
          <content>You should immediately provide us with your insurance information. [Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p38" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p39" marker="">
          <content>May be significantly more expensive than the insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p40" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p41" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(A)-p42" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(B)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="5" label="1024-MS-3(B)">
        <subject>MS-3(B)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(d)(2)(i)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p43" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p44" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p45" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p46" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p47" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Second and final notice—please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p48" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p49" marker="">
          <content>This is your second and final notice that our records show that your [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance [is expiring] [expired] [provides insufficient coverage], and we do not have evidence that you have obtained new coverage. Because [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance is required on your property, [we bought insurance for your property] [we plan to buy insurance for your property]. You must pay us for any period during which the insurance we buy is in effect but you do not have insurance.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p50" marker="">
          <content>You should immediately provide us with your insurance information. [Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p51" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p52" marker="">
          <content>[Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p53" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p54" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(B)-p55" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(C)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="6" label="1024-MS-3(C)">
        <subject>MS-3(C)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(d)(2)(ii)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p56" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p57" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p58" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p59" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p60" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Second and final notice—please provide insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p61" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p62" marker="">
          <content>We received the insurance information you provided, but we are unable to verify coverage from [Date Range].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p63" marker="">
          <content>Please provide us with insurance information for [Date Range] immediately.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p64" marker="">
          <content>We will charge you for insurance we [bought] [plan to buy] for [Date Range] unless we can verify that you have insurance coverage for [Date Range].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p65" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we [bought] [buy]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p66" marker="">
          <content>Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p67" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p68" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(C)-p69" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="modified" label="1024-MS-3(D)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="7" label="1024-MS-3(D)">
        <subject>MS-3(D)—Model Form for Force-Placed Insurance Notice Containing Information Required By § 1024.37(e)(2)</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p70" marker="">
          <content>[Name and Mailing Address of Servicer]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p71" marker="">
          <content>[Date of Notice]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p72" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Name]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p73" marker="">
          <content>[Borrower's Mailing Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p74" marker="">
          <content>Subject: Please update insurance information for [Property Address]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p75" marker="">
          <content>Dear [Borrower's Name]:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p76" marker="">
          <content>Because we did not have evidence that you had [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance on the property listed above, we bought insurance on your property and added the cost to your mortgage loan account.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p77" marker="">
          <content>The policy that we bought [expired] [is scheduled to expire]. Because [hazard][Insurance Type] insurance] is required on your property, we intend to maintain insurance on your property by renewing or replacing the insurance we bought.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p78" marker="">
          <content>The insurance we buy:</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p79" marker="">
          <content>[Costs $[premium charge]] [Will cost an estimated $[premium charge]] annually, which may be significantly more expensive than insurance you can buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p80" marker="">
          <content>May not provide as much coverage as an insurance policy you buy yourself.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p81" marker="">
          <content>If you buy [hazard] [Insurance Type] insurance, you should immediately provide us with your insurance information.</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p82" marker="">
          <content>[Describe the insurance information the borrower must provide]. [The information must be provided in writing.]</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p83" marker="">
          <content>If you have any questions, please contact us at [telephone number].</content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-3(D)-p84" marker="">
          <content>[If applicable, provide a statement advising a borrower to review additional information provided in the same transmittal.]</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
    <change operation="added" label="1024-MS-4(D)">
      <appendixSection appendixSecNum="12" label="1024-MS-4(D)">
        <subject>MS-4(D)—Written Early Intervention Notice for Servicers Subject to FDCPA (§ 1024.39(d)(2)(iii))</subject>
        <paragraph label="1024-MS-4(D)-p1" marker="">
          <content>This is a legally required notice. We are sending this notice to you because you are behind on your mortgage payment. We want to notify you of possible ways to avoid losing your home. We have a right to invoke foreclosure based on the terms of your mortgage contact. Please read this letter carefully.</content>
        </paragraph>
      </appendixSection>
    </change>
  </changeset>
</notice>
